<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Naylor_James_Ful_3_15</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1541.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The course of Life of Br James Naylor Widow<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi>.</l>
					<l>who departed happily April 30<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1770</l>
					<l>He was born October 23<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>d</hi> 1692 at Scholes in the Parish of Birstal, Yorkshire</l>
					<l>and came when a Child to live with his Grand Father Sam<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>l </hi>Hillas at Bankhouse,</l>
					<l>He serv&apos;d an apprintiesthep with his Uncle Sam<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>l</hi> Hillas in the Clothing Business, who lived</l>
					<l>in Oaker Lane in this Neighbourhood. In the yr 1728. He was married to Martha Naylor</l>
					<l>by whom He had one Son &amp; two Daughters, of whom 1 Son our B<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi> John Naylor in</l>
					<l>the Choir House, &amp; a Daughter are yet living. They lived 14 Years in Oaker Lane, after</l>
					<l>their Marriage &amp; then came to live at Bankhouse.</l>
					<l>When Mr Ingham preach&apos;d here abouts in the Churches he us&apos;d to attend constantly</l>
					<l>&amp; became concern&apos;d for his Salvation, &amp; when the B<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>rn</hi> came here &amp; Societies were Settled</l>
					<l>he became a Member thereof in the year 1741, &amp; prosper&apos;d in our Sav<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Grace, Octob<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi> 6th</l>
					<l>1744. He was Rece&apos;d into the Cong<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>n</hi> &amp; Dec<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi> 20<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>th</hi> the same year, was partaker of the</l>
					<l>The Communion. He shew&apos;d that his Election of Grace was weighty to him by a faithful</l>
					<l>concern for what belong&apos;d to our Sav<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Kingdom &amp; a readiness to be usefull in his degree</l>
					<l>to promote it. He Boarded the S Brn at Lane and for some years. Af terw. He &amp; his late</l>
					<l>Wife lived at the Hall for some time &amp; then was <hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>employed</hi> in the Manufactory, &amp; other matters suitable</l>
					<l>for him, in all which He has Legitimated himself as a faithful Br in the Cong<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi> belov&apos;d</l>
					<l>&amp; Respected by the Brn &amp; Srs &amp; esteem&apos;d by his acquaintance.</l>
					<l>Novr 13<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>th</hi>. 1759 He was made Acoluth. May 9th 1762 He become a Widower, in w<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>ch</hi> </l>
					<l>State he has spent his time in a Sabbatic enjoyment of his Choir grace, willingly employ</l>
					<l>ing his time in useful manner according to his active disposition in w<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>ch</hi> he continued</l>
					<l>till last February, untill it was insisted upon that he declined every thing &amp; suffered himself</l>
					<l>to be attended &amp; cared for according as the Circumstances sh<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>d</hi> require, w<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>ch</hi> his son our Br.</l>
					<l>Dr Naylor Dutifully engag&apos;d in. &amp; going in to see him one Day, he found him on his</l>
					<l>knees bending on his Chair w<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>ch</hi> struck him with * a particular impression. His Disorder was</l>
					<l>an extraordinary heat in his blood w<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>ch</hi> teaz&apos;d him much &amp; deprived him of Rest else had  </l>
					<l>no particular Sickness yet grew gradually Weaker from Day to Day, <hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>and</hi> In the beginning </l>
					<l>He had Thoughts of Recovery <hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>as</hi>  but he soon became sensible that his  days of</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1544.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Sojourning here were drawing to the end, &amp; wod say with vettedness the sooner the better</l>
					<l>&amp; as he had not much Sickness &amp; He thought sometimes he might continue a long time, but</l>
					<l>a Fortnight ages he was oblig&apos;d to take his Bed, altho he was not inclin&apos;d to</l>
					<l>speak much, yet nor of the experience he had of our Savr yet it was evident our Savr</l>
					<l>was his object &amp; his heart liv&apos;d in a Connection with him, his son observes, &quot;I had</l>
					<l>occasion to be asham&apos;d of myself when I found how near a Connexion he had with our</l>
					<l>Savr &amp; says farther I shall had many happy hours with him in his Sickness wch</l>
					<l>I shall never forget especially in 2 or 3 of his last Days, when he wish&apos;d that our</l>
					<l>Savr wod come soon &amp; fetch him home. His daughter &amp; Grand Daughter came to see</l>
					<l>him, &amp; at taking leave of him, his Son being present &amp; He look&apos;d at them &amp; said</l>
					<l>I have no other Council to give you but that ye Love our Savr &amp; one another,</l>
					<l>wch his son says melted my heart to hear that from Him. I thought it was something</l>
					<l>like what the Apostle John said viz little Childrn Love one another. He took tender leave</l>
					<l>of one of another of his Family who came to see him, &amp; chiefly was occupied in his</l>
					<l>Thoughts of being soon at home with the Lord waiting for the happy moment</l>
					<l>on Sunday the 29th he spoke particularly with his son of his expectation of going soon</l>
					<l>&amp; said</l>
					<l>thy mother</l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>&amp; call&apos;d to mind that</hi> when <hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>his dear wife</hi>  went home she gave one a Verse to Sing for</l>
					<l>her, but I cannot sing none, I have heard often of Brns Joining with the singing</l>
					<l>when they was blessd for going home with a strong voice but I cannot.</l>
					<l>more</l>
					<l>In the Evening Br Lyons Visited him again, &amp; spoke with him once of that happy</l>
					<l>change wch now drew near, then bless&apos;d him for his departure during the Singg. So go</l>
					<l>then go dear heart &amp; hide &amp;c &amp; some other Verses with a very happy Sensation of our</l>
					<l>he offered &amp; ask&apos;d him if he had understood what was said &amp; Sung, he said I feel it.</l>
					<l>Savr near presence. He afterw said to his Son I shall soon be in a very happy</l>
					<l>place, but continued in extream pains all Nlight till abt 5 oClock Monday Morning</l>
					<l>when his pains seem&apos;d to abate a little, &amp; he cod breathe easier, he lay compos&apos;d with</l>
					<l>an extraordinary clearness in his Countenance &amp; Eyes then Slept quite calmly for</l>
					<l>an hour, then opening his Eyes he looked very earnestly at his Son, but clos&apos;d them</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>soon again in happy final Sleep breathing his last without the least</l>
					<l>his Son says It was a happy hour to one during his Sleep &amp; departure tho</l>
					<l>I never shall forget Our Savr and so very near my heart that I cannot express</l>
					<l>&amp; am thankful to all the Brn &amp; Srs for all their Love &amp; faithfulness toward</l>
					<l>him. Our vunerable Br has thus cls&apos;d the time of his abode below in</l>
					<l>very blessed manner wch has lasted 77 Years &amp; 6 months.</l>
					<l>The W. Wd. was &quot;Thy Testimonies as are have I claim&apos;d as mine heritage</l>
					<l>for ever, &amp; why? they and the very Joy of my heart!&quot;</l>
					<l>Thy gospel &amp; its saving power, is like pure Milk &amp; honey.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
