<?xml-model href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/schema/MoravianMemoirs.xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Philip Molther: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>Repository Name</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="#">Name</msName>
						<!-- <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-03.jpg" />-->
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2019-06-10" who="#JAKA1">Updated header</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>name</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-01.jpg" n="1"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Life of brother Philip Henry Mol</l>
							<l>ther who departed at Bedford Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 9. 1780.</l>
							<l>extracted from his own manuscripts.</l>
							<l>I was born in the year 1714 Dec the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> at </l>
							<l>Imsheim in the vicinity of Bussweiler in Elsa</l>
							<l>tia where my father was the parish minister.</l>
							<l>Being 8 years old, I was sent to the school</l>
							<l>at Bussweiler with a view to lay the first</l>
							<l>foundation for studying divinity. I felt</l>
							<l>already in my infancy that the friend and</l>
							<l>Redeemer of my soul was drawing me</l>
							<l>by his grace. Tho&apos; I had many bad</l>
							<l>examples before me, I remained in inocent</l>
							<l>simplicity till in my 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year, when I </l>
							<l>was seduced into sin by one of my school</l>
							<l>fellows. Sin begat death, and my conscienc</l>
							<l>was repeatedly alarmed with this dreadful</l>
							<l>sentence: &quot;Thou art doomed to death&quot;, which</l>
							<l>caused me to feel unceasing anxiety of heart,</l>
							<l>&amp; imbittered the sinful pleasures of life to me, </l>
							<l><note type="catchword">serving</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-03.jpg" n="2"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>serving, through the kind care of the lover of my</l>
							<l>soul, as a barrier, which prevented me from</l>
							<l>rushing into misery. In the year 1734</l>
							<l>I was sent by my parents to Metz in</l>
							<l>France in order to learn the french langua</l>
							<l>Our Saviour pursued me also here by his</l>
							<l>Grace in many ways. Being once in</l>
							<l>company with my french master, I accom</l>
							<l>panied him at night to his lodgings seeming</l>
							<l>ly in good health. The next morning I was</l>
							<l>thunderstruck at hearing that he was dead,</l>
							<l>as my conscience forced immediatly this</l>
							<l>question upon me: what would have be</l>
							<l>come of you if this had been your case?</l>
							<l>I hastened to my room trembling, and</l>
							<l>throwing myself on the ground, and prayed</l>
							<l>to an unknown God for Grace and conver</l>
							<l>sion of heart from sin. But sometime</l>
							<l>after I fell again into a dilatory track.</l>
							<l>In the year 1735 I went to the university</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">at</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>

					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>at Jena, on which occasion I prayed to God with</l>
							<l>a concerned heart to preserve me from seduction</l>
							<l>and convert me. This prayer I repeated very</l>
							<l>often as I knew how hurtful bad the time</l>
							<l>was spent by the major part of the students,</l>
							<l>being afraid of falling into the same trade</l>
							<l>Soon after my arrival the late brother Daer</l>
							<l>baum went with me to the meetings of</l>
							<l>edification, held by the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d </hi>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brumhards</l>
							<l>Here I heard for the first time of Jesus</l>
							<l>readiness to receive the poorest and most</l>
							<l>miserable sinners which proved to me, a </l>
							<l>word worthy of acceptation. After the meeting</l>
							<l>I went to my lodgings and cast myself</l>
							<l>at the feet of the friend of sinners, entrea</l>
							<l>ting Him with many tears to have mercy</l>
							<l>upon me, and to assure me of my being</l>
							<l>accepted of him by delivering me from</l>
							<l>the dominions of sin in soul and body which</l>
							<l>had been on for some time a most grievous</l>
							<l>burthen to me. He caused me to look in</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">that</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-05.jpg" n="3"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>that moment believingly to Him, in a manner</l>
							<l>as I had never been able to do, and I</l>
							<l>felt that sin had been laimed maimed</l>
							<l>and lost its force. Declining the propo</l>
							<l>sal of my Father, to return home and</l>
							<l>to accept of a living, he withdrew his</l>
							<l>asistance, which on the one hand obliged</l>
							<l>me to find my support by teaching frensh</l>
							<l>but set me on the other hand at liberty</l>
							<l>from accepting my father&apos;s proposal con</l>
							<l>trary to the dictates of my heart. Christian</l>
							<l><add place="above">Renatus de</add> Zinzendorf coming in the year 1737 </l>
							<l>under the care of John Nitchman, to </l>
							<l>Jena, I had the pleasure to be his teacher</l>
							<l>in music and the frensh language.</l>
							<l>About easter the same year the late ordinar</l>
							<l>travelling through Jena, he had an enteview</l>
							<l>with all those who were employed to teach</l>
							<l>his son, and asked every one, after he had</l>
							<l>first spoke with each of us separately:</l>
							<l>Wether we were willing to devote ourselves</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">to</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>to our Saviour and the Congregation, and</l>
							<l><add place="above">were</add>desirous to be prepared for serving our Saviour</l>
							<l>Every one said yes. But the question being</l>
							<l>put to me, I answered: &quot;I am convinced</l>
							<l>that I ought to devote myself to our </l>
							<l>Saviour, and to be converted to him with</l>
							<l>my whole heart, for not doing it will</l>
							<l>render me an unfortunate man. But to</l>
							<l>be devoted to the Congregation I do not</l>
							<l>understand.&quot; He replied: &quot;It is very well,</l>
							<l>this matter is only for such as understand</l>
							<l>it, meanwhile you may continue to instruct</l>
							<l>my son&quot;. In June of the same year our </l>
							<l>Saviour was pleased to convince me, in </l>
							<l>a most striking manner of my call</l>
							<l>of to the brethren&apos;s church, which time I</l>
							<l>never shall forget. Till now I thought</l>
							<l>as is common in my circumstances, that</l>
							<l>I was bound in duty to serve my native</l>
							<l>country, which had prevented me from to </l>
							<l><note type="catchword">see</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>

					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-07.jpg" n="4"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>see or attend to our Saviour&apos;s views with me.</l>
							<l>Previous to my going to doctor Hamburgers</l>
							<l>lectures upon natural philosophy, I</l>
							<l>meditated about myself and prayed to</l>
							<l>our Saviour, who was pleased to speak</l>
							<l>to my heart and to lead me into a serious</l>
							<l>consideration concerning my past and</l>
							<l>future course. The following questions</l>
							<l>were brought home to my heart: &quot;What will</l>
							<l>become of you at last and in what manner</l>
							<l>will your studies terminate? You can&apos;t stay</l>
							<l>always at the university. If you become</l>
							<l>a minister in your native country what</l>
							<l>benefit will it be of to you on others;</l>
							<l>for if you go without being sent by me, you</l>
							<l>will be an unprofitable servant, and it</l>
							<l>may terminate with you as with other awa-</l>
							<l>kened students who did not prosper.&quot; It</l>
							<l>you will save your soul take refuge to</l>
							<l>the brethrens congregation&quot; &amp;c. These and </l>
							<l><note type="catchword">other</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>others considerations came with such clearness</l>
							<l>into my heart as if our Saviour was pre</l>
							<l>sent and speaking to me, and I was en</l>
							<l>abled to acquiesce and say amen to all,</l>
							<l>with my whole heart. Now I knew</l>
							<l>what I was about, heard and saw every</l>
							<l>thing in another light, and my eye being</l>
							<l>single the whole body was light, so that </l>
							<l>I could not help wondering at the change</l>
							<l>wrought in me. I moved with the consent</l>
							<l>of John Nitchman in the month of July</l>
							<l>into the <add place="above">house</add> of of the young count, and which was </l>
							<l>exceedingly happy in the company of the </l>
							<l>brethren. John Nitchman was betrued</l>
							<l>and respected as a father among us, and </l>
							<l>cared for the good of our souls with</l>
							<l>much love and faithfulness. Our main</l>
							<l>view was to become like little children, and </l>
							<l>such a spirit of love and zeal prevailed</l>
							<l>among us, that we sat many a night</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">till</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-09.jpg" n="5"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>till one a clock together, speaking of the </l>
							<l>state of our souls and singing praises to</l>
							<l>him, who had chosen us from before the </l>
							<l>foundation of the world, and called us</l>
							<l>from among the confusion of the learned</l>
							<l>world to his people, and to whom we</l>
							<l>now wished to devote ourselves, with heart</l>
							<l>felt joy as living sacrifices. In the year</l>
							<l>1733 we went with the young count to Berlin</l>
							<l>where his father resided, having about 70 pil</l>
							<l>grims with him. This was a blessed time </l>
							<l>for me. The singing of the brethren and </l>
							<l>Sisters and the discourses of the late ordinary</l>
							<l>were attended with unction and the demons</l>
							<l>tration of the spirit of God. Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></l>
							<l>I was received into the cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> and the 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></l>
							<l>I was admitted to the Lord&apos;s supper. </l>
							<l>Tho our lord had givin given me striking</l>
							<l>proofs of his Grace, I was yet subject</l>
							<l>to many changes. This true foundation </l>
							<l><note type="catchword">was</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>was laid in my heart, and I was delivered</l>
							<l>from sin. But being ignorant of the previ</l>
							<l>ledges our Saviour&apos;s patients are intitled</l>
							<l>to, I perplexed myself often at feeling </l>
							<l>my innate depravity and did not know</l>
							<l>how to look upon it. But now it pleased</l>
							<l>the friend of my soul to remove this by gran</l>
							<l>ting me the favor to cast a believing look</l>
							<l>upon Him as my all sufficient Saviour; for</l>
							<l>being at the comn Liturgy in deep and grate</l>
							<l>ful meditation concerning the great favor I </l>
							<l>had enjoyed in eating and drinking the flesh</l>
							<l>and blood of the son of man sacramentally,</l>
							<l>and sighing to him, to make me quite happy;</l>
							<l>he appeared in<add place="above">such</add> a most striking manner</l>
							<l>to my heart as my bleeding and suffering </l>
							<l>Redeemer, that I melted into tears like</l>
							<l>wax before the fire. From that time I </l>
							<l>proceeded from grace to grace and the</l>
							<l>connexion with Him any beloved Lord whose</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">love</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-11.jpg" n="6"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>love had captivated my heart became</l>
							<l>daily more confident, and my gracious</l>
							<l>call<add place="above">of Grace</add> to belong to the congn more impor</l>
							<l>tant and precious. Having stayed 5 months</l>
							<l>at Berlin we returned to Jena where the </l>
							<l>testimony of Jesu&apos;s Blood approved itself</l>
							<l>as the power of God to salvation upon many</l>
							<l>students and others. In the year 1739 we</l>
							<l>were called to Wetteravia, which proved a</l>
							<l>means to bring me to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at Marien</l>
							<l>born. July the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> the late Ordinary arrived</l>
							<l>from S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Thomas in the Westindies. As soon</l>
							<l>as he had saluted me he said: &quot;My brother</l>
							<l>I have spoken to our Saviour concerning</l>
							<l>you, whilst I was at sea. He has ordered</l>
							<l>me to mention to you in his name, that </l>
							<l>you are to go to Pensylvania to preach</l>
							<l>the gospel in the whole country.&quot; I replied:</l>
							<l>"Here I am may he do with me what is </l>
							<l>wellpleasing to him.&quot; Soon after I was ordai</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">ned</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>

					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>dained a Minister of the brethren&apos;s Church,</l>
							<l>and went in company with the late ordinary</l>
							<l>to a Synodal conf<hi rend="superscript">ce</hi> held at Ebersdorf. Short-</l>
							<l>ly before my setting out on my intended</l>
							<l>post, he put me to a very severe but blessed</l>
							<l>trial by saying <add place="above">before all present</add> &quot;Our brother Molter is </l>
							<l>now going to Pensylvania, there he&apos;ll perhaps </l>
							<l>meet with books wrote against us, or hear</l>
							<l>many bad things concerning the congregation</l>
							<l>which will confuse his mind and then he</l>
							<l>will go from us&quot; &amp; I answered: &quot;I can</l>
							<l>not boast of myself and make fair pro</l>
							<l>misses; but <del>one thing</del>><add place="above">this</add> I can assertain, that </l>
							<l>before I prove unfaithful to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>,</l>
							<l>I must first loose sight, and entirely for</l>
							<l>get our Saviour, nothing else can seperate</l>
							<l>me from the congregation&quot;, At this declara</l>
							<l>tion I could not refrain from tears. my</l>
							<l>answer removed his thoughtfulness concer</l>
							<l>ning me, and he dismissed me with the a</l>
							<l>kiss of love and many blessings. I now</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">went</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-13.jpg" n="7"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>went to Herrnhut, where I was much struck</l>
							<l>with the primitive simplicity of the place</l>
							<l>and the singing of all the single brethren</l>
							<l>who were just going in procession through</l>
							<l>the place when I arrived. Having enjoy</l>
							<l>ed many blessings during my abode there</l>
							<l>I returned to Marrienborn, where every</l>
							<l>thing relative to my future plan was settled</l>
							<l>and I was married to Johanna de Seydewir</l>
							<l>on the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. As circumstances </l>
							<l>required my setting out without her, she it</l>
							<l>was resolved that she should follow me, with </l>
							<l>the next company that was to go to America.</l>
							<l>Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> I sat out and arrived at</l>
							<l>London Oct. the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. As no ship was to </l>
							<l>sail <add place="above">to Pensylvania</add>till the middle of Jany I endeavoured</l>
							<l>to spend my time as useful as I could, </l>
							<l>and kept meetings to a member of Germans</l>
							<l>who had been awakened by means of the </l>
							<l>testimony of brother Richter, who <del>was</del><add place="above">had</add> de</l>
							<l>parted this life at Algier. to the english</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">brethren</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>brethren and Sisters. I kept meetings in the</l>
							<l>Latin language, having some body who inter</l>
							<l>pacted what I said into english, till I </l>
							<l>after sometime ventured to deliver discour</l>
							<l>ses in the E. language. There was at</l>
							<l>that time a Society at Fetterlane which</l>
							<l>was begun by b<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Peter Boehler and </l>
							<l>was then cared for by the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> John &amp;</l>
							<l>charles Wesly. As these people did not</l>
							<l>rightly know what they were at they were</l>
							<l>come into a strange fanatical way, so</l>
							<l>that I did not know what to think when</l>
							<l>I came for the first time into their mee</l>
							<l>tings and heard them sigh grown and howl</l>
							<l>in a very strange manner, which they cal</l>
							<l>led the demonstration of the spirit and the </l>
							<l>power of God. at speaking with the indi</l>
							<l>viduals of this society, I found many</l>
							<l>deeply concerned for their souls. As</l>
							<l>deficient as I was in expressing myself</l>
							<l>in the E. Language, they pressed me so </l>
							<l><note type="catchword">hard.</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="8">
					<head type="page">8</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-15.jpg" n="8"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Seeing that he could not obtain his aim</l>
							<l>he declined all further fellowship with the </l>
							<l>Society, and <del>stood</del> <add place="above">rising</add>from his seat with </l>
							<l>He walked out with the words: &quot;To me, all</l>
							<l>that are the Lord&apos;s&quot;. Some few followed</l>
							<l>him. Some brethren <add place="above">who</add> gave me an account</l>
							<l>of what had happened, I advised to be</l>
							<l>still, and to leave the isue to our Saviour.</l>
							<l>In August, I had the joy to welcome</l>
							<l>my wife here in London, on her way to </l>
							<l>America. It was left to me to let her</l>
							<l>proceed or keep her with me; but being</l>
							<l>convinced in my heart that it was the </l>
							<l>will of our Lord that she should go thither,</l>
							<l>and finding her willing to go, I accom</l>
							<l>panied her on board, where we prostrated</l>
							<l>in prayer before our Saviour and cove</l>
							<l>nanted with each other to be and remain</l>
							<l>his, after which we took an affectionate</l>
							<l>leave. In September I was recalled</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">from</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>from London to Marrienborn, where having</l>
							<l>stayed for some time, I was commissioned to</l>
							<l>travel into france in order to look for such</l>
							<l>as were awakened. In Paris I found</l>
							<l>some godly persons who were mysticks and</l>
							<l>valued the writings of M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Boerignor and </l>
							<l>Mrs <add place="above">Lady</add> de Guion. I also learned that there</l>
							<l>were a great many more of the same</l>
							<l>people who did not venture to make them</l>
							<l>selves known. From thence I went to Lyon</l>
							<l>Geneve by way of Lyon, here I stayed with</l>
							<l>the late Ordinary till May and enjoyed</l>
							<l>many blessings. On my road from thence</l>
							<l>to Holland I fell sick, which necessitated</l>
							<l>me to stay 10 weeks with my mother. I</l>
							<l>had no patience to wait till I was recovered,</l>
							<l>and before I reached Holland the fever</l>
							<l>had left me. In Septr I arrived at London,</l>
							<l>full of hopes and joy to pursue my destina</l>
							<l>tion to Pensylvania, but I was again seized</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">with</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="9">
					<head type="page">9</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-17.jpg" n="9"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>with another illness, so that my fellow travel</l>
							<l>lers entered upon their voyage without me. </l>
							<l>Tho&apos; it did not appear as if I should</l>
							<l>recover, I was informed by a letter that</l>
							<l>in case of my recovering I was to go</l>
							<l>against to Geneva to serve the awakened souls</l>
							<l>in that place. After 9 weeks illness I</l>
							<l>sat out for Geneva, where I <add place="above">arrived</add> after an</l>
							<l>agreeable stay of some days at Marien</l>
							<l>born, in Feb of the year 1742. I had</l>
							<l>not been there above a fortnight when</l>
							<l>I was ordered by the magistrates, who</l>
							<l>were dissatisfied with my stay there, to</l>
							<l>quit my private lodgings, and to move</l>
							<l>to an inn. Taking a journey in the coun</l>
							<l>try I fell sick again &amp; was received and</l>
							<l>treated as a servant of Christ at the house</l>
							<l>of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Elie Prendhomme, to whom I was </l>
							<l>recommended by his brother. It proved a</l>
							<l>great joy to me to see afterwards him and </l>
							<l><note type="catchword">his</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>his whole family, to whom I was is much </l>
							<l>indebted, to become children of God our Saviour.</l>
							<l>This was also the <add place="above">case</add>with the family of old</l>
							<l>father Pindent, who at another time served</l>
							<l>me in the same kind manner. About this</l>
							<l>time I ventured, in reliance upon the help</l>
							<l>of our Lord, to translate our Hymns into</l>
							<l>the frensh language and in about a years</l>
							<l>time I got 70 of them printed. In April</l>
							<l>1743 I returned to Marienborn, where I </l>
							<l>found my wife, who was arrived from Ame</l>
							<l>rica a few days before me. I received her</l>
							<l>as if she was given me quite anew by our</l>
							<l>Saviour. After some time we travelled toge</l>
							<l>ther to the Synod, which was held at Hirsch</l>
							<l>berg. there we were appointed to visit the</l>
							<l>awakened souls in Switzerland. This jour</l>
							<l>ney proved very agreeable to us both. When</l>
							<l>we were tired of walking we sat down in</l>
							<l>a lonely spot and sung a verse, feeling excee</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">dingly</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="10">
					<head type="page">10</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-19.jpg" n="10"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>dingly well thereat. In a town called Speyer</l>
							<l>where the whole frensh armee was quartered,</l>
							<l>we had a narrow escape of being killed,</l>
							<l>being nearly trodden under foot, by the</l>
							<l>horsemen who came from both sides upon us</l>
							<l>when we were just under the gate. In</l>
							<l>the critical moment, when nothing seemed</l>
							<l>to offer for our relief, I espied a little</l>
							<l>space between the horses, and snatching my </l>
							<l>wife into my arms I slipped through,</l>
							<l>wondering at and thanking our Lord for his</l>
							<l>kind protection. Nov 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I settled the in</l>
							<l>habitants of Montmirail-house into a cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></l>
							<l>but after some time it was broke up again,</l>
							<l>as we met with opposition in Switzerland</l>
							<l>and were even forbid to reside any more</l>
							<l>at Geneva. We now returned again in July </l>
							<l>1745 to Marienborn. In about the time of</l>
							<l>a year we went again into Switzerland, and</l>
							<l><add place="above">where besides my former office</add> I had also to care for the housekeeping, besides</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">this</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>this and the journies into the country I was</l>
							<l>employed in translating the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> accounts</l>
							<l>into the frensh language, as also with revi</l>
							<l>sing the hymns I had translated sometime</l>
							<l>ago and adding more hymns to them, which </l>
							<l>labour proved a refreshment to my heart.</l>
							<l>As circumstances required again our remo</l>
							<l>val from Montmirail, we met in the hall</l>
							<l>for the last time to thank our Saviour for</l>
							<l>all the grace he had given us to enjoy in</l>
							<l>this place. I arrived at Herrnhaag (in</l>
							<l>company of the frensh brethren and Sisters</l>
							<l>from Montmirail) in the last days of sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></l>
							<l>of the year 1748. My stay here was not</l>
							<l>agreeable to me, as I did not like the then</l>
							<l>course of that cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. I therefore kept retired</l>
							<l>and in stillness. These circumstances caused</l>
							<l>me to search my own heart thoroughly, the</l>
							<l>conclusion of which was, that our Lord was plea</l>
							<l>sed to give me a renewed impression of my </l>
							<l><note type="catchword">election</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="11">
					<head type="page">11</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-21.jpg" n="11"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>election of grace. In 1749 we were in </l>
							<l>Holland and England with the late ordinary,</l>
							<l>in whose house we spent the time very blessedly</l>
							<l>In 1750 we went to Barby, in hopes that</l>
							<l>the frensh brethren and sisters who were</l>
							<l>obliged to emigrate with the rest of the b<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></l>
							<l>and s<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> from Herrnhaag, would find it prac</l>
							<l>ticable to settle there. Meanwhile the </l>
							<l>Count of Neuwied altered to receive them</l>
							<l>in his Dominions and to grant them liberty</l>
							<l>of conscience. The late Ordinary having</l>
							<l>had an interview with the count of Neu</l>
							<l>wied, previous to his arival at Barby,</l>
							<l>he acquainted me, that he had found a place</l>
							<l>for the frensh b<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; s<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> and viz: Neuwied,</l>
							<l>and told me to prepare for my journey</l>
							<l>thither. In sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> I went to Herrnhaag</l>
							<l>and from thence with some of the frensh</l>
							<l>brethren and sisters to Neuwied, where we</l>
							<l>arrived Oct the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Soon after the remain</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">der</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>der of them <del>frensh</del> brethren &amp; Sisters arrived</l>
							<l>with us, after which we all partook of the holy</l>
							<l>Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at which our Saviours grace was power</l>
							<l>ful among us. We lived at first together </l>
							<l>in one house as one family. Love, simplicity,</l>
							<l>and grace and truth ruled among us, and </l>
							<l>He who regardeth the ready and poor, walked</l>
							<l>in our midst and the peace of God rested</l>
							<l>upon this cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. What trials of faith and</l>
							<l>patience we had to experience during the </l>
							<l>first 4 years is only known to our Saviour,</l>
							<l>but his faithfulness and support was our</l>
							<l>only dependence. These trials were the conse</l>
							<l>quence of our moving to Neuwied before</l>
							<l>matters had been finally settled with the </l>
							<l>count of Neuwied, for a deportation which</l>
							<l>treated afterwards with him in behalf of </l>
							<l>the unity returned after a stay of 3 weeks </l>
							<l>without being able to conclude upon anything,</l>
							<l>and we were left upon a very uncertain lasting</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">mean-</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="12">
					<head type="page">12</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-23.jpg" n="12"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>meanwhile occurred the wellknown hard trials</l>
							<l>in England, so that the brethren had no time</l>
							<l>to think of our settling here upon a sure footing,</l>
							<l>and upon all the letters we wrote during</l>
							<l>the space of 18 months, we received no answer</l>
							<l>All the newspapers were filled with the</l>
							<l>most bitter speeches against us, which were</l>
							<l>often repeated at our windows by persons who</l>
							<l>were evil inclined. We laid our heavy cir</l>
							<l>cumstances before our Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> who formed the </l>
							<l>unanimous resolution to hold our with cou</l>
							<l>rage and patience as long as possible.</l>
							<l>In the spring of 1753 the late ordinary sent</l>
							<l>a letter to the count of Neuwied importing,</l>
							<l>that his present circumstances made it im</l>
							<l>practicable for him, to assist the establish</l>
							<l>ment of a frensh Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at Neuwied, and</l>
							<l><del>that</del> <add place="above">the</add> people who had moved thither with </l>
							<l>that intent would probably be obliged to </l>
							<l>return to Switzerland. The Count expressed</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">his</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>his compassion <add place="above">for</add><del>with</del> us and encouraged us</l>
							<l>by saying: &quot;God can still give this matter</l>
							<l>a favourable turn and bring it to bear.&quot;</l>
							<l>In Nov. It was resolved in a Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Council</l>
							<l>to send a deputy to London, who was to procure</l>
							<l>a final resolution wether we were to stay</l>
							<l>here or to move away; but our deputy falling</l>
							<l>very ill at Teist we were obliged to be</l>
							<l>patient. In July 1754 we received the long</l>
							<l>wished for message, wich put an end to all</l>
							<l>our <add place="above">concern</add> that the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> was to stay at</l>
							<l>Neuwied, to build proper habitations and</l>
							<l>was to be augmented. The word of the day</l>
							<l>when I received this account form London</l>
							<l>(viz. July the 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>) was: &quot;The glory of the Lord</l>
							<l>shall be revealed, and all flesh shall ice it</l>
							<l>together: for the mouth of the Lord has spoken</l>
							<l>it.&quot; It is not possible to describe what joy</l>
							<l>this account occassioned in the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. All</l>
							<l>praised and adored the Lord for his kindness</l>
							<l>towards us. Our concession being drawn, up</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">and</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="13">
					<head type="page">13</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-25.jpg" n="13"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>and signed in 1755, we began to prepare for</l>
							<l>building and in 3 years time the hall and </l>
							<l>2 Choir houses for the s<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> b<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; s<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> were fini</l>
							<l>shed and sundry houses and gardens bought. </l>
							<l>The congregation encreased so fast that the</l>
							<l>number of souls amounted at the</l>
							<l>end of 1760 to 202. December the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1758.</l>
							<l>the cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> was settled by brother Johannes,</l>
							<l>&amp; the meeting hall concecrated. <del>and</del> In April</l>
							<l>1761 having been releas&apos;d from my office</l>
							<l>by brother Risler, we sat out for Herrnhut</l>
							<l>where we<add place="above">arrived</add> after a difficult journey. </l>
							<l>Thus far our late brother. </l>
							<l>He stayed with his wife about a year in</l>
							<l>Herrnhut from whence he was called to have </l>
							<l>the care of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at Dublin, where they </l>
							<l>arrived in the som summer of of 1762, previous</l>
							<l>to which they had brought their 3 sons to Cath</l>
							<l>rinenhatt, to be educated in the childrens Oec<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>.</l>
							<l>In 1767 he was called to Bedford to be </l>
							<l>the Minister and Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> helper in that Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></l>
							<l>It is sufficiently known from the reports of </l>
							<l><note type="catchword">that</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>that Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> with wat what unction and grace he</l>
							<l>served it. In 1775 he was called to the Synod</l>
							<l>at Barby and consecrated a Bishop</l>
							<l>of the brethren&apos;s Church. Before he returned</l>
							<l>to Bedford he visited his children in Uper</l>
							<l>Lusatia and Silivia and the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at Neu</l>
							<l>wied (where his former services are still remembe</l>
							<l>red with gratitude). He returned from thence</l>
							<l>by way of Teist to Bedford, where he arrived</l>
							<l>dec the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. From that time his strength de</l>
							<l>cayed and he grew mostly blind. In 1779</l>
							<l>he got a stroke of the palsy which lamed his</l>
							<l>right side. about a year after he had another </l>
							<l>attack of the same disorder which showed</l>
							<l>plainly that he was mean his end. He</l>
							<l>behaved himself under all these afflictions</l>
							<l>as a servant of Christ and expressed his</l>
							<l>joy at the prospect of being soon at home</l>
							<l>with the Lord, in short he was in </l>
							<l>last illness an edificiation and blessing to</l>
							<l><note type="catchword">all</note></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>

				<div type="page" n="14">
					<head type="page">14</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-27.jpg" n="14"/>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>all around him till he fell asleep in the </l>
							<l>Lord septr the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1780 in the 66<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year of</l>
							<l>his age.</l>
							<l>He lived 41 years in the married state and</l>
							<l>has had 7 children, of which 2 sons and</l>
							<l>one daughter are still alive.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
