<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Elizabeth Bethell: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p/>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
</rdf:RDF></xenoData><profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Elizabeth Bethell</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			
				<head>Elizabeth Bethell</head>
				<div n="1" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300006-01.jpg" n="1"/><p>1783. </p><p>Leominster ArchivesCourse of Life of our late Maid Sister Eliz: Bethell from her ownhand Writing.</p><p>I was born May the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1754 in the Town of Monmouth where my Father was placed as Officer in the Excise, &amp; in my third Year my Father was removed to Leominster in Herefordshire; When I was about Six Years old, my Aunt took me to her into Shropshire; She had no Child of her own, &amp; was tender to me; My Unkle was of a rough disposition and subject to swear very much, which made me think God would not love him; for <del>if</del> I thought if I did once Swear I sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> go to the bad Place, &amp; I often would go to the retir'd part of the Garden to pray to God to keep me from the place where bad Children were sent to. I was very fond of reading Books that mentiond anything about God; at last my Aunt began to be uneasy about me, &amp; thought I was not playfull enough like other Children: In my 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Year my Mother came for me, &amp; took me home that I might have better Education; This was a hurt to me, &amp; I soon got a Love for pleasure, &amp; vain amusements &amp;quite forgot my religious Course; My Mother was exceding fond of me &amp; often would remind me what a reward was promised to those that love God; but the ever faithfull friend of Sinners knew how to make my pleasant days bitter, by taking from me my tender, &amp; Affectionate Mother in a few Months after I came home; this was a great trial to me, &amp; the holy <del>Ghost</del> <add place="above">Spirit</add> showed me how I had Sinned against God in getting out of the simple track I was in, in my youngerYears; I often called to mind how my dear Mother on her death Bed cryed out Dear Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> come &amp; take me; &amp; in a short time he took her to himself without Sigh or groan: I found I had now lost a good Friend, &amp; had it more difficult in many respects; This was a means of stirring up my thoughts to a religious Course, &amp; I was glad to get into any Corner I could to pray to God; &amp; I often wish'd to return again to my Aunt, &amp; carried a Book in my Pocket to be ready to go at any time; In a short time I became so distress'd about my Salvation that I would freely have given my body to have saved my Soul from the Misery w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> I expected the Lord would lay upon me: I was now about 14 Years old; and my distress encreasing I once went into the Fields, &amp; wander'd about where there was no Path for </p></div><div n="2" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300006-02.jpg" n="2"/><p>any one to see me &amp; stay'd until it was dark: At another time theEnemy put such thoughts into my Head, as I saw no likelyhood  likelihood of myfinding happiness on Earth, I would therefore take the first Opportunity ofputting an end to my Life; and I went one day by the Water Side to com-pleat  plete my Wicked Intention; but the ever faithfull  faithful Friend of Sinners stillwatched over me, &amp; prevented my wicked design: I returned home withShame, &amp; true Repentance, begging of the Lord to put all such thoughtsfar from me, &amp; to look in Mercy on my afflicted Soul; A few Nights afterI dreamed that I was in my Fathers Garden, &amp; was sighing &amp; bemoaningmy distress of heart, &amp; I thought I heard a great Noise, &amp; looking uptowards the Sky I thought I saw numbers of Angels coming towards mewch lighted down by me, so that the Walk where I was was full; they were asI thought all dressed in white, &amp; I was the same , they had each of them twoWings wch I thought grew out of each Shoulder, but I thought I had none; Aftera short time spent in singing, &amp; a Sweet harmony of Musick  Music, I thoughtall those happy Spirits went to a fine Pool of Water wch was in a Meadow,&amp; I went with them, &amp; I thought we all washed our Feet; And after thatthey all flew up, &amp; I was left alone: I then got more easy in my Mind, &amp;thought I might take it for granted that God would forgive me my Sinsor I should not have had such a pleasant dream: I soon forgot to whomI was to look for preservation, &amp; got into a very Self working Strain forsometime. In my 22d Year was marrd to my present Husband, in thisnew State I was more Introduc'd to Company &amp; Pleasure, but still kept Self-righteousness very close to me; but at length I grew that I could mix -Religion &amp; the pleasures of the World together. I had a very tender and Affectionate Husband, &amp; I went on in my unhappy State very easy for about4 Years. (after I was marry'd  married) about wch time I went to hear the Brn now &amp;then, &amp; I soon began to Wish to be in some connexion  connection with them, wch wasgranted me, my dear Savr soon shewed me how filthy all my self righteousnessappeared, &amp; that nothing but being washed in the blood of the Lamb wouldmake me happy: The enemy of Man now began to Roar, &amp; great uneasiness</p></div><div n="3" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300006-03.jpg" n="3"/><p>arose on account of my leaving the Church; this was a time of great trialunto me: I saw I could not please God &amp; Mammon, &amp; our dear Savr gaveme the Grace to make choice of him, &amp; leave all other troubles to his direction.On Christmas Day 1781. I had the Grace to be recd into the Congn; &amp; on the13th of Aug: 1782. our dear Lord permitted me to be Spectator at the holyComn with the Congn in London the first time, wch blessed time I shall neverforget; Our dear Savrs Presence was so near me, that he appeared to meas hanging in his crucified form before my Eyes; I never can thank &amp;adore him enough for his unbounded Love to me the chief of Sinners,who makes such small returns, &amp; proves so ungratefull  ungrateful for such boundlessLove wch he bestows on me his poorest Creature: Soon after my returnhome from London I was taken ill, &amp; the Lamb that was Crucified -without the Gates of Jerusalem, that Friend of Sinners never withdrewhis sweet nearness from me during my Confinement; at wch time Irecd his Body &amp; Blood in the holy Comn for the first time on my SickBed to my Souls comfort: This memorial day was the 14th of October1782. Since wch time I have had repeated Seals of his Love; O grant I mayalways remain as a poor Sinner at his Feet</p><p>Thus far her own Account.</p><p>In our late Sisters heavy Sickness which begun last October ourLord supported her in a very gracious manner, &amp; many of her Friends&amp; Acquaintance who had been much against her were now quite over-come, &amp; agreeably Struck with her sereene  serene &amp; happy disposition of heart&amp; that Peace of God which was felt ruling in her heart; and the simplereal &amp; unaffected Confession of what our dear Savr is to a poor Creaturewho believes in him made a good Impression on many, and wch we hope -will not be forgotten: When at times she was better she attended the Meetingsdilligently  diligently, &amp; indeed often recover'd to our Surprize  Surprise; was particularlythankfull  thankful for being able to attend the Meetings when Br La Trobe was hereand to hear the Synod read, &amp; took it as a favour &amp; Gift from our Savr;Was much concern'd for her two Children (the younger being deaf &amp; dumb) that</p></div><div n="4" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300006-04.jpg" n="4"/><p>they might be preserv'd for our Savr; &amp; her whole desire was that they mightbe under the Care of the Brethen  Brethren, &amp; spoke fully thereon with her Husband &amp;Father. In the last Period of her Sickness which lastd about 3 Weeks, &amp; wasvery afflicting She had still to learn in the School of the H Ghost what a poorCreature she was, &amp; to be Stript  Stripped of every thing but Jesus &amp; his Mood; About14 Days before her departure when the extremity of Pain had brot her -almost to distraction, &amp; wherein the comfort from our Savr was not so clearto her heart; She was afterwards enabled to rejoice the more in the feeling of his graciousPresence &amp; Peace, and desired the Brn &amp; Srs to thank our Savr for what he had donefor Her, wch was done with a gratefull  grateful Impression: The same Evening beingagain able to speak she sent for Br &amp; Sr Mortimer &amp; spoke very heartilywith them, told them She had spoke fully with her Husband &amp; Father regardingthe Children &amp;c. Was Sinnerlike &amp; loving &amp; our hearts tenderly united to thankour Lord for all Mercy bestow'd on her, &amp; that he would still graciously Accom-plish all his Thoughts of Peace in her &amp; with her. On the 29th which was herlast she express'd her self very lovingly to all about her, and then said:O thou Lamb of God which takest away the Sin of the World thou hast alsotook away mine, &amp; wilt receive me bad as I am: Said to those about herHe has taken away my hearing, but has given me my Speech to tell Youhe will receive me. She then said: Thou hast made my Bed soft, whilethou diedst on the Ignominious Free; Thy Head was crown'd with ThornsThy Back plow'd with deep Furrows &amp;c. We could perceive almost toher last, or as long as she was able to aim at speaking it was about theSufferings &amp; death of our gracious Saviour: Her last moments wereaccompanied with our heart Prayers, beseeching our dear Lord to bless and toreceive this his redeemed Soul; who now enter'd into his everlasting Restin the 30th Year of this dying Life. </p></div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>