<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memoir</title>
                <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
                <principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
                </principal>
                <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Project Manager</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Developer</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
</rdf:RDF></xenoData></teiHeader>
    
    <text type="memoir" xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <head>Elizabeth Chambers</head>
            <div n="1" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-01.jpg" n="1"></pb><p>The Widow S.r Eliz. Chambers late Lewis who departed this life Apr. 6th 1802 at Fulneck &amp; has left the following Account of herself.</p><p>I was born in Bath April 27th 1765 baptiz'd in the church of England. In my childrens years I constantly attented the meetings of the Brethren, which my parents had no objection to.</p><p>I cannot remember that in those years I had any particular impression of our Savior in my heart. In my thirteenth year I was received among the great girls; at this time I began to reflect seriously on my eternal happiness, and of the greati mportance of living for our dear Savior in this world who out of love to my Soul procured my Salvation at no less price, then the shedding every drop of his most precious blood, that I might be happy here in time, and to all eternity. Many thanks are due</p></div><div n="2" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-02.jpg" n="2"></pb><p>to Him, that with unwearied patience he has sought and followed me to the present day, amidst many dangers and temptations which I was in my younger years expes'd unto indeed in my period of my past life, I can trace the mercy and goodness of my faithful Redeemer in bringing me his poor lost sheep by nature, among the Sheep fold of his my language now is:</p><p>Had He not sought me, and followed over I ne'er had sought Him had known him never </p><p>Who is like Him.</p><p>As a Girl I experienced our Saviors love in my heart, and firmly believed that He died on the cross to redeem me; and at times I was inabled thro his grace to look on the world, and the things of it, as nothing worth, when put in competition with what was to be enjoyed in the Lord, and among his people, thus I went on for some years very happy and cheerful in my course, not knowing as yet any thing of myself and the depravity that lies in human nature.</p><p>Jan 14th 1783 I was received into the Cong.n this was a day of peculiar blessing to my poort heart, I surrendered  myself</p></div><div n="3" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-03.jpg" n="3"></pb><p>myself anew to Him, who knew I had no other wish, but to be devoted to Him, with Soul and Body; I earnestly prayed to the Lord, that as he had given me leave to attain to this favor He would also Keep and preserve me, amidst the many spares, I was then surrounded with, and which to young minds without grace, was very pleasant and agreeable to be caught with, being in some measure conscious of my natural lively disposition. I often felt afraid, lest I should please the world, and the world should please me, as I felt at times, that things that were diametrically opposite to our Savior, had a very near access to my heart, this caused me to take shelter under the shadow of his wings, finding that in myself I had no power to resist temptations of any kind; such was my unseen friends faithfulness toward me, that whenever I entered into any thing that was contrary to His mind, and inconsistent with my profession, as a child of God, it was as if I heard Him say, by the voice of his holy Spirit in my heart; That is not the path I've appointed for you to walk in, you have once devoted yourself up to me with Soul and Body, and will</p></div><div n="4" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-04.jpg" n="4"></pb><p>you now pursue that path, that leadeth unto death; - In December the same year it pleased our dear Savior to call into eternal rest my dear mother. Her dissolution prov'd a real blessing to me; - She often beg'd me to price my happy lot of grace in belonging to the Brn Congn and to thank the Lord for calling me when young to a Knowledge of Himself, whom to know is life eternal, indeed her admonitions and advice will never be forgot by me. -</p><p>May 12th 1785 I was confirmed for the first enjoyment of the holy Comn byBr John Moore; I was the First Sister in Bath that was confirmed after the manner laid down in the Synod of 1782. This solemn act made an incredible impression on my heart, and the feeling of our dear Lord's precious nearness was sensibly felt by all present. During this transaction I felt so happy that I wish to retain the same Sensation throughout my life, but I had much to learn, having as yet not learnt to Know my depraved state by nature.</p><p>May 15th 1785 I partook for the first </p></div><div><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-05.jpg" n="5"></pb></div><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div><pb></pb><p/></div><div><pb></pb><p/></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>