<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memoir</title>
                <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
                <principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
                </principal>
                <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Project Manager</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Developer</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
</rdf:RDF></xenoData></teiHeader>
    
    <text type="memoir" xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <head>Elizabeth Chambers</head>
            <div n="1" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-01.jpg" n="1"></pb><p>The Widow S.r Eliz. Chambers late Lewis who departed this life Apr. 6th 1802 at Fulneck &amp; has left the following Account of herself.</p><p>I was born in Bath April 27th 1765 baptiz'd in the church of England. In my childrens years I constantly attented the meetings of the Brethren, which my parents had no objection to.</p><p>I cannot remember that in those years I had any particular impression of our Savior in my heart. In my thirteenth year I was received among the great girls; at this time I began to reflect seriously on my eternal happiness, and of the greati mportance of living for our dear Savior in this world who out of love to my Soul procured my Salvation at no less price, then the shedding every drop of his most precious blood, that I might be happy here in time, and to all eternity. Many thanks are due</p></div><div n="2" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-02.jpg" n="2"></pb><p>to Him, that with unwearied patience he has sought and followed me to the present day, amidst many dangers and temptations which I was in my younger years expes'd unto indeed in my period of my past life, I can trace the mercy and goodness of my faithful Redeemer in bringing me his poor lost sheep by nature, among the Sheep fold of his my language now is:</p><p>Had He not sought me, and followed over I ne'er had sought Him had known him never </p><p>Who is like Him.</p><p>As a Girl I experienced our Saviors love in my heart, and firmly believed that He died on the cross to redeem me; and at times I was inabled thro his grace to look on the world, and the things of it, as nothing worth, when put in competition with what was to be enjoyed in the Lord, and among his people, thus I went on for some years very happy and cheerful in my course, not knowing as yet any thing of myself and the depravity that lies in human nature.</p><p>Jan 14th 1783 I was received into the Cong.n this was a day of peculiar blessing to my poort heart, I surrendered  myself</p></div><div n="3" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-03.jpg" n="3"></pb><p>myself anew to Him, who knew I had no other wish, but to be devoted to Him, with Soul and Body; I earnestly prayed to the Lord, that as he had given me leave to attain to this favor He would also Keep and preserve me, amidst the many spares, I was then surrounded with, and which to young minds without grace, was very pleasant and agreeable to be caught with, being in some measure conscious of my natural lively disposition. I often felt afraid, lest I should please the world, and the world should please me, as I felt at times, that things that were diametrically opposite to our Savior, had a very near access to my heart, this caused me to take shelter under the shadow of his wings, finding that in myself I had no power to resist temptations of any kind; such was my unseen friends faithfulness toward me, that whenever I entered into any thing that was contrary to His mind, and inconsistent with my profession, as a child of God, it was as if I heard Him say, by the voice of his holy Spirit in my heart; That is not the path I've appointed for you to walk in, you have once devoted yourself up to me with Soul and Body, and will</p></div><div n="4" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-04.jpg" n="4"></pb><p>you now pursue that path, that leadeth unto death; - In December the same year it pleased our dear Savior to call into eternal rest my dear mother. Her dissolution prov'd a real blessing to me; - She often beg'd me to price my happy lot of grace in belonging to the Brn Congn and to thank the Lord for calling me when young to a Knowledge of Himself, whom to know is life eternal, indeed her admonitions and advice will never be forgot by me. -</p><p>May 12th 1785 I was confirmed for the first enjoyment of the holy Comn byBr John Moore; I was the First Sister in Bath that was confirmed after the manner laid down in the Synod of 1782. This solemn act made an incredible impression on my heart, and the feeling of our dear Lord's precious nearness was sensibly felt by all present. During this transaction I felt so happy that I wish to retain the same Sensation throughout my life, but I had much to learn, having as yet not learnt to Know my depraved state by nature.</p><p>May 15th 1785 I partook for the first </p></div><div><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-05.jpg" n="5"></pb><p>time of the Lords Body and blood in the holy Sacrament with the Bath Congn.The text for the day was as follows.</p><p>Oh Lord out thy light and thy truth, let them lead me, let them bring me unto thy holy hill, and to thy tabernacles</p><p>and the Antiphon:</p><lg><l>Lord Jesus Christ my life and and light</l><l>O let in every place</l><l>Thy sounds to me. Thine clear &amp; bright</l><l>And guide my Ages and ways.</l></lg><p>At this divine apart I cannot say I felt so happy, as I thought I should, this distressd me very much, as I wanted to enjoy still more happiness than at my confirmation, but I have since learnt  learned thro'our Savior's grace to be satisfied with what I am, a poor supplicant that approaches His table, having nothing to bring, but sin and misery, and to be content with the smalest blessing that he imparts. In Novr the same year it pleas'd our dear Lord to take home my dear Father rather suddenly, this wasa very heavy stroke to me, but my faithful Savior supported me admist all my trials. What shall I render unto</p></div><div n="6" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-06.jpg" n="6"></pb><p>Him for all his goodness and mercies bestowed on me, the least deserving of all his creations! The best reason for one like me, so wretched and so poor Is from his gifts to draw a plea, and ask Him still for more.</p><p>I had often felt a desire to leave the situation I was placed in - which was a very gay one - and retire from the noisy busy crowd to the calm and safe retreat of a far House in a place Congn, where I thought I could live more according to my Savior's mind, and not have so many things to draw me aside from Him, these thoughts were certainly right; but still I did not Know what a Self I had to take with me, and that I was going to a real and blessed school for my heart; for I had much to learn; In March 1789 I made my desire Known to my laboress that I should like to live in a Srs House, told her I had my choice to live in a place Congn; accordingly the Elder Contce wrote immediately to Fairfield as they wished me very much to leave the gay Town Bath. The answer soon came</p></div><div n="7" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-07.jpg" n="7"></pb><p>came that I had leave to come and live in the Srs House in Fairfield. I then began to repent. I had ever mentioned anything of the Kind, feeling myself very tenderly attached to my Brother who was 6 years younger than myself, having promis'd my parents that I would care for him untill  he had ended his apprenticeship of which he had 3 years to serve, but such was my faithful shepherds came over me that which on the one hand, affection towards my Brother drew me, yet on the other hand, I felt that I must now proceed in the path my Savior had appointed, Altho I had a great struggle in my mind to give all things up. April 15th 1789 I set out for Fairfield, and on the 18th I arrived safe and well at my destin'd place, here I was received in much love by all the Srs; the first year I spent here was very happy and chearful, untill  until the year 1790, a period of my life begun which I cannot pass over, and which will never be forgot by me; our Savior was pleased to show me what a very poor creature I was by nature, in such a manner that indeed I thought at times I should lose my Senses; darkness and despair</p></div><div n="8" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-08.jpg" n="8"></pb><p>caused me to carry my reasoning so far, as to think that what I had enjoy'd of the love of Jesus in my heart was merely the effect of fancy surely said I if it was reality; how is it possible that I am now so heaged in on every Side, and cannot see my one beam of hope; one ray of light, to comfort my poor afflicted mind. I often repeated that verse:</p><lg><l>If I love, why am I thus!</l><l>Why this dark, dejected frame!</l><l>Hardly sure, can they be worse</l><l>Who have never heard thy name.</l></lg><p>I thus went on for some months, not knowing which way to turn, and to the Lord I had no access; like the children of Israel, I often look'd back; and wish'd I had never Known Fairfield, nor the Brn Congn. In this distress'd situation of heart, I frequently visited my Laboress who always incouraged me to turn to our Savior with all my sin &amp; misery and that in his own good time He would help me thro' the many difficulties I had now to struggle with, it appeard to me impossible ever to get help from</p></div><div n="9" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300010-09.jpg" n="9"></pb><p>any source, so as to be brought into that happy track I had once been in. But adored be my Saviors name that He has had patience with me his poor wandering sheep: On Whitesunday the same year, having been appointed an intercessor for the first time, when Keeping my hour in a field by the Srs House, it was as if the Lord spoke to me, and said "I will be..troth thee unto me for ever." Those words prov'd very comfortable to my poor unhappy heart, and altho the load, under which I had for a long time labour'd was in some measure remev'd[?], yet I often thought and reasoned whether those words were the operation of the holy Spirit, or merely my own fancy, as I always think it a nice point to distinguish nature from grace, but my Savior enabled me to lay hold of that, and more of his precious promises,which to weary and heavy laden Sinners - such as I now feel myself - proves strength, and consolation; I could now feel the clouds were dispersing, and that I could take refuge to the Lord when storms were beginning to rise, on Him</p></div><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div/><div><pb></pb><p/></div><div><pb></pb><p/></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>