<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memoir</title>
                <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
                <principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
                </principal>
                <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Project Manager</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Developer</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
</rdf:RDF></xenoData></teiHeader>
    
    <text type="memoir" xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <head>Anna Louisa Eleanora Foster</head>
            <div n="1" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-01.jpg" n="1"/><p><hi rend="underline">Title: Memoir of the life of the married Sister Anna Louisa Eleonora Foster, maiden name Latrobe - who departed July 27th 1824 at Bedford, in the 63rd year of her age.</hi></p><p>Our late S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> not having left any written Memoir of her own life, the following has been compiled partly from Memorandums, furnished by her surviving husband &amp; her children, &amp; partly from Extracts of her very extensive &amp; interesting correspondence with some of her children &amp; other friends. She was the eldest daughter of our late highly respected B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; [Sr??] Benjamin Latrobe, &amp; was born Nov<hi rend="superscript">br</hi> 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1761 at Fulnec where her parents were at that time labourers of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>, &amp; by whom she was devoted at her birth, so that Saviour who created and  redeemed her. She was baptized by her late dear father into the death of Jesus. At an early age her parents placed her in the Institution for the Education of the children of the Ministers of the B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> church in that Settlement. When about 8 years of age, her father was called to be Provincial Helper of the Engl. Cong<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi>, &amp; removed to London; in consequence of which she was deprived of enjoying the immediate constant care &amp; tuition of her parents. She was from her earliest years of a serious reflecting turn of mind, &amp; soon showed talents far above her years. She especially took great pleasure in reading &amp; meditating upon the word of God, which was ever after the delight of her heart, as she found therein, thro' the Spirits teaching rich food for her soul.Often has she related with great interest &amp; heartfelt thankfulness to our Saviour, that while still a child, she was led by the operations of the Holy Spirit to a deep knowledge &amp; conviction of sin; so that even at that early period a solid awakening took place in her; for feeling herself to be a great sinner, she then already sought &amp; found grace in the blood of Jesus, &amp; devoted herself to Him, as His eternal property.To this grace she ever after remained faithful, and as she advanced in years she became more &amp; more established &amp; grounded in the faith of the Son of God, &amp; gradually learned more fully the lessons of His redeeming love, sitting with Mary at Jesus' feet &amp; humbly listening to His gracious words. She attained at an early period of life to the privilege of the B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; often spoke with much feeling of the blessing she enjoyed when for the first time she partook of the communion with the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. This was to her a truly happy hour of grace, she beheld by faith the countenance of her Saviour, who then unparted Himself to her &amp; made a covenant never to be forgotten, <note type="catchword">yea</note></p></div><div n="2" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-02.jpg" n="2"/><p>yea an everlasting covenant with her. Her feelings on this solemn occasion are beautifully expressed in our hymnbook N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 750 - "Great the feast, to which thou Lord hast bidden &amp;&amp;&amp;. - Such a worthless worm as me &amp;&amp;&amp; - At the early age of 16, before she entered into the Choir of S<hi rend="superscript">le</hi> Sisters, she was employed in the care &amp; instruction of the children in the Girls Boarding-School at Fulnec, in which employment she displayed great capacity &amp; the most disinterested &amp; persevering faithfulness, often labouring beyond her strength, &amp; ever willing to spend &amp; to be spent in her Lord's service - During the 8 years she was thus engaged, she was universally beloved &amp; respected by all her pupils &amp; had the pleasure to to see her exertions in their behalf attended with success. She possessed an admirable gift of bringing them forward in their various branches of learning, as many of them even now testify with gratitude; but what lay nearest to her heart, was - that she might be enabled to lead them, as the work of <hi rend="underline">His</hi> hands, to their creator &amp; redeemer, &amp; impress their tender minds with a sense of His love to children. During this period her health which was always delicate, tho' she possessed a sound constitution, frequently suffered, which was partly the consequence of over-exertion in the discharge of her duties. In more instances than one a decline was apprehended but a visit to her parents in London proved the means of restoring her strength &amp; spirits, &amp; enabled her to return with renewed vigour &amp; assiduity to the work allotted to her, &amp; to continue in the performance of it, which amidst many trials, discouragements &amp; severe exercises, she constantly looked up to the Lord for His blessing which she richly enjoyed. In 1786 her dear &amp; much respected father was called home to rest with the Lord from his labours. She was present on  the mournful occasion &amp; received his farewell blessing. This event affected her very deeply. On May 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1787 she was married to her surviving husband, our dear B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frederic William Foster, according to the gracious leading of our Lord, &amp; soon after they removed to London, B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Foster having been appointed Secretary to the English Provincial Helpers, the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> Wollin &amp; Tho<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> Moore. In 1789 they travelled together to Germany &amp; attended the General Synod, held at Herrnhut with real blessing &amp; profit. On their return to England they received an appointment as aspirants in the service of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at Bedford, where they remained till 1793 having for the last year of their stay there, the entire care of that Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> committed to them as B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Yarrel had become wholly incapacitated by illness. Wyke was the next sphere of their labours &amp; during their abode in that place, their 4 children were born, &amp; by their parents from their birth, devoted to that Lord, at whose hands they received them as a precious gift. In 1794 she was deeply afflicted by the departure of her beloved mother, who had at the close of the foregoing year, spent several weeks with her at Wyke, &amp; had been present at the birth of her eldest daughter, at which time she proved a great comfort &amp; support to our dear late Sister. <note type="catchword">In</note></p></div><div n="3" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-03.jpg" n="3"/><p>In her distress in consequence of this painful bereavement she turned to the Lord &amp; His consolations powerfully supported her &amp; alleviated the pungent grief occasioned by the loss of her only surviving &amp; tenderly beloved parent. Some years after she had also the grief to lose her mother-in law, whom she had always loved with much affection &amp; had been in return beloved by her; so much the more painfully did this renewed bereavement afflict her, in which she participated in the most sympathizing manner with her husband. In consequence of a severe cold caught on her return from the continent in 1789 she had for some time after been in so precarious a state of health, as frequently  to cause her relations &amp; friends great uneasiness. During her stay at Wyke she appeared however to have regained her usual strength. The natural vigour of her constitution enabled her to struggle thro' repeated serious illnesses, some of which brought her apparently to the brink of the grave; yet the Lord raised her up from time to time to the joy &amp; comfort of her husband &amp; children. When confined by illness &amp; looking forward to the probability of her dissolution, she was always calm &amp; composed, her mind being stayed on the Lord, &amp; resigned to His will for life &amp; for death.In 1800 she &amp; husband were called to the service of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at Fairfield &amp; our late Sister entered with cheerfulness &amp; zeal into the more extensive field for labour in his vineyard, now allotted to her. Amidst many trials incident to her official situation here, she was enabled to look to the Lord with confidence &amp; to commit to Him <hi rend="underline">all</hi> concerns as well as the concerns of those whom she was called to serve, in whose weal &amp; woe she always  took the tenderest &amp; most sympathizing share. Her youngest son &amp; daughter were born in Fairfield &amp; during her abode in that Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> she had the satisfaction of witnessing the marriage of her two eldest sons, one of whom settled in Fairfield &amp; the other in the neighborhood Sheffield; by them she had the pleasure to see 3 grandchildren, who where [sic] constant objects of her maternal affection &amp; fervent prayers at the throne of grace. Of her state of mind during the first 10 years of her active &amp; blessed exertions in the service of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at Fairfield, the following extracts from letters addressed to an intimate friend, will bear most edifying testimony:</p><p><hi rend="underline">Jan 7 - 1807. she writes:</hi> you must accept of an assurance of my best wishes &amp; prayers at the beginning of this year, &amp; particularly that our Saviour may direct, comfort, bless &amp; support you in the situation in which you are placed for His sake &amp; with a view to serve Him. I trust he will enable you to begin your work with that cheerfulness which always arises from the impression that we are serving Him. We ought to commit our course &amp; all our concerns to Him, <note type="catchword">with</note></p></div><div n="4" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-04.jpg" n="4"/><p>with the confidence of a child to a tender parent; but alas! we are too busy ourselves; our minds are often at work, &amp; we are apt to become gloomy thro' our own perverseness. Our Saviour's words, that we must become as little children, have lately been particularly impressed upon my mind; &amp; the idea has frequently struck me that we deprive ourselves of much, by not putting our whole trust in Him; nay - I have carried it so far as to believe, with regard to myself, that in a few instances, I have retarded the accomplishments of our Saviour's views with me by it. Do not think, my dear friend, that I conceive this to be your case; yet I believe that it is not impossible, considering all circumstances, that you may find your faith &amp; entire confidence tried. 'Tis true our Lord works by means, but the means &amp; the time when the means are to be resorted to, belong also to him; &amp;  upon this my dear friend must rest her confidence. Our Lord will let it appear, that He is gracious &amp; faithful to his poor children in all his dealings. -</p><p><hi rend="underline">In November the same year, she writes:</hi> you were very kind to remember me on the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> being my birthday. I feel that the good wishes you expressed were the effusions of true friendship. One year after another goes, &amp; brings us nearer to our journey's end. I could not help particularly reflecting on this subject on my birthday; it appears gloomy to me in as far as the children would be affected by such an event, viz: being deprived of a mother: This is indeed a clog to me, &amp; binds me to this poor life, yet, my dear friend, I am now &amp; then favored with a sweet foretaste of the Joys to come - &amp; at such times even those dear &amp; near ties are for the moment forgotten. How sweet, how indiscribably [sic] sweet is the reflection - no. I will not say reflection but the feeling truth, that a day will come when, "all tears will be wiped away &amp; sorrow &amp; sighing will be no more." May we both trust in those beautiful promises &amp; not give way to any thing, which leads us from true simplicity in believing the words of our Lord; the more childlikely we trust in him, the more reality we enjoy &amp; the more light we have into his word. With regard to yourself I can only say, that I trust, you will be enabled, thro' our Saviour's grace, to be satisfied. There are some things very grating, &amp; yet must be borne with. &amp; I know very well, one may be so situated, that there is nothing left to support, but the uprightness with which we act before God our Saviour. When this has been my case, I can truly say, I have enjoyed more comfort &amp; content than when I turn our trials into blessings &amp; we shall always look on those things to which we have submitted with the greatest satisfaction. Do not give way to gloomy ideas, but depend upon that help, which is offered [sic] to us in our greatest need. We are wrong when we sink; we have a merciful Saviour who claims all our confidence &amp; who does require <note type="catchword">our</note></p></div><div n="5" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-05.jpg" n="5"/><p>our entire resignation to His will. May he support &amp; comfort you, &amp; give you a cheerful heart, which views every trial with a comfortable hope, fasts [?] a better face upon every cross. Our Saviour amidst all your difficulties has blessed you abundantly, in spirituals &amp; temporals. My prayer for you is that you may let these considerations preponderate &amp; make large allowances for human affairs, the very best &amp; most prosperous of which are full of defect. I have great reason to pray for my own part, that I may keep the mercies I enjoy always in view; when I slacken in this my mind always becomes gloomy.I could write much on this subject with regard to myself; at present I only wish to express a wish for you, that our Saviour may enable you, at this time particularly to case your burdens on Him &amp; derive new courage. To do that work with pleasure which in your call &amp; measure our God for you to do ordained! </p><p>-"The following Extracts are from letters, written to the same friend, during the latter period of her abode in Fairfield.</p><p><hi rend="underline">In 1817 she writes:</hi> I cannot express in words, how much I am at times depressed by a sense of my unworthiness, wretchedness &amp; neglect of what I am called to enjoy. I must sink with shame at our Saviour's feet, &amp; crave that forgiveness, which He is willing to bestow, I believe, but, I sometimes doubt whether I do receive it. My feelings on this subject I cannot describe! pray for me, that I may be more faithful, more watchful over my poor frail heart.</p><p><hi rend="underline">In 1819:</hi> I remember a time, when the history of <hi rend="underline">"Dives &amp; Lazarus"</hi> was much impressed upon my mind; I was then quite a girl &amp; earnestly prayed to our Saviour, like a simple child, that I might be like Lazarus &amp; not like Dives, who had his good things in this life. I prayed with great sincerity, &amp; begged &amp; to lead me in his own way thro' life, so that I might attain unto the happiness of Lazarus at last.The recollection of the above period of my life, has often led me to think how defective I now am, in that devotedness which I then felt to follow our Saviour's leading with me, whatever the path might be; &amp; how often a murmur intrudes, when submission alone ought to predominate. Yes, my dear friend, I do deeply feel &amp; acknowledge with a humble &amp; grateful heart, that my path is, &amp; ever has been strewed with mercies, &amp; that the loving kindness of a gracious God &amp; Saviour has folled [sic] all the days of my life. May he draw me into closer communion with Himself &amp; give me grace to depend more childlikely on Him in all things. -These Extracts abundantly testify what was the state of her heart while employing her time &amp; talents in the service of the Lord &amp; his cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>, as well as what method she pursued in her dealings with <note type="catchword">her</note></p></div><div n="6" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-06.jpg" n="6"/><p>her friends, &amp; all those who were entrusted to her spiritual care, a method which won for her the most affectionate regard &amp; fullest confidence of all who had the favor to enjoy that care; for in that method she displayed the greatest faithfulness &amp; uprightness, joined to the tenderest feelings of sympathy &amp; love, which always prompted her to make the concerns of all, whether of a spiritual or temporal nature, truly her own. Indeed she had learned from deep experience to feel for &amp; wish those who were tried or afflicted; for it pleased the Lord to lead her especially during the latter years of her life, on a path bewstrewed with some very severe trials, with a view, no doubt, that the blessing promised to those that endure temptation, might finally &amp; fully be hers, to wit: that after having been tried she should receive the crown of life. In reference to some trials of this description, which owing to peculiar circumstances, were of a very painful &amp; distressing nature, she expresses herself in her letters to a friend, in the following truly edifying manner: - "There is a rest for the Children of God. This my dear friend, is a hard dispensation, but tho' we cannot understand it, we are assured that our Lord is wise &amp; good, &amp; that some great purpose is to be accomplished by it, it is no doubt intended for my humiliation &amp; blessing. - Amidst many failings arising  in some degree rejoice, as well as mourn. The cup of affliction is it, &amp; much may the Christian learn in the School of Adversity - but we often repine, lose our faith &amp; confidence &amp; thereby obstruct our Lord's work. I have great need to pray for more resignation to the will of our merciful Redeemer, in all his dispensations however dark they may appear. May we, my dear friend, cleave to Him with all our wants &amp; be favored with clearness &amp; freedom to pray, finding an open passage to the Throne of Grace."</p><p><hi rend="underline">At another time she writes</hi> (1819.) We can say with truth, that we have derived many blessings by means of dispensations most painful to us. Had our pilgrimage thro' this life been smooth, how many useful lessions would have been withheld from us! - trials have often brought us to the foot of the cross, &amp; procured for us many subjects for prayer &amp; humiliation, the fruits of which have been our best enjoyments &amp; sources of the sweetest comforts. I know that this has been your experience as well as mine; &amp; we feel how great our  debt of gratitude is to our Lord for <hi rend="underline">all</hi>; - for our days of sunshine &amp; for time of gloom &amp; difficulty. <note type="catchword">again</note> </p></div><div n="7" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-07.jpg" n="7"/><p/></div><div n="8" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-08.jpg" n="8"/><p/></div><div n="9" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-09.jpg" n="9"/><p/></div><div n="10" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-10.jpg" n="10"/><p/></div><div n="11" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-11.jpg" n="11"/><p/></div><div n="12" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-12.jpg" n="12"/><p>she declared to her most intimate friends her lively hope &amp; joyful expectation of being ere long permitted to quit this mortal tabernacle &amp; to be at rest with the Lord for ever. To her dear children however she rather refrained from a free disclosure of her apprehensions that she should not recover this illness. As long as any hopes of the possibility of recovery remained, her affection for them induced her to conceal almost from herself the distressing thought that a separation must shortly ensue. Indeed she did not scruple for a considerable period to intimate a wish: - that if it were the Lord's will, she might be spared yet a little longer, to watch over their temporal &amp; spiritual intersts &amp; to assist them individually with her maternal care. The frequent visits of her children resident in other places, contributed to enliven her during her tedious confinement, &amp; the affectionate assiduity of those who had the favor to live with her &amp; personally to administer to her comforts, was rewarded by many a kind word &amp; expression of a countenance with their beloved mother, which will not easily be obliterated from their recollection. Tho' her parental feelings continued unchanged to the last, of which she gave frequent &amp; affecting proofs, yet, at the close of her earthly pilgramage drew nearer, it became more &amp; more evident, that the Lord was preparing her for his heavenly kingdom, likewise by giving an increased measure of resignation as to all that concerned her children.</p><p>Whenever the conversation turned upon this tender subject during the last few weeks of her life, she did not hesitate to say that her anxieties on their behalf had been graciously allayed by the Friend of her soul &amp; she could now resign them all, as well as her affectionate partner into those hands, whereon by faith she saw their names engraven.</p><p>From April to the end of June she appeared at times to suffer much in her mind, indeed her frequent midnight tears testified that this was the case. Her daughter who slept in the same apartment with her, often found her awake in this state, &amp; once waking in the middle of the night, she overheard her repeating the verse: O that my sins might find their grave &amp;&amp;&amp; and- Saviour! till sight of thee I gain - may I this scene be oft revising! &amp;&amp; And during the last days, with clasped hands &amp; her eyes fixed, her lips often moved in fervent prayer, while she appeared  quite unconscious of those around her. There were full evidences of the true state of her heart as deeply humbled in the <note type="catchword">consciousness</note></p></div><div n="13" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-13.jpg" n="13"/><p/></div><div n="14" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-14.jpg" n="14"/><p/></div><div n="15" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-15.jpg" n="15"/><p/></div><div n="16" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-16.jpg" n="16"/><p/></div><div n="17" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-17.jpg" n="17"/><p/></div><div n="18" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-18.jpg" n="18"/><p/></div><div n="19" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-19.jpg" n="19"/><p/></div><div n="20" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300020-20.jpg" n="20"/><p/></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>