<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memoir</title>
                <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
                <principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
                </principal>
                <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Project Manager</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Developer</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
</rdf:RDF></xenoData></teiHeader>
    
    <text type="memoir" xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <head>Frances Sophia Tranaker</head>
            <div><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300046-01.jpg" n="1"/><p>Frances Sophia Tranaker was born at Westhofenin Alsatia Septr 25th 1727. Her Father Councellor Engelbach, who together with his wife loved our Savr &amp; his people, were much concerned for the true happiness &amp; preservation of their Children, for which reason they desired &amp; also obtained a marrd Br &amp; Sr from the Congn to live with them, in order to take care of their children. The awakening of our departed Sr was occasioned by her Father, who once late at night kneeled down before a Chair in the room where she lay, thinking she was asleep, &amp; prayed heartily to our Savr for himself &amp; his family,&amp; concluded his prayer with singing some Verses. This affected her very deeply, &amp; she wept &amp; prayed our Savr to have mercy on her &amp; to receive her as his Child. In 1740 she was sent by her parents, according to her own desire, to the Girls Oeconomy in Marienborn, where she arrived July 26th &amp; in Octr following she was received into the Congn, which she often called to mind as a very particular blessing to her, &amp; the 13th May 1741 she was admitted to the holy communion. After that time she became more &amp; more sensible of her deep depravity, which cost her much distress &amp; many tears: but our dear Savr manifested himself to her in his bleeding form on the Cross as the Atoner for her Sins, she was richly comforted, &amp; became very chearful cheerful. Sometime after she was made use of as an assistant in the labour among the great girls in Herrnhaag &amp; was afterds sent to Holland to serve in the Girls Oeconomy in Herrndyke &amp; 1750 she was called to go to England &amp; was used in the Girls Oeconomy then in Mile end near London, from whence she was taken into the family of the late ordinary in Lindsey house, where she remained 2 years, &amp; had (as she has often mentioned) such a blessed time for her heart, as remained unforgotten by her. In 1755 she was sent to Fulneck <note type="catchword">to</note></p></div><div n="2" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300046-02.jpg" n="2"/><p>to be Co=helper of the S: Srs &amp; choirhelper of the great girls: &amp; tho' she had here many trials of various kinds to go thro': yet she remained chearful  cheerful &amp; contented, &amp; Shewed  Showed much faithfulness in her office, &amp; enjoyed the love &amp; confidence of all her Srs &amp; g: girls.      Octr 29th 1759 she was married to Br George Franckere, &amp; on the 13th Novr following she was blessed by Br Johannes as a Deaconess of the Church of the Brethren, &amp; then she went with to her husband to Bedford, where they had the care of that Congn, as they afterwards also had of these in Bristol &amp; London: &amp; in 1776 they went in the same capacity to Fulneck where they arrived March 24th, &amp; had also the care ofthe 2 Childrens Oeconomies committed to them. One must give her the testimony, that, notwithstanding all her faults &amp; imperfections, she was very faithful in all she was intrusted with, having the concerns of her Sisters &amp; the Children in the Oeconomy, to whom she was a truly tender mother, very much at heart &amp; sparing no pains whatever in fulfilling all that she thought to be for their good. Her married state was blessed with 2 Sons &amp; 3 Daughters, of whom one son &amp; 2 Daughters are gone to rest before her, &amp; one Son &amp; one Daughter are in the Congn. At the end of last Septr she got a violent fever, which held her for several weeks, &amp; then turned to a Dropey, under which she laboured with encreasing  increasing pains for several months; but from the begining  beginning of her disorder it was clear in her mind, that she shod go to our dear Savr &amp; spoke often of it with mel[?]dness of heart &amp; tears of longing for that happy time; tho' it seemed sometimes as if she would recover. She express'd very often in an affecting manner her Sinner like love <note type="catchword">&amp;</note> </p></div><div n="3" type="page"><pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300046-03.jpg" n="3"/><p>&amp; hearty confidence to our dear Savr &amp; when her great pains, now &amp; then made her a little impatient [?????????], she was very sorry for it afterwards, &amp; said once among other things "O how insignificant" are my pains in compairson to what my dear" Saviour has suffered for my Sins"! The longer she lay, the more helpless she grew; but the love of the Srs &amp; their hearty willingness to serve her upon all occasions by night &amp; day was a great comfortto her &amp; all about her. On the 27th of March inthe Evening she desired her husband to bless herfor her departure, which (says he) I did witha feeling in my heart, which I am not able todescribe, delivering her up in a short prayer toher eternal husband &amp; pronouncing the Church'sblessing upon her in the presence of several Srs,who shed many tears on the occasion. OnMonday the 29th about noon, we saw that herdissolution drew near. She said, in brokenwords to me: "My faults are endless" &amp; uponasking her: Do you feel our Savrs gracious nearnessin your heart she answered, "I do." Then Isaid: When you come to our Saviour, will youkiss his thro'bred feel for us? She bowed herhead &amp; smiled: &amp; then her breath stop'd, &amp; herdear bought soul entered into her Lords joy inthe 57th year of her age.</p></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>