<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Haley_Joseph_Ful_3_36</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1648.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The life of Joseph Haley who has left the following in writing</l>
					<l>I was born at Little Town in the Parish of Birstall in Yorkshire June 25th</l>
					<l>1727. My Parents were very poor &amp; belong&apos;d to the Church of England,</l>
					<l>but before I was 11 years old, I was bound Prentice for the Space of 10</l>
					<l>Years to a Broad Clothier, which I faithfully served in Hardshead Parish.</l>
					<l>In the middle of my time Mr. Ingham &amp; Delamotte began to preach at</l>
					<l>Smith House &amp; Rawhead, where I often went to hear them &amp; got a lively</l>
					<l>Impression of the Friend of Sinners. But my Master being a Cross old</l>
					<l>Man, he would not let one go to hear the Brn, and as my time was</l>
					<l>almost out, I begd our Savr to keep me near his Person. My time</l>
					<l>being out I hired myself with another Master, who was a Methodist, when</l>
					<l>I became more Religious than before but could never get any Satisfaction</l>
					<l>&amp; my heart grew very dead &amp; cold. A the end of my Year I went to</l>
					<l>live at Hallifax to be an Hostler, there I plung&apos;d myself into all manner</l>
					<l>of wickedness. Soon after Iwent to live at Leeds where I was a</l>
					<l>Gentlemans Servant, here I became still more wicked &amp; miserable being</l>
					<l>tho&apos; I was always accused in my Mind &amp; knowing at the same time my Course was</l>
					<l>hurtfull to body &amp; Soul, so that my Life become burthensome to me.</l>
					<l>My Mother being a good old Methodist &amp; knowing of my going on</l>
					<l>She was much dissatisfied with me, &amp; often desired me to come</l>
					<l>home &amp; settle to my own Business, but I found it very difficult</l>
					<l>to leave my old wicked Companions, thinking I was fit for no</l>
					<l>other Company. Now my Confliction was broke &amp; I was befall&apos;n</l>
					<l>with a sore Sickness, which reduced me to great poverty &amp; being</l>
					<l>hardly fit for any thing, I then began to wish, that I could have</l>
					<l>called back the Time I had lost &amp; Spend without our Saviour.</l>
					<l>Having served in this place 4 Years and 5 Months I left my</l>
					<l>Master &amp; went to live with my Parents at High Town but</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1650.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>did not know what Course to take, for I was like a Spotted Bird</l>
					<l>even amongst the worldly People. I went again to hear the Methodists</l>
					<l>however here I could find no comfort &amp; my poor Heart felt always</l>
					<l>dissatisfied which made me resolved to go &amp; hear the Brn but I always</l>
					<l>found Something to hinder me. Soon after it happened that I</l>
					<l>went to live with Wm Taylor a Single Man of Cleckheaton who belongs</l>
					<l>to the Brn. Hearing that there was a very pious Minister at White Chapple</l>
					<l>I went to hear his Sermons, but as he preached only the Law, I soon got</l>
					<l>a Dislike &amp; in the beginning of the Year 1757 I went to hear Br Pyrleaus</l>
					<l>who preachd on these Words: Lord, save us, we perish, there my heart</l>
					<l>was laid so hold of that I shall never forget it. Having great uneasiness</l>
					<l>of Mind, I wished for an opportunity to speak with a Br which happened</l>
					<l>soon after to my great Satisfaction. I also got leave to come to the</l>
					<l>1759</l>
					<l>Classes of the Single Men &amp; in March the same Year I was received into</l>
					<l>the Society, at which I felt our Savr very near to me. I beg&apos;d He might</l>
					<l>keep me close to Him. I being so exposed to the world made me think</l>
					<l>I shoudl never come thro&apos;. I often came to Fulneck &amp; saw the Brn</l>
					<l>lived so happy together as I never saw People live before, I thought</l>
					<l>I could never be rightly happy unless I was there. Yet I could never</l>
					<l>offer to ask for it feeling my own Misery &amp; wickedness I thought they</l>
					<l>would never allow in to come there. In this way I continued like a</l>
					<l>Standing Water till March 1760 when my Master Wm. Taylor got leave to move</l>
					<l>into the Choir House which caused me many Tears thinking our Savr had</l>
					<l>left me alone to myself on account of my unfaithfulness, what would become</l>
					<l>of me I did not know. As I was very uneasy &amp; being resolved to become our</l>
					<l>Savrs I desired leave to live in the Congn at Fulneck which I also obtain&apos;d</l>
					<l>&amp; moved thither Octr 20 th 1760 very glad &amp; thankfull. March 23d 1761 I was</l>
					<l>received into the Congn which was a great Blessing to me. In July I had</l>
					<l>a hard Sickness, in during which our Savr gave me a new Seal of</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>my Grace Election &amp; comforted me about all past things. Decr 20th 1761</l>
					<l>I was made a partaker of my Lords Corpse &amp; Blood in the holy Sacra-</l>
					<l>ment which was an unspeakable Grace to me, &amp; I esteemed this Year</l>
					<l>a Year of Blessings bestowed upon me, which I shall never be</l>
					<l>able to express, &amp; I wish that I may always have that Impression</l>
					<l>of it till our Savr calls me home to himself. Oh! could I but</l>
					<l>always prize my Call &amp; Election sufficiently &amp; thank our Savr</l>
					<l>that he has granted me a nest amongst his People I cannot but</l>
					<l>be ashamed that my heart does not burn more in Love towards Him.</l>
					<l>Thus far his own words.</l>
					<l>In the Year 1763 he got a Call to go to Bedford, of which he accepted</l>
					<l>in a Childlike manner &amp; served the Brn in Bedford as Cook for several</l>
					<l>Years &amp; then went to Duckenfield. On March 26th1767 he came again</l>
					<l>to live here &amp; went on in a happy Course. In the beginning of June</l>
					<l>1770 he went to live in the Oeconomy at Mirfield. He was Naturally</l>
					<l>a peevish Temper, but his plain Honest &amp; upright way of acting made</l>
					<l>him beloved amongst his Brn. He was free &amp; openhearted with his</l>
					<l>Labourer nor did he speak better of himself than it was. He often</l>
					<l>felt the oppression of his Sickly Tabernacle, especially in the Spring and</l>
					<l>Autumn, but this last Spring it soon appeared that his Sickness</l>
					<l>was a Consumption &amp; that he would not recover again on which</l>
					<l>account he wishd to come to Fulneck &amp; go home in the Choirhouse</l>
					<l>last</l>
					<l>here, which was also granted him, July the 11th for which he was</l>
					<l>very thankful. He spend his time in the Sick Room in a true Concession</l>
					<l>with our Savr, waiting with resignation for the happy Hour of his Disso-</l>
					<l>lution which came to pass the 10th instant, when our Savr took him happily</l>
					<l>to himself as a Sinner who had found Grace in His Death and</l>
					<l>Sufferings.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
