<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Gray_Timothy_Ful_3_11</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1518.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Life of the widower, Br Timothy Gray, who </l>
					<l>departed to our Svar at Wyke Aug. 11th 1795.</l>
					<l>He has left the following account of his course </l>
					<l>thro time. </l>
					<l>I was born Aug. 5th 1719 at North Owram in </l>
					<l>the parish of Halifax. I lived with my parents</l>
					<l>till I was 14 years old, when I was put appren-</l>
					<l>tice to a cloth maker at Birkenshaw. During</l>
					<l>my apprenticeship, I became very uneasy about</l>
					<l>the state of my soul, &amp; took to praying &amp; self</l>
					<l>working, but soon found, that I could not help</l>
					<l>myself. Soon after I became acquainted with</l>
					<l>one John Nelson, to whom I could freely open</l>
					<l>my mind. Upon his enquiry, I told him, how</l>
					<l>I had proceeded, &amp; that with all my endeavors</l>
					<l>I could not attain to rest for my soul, but </l>
					<l>found myself as wretched as ever. His answer</l>
					<l>was: I find that you are a poor slave of the</l>
					<l>devil. He then told me his experience, that</l>
					<l>he had been of the same way of thinking, but</l>
					<l>had found all laboring in his own strength to be</l>
					<l>in vain. He advised me to go to hear Mr Wesley,</l>
					<l>he would teach me the right way to heaven. </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1520.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>me with cards of love to himself. I longed but, as</l>
					<l>it were, to touch the hem of his garment, &amp; this </l>
					<l>our Savr graciously granted me, &amp; I felt, that he</l>
					<l>owned me as his. About this time I lived with</l>
					<l>my Sisters at Birkenshaw, where we were visited</l>
					<l>by the Brn, my shyness towards them wore off</l>
					<l>by degrees, &amp; I soon had the favor to become a</l>
					<l>member of the congn. Now a new school commenc</l>
					<l>ed in my heart, I learnt more &amp; more to Know</l>
					<l>my natural corruption, but my Savr likewise</l>
					<l>granted me the grace to depend more &amp; more upon</l>
					<l>him, for which I have great reason to thank</l>
					<l>him all my days. Soon after I went by advice</l>
					<l>of the Brn to live at Mirfield with John Sheard,</l>
					<l>where I staid nearly 2 years, &amp; then spent 4</l>
					<l>years agreably with the Brn at Wyke. Then I </l>
					<l>moved into the single Brns choir house at Fulneck</l>
					<l>but here I got into company with some of a reas-</l>
					<l>oning spirit, whereby I suffered hurt in my soul,</l>
					<l>&amp; this provedthe occasion, that I left the Brn</l>
					<l>for some time, &amp; came to live at Wyke. Neverthe-</l>
					<l>less my Savr held his hand over me, &amp; in his </l>
					<l>due time brought me back to his fold. </l>
					<l>Thus far our late Brs own account.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>He was received into the congn at Fulneck, Oct.</l>
					<l>admitted to the H Comn in 1749. He married </l>
					<l>12th 1748 &amp; married to his late wife, Elizabeth whose</l>
					<l>maiden name was Ubank in 1755, which marriage</l>
					<l>was blest with 1 son &amp; 2 daughters, of whom only</l>
					<l>1 daughter has survived him, &amp; is now married</l>
					<l>to Br Wm Ellis at Hopton. In 1749 he was admitted</l>
					<l>to the holy comn with the congn. In 1789 he became</l>
					<l>a widower. He has been for many years a respect-</l>
					<l>had</l>
					<l>able member of this congn, tho he his weak-</l>
					<l>nesses &amp; singularities, which sometimes rendered</l>
					<l>his course heavy to himself &amp; others, yet amidst</l>
					<l>all, it was evident, that his heart cleaved to</l>
					<l>our Savr, &amp; that he had sunk down upon him, </l>
					<l>as the only sure foundation. It was always a</l>
					<l>pleasure to him to be visited by the Brn &amp; Srs</l>
					<l>&amp; he delighted to speak freely with them of what our </l>
					<l>Lord had done upon his soul. He prized his</l>
					<l>election of grace to belong to the Brns Congn, &amp; there </l>
					<l>was nothing he regretted so much, when confined</l>
					<l>by sickness, as to be deprived of the opportunities</l>
					<l>of blessing to be enjoyed by children of God in fel-</l>
					<l>lowship. He however endeavored in some mea-</l>
					<l>sure to make up for this loss by reading dili-</l>
					<l>gently in the bible, &amp; meditating daily in stillness</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1522.jpg' n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>on the texts of the day, which was his constant </l>
					<l>practise, &amp; whereby according to his own testimony, </l>
					<l>he often received gracious visits from our Savr. </l>
					<l>Of late years, the infirmities of age, &amp; increasing </l>
					<l>bodily weakness, depressed him greatly, &amp; his </l>
					<l>strength declined visibly. His constitution was </l>
					<l>by degrees quite worn out, &amp; he sighed, like a </l>
					<l>weary traveller for repose, longing ardently to </l>
					<l>be released from pain, &amp; at home with his Lord. </l>
					<l>A couple of days before his departure; he declared </l>
					<l>that he had nothing, that lay heavy upon his </l>
					<l>mind, but was ready to go hence with joy, as a </l>
					<l>poor, but pardoned sinner, trusting alone in the </l>
					<l>merit of Christ, &amp; thus he fell gently &amp; happily </l>
					<l>asleep in the Lord, aged 76 years &amp; a few days.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
