<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Horsfall_Sarah_Ful_SS_65</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1298.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The married Sr Sar: Horsefall was born at Barnsley</l>
					<l>Decr: 5th 1697. Her Parents being religious Members of the Church</l>
					<l>of England brot her up in the same way, and when her Father</l>
					<l>was about to depart this Life, which happened when the</l>
					<l>deceased Sr was 7 Years old, he desired that this his Daugh</l>
					<l>ter, for whom he had a great Love, might go to live with her</l>
					<l>Grand Mother who was a pious old Woman. With her she </l>
					<l>remained till she departed this Life, and then went to wait</l>
					<l>on a Gentlewoman, in which Place as well as in some other</l>
					<l>Gentleman&apos;s Families she was never easy in her Mind, but</l>
					<l>always thoughtfull about her future State till she was</l>
					<l>married to the present Widower at Glosop in Derbyshire</l>
					<l>July 2d: 1727, by whom she had 7 Children, 1 Son is in the S Brns</l>
					<l>House at Fulneck and 1 Daughter marrd in Gohar &amp; in our Society;</l>
					<l>3 are gone home before her &amp; 2 in the World.</l>
					<l>About the Year 1743 Her Husband went to hear Mr Ingham</l>
					<l>preach at Smithhouse, whereby he became awaken&apos;d, and his</l>
					<l>frequent attending the meetings of awaken&apos;d People caused</l>
					<l>a good deal of uneasiness between them both, till being</l>
					<l>drawn by Curiosity to see what her Husband was so fond</l>
					<l>of, she went herself and soon found that she was in a very</l>
					<l>wretched Condition as touching her Salvation. Then it became</l>
					<l>clear to her what it was that made her Husband so diligent</l>
					<l>in going to the meetings at such a distance, she asked his</l>
					<l>Pardon with shame for her past behaviour and nothing</l>
					<l>cou&apos;d prevent her going along with him ever after. About</l>
					<l>the same time she desired the Gospel might be preached in their</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1299.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>House for the Benefit of her Neighbours, whose Souls Hap</l>
					<l>piness she thirsted after, and it has continued there with</l>
					<l>blessing ever Since. She turn&apos;d to our Saviour as a poor</l>
					<l>lost Sinner and found him gracious to the forgiving her</l>
					<l>all her Sins and cleansing Her from all Unrighteousness,</l>
					<l>the clear impression of which she retained unalterably to </l>
					<l>her last Moment. She was received into the Congn at Fulneck</l>
					<l>Decr 21st 1748. to her great Joy, and went the first time to</l>
					<l>the holy Comn with the Congn in Gumersal Chapel Decr 4th 1751</l>
					<l>From that time she prized her Elec</l>
					<l>tion of Grace to the Congn as dear and precious, and missed</l>
					<l>no Oppertunity either at Mirfield or Fulneck till old Age</l>
					<l>and bodily Infirmities obliged her to stay at home much</l>
					<l>against her will. When she at any time heard Brn &amp; Srs excuse</l>
					<l>their not attending the Meetings on Account of family Con</l>
					<l>cerns or Business, she always replied: That never hindered</l>
					<l>me, for if I knew of a blessing for my heart, I always recom</l>
					<l>mended my family concerns to our Savr and went, and</l>
					<l>when I return&apos;d, found things in better order than if I had</l>
					<l>been at home my Self.&quot; She was a faithfull and carefull</l>
					<l>Hostess and Nurse to all Brn &amp; Srs who came to her House </l>
					<l>and had at such times much of the Martha Spirit mised</l>
					<l>with Marys Disposition of heart to enjoy. &apos;Tis true, Her</l>
					<l>Activity of Soul was sometimes hurtfull to her, but when</l>
					<l>ever she was reminded of it she always acknowledged her</l>
					<l>fault and came to rights again. This</l>
					<l>ick disposition very often hurried her beyond her</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1300.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Strength of Body and brot on slight Sicknesses, which in</l>
					<l>a little time went of again, but Sepr 9th being much hurry&apos;d</l>
					<l>in providing for those who were working in the Harvest</l>
					<l>was the Day on which she took her last Sickness. However</l>
					<l>she was well at Noon and dined with her Husband &amp; Br Wor</l>
					<l>thington who went there to keep the meeting, in her usual</l>
					<l>chearfull way; but suddenly got up from Table and went</l>
					<l>out complaining of an uncommon Pain in her Head. Her</l>
					<l>long stay caused her Husband to follow her, and finding her</l>
					<l>incapable of helping herself, he brot her in and put her</l>
					<l>to Bed where her disorder soon shewed itself to be a hot</l>
					<l>fever. When her pain was most Violent she soothed her Soul</l>
					<l>to ease &amp; rest with the tormenting Anguish &amp; Pain of her</l>
					<l>dear Saviour which she told Br Worthington that same day.</l>
					<l>Sunday Sepr 15th: when Br Worthn: went to preach at Golear</l>
					<l>he found her much easier as if the fever had left her Up:</l>
					<l>on asking her if she thot she shou&apos;d go home? she said: that</l>
					<l>wou&apos;d be my hearts Inclination, for I have lived long enough</l>
					<l>without seeing him, tho&apos; he has never left me from the first</l>
					<l>time I knew him to this Hour, but I cannot tell how it will</l>
					<l>be. However if he will take me I am ready, for I have his</l>
					<l>Blood and Righteousness, tho&apos; I feel my Self more vile</l>
					<l>than ever I did in my Life. Sunday Sepr 22d: Her Husband</l>
					<l>reminded her that it was the Comn day. she replied I know</l>
					<l>it and have no Mind for eating or for drinking food which</l>
					<l>must corrupt again; of Gods Bread that heavenly I </l>
					<l>am thinking, Jesus Christs flesh I&apos;d obtain; who was</l>
					<l>formed of the Seed of David &amp; his Blood is Drink Oh! how</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1301.jpg' n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I crave it from Earth&apos;s life to be set free in Love&apos;s Immortallity.</l>
					<l>She continued mostly in a Slumber till Tuesday the 24 at Night</l>
					<l>when her Soul took flight to the Arms of her eternal Bridegroom</l>
					<l>about 10 oClock in the 68th: Year of her Age.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
