<?xml-model href="../../Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mary Peel: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel">Mary Peel</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-04.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Mary Peel</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-08-28" who="#JAKA1">Created memoir file</change>
			<change when-iso="2019-10-22" who="#cpirmann">corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Mary Peel</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-01.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I was born at Northarm in the parish of Halifax</l>
					<l>in the <add place="above">May 29</add> year 1722. My Parents being very religious</l>
					<l>endeavour&apos;d to bring me up strictly in the fear of God.</l>
					<l>they very early perceiving my natural turn to be quick livly</l>
					<l>and active, on that account took the greater care of me takeing</l>
					<l>me with them constantly to the Decenters meetings, as I at that</l>
					<l>time did not understand their meaning, I look upon it as being</l>
					<l>very hardly dealt with, but afterwards saw clearly that their</l>
					<l>intentions where only to prevent my entrance on a very loose course</l>
					<l>of life which I might have fall&apos;n into, had not their unwearied</l>
					<l>care &amp; faithfullness, been a great means of preserving me, together</l>
					<l>with an invisible Hand, which I often felt While very young over</l>
					<l>me without any knowlidge of the meaning thereof for which I</l>
					<l>shall forever remain thankfull, I went on much in this way</l>
					<l>till M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Inham came to these parts, to whose preaching the</l>
					<l>greatest part of the people resorting, I went among the rest, being</l>
					<l>thereby stir&apos;d up &amp; often brought to reflect on my state, but with</l>
					<l>out any lasting impression. I remember one night being very</l>
					<l>thoughtfull when going to bed, I dream&apos;d that I was to be put to</l>
					<l>death, at which I was very much perplex&apos;t, I intreated to be spar&apos;d</l>
					<l>while I was set to die. The earnestness I was in awoke me,</l>
					<l>but the impression of this I never lost, &amp; by means of the uncom</l>
					<l>mon feelings I had somtimes I thought surly there was some</l>
					<l>thing to be injoy&apos;d, to which I was as yet a stranger, but was</l>
					<l>not rightly satisfy&apos;d to be without it.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>In the year 17 <add place="above">came</add> <hi rend="superscript">coming</hi> the Brethern into Yorkshire with a<hi rend="strikethrough">n</hi></l>
					<l>vein <hi rend="strikethrough">intention</hi> to settle societies, accordingly tookdown the names of</l>
					<l>those who constantly atended the preaching. I therefore was willing</l>
					<l>to have mine taken down, which was no sooner done, but I was</l>
					<l>amazingly struck, thinking I am now however fast, but did not</l>
					<l>repent it. I soon found it was not alone the taking down the</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-02.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>names but they entended to look more particularly after each one</l>
					<l>therefore they soon settled Bands to which I was admitted &amp; geting</l>
					<l>a great love for them they were very much blest to me. Some of my</l>
					<l>Companions being soon after this receiv&apos;d into the Congregation it</l>
					<l>Cause&apos;d me many uneasy hours, as I was left, however I thought</l>
					<l>to try &amp; get to them though I knew not how to set about it, when almost</l>
					<l>dispairing I often felt exceedingly encouraged and very much strengthened</l>
					<l>I was not allow&apos;d to go to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> meetings this drove me to the</l>
					<l>determination to make my mind known which I did by a letter</l>
					<l>to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> expressing my greatest desire to be embody&apos;d with them.</l>
					<l>My request was soon granted our in year 1745 this was an inex</l>
					<l>pressible grace &amp; favour to me past discribing being then very</l>
					<l>chearfull I thought I had then got all that could make my happiness</l>
					<l>compleat. In this way I went on for some time.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>In the year 1747 the first Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Oeconomy was settl&apos;d at Oxhaighs I</l>
					<l>having the favour to be one of the first, I look&apos;d on it &amp; accepted it with</l>
					<l>a real thankfull heart, &amp; the blessing which I then enjoy&apos;d will never</l>
					<l>be forgot by me. This happiness lasted for some time but before I was</l>
					<l>aware it all vanishd away and I was left as much distresst as ever</l>
					<l>being ready to determin to leave the Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> &amp; take my thing in the world but my Consionec would not permit me to take such a step</l>
					<l>on this account I often whr&apos;d to a lonly place, which I had found</l>
					<l>quite to my mind, then I often lamented my state without the least</l>
					<l>hopes of being helpt through, &amp; sav&apos;d at last but my best &amp; faithfull</l>
					<l>friend notwithstanding my negligence followed me endeavouring</l>
					<l>to bring me to the place where I at all times bught to have a remaind</l>
					<l>er at his feet, he thererfore an Oppertunity to show me my state</l>
					<l>by nature &amp; convincd me that noself working would avail me any</l>
					<l>thing, but he was willing to take my care on himself. I was hereby</l>
					<l>quite overcome, by his asuring me I was his, which so worked on me</l>
					<l>that I was determin&apos;d to be his intirly with soul &amp; body, and as a poor</l>
					<l>Sinner to receive grace at his hand.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-03.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>My longing was now daily increased to become a partaker of the</l>
					<l>Holy Sacrement which grace was granted me Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 1747 after</l>
					<l>which I believd simply I should yeild more satisfaction to the</l>
					<l>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; my self. These thoughts brought me into a very loyal</l>
					<l>way but could not with my best endeavours effect what I wish for,</l>
					<l>and having no Laboress at that time to help &amp; encourage us,</l>
					<l>I thought to direct myself, but not being able this way only brought</l>
					<l>me into confusion. At last I was convinc&apos;d that even those who were</l>
					<l>partakers of his body &amp; blood could lay up no store without a</l>
					<l>daily &amp; hourly supply from the fountain from whence all good</l>
					<l>springs. Therefore I determin&apos;d to be directed and Influenced</l>
					<l>alone by him who has often approv&apos;d himself as my friend in need.</l>
					<l>In the year 1748 I mov&apos;d to home Oeconomy where I liv&apos;d a year</l>
					<l>Chearfully &amp; satisfy&apos;d then there being a new Oeconomy began</l>
					<l>at Littlemoore. I was one that was place&apos;d there where I learnd</l>
					<l>to know more of myself and the leading of our Saviour with me</l>
					<l>then I was sensible of before. In the year 50 I mov&apos;d again</l>
					<l>to the Oeconomy at Conhouse, where I thought to live Chearfully</l>
					<l>with the rest of my Companions. But here I must observe</l>
					<l>I was again disturb&apos;d by my own Corruption of which I thought</l>
					<l>I had sufficient Knowledge <add place="above">before</add> but found the depth of my natural</l>
					<l>Corrupted heart was unfathomable which made me almost</l>
					<l>conclude it was unpossible for me to be help to the end of days</l>
					<l>I was often encouraged by those about me to</l>
					<l>believe I was not to bad for our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> but to no purpose, till I</l>
					<l>felt it scals &amp; made clear to my heart by my best friend. He</l>
					<l>often took such oppertunities as these to melt &amp; bow my heart before</l>
					<l>him anew, &amp; thereby to make my call &amp; diction of grace of greater</l>
					<l>value to me. The same year the Oeconomy mov&apos;d to fulneck</l>
					<l>there to reside till the Choir house which was their building,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-04.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>was finish&apos;d, into which as soon as it was ready, I mov&apos;d with</l>
					<l>the first company, at the entrance of which I again renew&apos;d</l>
					<l>my Covenant with my d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and partook of the grace</l>
					<l>which in a particular manner prevail&apos;d at that time.</l>
					<l>here as well as in all other places &amp; during my whole life</l>
					<l><add place="above">notwithstanding</add> <hi rend="strikethrough">during</hi> all failings wants &amp; defects I was alway follow&apos;d</l>
					<l>and often comforted by him who has alway approv&apos;d himself</l>
					<l>as my only effectual Comforter &amp; Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. So he will Continue</l>
					<l>to me to the end of my days. he has often been so visibly near</l>
					<l>my heart as if I had seen him with my bodily eyes, yea I could</l>
					<l>Converse with him as with an intimate friend about every</l>
					<l>thing. In the year 1760 I had a Call to go to Bedford, as</l>
					<l>it was thought best I went out of Obedience at which place</l>
					<l>I was receiv&apos;d with so much love &amp; heartiness as I can&apos;t express</l>
					<l>but <add place="above">and</add> I <add place="above">have often</add> reflected on it with thankfullness, So far Her own </l>
					<l>words</l>
					<l>but meeting with difficulties of various sorts, the employment</l>
					<l>for which I went there not answering the wish for end,</l>
					<l>and having a great desire to return to fulneck, as my</l>
					<l>Bodily Health was also much impair&apos;d I made my desire</l>
					<l>Known, which after Consideration was consented too &amp; I returnd</l>
					<l>feb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 16 1770 <note>From this point on, memoir is in a different hand.</note> Here she liv&apos;d several years in the Sist<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Oeconomy with great</l>
					<l>faithfullness till thro bodily circumstances she was oblig&apos;d to retire into the Choir</l>
					<l>House there but finding Her <add place="above">self no better</add> <hi rend="strikethrough">weakness increase</hi> She defin&apos;d &amp; obtaind  leave</l>
					<l>to remove back again to The Choir House in Fullneck where she arriv&apos;d Feb 16 1770</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
