<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Bentham_John_Ful_3_18</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The Life of the mar&apos;d Brother John Bentham who</l>
					<l>was called Home the 9th August 1772. </l>
					<l>He has dictated the following concerning himself.</l>
					<l>I was born at Black Hay in Pudsey Township 1713</l>
					<l>&amp; baptised in the Church of England My Mother being poor &amp;</l>
					<l>not able to care for me I was put out by the family as a Towns apprentice to</l>
					<l>a Presbiterian. I had no Mind to go on Sundays with any</l>
					<l>Mother to his place of Worship, &amp; having no Concern on my Mind</l>
					<l>about my Salvation I went no where. My Master observing this</l>
					<l>told me I should be lost if I continued in the way I then was, &amp; should go</l>
					<l>to a place of Torment when I died. This had the Effect upon me</l>
					<l>that I went to Church &amp; then I thought my Case was safe, but even</l>
					<l>this proved the Occasion to hurtful Entanglements, &amp; also to my</l>
					<l>marrying unhappily which was attended with many painful Con-</l>
					<l>sequences. By this Marriage I had 2 Daughters. When Mr. Ingham</l>
					<l>began to preach in these parts I want to hear him, &amp; the Word had</l>
					<l>some Effect upon me for some Time, but alas, I soon got into my</l>
					<l>old wretched Course again. Being one Sunday at Tong Church I was</l>
					<l>asked by the late Br Jonathan Heartly to go with him to hear the</l>
					<l>Brethren at Bankhouse; at first I told him I would not, but he</l>
					<l>however prevailed upon so to do, &amp; I have abundant Reason to</l>
					<l>thank my dear Savr that He inclined me to go. What I there heard</l>
					<l>of the Love of our Savr melted my heart &amp; had the Effect upon</l>
					<l>me that I returned home in a very different Mind to what I</l>
					<l>had before, being now determined to seek in earnest after</l>
					<l>the Salvation of my Soul, nor could I afterwards have Rest</l>
					<l>or Satisfaction till I found Mercy &amp; peace in Jesus Christ.</l>
					<l>Soon after this I was rec&apos;d into the Society, &amp; March 25th 1758 I was</l>
					<l>red&apos;d into the Congn, &amp; the same Year was admitted to the holy Com-</l>
					<l>munion &amp; spent my Time in a truly happy Manner in sweet</l>
					<l>Fellowship with my kind Lord &amp; Redeemer. This was a most</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>blessed Season to my poor Heart, &amp; happy would it have been</l>
					<l>for me if I had remained in this Connexion with my Savr</l>
					<l>but turning aside from Him &amp; not proving this Grace nightly </l>
					<l>I gave Opportunity to the Enemy to blind my Eyes again, to</l>
					<l>lay hold of me as his Captive &amp; to lead me according to his Will,</l>
					<l>&amp; thus was brought into most shameful &amp; scandalous Things</l>
					<l>to the unspeakable Grief of the whole Congn, &amp; still more to</l>
					<l>the Grief &amp; Reproach of my merciful Savr, &amp; which was</l>
					<l>oftenwards attended Lord with much Loss, Distress &amp; Anguish</l>
					<l>to my own Soul as no one but myself can have a true Con-</l>
					<l>ception of. I brought myself into Hell Torment indeed</l>
					<l>for I forfeited my place &amp; privileges in the Congn, &amp; lost</l>
					<l>all Sight &amp; feeling of my Savr &amp; my Sins lay so heavy upon</l>
					<l>me that I knew no possible way of living in this Condition,</l>
					<l>All which Misery was occasioned by the well known Circum-</l>
					<l>stances of my second Marriage. I &amp; my wife being both</l>
					<l>guilty &amp; also both miserable &amp; unhappy beyond Description</l>
					<l>we knew not what to do but to weep &amp; cry to Jesus that if</l>
					<l>possible He might look on us in our deplorable Condition</l>
					<l>&amp; shew Mercy unto us. He was also entreated of us &amp;</l>
					<l>had Mercy upon such abominable Sinners as we were,</l>
					<l>that we could believe &amp; feel that He had pardoned our many</l>
					<l>&amp; heinous Transgressions. We then prayed the whole Congn</l>
					<l>to forgive us &amp; receive us once more into her Fellowship</l>
					<l>&amp; which in Time was granted unto us to our abiding Consola-</l>
					<l>tion. This was a Grace which I shall thank my sweet Savr</l>
					<l>for throughout my whole Life &amp; also in Eternity. From this</l>
					<l>Time I have been enabled to live under a bowing Sense of</l>
					<l>my sweet Savr Love, &amp; the Blessings I have enjoyed in the</l>
					<l>Congn have been highly prized by me; yea every the least</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Crumb I enjoyed I rec&apos;d</l>
					<l>out of Mercy as a Favour I was undeserving of.</l>
					<l>I shall never be able to thank Him duly for what He has done for me</l>
					<l>poor unfaithful Sinner, but shall etarnally sing of his Love &amp;</l>
					<l>Mercy &amp; Faithfullness. So far out of his Account.</l>
					<l>Since his Readmission to the Congn he has spent his Time</l>
					<l>as a Sinner who had received Grace, &amp; acknowledged him-</l>
					<l>self very undeserving of what he enjoyed. Some Time ago</l>
					<l>his Constitution began to break &amp; he daclinad gradually, but</l>
					<l>was chearful in his Heart &amp; confident to our Savr &amp; thus</l>
					<l>continued till he obtained permission to enter into the </l>
					<l>joy of his Lord.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
