<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ann Krugelstein: Memoir
               <lang>English</lang>
            </title>               
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator
               <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>               
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Life of Ann Krugelstein</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>

                 <div type="memoir">
                    <pb type="page" n="1" ana=".10250.26225"/>
            <figure n="250-01">
               <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-01.jpg"/>
               <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 1</ab>
            </figure>
                    
                    <head>Life of the Widow, Sister <persName><hi rend="underline">Ann Krügelstein</hi></persName></head>
                                  
            <div type="para" n="1">
            <p>
               <lb/> by 
               <lb/>Maiden Name <persName sameAs="Krugelstein">Gold</persName> of <placeName>Moravia</placeName> who departed in <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>
               <lb/><date>Apr. 30th 1778</date>. She has left the following remarkable Account of
               <lb/>the Grace &amp; Mercy the Lord bestowed upon her during her Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="para" n="2">
               <p>          
               <lb/>I was born <date>July 10th 1713</date> at <placeName>Zauchtenthal near Fulneck
                  <lb/>in Moravia</placeName>. Already in my second Year I experienced a grac-
               <lb/>ious Preservation of God. My Mother used to gather Grass
               <lb/>for her Cattle, &amp; generally took me along, &amp; laying me once down 
               <lb/>near a Tree, a Wolf came, placed himself close by me, &amp; smelt
               <lb/>at me. My Mother felt at once very anxious, &amp; turning
               <lb/>about to look for me, she saw the ravenous Beast with me.
               <lb/>She then run hastily towards me, and the Wolf went a few
               <lb/>Steps back, so that she could take me. My Parents reveiwed 
               <lb/>me anew as a Gift of God, and thanked him with Tears for
               <lb/>my Preservation, for they were both devout People; and 
               <lb/>having looked upon me from my Birth as a gracious Gift
               <lb/>of God, they endeavoured to educate me according to his
               <lb/>Mind, wept &amp; prayed often to God in my Behalf &amp; took
               <lb/>all possible Pains with me. In my 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year I became
               <lb/>much concerned about regaining a Fellowship with God 
               <lb/>through Jesus Christ, because I had heard my Father
               <lb/>say, that we had lost it by the Fall of Adam, but that
               <lb/>the second Adam Jesus Christ had procured it again
               <lb/>through his Sufferings and Death. The Holy Ghost took

                  <pb type="double_left" n="2" ana=".10250.26226"/>         
                  <figure n="250-02">
                     <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-02.jpg"/>
                     <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 2</ab>
                  </figure>
                  <lb/>me upon this Occasion into a particular School , stirred
                  <lb/>up in my a Confidence to God, so that I could converse
                  <lb/>with him quite familiarly, &amp; preserved me in many Dan, 
                  <lb/>gers from Deviations, giving me an Admonition when 
                  <lb/>I was not on the right Track. He at the same time wrought 
                  <lb/>in me a Fear of falling into Sin, and granted me the 
                  <lb/>Grace to speak uprightly with my Parents about every
                  <lb/>Thing. By which means I escaped many Temptations
                  <lb/>of the Enemy of my Soul.</p>
               </div>
                    
                    <div type="para" n="3">
                       <p>
     
                  <lb/>In the Year <date>1724</date> there was a great Awakening among
                  <lb/>the Children in <placeName>Moravia</placeName>. I heard that we must get a 
                  <lb/>new Heart if we will be saved, &amp; that God alone was able 
                  <lb/>to give it. This occasioned new Perplexity in me, seeing
                  <lb/>that I was deficient herein <add>&amp;</add> I was much troubled. I at the
                  <lb/>same Time looked out for some Companions, to whom I would
                  <lb/>discover this my Concern, &amp; our Saviour gave me eight who
                  <lb/>had the same Mind; we often went into hollow Roads and
                  <lb/>Bushes, where we were alone, &amp; wept and prayed for the new Heart.
                  <lb/>A Hope was also kindled within me, that I should become 
                  <lb/>a Partaker of it, tho' I felt myself very unworthy.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="4">
                       <p>
                  
                  <lb/>In <date>1727</date> the Persecution in <placeName>Moravia</placeName> rose to that Pitch
                  <lb/>that Orders were given, that everyone should swear Allegiance
                  <lb/>to the roman catholic Religion. My Mother who had a
                  <lb/>faithful Heart to our Savior, would &amp; could not do it, but
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">resolved</note>

<pb type="double_right"/>
                  <lb/>resolved rather to emigrate. She asked me whether I would
                          <lb/>accompany her? I consented directly, &amp; the Concern of our Heart
                          <lb/>to see our Souls saved, was so great, that nothing could detain us.
                       </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="5">
                       <p>

                          <lb/>While these Things were going on, my Mothers older Brother
                          <lb/><persName>John Nitschman</persName> arrived with us from <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, who emigrated
                          <lb/>before us, to him we discovered our Intention , &amp; he being willing
                          <lb/>to accompany us, my Father made directly secret Preparations for
                          <lb/>our Departure. And thus we left our House &amp; Mother Country
                          <lb/><date>June 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1727,</date> &amp; set out for <lb/><placeName>Herrnhut</placeName> My <sic>Oncle <corr>Uncle</corr></sic> |: her Mothers
                          <lb/><persName>Brother Melchior Nitschman </persName>:| who was in Jail at <placeName>Kunewalde</placeName> |: who 
                          <lb/>at last died in Prison at <placeName>Kremsir</placeName> as a Martyr :| and to whom I 
                          <lb/>brought from time to time what he stood in Need of; to him I had
                          <lb/>discovered our Intention, shortly before, &amp; had taken a very moving
                          <lb/>Leave of him. He recomended us there to the Protection of the Lord, 
                          <lb/>and said to me during a particular Sense of the Peace of God: " I
                          <lb/>am sure I shall find thee once among the Number of those who are
                          <lb/>with the Lord " On our Journey we were several times in Danger
                          <lb/>of our Lives, &amp; besides this had to suffer much Distress, Hard
                          <lb/>ships &amp; Anxiety. But our Savior helped us, so that we arrived 
                          <lb/>safe, chearful and happy <date>July 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>.</date> at <placeName>Berthelsdorf</placeName> to our unspeak-
                          <lb/>able Joy. The next Day we went to <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, &amp; were welcomed 
                          <lb/>with much Affection by the little Congregation there. But we had
                          <lb/>to live yet for some Time in <placeName>Berthelsdorf</placeName>.
                       </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="6">
                       <p>
                          
                          <lb/>My Concern for my Salvation increased here more &amp; more.
                          <lb/>I yet remember that I felt something extraordinary during the

                          <pb type="double_left" n="3" ana=".10250.26227"/>         
                          <figure n="250-03">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-03.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 3</ab>
                          </figure>
                          
                          <lb/>great Comunion <date>Aug. 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1727</date>, and I begged the Lord Jesus,
                          <lb/><hi rend="strikethrough">attended</hi> with many Tears to think also of me. I went here to
                          <lb/>School to <persName>Mr. Krumpa</persName>, who often told us that he loved the
                          <lb/>Lord Jesus, because he had shed his Blood for us. This excited
                          <lb/>in me a Confidence to our Savior that he probably had also
                          <lb/>shed his Blood for me, &amp; would have Mercy upon me. At the
                          <lb/>Time when in <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName> the great Awakening among the Children
                          <lb/>began, he asked once his Scholars: Whether they also would love
                          <lb/>our Savior &amp; give him their Hearts, so that He might wash them
                          <lb/>wih his Blood? With those who expressed a Desire for it, he
                          <lb/>made a Covenant, to love Him above all Things who loved us
                          <lb/>first. Upon which Occasion He in whose Eyes we were precious
                          <lb/>walked certainly in our Midst, &amp; none of us knew what had hap,
                          <lb/>pened unto us. It occasioned a great Joy in <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, that our 
                          <lb/>Savior had also graciously visited the Children in <placeName>Berthelsdorf</placeName>.
                          <lb/>We wept &amp; prayed together during an inexpressible Feeling of the
                          <lb/>Nearness of Jesus.
                       </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="7">
                    <p>

                          <lb/>My Parents moved soon after to <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, where we had
                          <lb/>it outwardly very pinching &amp; hard. But I must say to the 
                          <lb/>Praise of our Savior, that I could suit myself pretty well into
                          <lb/>poor Circumstances, for I had left my Mother Country with
                          <lb/>no other Intention, than to be satisfied with Bread and Water.
                          <lb/>But the H. Ghost begun a new Work in me. I learned to know
                          <lb/>our Savior as the Friend of poor Sinners; he forgave me 
                          <lb/>the Sin of Not believing in Him and His Merit, &amp; showed me my
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">Name</note>

<pb type="double_right"/>

                          <lb/>Name engraven into his Hands. Now happy did my Heart
                          <lb/>feel when he cleared it up to me, that His Sufferings, his Death
                          <lb/>&amp; Bloodshedding had also happened for my sake, &amp; that I was
                          <lb/>his Property. I could not sufficiently contemplate our Savior
                          <lb/>in his Sufferings Beauty, whereby all external Troubles &amp;
                          <lb/>Difficulties were made quite easy to me. In <date>January 1729</date>
                          <lb/>I was to my inexpressible Joy admitted to the H. Comunion
                          <lb/>with the Congrn. I then made |: as it was the Custom at that
                          <lb/>Time :| a public Confession before the Cogrn. that I would be,
                          <lb/>long with Soul &amp; Body to my Redeemer &amp; devote to Him
                          <lb/>Life &amp; All. In this blessed Enjoyment of our Savior, I went
                          <lb/>on during a particular Care of the never to be forgotten Dis-
                          <lb/>ciple of the Lord, <persName>Count Zinzendorf</persName>, who took much Care &amp;
                          <lb/>Pain with me, till <date>1732</date> when i came to <placeName>Ebersdorf</placeName>, to take
                          <lb/>Care of some young Countesses. Here I was to my Heart
                          <lb/>somewhat removed from the Simplicity in Christ Jesus.
                          <lb/>But our Savior, according to his great Faithfulness, did not
                          <lb/>suffer me to be plucked out of his Hand, but renewed in me that
                          <lb/>Mind to devote myself to him <sic>intirely <corr>entirely</corr></sic>, &amp; to look upon it as my
                          <lb/>destined Share to follow him, in Poverty &amp; Reproach. By Occasion
                          <lb/>that I was joined in H. Matrimony <date>Sept. 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1733</date> with that
                          <lb/>Servent of Jesus my late Husband <persName>David Kriegelstein</persName>, I re-
                          <lb/>newed the Covenant with our Savior to be his with Soul and Body, and
                          <lb/>begged Him to be with me, &amp; lead me by his Hand, till he would
                          <lb/>happily take me home. He did not last long, before we had to

                          <pb type="double_left" n="4" ana=".10250.26228"/>         
                          <figure n="250-04">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-04.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 4</ab>
                          </figure>

                          <lb/>experience Poverty &amp; Reproach of various Kinds. Till <date>1736</date>
                          <lb/>we had the Care of the Girls <sic>Oeconomy <corr>Economy</corr></sic> in <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, &amp; assisted in
                          <lb/>the Work of the Lord &amp; the Congrn. and particularly the married Choir. 
                          <lb/>In <date>June the same Year</date> we went to <placeName>Ronneburg in Wetteravia</placeName>, &amp;
                          <lb/>from there to <placeName>Frankfort upon Mayn</placeName>, &amp; with these Journies we made
                          <lb/>the Beginning of a poor Pilgrim Life, having often at our Nights Lodgings
                          <lb/>neither Bed Clothes above nor under us; and in the latter Place,
                          <lb/>there arose soon a Persecution against the Brethren, so that we
                          <lb/>were obliged to leave the City. We then stayed with the Pilgrim 
                          <lb/>Congrn. at <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, &amp; afterwards in <placeName>Wetteravia</placeName> till in <date>Oct. 1738</date> when
                          <lb/>we set out on our Journey from <placeName>Marienborn to Livonia </placeName>with a Visa
                          <lb/>to go, agreable to our Call, through Russia to Persia. Our Savior
                          <lb/>blessed our Abode in <placeName>Livonia</placeName> to many Souls, &amp; granted us the Grace
                          <lb/>to testify with a hearful Heart to People in high &amp; low Rank
                          <lb/>what Jesus Blood each do on Sinners <unclear>base</unclear>. I shall never 
                          <lb/>forget it, what a powerful Grace ruled at that Time among
                          <lb/>the Estonians &amp; Lettonians. 
                       </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="8">
                       <p>

                          <lb/>In <date>1740</date> we returned to <placeName>Marienborn</placeName>, where I enjoyed a very
                          <lb/>blessed Time. The Year following |:<date>1741</date>:| we resided with the
                          <lb/>Pilgrim Congrn. at Geneva and Montmirail and in <date>May 1742</date> we
                          <lb/>went with <persName>Count Zinzendorf</persName>s Family the second Time to <placeName>Livonia</placeName>.
                          <lb/>But we found it this time very different from the Time we had
                          <lb/>been there before; because a great Enmity had arisen against
                          <lb/>the Brethren &amp; which increased more &amp; more, and in <date>April
                             <lb/>1747</date> the Beginning was made to put the Brethren in Prison.
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">The B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></note>
<pb type="double_right"/>

                          <lb/>The <persName>Brn. Gutslef</persName> and <persName>Helderhof</persName>were first brought as Pri-
                          <lb/>soners to <placeName>Petersburg</placeName>, and in <date>June</date> following also <persName>Br. Fritshe</persName>
                          <lb/>and my Husband. Though there was a very strict Prohibition, that
                          <lb/>none of the Brn. &amp; Srs. should be suffered either to leave the Country
                          <lb/>or come into it; I ventured it however to travel with my Son 3<unclear>1/2</unclear>
                          <lb/>Years old, whom our Savior had given me in <placeName>Livonia</placeName>, &amp; a Foster
                          <lb/>Daughter <persName>Mary Jacob</persName>, to <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>. Having no Passport I could not
                          <lb/>travel on the public Roads, &amp; as besides this 6000 Russians
                          <lb/>had formed a Line from the <placeName>River Dina</placeName> to the Boundaries |:it being
                          <lb/>then War:| there was according to all human Appearance no Probabi,
                          <lb/>lity to come through. But our Saviour who was so inexpressibly
                          <lb/>near to me at the time when my Husband was taken Prisoner
                          <lb/>so that it was as if he spoke personally with me, comforted and sup-
                          <lb/>ported me powerfully. I simply followed his Leading, and he brought
                          <lb/>me at last through many Dangers, round about Ways, Wildernesses
                          <lb/>&amp; Morasses to <placeName>Angermünde in Curland</placeName> to the <persName>Rev. M. Laskiell</persName>
                          <lb/>where I was richly strengthened &amp; refreshed. They also cared for it
                          <lb/>that I safely arrived at <placeName>Königsberg</placeName>, from whence I was accompanied
                          <lb/>to <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, where I arrived in <date>Aug. the same Year |:1747:| </date>For
                          <lb/>Joy that I was in my dear <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, I forgot for some Time all
                          <lb/>my Griefs &amp; Sorrows, and <persName>Count Zinzendorf</persName> took a fatherly Care
                          <lb/>of me, so that I would speak fully with him about all my Circum-
                          <lb/>stances. However the Grief about my dear Husband, of whom
                          <lb/>I would get no Account to be depended upon, returned soon, &amp;
                          <lb/>besides this I had many laudy &amp; heavy Hours, so that it was
                          <lb/>a Wonder that I was so safely delivered of my Son <persName>John Friederich</persName>

                          <pb type="double_left" n="5" ana=".10250.26229"/>         
                          <figure n="250-05">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-05.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 5</ab>
                          </figure>

                          <lb/><date>Jan. 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1748</date>. In Aug. the same Year I moved to <placeName>Lindheim
                          <lb/>in Wetteravia</placeName> to have the Care of the Childrens <sic>Oeconomy <corr>Economy</corr></sic>, where
                          <lb/>I had the Pleasure to recieve the first Account to be depended
                          <lb/>upon from my dear Husband, by a most affectionate Letter
                          <lb/>of his own Handwriting. In <date>1751</date> <persName>Br. Risler</persName> came to <placeName>Marien</placeName>,
                          <lb/>born from <placeName>Petersburg</placeName>, &amp; brought me by Word of Mouth good Ac,
                          <lb/>counts of my dear Husband, &amp; offered me to take me along with
                          <lb/>him. This Offer I received as out of the Hand of our Savior. And
                          <lb/><date>Aug. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></date>. I sat out with him &amp; his dear Wife thither with the Blessing
                          <lb/>of <persName>Count Zinzendorf </persName>and the <hi rend="underline">Brn</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Srs</hi>. My four Children I re,
                          <lb/>comended to the faithful Heart of Jesus &amp; the Congregation, &amp;
                          <lb/>my Heart was then so disposed: I know that I am Jesus Pro-
                          <lb/>perty; of his Flesh &amp; of his Bone, &amp; shall remain his eternally
                          <lb/>tho' I am very poor and wretched. I go with that Mind to my 
                          <lb/>dear Husband to do that which our Savior would have me to
                          <lb/>do, and I shall continue sitting at the Feet of Jesus. The <date>29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 
                          <lb/>the same Month</date> we arrived at <placeName>Petersburg</placeName>. But I had to keep
                          <lb/>myself at first very still in <persName>Br. Koehlers</persName> House, till he had
                          <lb/>procured Leave for me to come to <placeName>Petersburg</placeName>. Besides this I
                          <lb/>grew so sick, that I could not think otherwise, but that I should
                          <lb/>depart this Life without having seen my Husband. Add to this
                          <lb/>that I could not even let my Husband know anything of my
                          <lb/>Trouble, because whatever I wrote to him I had to regulate
                          <lb/>so that all might read it, because Leave for my Journey to
                          <lb/><placeName>Petersburg</placeName> was not yet procured. This was a very hard Trial
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">for me</note>

<pb type="double_right"/>
                          <lb/>for me, &amp; yet but a small one in Comparison of those to come.
                          <lb/>I spent my sleepless Nights in Conversation with my only Friend,
                          <lb/>wetted my Pillows with Tears; Jesus Perplexities, his merit-
                          <lb/>orious Tears, &amp; nightly Prayers, were of great Service to me,
                          <lb/>they strengthened &amp; comforted me, so that I could childlikely
                          <lb/>resign myself to him, &amp; believe that if I even should go home
                          <lb/>to Him without having seen my Husband, that he however
                          <lb/>would be my most faithful &amp; never failing Friend, who knows
                          <lb/>best for what Reason he has brought me hither. <persName ana="Risler">Br.</persName> &amp; <persName>Sr Risler</persName>
                             <lb/>&amp; <persName>Ferbers</persName> visited me as often as possible, &amp; refreshed my
                          <lb/>needy Soul, which I shall acknowledge with Gratitude as long as 
                          <lb/>I live. I however recovered again &amp; <date>Sept 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. |:1751:|</date> being our
                          <lb/>Wedding Day, <persName>Br. Koehler</persName> made me the Pleasure &amp; led me in-
                          <lb/>cognito with his Family to the Brethren in Prison. This
                          <lb/>was indeed a great Joy to see each other again after so long a
                          <lb/>Time. In <date>Oct. 1751</date> I obtained at last Leave to move to my
                          <lb/>dear Husband, to whom Leave was granted to move with the
                          <lb/><persName>Brn Helterhof</persName> &amp; <persName>Fritshe |:Gudslef</persName> was already gone to our Savior:|
                          <lb/>into the hired House of <persName>Sr. Helterhof</persName>. This was a great Refresh-
                          <lb/>ment for my sick &amp; weary Heart. But even this could not come
                          <lb/>to pass without Trouble, for there came soon Counter Order
                          <lb/>that I should not yet move to my Husband, &amp; I had to live 6
                          <lb/>Days with <persName ana="Risler">Br.</persName> and <persName>Sr Risler</persName> in a private Manner. However we
                          <lb/>had afterwards the Pleasure to live together for some Time,
                          <lb/>which was effected by the inexpressible Pain <persName>Br. Koehler</persName> took, who
                          <lb/>for our sake had to put up with much Vexation &amp; Reproach.
                       </p>
                    </div>

                          <pb type="double_left" n="6" ana=".10250.26230"/>         
                          <figure n="250-06">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-06.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 6</ab>
                          </figure>
                    <div type="para" n="9">
                       <p>
                          <lb/>But our Joy did again not last long, for in <date>May 1752</date> our
                          <lb/>Brn had to return again to the Catacombs |: <hi rend="strikethrough">subterrarious</hi> Vaults:|
                          <lb/>on account of the Misbehaviors of another Prisoner. We Sisters
                          <lb/>viz. <persName>Sr. Helderhof </persName>and I had however Leave to visit &amp; to nurse
                          <lb/>them. <date>Nov. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>.</date> the same Year they and we came into great Distress
                          <lb/>by Water, the Nerva swelling to such a Degree that the Water rose
                          <lb/>in the Catacombs up to the half of the Windows, &amp; in our House
                          <lb/>so that I stood up to the Belly in Water, &amp; thus had to retire
                          <lb/>to the upper Story of the House, without being able to put on
                          <lb/>dry Clothes. To my great <sic>Surprize</sic> <corr>Surprise</corr> I continued well &amp; healthy
                          <lb/>&amp; the next Morning I could go to the Prisoners, who to save
                          <lb/>themselves had got up on the Wall, where they had to continue
                          <lb/>2 Nights &amp; one Day in the open Air in great Cold, Snow &amp; Rain.
                       </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="10">
                       <p>
                          
                          <lb/>We brought them &amp; also to other Prisoners some Refreshments to
                          <lb/>make them warm; but we could not come to them without great 
                          <lb/>Danger of our Lives, the Stream having torn the Bridge leading
                          <lb/>to the Fortress in such a Manner that scarce a Soldier ventured
                          <lb/>to cross it. Similar Inundations happened <date>the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. and 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of Nov.</date>
                          <lb/>but against which better Precautions were taken.<date> Dec. 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date> we
                          <lb/>had again the Joy to obtain Leave to live together;<persName> Secretary Na-
                          <lb/>bakof</persName> having procured free Lodgings for us in the Suburbs, in
                          <lb/>which we could live very comfortably.
                       </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="11">
                       <p>

                          <lb/><date> Oct. 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. 1753</date> our Savior gave me a little Daughter, &amp; this our
                          <lb/>little Fellow Prisoner was baptized by the <persName>Rev. Mr. Buzow</persName>
                          <lb/>Minister of the great lutheran Church in <placeName>Petersburg</placeName>, during a
                          <lb/>very blessed Feeling of the near Presence of our Lord. She was
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">called</note>
<pb type="double_right"/>

                          <lb/>called <persName>Johanna Christina</persName>. The Minister recomended her with
                          <lb/>particular Affection to the Preservation &amp; Protection of our Savior here
                          <lb/>in this strange Country; Many Tears were shed upon this Occasion.
                       </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="12">
                       <p>

                          <lb/>We lived yet sometime very chearful &amp; in Sickness, &amp; the va-
                          <lb/>rious Frights, which never were wanting, were so much the easier
                          <lb/>to be born, because we could still live together. But still in the
                          <lb/>same Year it pleased our dear Lord to take our faithful Friend
                          <lb/><persName>Secretary Nabakof </persName>out of this World. He believed in Jesus. During the
                          <lb/>Direction of his Successor, who did not know us, we were first more
                          <lb/>confined, and in the Night of the <date>28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of Aug.</date> my Husband and the <persName>Brn
                          <lb/>Helterhof</persName> &amp; <persName>Fritshe</persName> were fetched &amp; carried away, without knowing
                          <lb/><hi rend="underline">why</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">whither</hi>. I myself had to assist in putting my Husband who
                          <lb/>was sick unto Death into an open Boat, &amp; see him thus carried away
                          <lb/>on the Water in Storm &amp; Rain. We two Sisters spent the Night weeping,
                          <lb/>&amp; when the next Morning Enquiry was made of those who had carried
                          <lb/>them away, whether they had been brought; we were still more frighted
                          <lb/>by fearful Accounts of their Fate. At last we received the joyful
                          <lb/>News, that they had been brought to their former Prison, &amp; that we
                          <lb/>might visit them. We hastened directly to them, to bring them 
                          <lb/>some Refreshments. This proved to be a great Joy to see those
                          <lb/>yet alive whom we believed dead. To my great Astonishment
                          <lb/>I found my Husband a little better, tho' sometimes so weak, that 
                          <lb/>I went away in the Evening with the Thought of having seen him
                          <lb/>the last Time. I spoke confidently with our Savior about there
                          <lb/>Circumstances, and He convinced me that it was according to His Heart

                          <!-- page 7 is a duplicate -->
                          <pb type="double_left" n="8" ana=".10250.26232"/>         
                          <figure n="250-08">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-08.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 7</ab>
                          </figure>
                          <lb/>&amp; Mind, that they were Prisoners here in <placeName>Petersburg</placeName>; my
                          <lb/>Husband was also convincedof it, &amp; we encouraged each other
                          <lb/>often to be resigned to our Fate, &amp; happy &amp; chearful in the Near-
                          <lb/>ness of our dr. Lord, and to have all our Troubles sweetened by
                          <lb/>the Converse with Him. Leave was indeed given us to visit the
                          <lb/>Brethren in the Day Time as often as we pleased; but there were
                          <lb/>always People who made it very difficult, <unclear>you</unclear> often impossible
                          <lb/>for us, &amp; thus we got one Fright after another. And besides this
                          <lb/>our Savr. took in <date>1755</date> <persName>Sr. Helterhof </persName>to himself, &amp; thus I was quite 
                          <lb/>alone in the House with my Child. Not understanding the russian
                          <lb/>Language, &amp; being obliged to leave my Child alone in the House,
                          <lb/>when I had to go out, &amp; being in continual Danger of a <sic>Sur,
                             <lb/>prize</sic> <corr>Surprise </corr>by Robbers; the Brn. &amp; Srs. in <placeName>Petersburg</placeName> advised me
                          <lb/>to make Application to the Cong<hi rend="underline">rn</hi> for somebody to assist me, &amp;
                          <lb/>I got <persName>Br. Grumberg </persName>who took a most faithful Care of me &amp; my
                          <lb/>Child. I had also taken a russian Girl out of Compassion , who got
                          <lb/>a Love for our Savior, &amp; when I went out |:for I had to carry to
                          <lb/>the Brn. all their Necessaries:| she entertained my Child with Singing
                          <lb/>Verses. Once in Winter <date>1757</date> when going over the <placeName>River Neva</placeName>, the 
                          <lb/>Ice broke under me, &amp; the Stream carried me a Piece along,
                          <lb/>so that I must have been drowned, if the Eye &amp; Watchman of
                          <lb/>Israel had not so faithfully preserved me, But I became very
                          <lb/>sickly afterwards. In this Distress I prayed fervently to our
                          <lb/>Savior, to grant me the Satisfaction, to nurse the three Prisoners
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">as</note>
<pb type="double_right"/>

                          <lb/>as long as they stood in Need of Care &amp; Nursing in this Vale
                          <lb/>of Tears &amp; Trouble, though it should even be done in ever so
                          <lb/>great Weakness. And this He has done graciously &amp; helped me
                          <lb/>so, that through it seemed sometimes as if the <unclear>Tabernacle</unclear> would
                          <lb/>break, the B<hi rend="underline">rn.</hi> suffered however no Want. At this Time I had
                          <lb/>a particular Confidence in conversing with our Savior. One of
                          <lb/>these Conversations in <date>Oct. 1758 </date>was very imppressive to me, when
                          <lb/>I spoke fully with him about my whole Course of Life, &amp; was
                          <lb/>richly comforted about all my Mistakes. In <date>Febr. 1759 </date>we were
                          <lb/>at last set at Liberty, but ordered to go to Casan. We were 5 in
                          <lb/>Number, viz. my Husband, the <persName>B<hi rend="underline">rn.</hi> Helterhof</persName> &amp; <persName>Fritshe</persName> &amp; I &amp; my
                          <lb/>Child. On this Journey new Trials came upon us. The Brethren could
                          <lb/>not bear the violent Shaking of the Waggons, on the bad Roads &amp;
                          <lb/>Causeways, made of round Wood, after sitting so long in Prison, &amp;
                          <lb/>they had to suffer much, particularly my Husband, who had always
                          <lb/>been weak. Add to this the Fright of being attacked by Robbers on the
                          <lb/>other side of <placeName>Moscovia</placeName>, who most cruelly beat our Guards; he be-
                          <lb/>came quite enervated, &amp; a mortal Sickness befel him, so that he
                          <lb/>lost his Speech. His Mouth was at were burnt up, &amp; his Tongue
                          <lb/>withered, I had not even as much as a Drop of Water to refresh
                          <lb/>him. I often begged our Savior to comfort him with his Thirst. Besides
                          <lb/>this we saw nothing but inexpressible Difficulties before us. The People
                          <lb/>did not like to have any Dealings with us, because we had Soldiers
                          <lb/>with us, so that we often did not know, where to get a Morsel to eat,
                          <lb/>particularly as it was Lent Season, wherein the Russians are very

                          <pb type="double_left" n="9" ana=".10250.26233"/>         
                          <figure n="250-09">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-09.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 8</ab>
                          </figure>
                          <lb/>strict. At last we arrived at <placeName>Maram</placeName> upon the <placeName>River Ocke</placeName>, where 
                          <lb/>we met with more friendly People,who looked upon &amp; loved as par-
                          <lb/>ticular good Christians &amp; Children of God, &amp; served as as well as
                          <lb/>they could. We felt well among these People, &amp; I believe they will be
                          <lb/>counted among those to whom Jesus will say: I was sick and ye
                          <lb/>have come to the highest Pitch, for he could not even move his
                          <lb/>Tongue, &amp; lay quite speech &amp; senseless. The Creature begun now to
                          <lb/>plead with the Creator, &amp; I was quite at a Loss what to think or say, 
                          <lb/>when I considered that the Departure of my Husband was so near
                          <lb/>at Hand. But then in my greatest Trouble, &amp; when I was at the
                          <lb/>Brink of Despair, the loving Heart of Jesus interfered, &amp; set Bounds
                          <lb/>to the raging Waves; for our Savior gave Strength to my Husband
                          <lb/>that he in some Measure recovered, so that, to my great <sic>Surprize</sic> <corr>Surprise </corr>he 
                          <lb/>spoke fully with me about our Course hither to, &amp; particularly about
                          <lb/>this Journey, whereas he could not speak one Word before. He said
                          <lb/>among the rest: Be not discouraged about these Circumstances; thou
                          <lb/>knowest that our Savior already in <date>1738</date> gave Directions, that we
                          <lb/>through <placeName>Russia</placeName> should go to <placeName><sic>Assia <corr>Asia</corr></sic></placeName>, but the Enemy has thrown some
                          <lb/>Obstacles in the Way, so that it was stopt, about which I never could
                          <lb/>be satisfied, but now our Savr., with whom I have kept up on un,
                          <lb/>interrupted Conexion, amidst my Weaknesses of Soul &amp; Body has
                          <lb/>satisfied me about it, by this that the russian Government itself
                          <lb/>sends us now thither, so that we however shall see Asia, &amp; sojourn in it.
                          <lb/>My great Weakness is a natural Consequence of the great &amp; sudden
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">Alteration</note>
<pb type="double_right"/>

                          <lb/>Alteration of my Way of Life hitherto, &amp; belongs to the final Com-
                          <lb/>pletion of my Sufferings. And it is a Grace to me, that also in
                          <lb/>Sufferings I am made conformable to my best Friend. Our Savior
                          <lb/>well certainly restore my Health so that I shall reach the Place of
                          <lb/>our Destination. In <placeName>Casan</placeName> I shall probably go home to our Savior
                          <lb/>but <unclear>thote</unclear> wilt go again to the Cong<hi rend="underline">rn</hi>. with thy Child, &amp; with all our
                          <lb/>Children enjoy there much Goodness &amp; Mercy from our Savr. We
                          <lb/>then pursued our Journey &amp; my Husband recovered more &amp; more,
                          <lb/>yet I had to care for &amp; nurse him like a Child. At last <date>Apr 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 
                          <lb/>1769</date> we arrived at <placeName>Casan</placeName>, having been three times in evident
                          <lb/>Danger of our Lives, after we had entered the Borders of <placeName>Asia</placeName>. 
                          <lb/>In <placeName>Casan</placeName> we found it better, than we expected. The People there
                          <lb/>showed much Love &amp; Respect to us, and even the Governor himself
                          <lb/>behaved very friendly towards us. I often begged our Savior to
                          <lb/>give us at least one Soul, where our Testimony of him might
                          <lb/>find Entrance, &amp; it was not a small Satisfaction to us, that
                          <lb/>we could brave the Labour of the H. Ghost, with some Russians
                          <lb/>and Turks. I wept &amp; prayed much both on the Journey &amp; particu-
                          <lb/>larly here in behalf of the Inhabitants of this Country, &amp; I must
                          <lb/>own, that when I spoke right confidently with our Savior about it, he
                          <lb/>gave me a very gracious Look, &amp; the Assurance into my Heart
                          <lb/>that a Light will yet spring up in this Country. <date>Nov. 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. 1760</date>
                          <lb/><persName>Br. Fritche</persName> departed this Life happily, &amp; on the <date>9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of the following
                             <lb/>Month of Dec. </date>my Husband followed him in the 63<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Year of his Age, &amp;
                          <lb/>entered into the Joy of his Lord, &amp; everlasting Freedom &amp; Peace after
                          <lb/>a Captivity of more than 13 Years. I mentioned it directly to the <persName>Com-
                          
                          <pb type="double_left" n="10" ana=".10250.26234"/>         
                          <figure n="250-10">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-10.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 9</ab>
                          </figure>
                          
                          <lb/>mander Plaisin</persName>, who out of Love to my Husband, procured a 
                          <lb/>Passport for me from <placeName>Petersburg</placeName>, that so I might safely come thither.
                          <lb/>And though the Roads were very unsafe, &amp; much was heard of robbing
                          <lb/>&amp; murdering, I nevertheless ventured it on our Savior, to whose
                          <lb/>Care &amp; Protection I had quite anew surrendered myself; and it did 
                          <lb/>not come into my Mind that any Evil could happen unto me. And
                          <lb/>my Eyes flow with Tears of Gratitude &amp; Abasement, when i consider
                          <lb/>how evidently our Savior has cared for me, &amp; what Wonders of
                          <lb/>Grace &amp; Mercy he has shewn unto me. Just when I was going to
                          <lb/>set out on my Journey &amp; had called upon to accompany me , it was
                          <lb/>ordered so, that a Libonian <persName>Captain Durnstern</persName> had to travel the
                          <lb/>same Way; he took me gladly into his Company &amp; we set out
                          <lb/><date>Jan. 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1761</date> from <placeName>Casan</placeName>. My <lb/>taking Leave of <persName>Br. Helterhof</persName>
                          <lb/>who of the three captive B<hi rend="underline">rn</hi> alone was left, is known to our
                          <lb/>Savior, &amp; not to be expressed in Words. The Captain shewed in
                          <lb/>expressible Love &amp; Faithfulness to me &amp; my Child, &amp; more than
                          <lb/>once ventured his Life for our sakes particularly <date>Jan. 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date> when it
                          <lb/>had the Appearance as if we should find our Graves in the <placeName>River
                             <lb/>Wolga</placeName>; for the Ice begun to sink, &amp; to get Holes, &amp; some of the
                          <lb/>first Sleds fell already in the Water. We could not think of turning
                          <lb/>or evading it, for on one Side was already upon Water above the Ice
                          <lb/>&amp; on the other was a very steep high Shore. In this Distress came the
                          <lb/>Captain through the Water to us, broke off Branches from the Bushes
                          <lb/>which grew along the Shore, &amp; covered the Holes with them, &amp; himself
                          <lb/>led our Horses over them. And thus with the Help of God, we were de-
                          <lb/>livered out of this Distress, in which we had been from Noon till towards
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">Midnight</note>

<pb type="double_right"/>

                          <lb/>Midnight. The Captain cared for me &amp; my Child throughout the whole
                          <lb/>Journey like a Father, did not only pay all Expences, but let always one
                          <lb/>of his Servants stay with us, &amp; when distressing Circumstances occurred 
                          <lb/>he himself with some others hastened to our Assistance. He everywhere
                          <lb/>gave us out to be his Relations, &amp; took Care of our Things in the best
                          <lb/>Manner. I brought my Child very sick of the small Pox to <placeName>Mascovia</placeName>; but
                          <lb/>as the Captain would take me with him as far as <placeName>Novograd</placeName>. I set out 
                          <lb/>with my Child sick as it was, &amp; our Savior prevented all ill Consequences.
                          <lb/>But in <placeName>Novograd</placeName> where our Road parted, the Captain was very un,
                          <lb/>easy about me, particularly as he had heard of his Servants, that
                          <lb/>my Drivers had evil Designs against me, as soon as we should
                          <lb/>be alone. But in this Perplexity, we met quite unexpectedly, &amp; to
                          <lb/>our Joy, as russian <persName>Lieutenant of the Guard Milkanoth</persName>, who was
                          <lb/>a good Friend of the Captain, &amp; also knew <persName>Br. Koehler</persName> in <placeName>Petersburg</placeName>
                          <lb/>very well, who was also travelling thither. I took Leave of my Bene,
                          <lb/>factor with a thankful Heart, and he delivered me to the Lieutenant
                          <lb/>as his Relation, &amp; begged him to pay strict Attention to our Things
                          <lb/>&amp; Drivers, &amp; not suffer them to stay behind with me, saying: All you
                          <lb/>do unto her I shall look upon as done unto myself. The Lieutenant
                          <lb/>executed also his Commission in the best Manner, and our Savr. brought us
                          <lb/>safe &amp; well to <placeName>Petersburg</placeName> <date>Febr. 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1761.</date> O how glad &amp; thankful was I
                          <lb/>to be again among Brn. and Srs. But I met again with Difficulties on
                          <lb/>account of my farther Journey, everybody representing it to me 
                          <lb/>as impossible to get a Passport. But according to my Custom I re-
                          <lb/>comended also this Affair to my dear Lord, &amp; begged him to take it in
                          <lb/>Hand himself &amp; execute it. And this he did also to my great Joy &amp;
                          <lb/>Abasement, for he directed Matters so, that I got a Passport under

                          <pb type="double_left" n="11" ana=".10250.26235"/>         
                          <figure n="250-11">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-11.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 10</ab>
                          </figure>
                          
                          <lb/>the Name of the Ambassador of Saxony. Having now rested here a 
                          <lb/>little after so many sleepless Nights, Dangers, Troubles &amp; Distress, I
                          <lb/>sat out from <placeName>Petersburg</placeName> by Water, with my little Daughter, whom I had
                          <lb/>preserved as a particular Gift with all possible Care &amp; Faithfulness,
                          <lb/>accompanied by <persName>Br. Kryman</persName>, <date>May 18th. 1761</date>. The taking Leave of the
                          <lb/>Brn. &amp; Srs. here was very painful on both Sides. Towards Evening we
                          <lb/>set Sail, but we soon got a Storm, which was against us, &amp; a total
                          <lb/>Eclipse of the Moon rendered it quite dark, so that we saw nothing
                          <lb/>before us but our Destruction, particularly as our Vessel was
                          <lb/>too deeply laden, &amp; the <placeName>Neva</placeName> being in that Place full of Sand Banks.
                       </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="13">
                       <p>
                          
                          <lb/>We returned in great Danger &amp; sailed again the next Day for
                          <lb/><placeName>Cronstadt</placeName>. Here I had again new Troubles, but our Savior helped
                          <lb/>me thro', &amp; we could now pursue our Voyage without any Hindrance.
                          <lb/>I now looked once more at the Land of my Troubles with Tears
                          <lb/>in my Eyes, &amp; recomended it to the faithful Heart of Jesus.
                          
                          <lb/>So as the faithful Eye &amp; Watchman of Israel watched hitherto
                          <lb/>over me on my Journies, so I experienced it also on my farther
                          <lb/>Travels by Sea &amp; Land. It was as if the Arms of my dear Savior
                          <lb/>enclosed me around, especially at <placeName>Lüneburg</placeName> on the rest of my
                          <lb/>Journey. During the Time of our Abode at <placeName>Lüneburg</placeName> which lasted 10 Days
                          <lb/>there were every Day such violent Storms of Thunder &amp; Lightning as no,
                          <lb/>body remembered ever to have seen, but when we sat out the Weather
                          <lb/>was fair &amp; pleasant. And tho' that whole District was then sur-
                          <lb/>rounded with War, we saw nothing of it, &amp; arrived at last <date>July 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date>
                          <lb/>safe &amp; well at <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName> to our inexpressible Joy. Ah! what Tears of Joy 
                          <lb/><note type="catchword">and</note>
<pb type="double_right"/>

                          <lb/>and Thankfulness trickled down my Cheeks that my faithful Savior
                          <lb/>brought both me &amp; my Children to the Cong<hi rend="underline">rn</hi>. I devoted it, &amp; myself
                          <lb/>anew to Him as his "Property." Thus far her own Relation.
     
                          <lb/>Her Heart was filled with Thanks &amp; Praise, that our Savior had
                          <lb/>accomplished her ardent Desire to be again in the Cong<hi rend="underline">rn</hi> at <placeName>Herrn,
                             <lb/>hut</placeName>, so that she now would enjoy a happy Sabbath in the Cong<hi rend="underline">rn</hi>,
                          <lb/>&amp; with her Children. <date>July 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</date> she moved into the Widows House
                          <lb/>&amp; was made Use of as an Assistant, till <date>1764</date> when she moved to
                          <lb/><placeName>Marienborn</placeName>, &amp; <date>1766</date> to <placeName>Zeyst</placeName> with the then Directory. In <date>1768</date>
                          <lb/>she went to <placeName>England</placeName> with <persName ana="Boeler">Br.</persName> &amp; <persName>Sr. Boeler</persName> &amp; <persName>Count Dohnas</persName>, &amp; the Year
                          f<lb/>ollowing again to <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>. In <date>1770</date> she got a Call to go with <persName ana="Treyden">Br.</persName>
                          <lb/>and <persName>Sr. de Treyden </persName>to <placeName>Curland</placeName>, &amp; though she found it hard to leave
                          <lb/><placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, she however accepted it with a willing Heart. <persName>Sr. de
                             <lb/>Treyden </persName>gives the following Account of the Abode &amp; Service of
                          <lb/>our late Sister with them: "We were very thankful to our Savior
                          <lb/>that he would give us this, through many heavy Trials approved
                          <lb/>of Hand Maid of his to go along with us; both to be a Partaker
                          <lb/>of our Joy &amp; of the Troubles which befel us. She assisted us
                          <lb/>faithfully with good Advice and actual Help, &amp; proved parti-
                          <lb/>cularly a real Comfort &amp; Benefit to me after the Departure 
                          <lb/>of my dear Husband. Her cordial &amp; confident <unclear>Connection</unclear> with
                          <lb/>our Savior, alleviated all Difficulties to us both. She took a very
                          <lb/>near &amp; affectionate Share in all my Circumstances. She experi-
                          <lb/>enced also here in Curland various Trials, but her <unclear>Endeavours</unclear>
                          <lb/>for the Good of the Souls were attended with Blessing, the Fruits
                          <lb/>of which will shew themselves in Time to come. Both high

                          <pb type="page" n="12" ana=".10250.26236"/>         
                          <figure n="250-12">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0250a-12.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">Ann Krugelstein, Page 11</ab>
                          </figure>
                          
                          <lb/>&amp; low had a particular Love, Confidence &amp; Esteem for her.
                          <lb/>She has shewn inexpressible Faithfulness to me &amp; my Child <unclear>till</unclear>
                          <lb/>to her End. May our Savior reward her now richly for it. He
                          <lb/>alone can comfort me about the Loss of this venerable Mother, &amp; in-
                          <lb/>timate Friend of mine. <date>Sept. 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1773</date> she returned with me &amp; my
                          <lb/>Child to <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>, glad &amp; thankful for all the Proofs of Grace 
                          <lb/>&amp; Merry shewn to us all, by our dear Lord."</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="para" n="14">
                       <p>                                                
                          <lb/><date>April 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. in this
                          <lb/>1778<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. year</date> she grew very weak; she
                          <lb/>said directly, that she had spoken fully with our Savior about
                          <lb/>her whole Course of Life, &amp; had got the Assurance, that he would
                          <lb/>soon take her to himself. She added: Ah how sweetly will it
                          <lb/>sound, when I shall be with my dear Savior &amp; sing Praises
                          <lb/>unto Him; Yet I shall ne'er o'er my Happiness, joy otherwise
                          <lb/><unclear>that</unclear> with a blushing Face. I have not to shew any great 
                          <lb/>Actions or Deeds all is covered with Faults, so that I have
                          <lb/>nothing to say, but: Lord forgive me my Tresspasses. The Weak-
                          <lb/>ness &amp; Straitness in her Breast increased more &amp; more, &amp;
                          <lb/><date>Apr. 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date> this Hand Maid of Jesus entered into the Joy of her
                          <lb/>Lord after a remarkable Course thro' this Time. Her Age
                          <lb/>was 64 Years 9 Months and 19 Days.
                       </p>
                    </div>
                 </div>


      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
