<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nicholas Henry Eberhard: Memoir <lang>English</lang>
            </title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator
                  <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator
                  <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0
                  International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Life of Nicholas Henry Eberhard</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <div type="memoir">
            <pb n="1" ana=".10205.26050"/>
            <figure n="205-01">
               <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0205a-01.jpg"/>
               <ab type="caption">Nicholas Henry Eberhard, Page 1</ab>
            </figure>

            <div type="para" n="1">
               <p>
                  <placeName>New York.</placeName> Memoirs of <persName>B</persName><hi
                     rend="superscript"><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>. </persName><hi
                     rend="underline"><persName>Nicholas Henry Eberhard</persName>,</hi> so as He
                  himself penn'd them down in the Beginning of this Year, in a probable Expectation
                  of being soon calld home. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="para" n="2">
               <p> I was born in <placeName>Copenhagen</placeName>, <date>March 20<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1723</date> where my Father was Doctor and
                  Surgeon to a <sic>Grenadeir</sic>
                  <corr>Grenadier</corr> Regiment, and educated in the Lutheran Religion. After some
                  Years my Parents remov'd to <placeName>Helsingoer</placeName>, and my Mother
                  having nurs'd one of the young Princes, my Father on that Account was preferr'd
                     <add>by royal Favour</add> to an Office in the Tribute or Custom House at
                     <placeName>OEresund</placeName>. Here I was kept to a Latin School till in the
                     19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Year of my Age; In <date>1741</date> I went
                  to the University at <placeName>Copenhagen</placeName>. I had felt Motions of
                  Grace in my Heart from my tender Infancy, and shove the longer the more earnest to
                  free my Self from the Connections of the World and the Stirrings of Sin, but all
                  in vain. But after my Return in <date>1743. in March</date> our Saviour appeard to
                  my Heart in his suffering Form so lively, and let me feel the Forgiveness of my
                  Sins, and his Love, so powerfully, that all the Bands of Sin and the World, which
                  had hitherto fetter'd me, were at once broke asunder, and my Heart set in a Flame
                  of Love towards Him. This <pb type="double_left" n="2" ana=".10205.26051"/>
                  <figure n="205-02">
                     <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0205a-02.jpg"/>
                     <ab type="caption">Nicholas Henry Eberhard, Page 2</ab>
                  </figure> Change was particularly alarming to my Parents, so that my Father, after
                  all the Pains taken by the <unclear>Eulesias- -ticks</unclear> by his Advice, to
                  bring me to other Thoughts, had proved fruitless, at last forbid me his House.
                  <gap/>After the sudden Death of my Father in <date>May 44.</date> I took upon me
                  the Instruction of Children in a Gentlemans Family in the Country, who took a
                  particular Liking to Me, and He and the Rector of the Parish, made me some
                  interesting Proposals, which brought <add>me</add> into Danger of being entangled,
                  and indeed they operated so on one, that the Love of my Heart to our Saviour,
                  began to be lukewarm. But the faithful Shepherd who would not again
                     <sic>loose</sic>
                  <corr>lose</corr> his found Sheep, helpd me out of this Danger, and for that
                  Purpose made use of a Book which by Chance fell into my Hands, which was writ
                  against all Manner of Swearing, and even that which the serving an Office may
                  require. I thought: now I can neither be a Minister nor Schoolmaster, nor serve
                  any Office, as I can't with a good Conscience take the enjoind Oath, and by this
                  came into great Perplexity, not knowing what to do; I had also no Rest in my
                  Heart, <pb type="double_right"/> 'till I resolv'd to apply for my Dismission,
                  which the afore mentiond Gentleman tho' unwillingly, yet at last granted. I then
                     <sic>travell'd</sic>
                  <corr> travel'd</corr> to <placeName>Copenhagen</placeName>, where in <date>Jan<hi
                        rend="superscript">y</hi>. 45</date> I sought and obtaind Acquaintance with
                  the Brethren, of whom, as also of the Congregation I had heard some Time before.
                  The Occasion to this Proceeding was the <placeName>Bidingen</placeName>
                  Collections, by which I saw that the Brethren's Foundation of Happiness was the
                  Allsufficient Atonement of Christ, and that they among Themselves, as poor Sinners
                  heartily loved each Other. For as I had before heard so many strange Stories
                  related of the Pietists, I had resolv'd to go my Way in <sic>Stilness</sic>
                  <corr>Stillness</corr> for my self alone | But now I was determin'd to have Fellow
                  -ship with the Brethren, because my Heart was One with Them in this Matter. In
                        <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 46</date> I went thro' an
                  Examination in Divinity, not with Intent to commence Preacher in my Religion, for
                  my Call to the Congregation was indisputable to Me, but because I believed it
                  might other Ways be of Ad- -vantage. In the mean While my Longing for the
                  Congregation increased to that Degree, that I had no Rest in
                     <placeName>Copenhagen</placeName>, and therefore in <date>April 47.</date>
                  resolved with 3 other Brethren to go to <placeName>Herrnhaag</placeName>, where we
                  happily arrived the <date>16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of May.</date> I <pb
                     type="double_left" n="3" ana=".10205.26052"/>
                  <figure n="205-03">
                     <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0205a-03.jpg"/>
                     <ab type="caption">Nicholas Henry Eberhard, Page 3</ab>
                  </figure> soon obtaind Leave to Stay, came the <date>7<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> of July</date> into the Seminary at
                  <placeName>Lindheim</placeName>, and in the <date>Beginning of August</date>
                  removed with the Seminary and Nursery to <placeName>Ma- -rienborn</placeName>, and
                  was on the <date>30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of the Same</date> received into
                  the Congregation. But as I reason'd too much over the then flighty Period, and the
                  Feeling of the poor Sinnership was yet wanting to me, this caused that my Heart
                  did not rightly enjoy the Grace of Reception. In <date>Oct<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi> the same Year</date> I came to live with the Children, and the
                        <date>2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>
                     40.</date> to the first Participation of the Holy Sacrament with the
                  Congregation, and was admitted an Acolyte. But notwithstanding all these
                  Blessings, the Confusion of my Mind still continued: the being happy as a poor
                  Sinner was a Mystery to me, but my faithful Saviour sought to bring me upon my
                  original Depravity in Soul and Body, and I would feel nothing of all This, but
                  would only feel happy. By this I at last got into such Anxiety that the World
                  seemd too narrow for me. There was no Body that I had a Confidence to, to unbosom
                  my Distress to him; in the Congregation I had no Happiness, I tho<hi
                     rend="superscript">t</hi>. <pb type="double_right"/> many 1000 Times of going
                  away, but which way so ever I turn'd my Thoughts, I found nothing to comfort me;
                  yes the Disorder of my Mind went so far, that I reasond. Is there a God, or
                  Saviour? perhaps all the Grace that I have felt is only Fancy. <gap/>But the
                  Thought that our Saviour; out of unfathomable Love, had brought me to himself and
                  to his Congregation, at last gaind the upper -hand. I felt that if I were as holy
                  as an Angel, and had no Enjoyment of Jesu's Blood and Wounds, I should only be as
                  a dry Stick. This gave my Reasoning a mighty Shock, my Heart and Mind grew serene
                  as a poor Sinner I viewd the Wounds of Jesus with Delight, and began now | after I
                  had spent 3 long Years in this Situation of Heart | to expect every Day from our
                  Saviour, what would make me and preserve me happy. In the while I had removed with
                  the Seminary to <placeName>Barby</placeName>. Here I received my Call to
                        <placeName><sic>Pensylvania</sic>
                     <corr>Pennsylvania</corr></placeName> in <date>August 57.</date> and in
                  Consequence of that <sic>travelled</sic>
                  <corr>traveled</corr> with the Breth<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>
                  <persName>Bader</persName> and <persName>Rund</persName> to
                     <placeName>London</placeName>, and after some Stay there, pro- -ceeded with
                     <persName>B</persName><hi rend="superscript"
                     ><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>. Joseph</persName> and his Company to
                     <placeName>New York</placeName>, and arriv'd happily in
                     <placeName>Beth</placeName><hi rend="superscript"
                     ><placeName>m</placeName></hi><placeName>.</placeName> the <date>11</date><hi
                     rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date>. of Dec</date><hi
                     rend="superscript"><date>r</date></hi><date>.</date>
                  <gap/>The Year <date>52</date> was a blessed year to me, the happy
                     <sic>Sinnor</sic>
                  <corr>Sinner</corr> Point was invaluable, and <pb type="double_left" n="3"
                     ana=".10205.26053"/>
                  <figure n="205-04">
                     <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0205a-04.jpg"/>
                     <ab type="caption">Nicholas Henry Eberhard, Page 4</ab>
                  </figure> I perceivd that our Saviour had me now just in the same Spot, where He 9
                  Years before, let me feel his unspeak- -able Love the first Time. viz<hi
                     rend="superscript">t</hi>. To account all but Loss in Competition with him, and
                  rather let all the Members go to wreck, than that one of them should be Cause of
                  Grief to Him. <gap/>In the same Year after <persName>B</persName><hi
                     rend="superscript"><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>.
                     Brownfields</persName> De- -cease, the Book-keeping in the Congregation was
                  committed to Me, and I accepted of it in childlike Confidence to our Saviour, who
                  also helpd me in it notwithstanding my In- -experience and Unfitness; I had also
                  the Grace to be admitted into the <orgName>Band of Hourly Intercessors</orgName>,
                  and <orgName>Con- -gregation and Choir Disciples</orgName>. <date>Anno 53. the
                     26</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date>. of March</date>, I
                  was appointed to be Steward of the <orgName>Single B</orgName><hi
                     rend="superscript"><orgName>rs</orgName></hi><orgName> Choir</orgName>; and
                     <date>Anno 55 the 19 of Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi></date> at the Synod at
                     <placeName>Beth- -el</placeName> was ordaind Deacon of the Brethren's Church.
                  In <date>Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 56</date> I went to
                     <placeName>Scatticoke</placeName> according to a Call received, where I served
                  the little Indian Flock there according to the Grace our Saviour gave me, 1 Year
                  and 9 Months, and return'd in <date>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 57</date> to
                     <placeName>Bethlehem</placeName>. In <date>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                     following</date> I came to <pb type="double_right"/>
                  <placeName>Nazareth</placeName> Hall as Amanuensis to <persName>B</persName><hi
                     rend="superscript"><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>. Joseph</persName>,
                  and in <date>April 50</date> to <placeName>Litits</placeName>, to oversee and
                  direct the Building of the Choir Houses there. <gap/>In the Year <date>59.</date>
                  I felt almost a constant Pressure, because that I had yet so little Burning of
                  Heart towards my incomparable Bridegroom, and because that his precious Nearness
                  was not so constantly felt by me. O how oft has my Heart cried, and my Eye
                  overflowd, for a Heart in Him enamour'd? <date>Anno 61.</date> I had the Pleasure
                  of living with the Single Brethren in their new Choir House. <gap/>And now the
                  Oversight of the Building of the Congregation House was also committed to me, but
                  I must acknowledge that this Burden was made abundantly easy to me, as I resignd
                  my self entirely to the immediate Care of my heavenly Father. At the Conservation
                  of which on the <date>18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Sept<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> 63.</date> I was appointed General Deacon and As-
                  -sistant to my dear <persName>Bro</persName><hi rend="superscript"
                        ><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>.
                  </persName><persName>Hehl</persName>, in Preaching and Keeping Meetings; and to
                  that End the <date>21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of Feb<hi rend="superscript"
                        >y</hi> 64.</date> in <placeName>Bethl</placeName><hi rend="superscript"
                        ><placeName>m</placeName></hi><placeName>.</placeName> was joind in holy
                  Marriage with <persName>S</persName><hi rend="superscript"
                     ><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>. Sara van Vleck</persName>, with whom I
                  returnd to <placeName>Litits</placeName> in <date>April the same Year</date>.
                     <date>Anno <pb type="double_left" n="3" ana=".10205.26054"/>
                     <figure n="205-05">
                        <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0205a-05.jpg"/>
                        <ab type="caption">Nicholas Henry Eberhard, Page 5</ab>
                     </figure> 65. in June</date> We received a Call to <placeName>Oldmans Creek in
                     the Jersey</placeName>, to the Service of the Congregation there. <gap/>Here in
                     <date>June 66.</date> I was so violently seized with a Fever, that every Body
                  doubted of my Recovery; after I was grown somewhat better, I was again taken ill
                  with a Fever and Ague, which greatly reduced my Strength, and brought me into no
                  small Perplexity, as I had no One to assist in the Service of the little Flock
                  there. In this Pressure I turnd me unto our Saviour, and he heard my Sighs. After
                  We had served the Congregation there, with the gracious Support and Blessing of
                  our Saviour, 2 Years and 3 Months, We went to <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                  in Consequence of a Call we received to the Service of the Congregation there. But
                  this Call was soon revoked, so after a pleasing Stay of 2 Months in
                     <placeName>Bethlehem</placeName> We came here to <hi rend="underline"
                        ><placeName>Manakesy</placeName></hi><placeName> in Mary- -Land</placeName>,
                  in <date>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the same Year</date>; Where our Saviour
                  has hitherto graciously blest and guided me, and has let me have much Joy of the
                  Souls here. <pb type="double_right"/> especially I adore in the Dust before him,
                  with a thank- -ful Sinner Heart, for the particular Feeling of his precious and
                  consolatory Nearness. <gap/>So far our deceased Brother's own Words. Of his last
                  Days and Hours, his Widow has com- -municated the following. <gap/>In the Night
                  between the <date>3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> and 4<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> of April</date>, my dear Husband was seized with a violent Fever
                  and Pain in his Breast; notwithstanding which on the <date>4<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi>.</date> He kept the usual Wednesday Meeting. But the <date>8<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date> in the Night he was so weak, that I and
                  the Brethren and Sisters present thought, he would imme- -diately go home.
                  <gap/>This Paroxysm lasted 4 Hours; We at last found that He was in a Lethargy,
                  and after much Pains taken we brought him to himself again. He was uncommonly
                  feeble, and said: O could I have gone to our Saviour! the <date>9<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date> he said to me, I have never had in any
                  Sickness such a homeward Feeling as in This. <gap/>And as he perceived my Tears,
                  he lookd on Me <pb type="double_left" n="3" ana=".10205.26055"/>
                  <figure n="205-06">
                     <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0205a-06.jpg"/>
                     <ab type="caption">Nicholas Henry Eberhard, Page 6</ab>
                  </figure> and said: weep not, but rejoice with me. Oh what a Festivity would that
                  be for Me, if our Saviour would take me to himself! I then askd him, if he would
                  go and leave me? upon which he answerd: you will once follow me; beg of our
                  Saviour to preserve you from unnecessary Concern, for he will care for You, and be
                  himself your exceeding great Reward, for all that you have done, and still do for
                  me. He then desired me to bring him the Account Book of the Congregation here, and
                  gave me an Explanation of all the Particulars. The <date>10<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi>.</date>
                  <persName>B</persName><hi rend="superscript"
                     ><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>. &amp; S</persName><hi
                     rend="superscript"><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>. Powel</persName>
                  having heard of his Illness, came to us from <placeName>Carols
                        </placeName><sic><placeName>Mannor</placeName></sic><placeName> </placeName><corr><placeName>Manor</placeName></corr>:
                  He sat up, and confer'd with us about the Celebration of the <sic>Holydays</sic>
                  <corr>Holidays</corr>, altho' he was in a high Fever and had a great Pain in his
                  Breast. As we ask'd him, if we should not send for a Doctor to Him? he replied: I
                  want none; our Saviour shall be my Physician. He was childlikely resignd and pa-
                  -tient, so that even the visiting Strangers wonder'd at it. Among other Things he
                  said: that as often as he dosed a little, he was always busy about the Sacrament.
                     <pb type="double_right"/> and could not leave off. There was a sweet Nearness
                  of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. attended his Sickness, and therefore the
                  Watchers and <sic>Visiters</sic>
                  <corr>Visitors</corr> about him had always an agreeable Feeling. When we made his
                  Bed to Day, and laid him in again, he said: Oh could I so sink into my Saviours
                  Arms! and another Time. Oh that this Time was shortend! I would fain give a
                  Spring, and as in Flight go to our Saviour! the <date>17<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi>.</date> his <sic>chearful</sic>
                  <corr>cheerful</corr> Looks gave us Hope, that his Distemper was broke; But there
                  soon appeard evident Signs that our best Friend would fetch his Soul home. Which
                  he did the <date>18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</date> about 4 in the
                  Afternoon, with the Watch Word. "My Thoughts are not your Thoughts."
                     <persName>B</persName><hi rend="superscript"
                     ><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>. Powel</persName> imparted to him the
                  last Blessing in a Liturgy accompanied by a soft peaceful Sensation. <gap/>I can
                  give him this Testimony, that He behaved towards me as a very tender Husband, yea
                  rather as a loving Father. may our Saviour reward Him! <gap/>The Intercourse with
                  the Man of Smart, was the only Object of his Heart. and espe- -cially for a Year
                  past, me could perceive that his Conversation was already more in Heaven than here
                  below. <gap/>Wherefore He often express'd his Desire to be dissolved, and to be at
                  home with Christ. which came to pass at the Age of 47 Years and 1 Month. </p>
            </div>

         </div>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
