<?xml-model href="../../TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian Bell: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
               <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
               <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary">Mary Allot</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-05.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="subject">
               <persName ref="mlper000217">Mary Allot</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <place>
               <placeName ref="mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>
            </place>
         </settingDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-07-16" who="#JAKA1">Checked semantic markup</change>
         <change when="2019-06-17" who="#jschaumberger">Finished markup of the memoir</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head><persName ref="#mlper000217">Mary Allot</persName></head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head type="page">1</head>
               <pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-01.jpg" />
               <p><persName ref="#mlper000217">Mary Alott</persName> Was born at <placeName>Barksland in the Parish of Elland</placeName>. On the <date when-iso="1734-12-12">12th of Dec<hi
                        rend="superscript">r </hi>1734</date> N S. When she was about <date when-iso="1737" cert="medium">three years old</date> her Father dyed &amp; she liv'd with her mother &amp;
                  her <persName ana="Betty Midgley">Aunt</persName> (Namely Betty Midgley) who jointly Nurs'd &amp; maintain'd her <hi rend="superscript">till</hi>
                  <date when-iso="1741" cert="medium">she was about seven</date>, then her mother being again married her <persName ana="Betty Midley">aunt</persName> left them took a Room &amp;
                  design'd to live by herself, But <hi rend="superscript">Mary</hi> not being at all willing to be left behind often begg'd her <persName ana="Betty Midgley">Aunt</persName> to take
                  her with her, which according<add place="above">ly</add> in a few weeks after she willlingly did, &amp; cared for her as her own.</p> 
               <p><date when-iso="1743">When she was about Nine years
                     old</date> she by the drawing of the <persName type="diety">Holy ghost</persName> was inclin'd to hear the gospel which she of her own free accord begun &amp; Continued constantly
                  to do. Some time after her <persName ana="Betty Midgley">Aunt</persName> had a mind for the more Convenince of hearing the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> to live nearer
                     <placeName>Smith House</placeName> &amp; she made it come &amp; remain with her which she was very glad off.</p>
               <p>In <date when-iso="1748-07">July 1748</date> they both of them
                  together got leave to live with the Single Sisters in <placeName>Cack Heaton</placeName> &amp; she remain'd there &amp; in the same Oconomy at <placeName ana="Tyersal">Tyresell
                     Hall</placeName> till we came in the Choir House (Which I shall take Notice of afterwards)</p>
               <p>In the year <date when-iso="1751-04-05">1751 on the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of April</date> she was <name
                     event="reception">receiv&#39;d in the Congregation</name> which <name type="empotion">pleas'd</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head type="page">2</head>
               <pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-02.jpg" />
               <p>her very much. In <date when-iso="1753-02-25">1753 on the 25 of February</date> she after many a Hearty with &amp; Earnest longing for it was <name event="sacrament">addmitted to the
                     Lords Supper</name>- In the same year was Receiv'd from the <orgName en="greater girls choir">Great Girls</orgName> to teh <orgName en="single sisters choir">Single Sisters
                     Choir</orgName>.</p> 
               <p>She has since about <date when-iso="1744" cert="medium">10, or 11, years old</date>, carried about a very sickly &amp; weakly <name health="disease">Tabernacle</name> which she bore
                  without Complaint, &amp; being of an exceeding still quick, but also very solid &amp; sensible <del>diposion</del>
                  <name health="disease">Dispossition</name> she was seldom heard to speak about any thing except when spoken to: But however as we now have found she took good Notice of ever thing
                  &amp; Ponder<add place="above">d </add>them in her Heart.</p>
               <p><date when-iso="1754-02">In February this present year</date> she had the <name health="disease">Small-Pox</name> which not only went very hardly with her But also left that
                  remaining on her which Render'd her much more Weak &amp; Sickly than before a <name health="disease">Consumption</name> appearing thro' her whole Constitution: It was manifest to all
                  about her she could not hold it out long, tho she herself would commonly say when ask'd about it &quot;that she was pretty well. Nevertheless what she inwardly felt brought her <add
                     place="above">lso</add> upon the thoughts &amp; consideration of going to <persName type="diety">Our Saviour</persName> (as she afterward, declar'd with joy.)</p>
               <p>In <date when-iso="1754-07">July</date> she was a little Better but the <name health="disease">disor der</name> presently return'd more strong than ever: Yet she continued to walk
                  about till the <date when-iso="1754-11-22">22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of November</date>, then she entirely took her to her Room &amp; soon after to her Bed.</p> 
               <p>Now she freely
                  acknowledgeing that she had all this summer last, been in a Continual meditation &amp; Consultation with her <persName type="diety">Dear Saviour</persName> <note type="catchword">about</note></p>
               <cb/>
               <p>her going to him, having <add place="above">all</add> along been Sensible of it for herself that she should not stay here but the Reason why she would not confess it openly was
                  because she was <name type="emotion">affraid</name> she should not go as soon as she wish'd for.</p> 
               <p>She was now <name health="disease">exceeding Bad</name>, but quite <name type="emotion">Brisk in <add place="above">her</add> spirits</name> &amp; <name type="emotion">chearful in
                     Heart &amp; Soul</name>, &amp; as before even Ever since we have known her she has been us'd to speak very little, so now to the Contrary, <add place="above">she</add>spoke a
                  great deal especialy to these with whom she had had an intimiate acquaintance &amp; Perticularly with Our dear <persName>Sister Mary </persName> who very faithfully visited her all
                  the time</p>
               <p><date when-iso="1754-12-12">On the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> instant she had her Birth-Day (being 20 years old,)</date> when many Sister who visited her Express'd their Hearty
                  wishes for her which receiv'd, &amp; answer'd with much satisfaction: In the afternoon her class made her a Very Pretty Love-Feast which rejoiceed her Exceedingly &amp; in which she
                  spoke of her Departure with such <name type="emotion">Pleasure &amp; Delight </name> as she never had done before; she spoke with <persName>sister Mary</persName> &amp; made out
                  Ev'ry thing that was in her Mind about her Burial, as well as all the Hearty wishes &amp; desires of her heart for her Class &amp;c. In short she said that this had been to her the
                     <name type="emotion">Happiest day she ever had had in all her Life.</name> This day &amp; forward she unbosom'd &amp; declar'd what she had (Perhaps) kept Treasur'd up in her
                  Heart to this Oppertunity for some years Past, She spoke of her various Troubles &amp; Anxieties in Particular Circum <note type="catchword">-stances</note> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head type="page">3</head>
               <pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-03.jpg" />
               <p>Circumstances, such as no body had perciev'd on her with <del>with</del> a <name type="emotion">chearful &amp; Thankful Heart</name>, being bowed with Shame before him with whom she
                  had spent many happy moments, days years</p>
               <p><date when-iso="1754" cert="low">About the 15th</date> it being two years since we came in <add place="above">our</add>
                  <placeName>Choir House</placeName> she told <persName>Sister Mary</persName> Ev'rything how she had been &amp; was in <placeName>Tyre-sell Hall</placeName> at that time, What <name
                     type="emotion">Anxiety &amp; Concern she felt</name> about coming in the <placeName>Choir House</placeName>
                  <name type="emotion">fearing</name> Least she should not have leave to come &amp; how she had in Shillness Pray'd &amp; wept before her dear Lamb, that he would give her leave to
                  come &amp; that if she should have that favour that he would grant her the feeling &amp; nearness of his Wounds that she might be faithful to him therein &amp;c. Nay 'tis almost
                  incredible, how quick &amp; active her memory was over this matter she not only gave Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  <persName>Mary</persName> an account of herself but of all the <orgName>Sisters</orgName> in <placeName>Tyre-sell-Hall</placeName> at that time, she (unperceiv'd) had taken notice of
                  ev'ry Ones conduct words &amp; behaviour, But to return she also Express'd herself in a very lively manner with grace &amp; understanding <hi rend="underline">how</hi> Exceedingly
                  she was Rejoiced when she was assured she should come here. She at the same time viz the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Instant spoke w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> with an <name type="emotion">inly
                     tender feeling</name> about the <placeName>Choir</placeName> &amp; what her dear Bridegroom has done from time to time on her therein, &amp; Particularly in this Present year,
                  together with the Esteem <note type="catchword">&amp;</note></p>
               <cb/>
               <p>
                  &amp; Satisfaction she has had for, &amp; in the <placeName>Choir House</placeName> this she did from time to time Repear and
                  also she would allways take notice of many sisters whom she saw &amp; Reflected on their Situation at Present and time Pass &amp; when <persName>Sister Mary</persName> came to her
                  then she would sell her all her mind about them &amp; Especialy the concern she had had, about her Class under some heavy Circumstances some months agoe &amp; being ask&#39;d why she
                  did not speak as such time what she had in her mind? She answer&#39;d &quot;that she always thought herself too mean &amp; too insignificant to Speak Her mind about any thing, But
                  she had instead of that gone somewhere in a Corner &amp; Wept for them be- fore her dear <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName> &amp; Pray&#39;d hum that he would Bless Preserve
                  &amp; keep <hi rend="underline">them</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Her</hi> &amp; that they might <hi rend="underline">all</hi> become a joy to <persName type="diety"
                     >Him</persName> Once in <persName>sister Mary</persName> Presence after having fully spoken &amp; Open&#39;d all her mind to her a- bout many things, she took motice that her
                     <persName ana="Betty                      Midgley">Aunt</persName> (who faithfuly tended &amp; nurs&#39;d her all the time of sickness) was a Cry- ing: So she demanded the Reason
                  of her why she wept, telling her she had no ocassion to weep for her since &quot;says she&quot; I am fully satisfied &amp; Reconciled both with my Lamb &amp; &amp; with all my
                     <orgName>Sisters</orgName> &amp; have spoke my mind about Everything &amp; now am Ready to go whenever he Pleases Thus she continued under a Deep Sense &amp; speaking of herself
                  &amp; her Choir &amp; often Expressing her Desire to go. But yet she </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head type="page">4</head>
               <pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-04.jpg" />
               <p>would secretly sometimes say to her <persName ana="Betty Midgley">Aunt</persName> that she believ&#39;d she should live till <name type="holiday">Christmas</name>, but of our
                     <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName> Pleasd to take her before, she would be glad Sunday Lan about 11 or 12 in the Evening she was siez&#39;d with the monst <name
                     type="emotion">Violent pain</name> so that <persName>Sister Mary</persName> who at the same time watchd with her Perceiv&#39;d such a sensible alteration not only by her Excessive
                  Pains but also by the method &amp; alteration of all her Faculties that she thought she Really would go, &amp; thereupon ask&#39;d her if she was now quite Ready. She with <name
                     type="emotion">pleasure &amp; serenity</name> answerd &quot;yes! I am quite Ready now &amp; shall be glad to go to my Lamb as soon as he Pleases&quot; However she reviv&#39;d a
                  little &amp; then desired 2 verses which she named to be sung for her viz<hi rend="superscript">+ </hi>appear as her protector who turns to joy all fears &amp; When she shall get Per
                  mission to leave this mortal tent, from Pains &amp; griefs Dissmission thy sell just then present And then says she &quot;Sing Hush stif not up the friend of Christ, Wake not the
                  lovely Bride &amp; She was very Bad all night &amp; day like one Expireing till toward night on Monday Get the Bore her Pains with much more Paternity than any one could Expect who
                  did but <hi rend="underline">see</hi> how she was- Minday- night she was some waht Easier &amp; appear&#39;d to ys as if she might Possibly continue a few days, But if she heard any
                  one take notice of the near approach </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="5">
               <head type="page">5</head>
               <pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-05.jpg" />
               <p>so she sweetly went to sleep in the arms of her lover about 5 o'clock in the Evening <date when-iso="1754-12-25">on Christmas Day.</date> It is to be Oberv'd that this dear Heart was
                  the Only One great girl in all the Oconomies was One of the first that was Receiv'd in the Congregation The Only One that came in the <placeName>Choir House</placeName> at first she
                  was the first that was admitted to the sacrament. And now the first that is gone to Our <persName type="diety">saviour</persName>. Where she Rests from all her Pain: And has left
                  behind her the Char acter of an Honest Unright Unaffected &amp; Enamour'd Virgin Heart she has hear Known by those who have liv'd with her from her first Commg <hi rend="superscript"
                     >among us</hi> to this Her Dissalution to be an Example of Patience of steadfastness &amp; Constanes in her Love to him who first gave her confidence to believe in his Wounds she
                  never once having been perceiv'd to draw back or to slight her calling in joy or in Smart, and now at last her mourn has made <del>a</del> a Brief Confession of <persName
                     type="diety">Him</persName> Whom her Heart has Loved felt &amp; Believ'd on. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
