<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mary Allot: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>Fulneck, UK</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary">Mary Allot</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-05.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2019-08-27" who="#JAKA1">Created memoir file</change>
			<change when="2019-06-10" who="#JAKA1">Updated header</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Mary Allot</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-01.jpg" />
					<p> Mary Alott Was born at Barksland in the Parish of Elland. On the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Decr 1734 N S. </p>
					<p> When she was about Three years old her Father dyed &amp; she liv&apos;d with her Mother &amp; her Aunt (Namely Betty Midgley) who jointly Nurs&apos;d &amp; Maintain&apos;d <add
							place="above">her</add> till she was about seven, then her Mother being again Married her Aunt left them took a Room &amp; design&apos;d to live by herself, But <add
							place="above">Mary</add> not being at all willing to be left behind often begg&apos;d her Aunt to take her with her, which according<add place="above">ly</add> in a few
						weeks after she Willlingly did, &amp; Cared for her as her own. </p>
					<p> When she was about Nine years old she by the Drawing of the Holy Ghost was inclin&apos;d to hear the Gospel which she of her own free accord begun &amp; Continued Constantly to
						do. </p>
					<p> Some time after her Aunt had a mind for the more Convenince of hearing the Brn to live nearer Smith House &amp; she made it out with the Brethren that Mary should also come
						&amp; remain with her which she was very glad off. </p>
					<p> In July 1748 they Both of them together got leave to live with the Single Sisters in Clack- Heaton &amp; she remain&apos;d there &amp; in the same Oconomy at Tyre-sell-Hall
						till we came in the Choir House (Which I shall take Notice of afterwards) </p>
					<p> In the year 1751 on the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of April she was receiv&apos;d in the Congregation which Pleas&apos;d </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-02.jpg" />
					<p> her very much. In 1753 on the 25 of February she after many a Hearty wish &amp; Earnest longing for it was addmitted to the Lords Supper In the same year was Receiv&apos;d from
						the Great Girls to the Single Sisters Choir. </p>
					<p> She has since about 10, or 11, Years Old, carried about a Very Sickly &amp; Weakly Tabernacle which she bore without Complaint, &amp; being of an exceeding shill quiet, but
						also very solid &amp; sensible <del>Dispossition</del> she was seldom heard to speak about any thing except when spoken to: But however as we now have found she took good
						Notice of ever thing &amp; Ponderd them in her Heart. </p>
					<p> In February this present year she had the Small-Pox which not only went very hardly with her But also left that remaining on her which Render&apos;d her Much more Weak &amp;
						Sickly than before a Consumption appearing thro&apos; her Whole Constitution: It was manifest to all about her she could not hold it out long, tho she herself wod commonly say
						when ask&apos;d about it &quot;that she was pretty well Nevertheless what she inwardly felt Brought her <add place="above">also</add> upon the thoughts &amp; consideration of
						going to Our Saviour (as she afterward, de clar&apos;d with Joy.) </p>
					<p> In July she was a little Better but the disor der Presently return&apos;d more strong than ever: Yet she continued to walk about till the 22d of November, then she entirely
						took her to her Room &amp; soon after to her Bed. </p>
					<p> Now she freely acknowledgeing that she had all this summer last, been in a Continual meditation &amp; Consultation with her Dear Saviour <note type="catchword">about</note>
					</p>
					<pb />
					<p> about her going to him, having <add place="above">all</add> along been Senscible of it for herself that she should not stay here but the Reason why she would not confess it
						openly was because she was affraid she should not go as soon as she wish&apos;d for. </p>
					<p> She was now exceeding Bad, but quite Brisk in <add place="above">her</add> Spirits &amp; chearful in Heart &amp; Soul, &amp; as before even Ever since we have known her she has
						been us&apos;d to speak very little, so Now to the Con trary, <add place="above">she</add> spoke a great deal especialy to these with whom she had had an intimiate acquaintance
						&amp; Perticularly with Our dear Sister Mary who very faithfully visited her all the time </p>
					<p> On the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> instant she had her Birth-Day (being 20; years old,) when many Sisters who vis ited her Express&apos;d their Hearty wishes for her which
						she receiv&apos;d, &amp; answer&apos;d with much satis faction: In the afternoon her Class made her a Very Pretty Love-Feast which rejoice ed her Exceedingly &amp; in which she
						spoke of her Departure with such Pleasure &amp; Delight as she never had done before; she spoke with sister Mary &amp; Made out Ev&apos;ry thing that was in her Mind about her
						Burial, as well as all the Hearty wishes &amp; desires of her heart for her Class &amp; c. In short she said that this had been to her the Happiest day she ever had had in all
						her life. This day &amp; forward she unbosom&apos;d &amp; declar&apos;d what she had (Perhaps) kept Treasur&apos;d up in her Heart to this Opper tunity for some years Past, She
						spoke of her various Troubles &amp; Anxieties in Particular Circum <note type="catchword">-stances</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-03.jpg" />
					<p> Circumstances, such as no body had perciev&apos;d on her with a Chearful &amp; Thankful Heart, being bowed with Shame before him will whom she had spent many happy Moments,
						days &amp; years </p>
					<p> About the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> it being Two years since we came in <add place="above">our</add> Choir House she told Sister Mary Ev&apos;rything how she had been
						&amp; was in Tyre- sell-Hall at that time, What Anxiety &amp; Concern she felt about coming in the Choir House fearing Least she should not have leave to come &amp; how she had
						in Shillness Pray&apos;d &amp; wept before her dear Lamb, that he would give her Leave to come &amp; that if she should have that favour that he would grant her the feel ing
						&amp; nearness of his Wounds that she might be faithful to him therein &amp;c. Nay his almost incredible, how quick &amp; active her Memory was over this matter she not only
						gave Sisr Mary an account of herself but of all the Sisters in Tyre-sell-Hall at that time, she (unperceiv&apos;d) had taken Notice of ev&apos;ry One, conduct words &amp;
						behaviour, But to return she also Express&apos;d herself in a very Lively manner with grace &amp; Understanding <hi rend="underline">how</hi> Exceedingly she was Rejoiced when
						she was assured she should come here. She at the same time viz&apos; the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Instant spoke w<hi
							rend="superscript">th</hi> with an inly Tender feeling about the Choir &amp; Choir Grace what she has felt since she was Receiv&apos;d in the Single Sisters Choir &amp;
						what her dear Bridegroom has done from time to time on her therein, &amp; Perticularly in this Present Year, together with the Esteem <note type="&amp;" />
					</p>
					<pb />
					<p> &amp; Satisfaction she has had for, &amp; in the Choir House this she did from time to time Repeat And also she would allways take notice of many Sisters whom she saw &amp;
						Reflected on their Situation at Present and time Pass &amp; when Sister Mary came to her then she would sell her all her Mind about them &amp; Especialy the concern she had
						had, about her Class under some heavy Circumstances some Months agoe &amp; being ask&apos;d why she did not speak at such time what she had in her mind? She answer&apos;d
						&quot;that she always thought herself too mean &amp; too insignificant to Speak Her mind about any thing, But she had instead of that gone somewhere in a Corner &amp; Wept for
						them be fore her dear Saviour &amp; Pray&apos;d him that he would Bless Preserve &amp; keep them &amp; Her &amp; that they Might all become a Joy to Him </p>
					<p> Once in Sister Mary&apos;s Presence after having fully spoken &amp; Open&apos;d all her Mind to her a bout Many things, she took Notice that her Aunt (who faithfuly tended
						&amp; Nurs&apos;d her all the time of Sickness) was a Cry ing: So she demanded the Reason of her why she wept, telling her she had no Ocassion to weep for her since &quot;says
						she&quot; I am fully Satisfied &amp; Reconciled both with My Lamb &amp; &amp; with all my Sisters &amp; have spoke my mind about Everything &amp; Now am Ready to go whenever he
						Pleases </p>
					<p> Thus she Continued under a Deep Sense &amp; Speaking of herself &amp; her Choir &amp; Often Expressing her Desire to go. But yet she <note type="catchword">wld</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-04.jpg" />
					<p> would Secretly sometimes say to her Aunt that she believ&apos;d she should live till Christmas, but If our Saviour Pleasd to take her before, she would be glad </p>
					<p> Sunday Last about 11 or 12 in the Evening she was Siez&apos;d with the monst Violent pain So that Sister Mary who at the same time watch&apos;d with her Perceiv&apos;d such a
						Senscible Alteration not only by her Excessive Pains but also by the Motion &amp; Alteration of all her Faculties that she thought she Realy would go, &amp; thereupon
						ask&apos;d her if she was now quite Ready. She with Pleasure &amp; Serenity answerd &quot;yes! I am Quite Ready now &amp; shall be glad to go to my Lamb as soon as he
						Pleases&quot; </p>
					<p> However she reviv&apos;d a little &amp; then desired 2 verses which she named to be sung for her viz Appear as her Protector who turns to Joy all Tears &amp; When she shall get
						Per mission to leave this Mortal Tent, From Pains &amp; Griefs Dissmission Thy self Just then present And then says she &quot;Sing Hush stir not up the friend of Christ, Wake
						not the lovely Bride &amp;c </p>
					<p> She was very Bad all Night &amp; Lay like one Expireing till towards Night on Monday Yet she Bore her Pains with Much more Patience <add place="above">than</add> any one could
						Expect who did but <hi rend="underline">see</hi> how she was Munday night she was some waht Easier &amp; appear&apos;d to ys as if she might Possibly continue a few days, But
						if she heard any one take notice of the near approach <note type="catchword">of</note>
					</p>
					<pb />
					<p> of Christmass &amp; of the Joy we Expected in the Birth day of our Saviour She would readly answer them that if our Saviour only was Pleas&apos;d to let her go to him before or
						in the Holidays She should have a far Better Christmass than We and that she would be glad of. </p>
					<p> Tusday Night she Alter&apos;d again &amp; on Wed nesday Morning was much Worse. In the Forenoon we thought again she would Certain ly Depart, But she continued and lay severly
						Oppresse&apos;d with the Most Excessive Pangs thro&apos; Ev&apos;ry Limb &amp; Fibre, Speaking very little, But Panting in Stillness for the Happy Moment when she should get
						the Departing Kiss, And when Sometimes her Tabernacle seem&apos;d to be almost Rack&apos;d in Pieces with the most shock ing &amp; Excessive Pain as almost could be thought
						Unpossibl a Human Creature could Bear. she would say &quot;Ah! how shall I hold it Out Why does he not fetch me Sis Mary then would remind her of the Hard Toil &amp; Conflict
						of our Saviour which he bore in his Humanity Saying My dear Heart it is but a few Minutes &amp; you will be with him, She that Moment was again in a Calm Serenity<add
							place="above">Heavenly</add> &amp; Peace <add place="above">&amp;</add> Said O! yes he soon will fetch me to his Embraces, Which she Obtain&apos;d Under these Words, The
						Lamb w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> all his Grief &amp; Smart Remains the Pleasure of the Heart Long as it Moves in Thee And Now when Here it Beats no more There where the
						Spear His Side did bore thou Last thy Place Etneraly and </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_12AllotMary-05.jpg" />
					<p> so she sweetly went to sleep in the Arms of her Lover about 5 o&apos;clock in the Evening on Christmas Day. </p>
					<p> It is to be Oberv&apos;d that this dear Heart was the Only One Great Girl in all the Oconomies was One of the first that was Receiv&apos;d in the Congregation The Only One that
						came in the Choir House at first She was the first that was admitted to the Sacrament. And Now the first that is gone to Our saviour. Where she Rests from all her Pain: And has
						Left behind her the Char acter of an Honest Upright Unaffected &amp; Enamour&apos;d Virgin Heart She has been Known by those who have liv&apos;d with her from her first Commg
							<add place="above">among us</add> to this Her Dissalution to be an Example of Patience of Steadfastness &amp; Constancy in her Love to him who first gave her Confidence to
						believe in his Wounds she never Once having been Perceiv&apos;d to Draw back or to Slight her Calling in Joy or in Smart, and Now at last her Mouth has made <del>a</del> a
						Brief Confession of Him Whom her Heart has Loved Felt &amp; Believ&apos;d on. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
