<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>John Thompson Beck: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal
					Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator,
					2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-2020</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0
						International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Memoirs from the Fulneck Archive</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">John Thompson Beck</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>John Thompson Beck</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<pb n="1"
						facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_115_Bentley_Watson_Beck-12.jpg"/>
					<p> 3. John Thompson Beck, aged 22 years/ <lb/> Previous to his illness he gave
						no indication of <lb/> spiritual life; for tho&apos; a moral character, his
						mind was so <lb/> fixed on earthly pursuits, that it produced a degree <lb/>
						of hardness of heart and feeling not often found in one <lb/> so young. All
						his affections were enlisted in the acqui- <lb/> sition of money, after for
						which he panted with fearful <lb/> eagerness. In this state he continued for
						a considera- <lb/> ble time after he was confined to the house, and even
						<lb/> long after it was apparent that he would no get better. <lb/> So hard
						were his feelings that it was painful to visit <lb/> him, and so severe was
						the conflict on his mind when <lb/> he saw that death would soon put an end
						to al his <lb/> schemes, that it was truly distressing. The mental <lb/>
						struggle and his fond clinging to life, reeked and tor- <lb/> tured his
						soul. Many times have I left the house </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<pb n="2"
						facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_115_Bentley_Watson_Beck-13.jpg"/>
					<p> with the most painful feelings, and had I not been con- <lb/> vinced that
						the Word of reconciliation can soften <lb/> the most obdurate heart, I
						should have desponded. Fre- <lb/> quent and fervent were my prayers, that
						the Lord <lb/> would open the eyes of this young man. Still no signs <lb/>
						of spiritual life appeared; my conversations with <lb/> him, the reading of
						the scripture, and Hymns, see- <lb/> med to fall on a rock. At length the
						grace of God <lb/> triumphed, and this unhappy state gave way to sen- <lb/>
						timents and feelings of a different kind.</p>
					<p> The first symptoms of a sounder state of mind <lb/> appeared some months
						ago. He became an humble <lb/> inquirer and listened to the instructions
						given him <lb/> in spiritual things; and the silent tears rolling down <lb/>
						his cheeks, proved that degree of light was spin- <lb/> ning up in his soul.
						His friends observed the <lb/> change with pleasure; but I thought it was
						<lb/> prudent to take no notice of it, but his alteration <lb/> should be
						diverted from the great object of his <lb/> faith and absorbed in himself
						and his feelings. <lb/> He now loved the Lord Jesus; he loved to hear <lb/>
						of His sacrifice and death. His confessions showed <lb/> much humility and a
						hope of happiness groun- <lb/> ded in the atonement of Christ.</p>
					<p> One day, about a fortnight after this change <lb/> had taken place, when he
						was more communi- <lb/> cative than he had been before, I ventured to <lb/>
						remark, that he had different thoughts and </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<pb n="3"
						facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_115_Bentley_Watson_Beck-14.jpg"/>
					<p> feelings now from what he had had a few <lb/> weeks before ago, he ascented,
						expressing his <lb/> thankfulness that this was the case. To my <lb/>
						question, &quot;When did you begin to think more <lb/> seriously on these
						things, and what led you to it?&quot; <lb/> he replied; &quot;Do you
						remember the evening <lb/> when you and my uncle were here, and conversing
						<lb/> about the love of Jesus, our Saviour, in giving His <lb/> life a
						ransom for sinners, suffering and dyeing on <lb/> the cross for our sins,
						and of His mercy in saving <lb/> all who come to Him in faith? That
						conversa- <lb/> tion I could not forget, and for three hours after <lb/> I
						went to bed, I was thinking about it. I prayed <lb/> for grace to believe; I
						prayed for pardon and <lb/> I felt a hope that I should not be lost, that
						Jesus <lb/> would save me. Since then my mind has at <lb/> times been very
						comfortable, when I think of <lb/> my Saviour and pray to Him.&quot;</p>
					<p> From that day the operations of the Holy <lb/> Spirit on his heart became
						more evident, and <lb/> showed their blessed effects by a complete surrender
						<lb/> of himself to the Lord, and submission to His will; <lb/> and by being
						delivered from the fear of death, and <lb/> bearing his severe suffering
						with exemplary pa- <lb/> tience, often saying, &quot;It is the Lord&apos;s
						will, let Him <lb/> do with me what He pleases.&quot; He was mercifully
						<lb/> preserved from any reasons of gloom or darkness <lb/> of mind, and to
						the last confined in a tranquil </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<pb n="4"
						facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_115_Bentley_Watson_Beck-15.jpg"/>
					<p> and peaceful state. He had buried his hopes on <lb/> the Rock of ages, and
						in a childlike manner fixed <lb/> his mind on the suffering of the Lamb of
						God. In <lb/> consequence of this, tho&apos; his frames and feeling varied,
						<lb/> he was kept in perfect peace. Eight weeks ago, <lb/> when racked with
						the most excruciating pains of body, <lb/> his soul was graciously supported
						by inward conso- <lb/> lations. Peace beamed in his countenance, and <lb/>
						joy glowed in his expressions. &quot;Don&apos;t weep for me&quot; <lb/>
						Addressing those present he said, &quot;Don&apos;t weep <lb/> for me; it
						will soon be all over; my Saviour is <lb/> great; He will not leave
						me.&quot; Subsequently <lb/> his pains were partially relieved; when he
						never <lb/> failed to impress the importance of eternal things <lb/> on all
						who visited him.</p>
					<p> On Sunday August 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> he was he was asur- <lb/>
						ably to his earnest desire, acknowledged a member <lb/> of our Church, and
						commended to the sympathy <lb/> and prayer, of the cong<hi
							rend="superscript">n</hi>. and in the evening <lb/> the H. Communion was
						administered to him <lb/> and his parents, in the presence of the other mem-
						<lb/> bers of the family and a few friends. Du- <lb/> ring this solemn act
						the peace of God was power <lb/> fully felt by all present, and he himself
						testified <lb/> by his look, his the heavenly joy that filled his <lb/>
						soul. When the service was over he exclaimed, <lb/> &quot;this has been a
						blessed meeting; nothing but </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<pb n="5"
						facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_115_Bentley_Watson_Beck-16.jpg"/>
					<p> heaven can exceed this.&quot; His bodily sufferings <lb/> were forgotten,
						and the happenings of his soul seemed <lb/> almost too great for his weak
						frame to enterain. <lb/> The day after, speaking to one of his sisters of
						his en- <lb/> joyment, he was unable to express himself in <lb/> language
						sufficiently strong, saying, &quot;O what a <lb/> meeting that was! If you
						had felt as I did, you <lb/> would never forget it.&quot;</p>
					<p> The last week of his life was one of very severe <lb/> suffering, but of
						inward peace. In the midst of his <lb/> sufferings he frequently exclaimed;
						&quot;Glory, glory be <lb/> to God! I shall soon be with Him. I am going
						fast; <lb/> my Saviour will soon come to fetch me home. I <lb/> shall soon
						be with him in Heaven; there I shall <lb/> see Him face to face; I shall be
						near Him and shall <lb/> see the wounds He bore for my sins.&quot; At one of
						my <lb/> last visits to him, when he appeared very near <lb/> his end, he
						said, turning his face to me, &quot;You will <lb/> soon have to preach my
						funeral sermon. I wish <lb/> the young people may take warning by me, and be
						<lb/> led to give themselves to the Lord.&quot;</p>
					<p> The Satturday before he died, he was much exhau- <lb/> sted by pain, and
						could say very little; but seemed to <lb/> derive comfort from the words
						addressed to him. <lb/> When about to leave him he exerted himself to say
						<lb/> something, the substance of which was, that he enjoyd <lb/> sweet
						comfort and peace by in feeling our Saviour&apos;s pre- <lb/> sence, and in
						meditating on His sufferings &amp; death, ad- <lb/> ding, &quot;O how I long
						to go and see The Lamb of God, who <lb/> died for me &amp;c.&quot; On
						shaking hands with him he said with <lb/> a smile, &quot;All will be well at
						last.&quot; He departed the following Tuesday. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
