<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mercy Carter: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_48_CarterMercy">Mercy Carter</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_48_CarterMercy-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_48_CarterMercy-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_48_CarterMercy-03.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#"
				xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
				xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#"> </rdf:RDF></xenoData>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Mercy Carter</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_48_CarterMercy-01.jpg" n="1" />
			<p>
					<hi rend="underlined:true;">Occurrences in Wike Cong</hi><hi rend="underlined:true; superscript:true;">n</hi><hi rend="underlined:true;"> for the Month of Jan. 1771</hi>
					<del>The 4th</del>
						<add place="above">Out of Wyk Plan</add> our dear S<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> Mercy Carter went to our Saviour <add place="above">On the 4<hi rend="superscript:true;"
								>th</hi> Jan.</add> Of her
					Course thro' this World the following is to be observed:
				</p>
			<p>
					She was born at Greatland in Hallifax Parish: March 29<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi>
					1716, and brught up in the establishd Church. Her Parents depar
					ting this Life when she was very young, and they being at the same
					time but low in the World, she was cared for by the Town to which
					she belong'd. and tho' she was in the midst of the World in her 19<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi>
					and 20<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> Years, yet she could not be brought in the comon sinful
					Track thereof, partly oweing to an invisible Hand of Preservation
					from our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>, and partly to Stirrings and Convictions she had
					in her Heart from her earliest Remembrance. This Spark, which
					lay in her soul from a Child, was fed and nurish'd by the Testi
					mony she heard of M<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> Ingham and M<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> Dellamot of the free grace
					in Jesus Blood and Death. and being very anxious and Restless
					for the Forgiveness of her Sins and true life out of Jesus in her
					Heart, she followed the Course and Track peculiar to those times,
					in hearing the Reaching of the Gospel; But her poor Soul never
					found Deliverance and Peace, <add place="above">till</add> in the Year 1739, <add place="above">when</add> she once heard
					our dear B<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> Beohler, during which our dear Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> manifested,
					himself to her, so as he sweated Bloody in the Garden of
					Gethsemane on her account: This not only gave her love and
					Peace, but life and love. 
				</p>
			<p>
					In 1746 a Society of the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi>
					was settled at Greetland, to which she belong'd from the Begining.
					In 1746 she <add place="above">was</add> married to the present Widower. When the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi>
					removed from Newhouse, she and her Husband moved with
					our B<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> Jeremy Carter into the same in order to be nearer the
					Cong<hi rend="superscript:true;">n</hi> into which she was received at Fulneck May 12<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> 1759
					and the following year <hi rend="strikethrough:true;">in</hi> Sep<hi rend="superscript:true;">t</hi>: 3<hi rend="superscript:true;">d</hi> she with her Husband enjoy'd
					the holy Comunion for the first time with the Cong<hi rend="superscript:true;">n</hi>. Their
					Marriage has been bless'd with 4 Child<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi>, 1 is already with the
					Lord, and 1Son and 1 Daughter are in the respective Choir
					Houses at Fulneck, for which she was inexpressibly thankful
					to our dear Lord.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_48_CarterMercy-02.jpg" n="2" />
			<p>
				
					she being an applied of solid Sister, and as such respected by
					our People, she was accordingly made use of as a Helper in
					a Band; and when the late Helpers Conference was settled 
					she became a Member thereof. Our late Sister had a peculiar
					Talent for visiting her Sisters, and contriving to relieve the
					needy and those in Distress. When in the dayly Course of
					her House affairs, she got an impulse to visit this as the
					other Sister, either confined by Sickness, or whereever she felt it
					was necessary, she acquainted her Husband with her Intention
					and recommended herself to him for that Purpose; and he
					during her absense would Sigh to our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> in her behalf,
					that his aim with her Visiting might be answered; and
					when in the Evening she related to him of what had occurred,
					they both rejoiced together that our dear Lord had heard the
					Sighs of the one and blessed the weak Endeavours of the
					other.
				</p>
			<p>
					Whenever one of our Sisters was in external need,
					she used to go about among the heartiest Sisters, and pro
					pose to make a Collection for the Relief of such a one;
					in which she always succeeded, and as for her own Part
					in such a Case, her left hand did not know what her right
					Hand did.
				</p>
			<p>
					Thro' her very maternal and loving Way, peculiar to
					herself, she gain'd the affection of such Child<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi> who were not
					her own, but about her in such a manner, that they would
					scarcey be seperated from her; and where ever she could
					invent any thing to be helpful to them wether it related to
					internal or external Matters, in order to secure them for
					our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>, she left no Stone unturned, and as a Proof
					that our dear Lord was with her in this Respect she
					has left Trails behind her new in the single Sisters House
					at Fulneck
				
			</p>
			<cb />
			<p>
				
					the heaviest Circumstances, which she experienced during
					her course of grace, happened about a year and a half ago,
					when her eldest Son turning quite from our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> and the
					Inclinations and Convictions he had in his Heart, when among
					the Boys, so that the Steps he then took caused her much grief
					and trouble. and altho' she became comforted by our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>
					upon that head, that she could leave the Issue to his merciful
					heart, yet her sickly Tabernacle reiceved such a Shock thereby,
					that we are inclined to think it rather proved a Furtherance
					to her Dissolution. about 4 month ago she uttered the first
					apprehension that she should not be here long, for she said to
					her Husband when coming from the married festival last
					Septs this will be the last married festival I shall celebrate!
					an old Breast complaint which was renew'd by getting repeated
					later and a bad State of Blood, were seemingly the Cause of
					her going to our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>. about 2 Month ago she was the
					last time here of the h. Comunion, and tho' exceeding weak
					yet very much rejoiced to be once more together with her
					B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi> and S<hi rend="superscript:true;">rs</hi> in so Solemn an Ocasion: for she was a very
					constant attender of all the Meetings. The nearer she
					drew to her End the more Childlike she became, and used to express
					herself thus, I want to be nothing else than my Saviours little
					Child! She was always much pleased and comforted when
					she was visited, especially by her Band Sisters: after our
					last Comunion B<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> and S<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> Tander brough her her share
					after which she had long'd much and which she enjoy'd
					with great Eagerness together with her Husband. She being
					once asked how she was and felt in her Heart? she answered,
					my Heart is happy, I am my Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">rs</hi> little Child, He shall
					so with me what he pleases! On the 4<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> instant B<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>
					Tander call'd there, and finding her remarkably altered,
					told her, that she would soon be with her Redeemer, she
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_48_CarterMercy-03.jpg" n="3" />
			<p>
				
					answered: that's well, I have nothing to plead but his
					precious Blood and Rightousness. having sung a few
					verses with her, and telling her that she departed, <add place="above">to our dearest Lord</add> with the
					entire Blessing of his Church below, and she sitting by the fire
					side, she bowed down her Head in order to have it imparted
					to her; this being done, there was such a feeling of our
					dear Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">rs</hi> Presence, that none present could refrain from
					shedding Tears. And tho' there was not an immediate
					Appearance of her going directly, yet after having taken
					leave of her Child<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi> and those she had been like a Mother
					to, she laid down, and in about 4 Hours after, her happy
					Soul took its' Flight into the Wounds of Jesus.
				
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
