<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Sarah Cennick: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick">Sarah Cennick</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-01.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-02.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-03.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-04.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-05.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-06.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-07.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-08.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-09.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-10.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-11.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-12.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-13.jpg"/>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-14.jpg"/>
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">

<rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/"><![CDATA[
{
	"@context": {
		"dcterms:created": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:created"
		},
		"dcterms:issued": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:issued"
		},
		"oa:motivatedBy": {
			"@type": "oa:Motivation"
		},
		"@language": "en",
		"rdf": "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#",
		"rdfs": "http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#",
		"as": "http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
		"cwrc": "http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#",
		"dc": "http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/",
		"dcterms": "http://purl.org/dc/terms/",
		"foaf": "http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/",
		"geo": "http://www.geonames.org/ontology#",
		"oa": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#",
		"schema": "http://schema.org/",
		"xsd": "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#"
	},
	"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/ML/master/Fulneck/SemanticXML/cennick_sarah.xml?date_annotation_20200320112744779",
	"@type": "oa:Annotation",
	"dcterms:created": "2020-03-20T15:27:44.779Z",
	"dcterms:issued": "2020-03-20T15:27:53.142Z",
	"dcterms:creator": {
		"@id": "https://github.com/djakacki",
		"@type": [
			"cwrc:NaturalPerson",
			"schema:Person"
		],
		"cwrc:hasName": "Diane Jakacki",
		"foaf:nick": "djakacki"
	},
	"oa:motivatedBy": "oa:identifying",
	"oa:hasTarget": {
		"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/ML/master/Fulneck/SemanticXML/cennick_sarah.xml?date_annotation_20200320112744779#Target",
		"@type": "oa:SpecificResource",
		"oa:hasSource": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/ML/master/Fulneck/SemanticXML/cennick_sarah.xml",
			"@type": "dctypes:Text",
			"dc:format": "text/xml"
		},
		"oa:renderedVia": {
			"@id": "https://cwrc-writer.cwrc.ca/",
			"@type": "as:Application",
			"rdfs:label": "CWRC Writer",
			"schema:softwareVersion": "1.0"
		},
		"oa:hasSelector": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/ML/master/Fulneck/SemanticXML/cennick_sarah.xml?date_annotation_20200320112744779#Selector",
			"@type": "oa:XPathSelector",
			"rdf:value": "TEI/text/body/div/div/p/hi/date"
		}
	},
	"oa:hasBody": {
		"@type": "xsd:date",
		"rdf:value": "1770-01-24"
	},
	"as:generator": {
		"@id": "https://cwrc-writer.cwrc.ca/",
		"@type": "as:Application",
		"rdfs:label": "CWRC Writer",
		"schema:url": "https://cwrc-writer.cwrc.ca",
		"schema:softwareVersion": "1.0"
	}
}
]]></rdf:Description></rdf:RDF></xenoData><profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Sarah Cennick</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-08-30" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Sarah Cennick</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-01.jpg"/>
					<p>
						<hi rend="underline">The Life of the S. S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sarah Cennick who went happily home <date when="1770-01-24" cert="high">Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
							1770</date></hi> I was born June the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> old Style 1712 in Reading Berks. wass baptiz'd in the Church of England and brought up in that Comunion.
						The first thing I remember is the simple and happy intercourse I lived in with the Lord: I knew he lov'd me; and I lov 'd him; &amp; therefore used to have recourse
						to Him without the least reserve. </p>
					<p> When I was about 5 Years old, I remember to have been particularly naughty &amp; selfwilld, which caused me much heaviness, tho' I strove all I could to divert and get rid
						of the Conviction by play &amp;c. But running hastily into my Mothers room, where she was sitting with my late d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bro<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
						John - then an Infant - lying in her lap. I saw her weeping with lifted up hands, and heard her pray. I was much affected: But felt so hard, to acknowledge my fault, but upon
						repeatedly asking my Mother, why she cried and what she was saying? She referr'd the Cause to me and Said: "I was praying for <hi rend="underline">you</hi> and for
						your Brother." This pierc'd me through, and I thought my heart would break. For I thought, The Lord also is greived! I therefore silently withdrew condemn'd and
						asham'd and hasted to a private Place, where with many Tears, I beged Him to forgive me; which he most graciously did directly, and all my Burthen instantly removed. </p>
					<p> My Father and his Relations being all Quakers of the most primitive sort, and my Mother and hers all strict Church of England; Her attachment to, and chief acquaintance were
						the Clergy; So that I had the Oppertunity of an intimate familiarity with <add place="above">each</add>, not perceiving, at this time, the least disunion on either Side. </p>
					<p> Our Parish Vicar and his Family was a part of our most intimate acquaintance, and his Daughter, who had taken a liking to me from my Infancy, calling me her own Child, at last
						prevailed with my Parents, to take me more particularly home to her; But our houses Joining each other, I was nearly as much with my Parents as I was with them. This lady,
						taking me, to a friends house with her, I slip'd out from the Company, and saw two small Boats fastened to the Landing Place in a deep Moat, I got into one of them and
						reached out of it to the Side of the other Boat: when both parting, and swiming from each other had dragged me out of that I stood in, had not the toes of my shoes hitch'd
						in something, and prevented it: Thus hanging over the Water between both, I had scarce time to give my self up for lost, Before I Slip'd my hold and pitched into the
						Water, where to my Joyfull surprise, instead of Sinking I found, as it were, Hands </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-02.jpg"/>
					<p> bearing so strong against my hands as to get and keep my head above water. Yea those kind Assistants bore me up so long, even till I was capable of taking hold with one Hand of
						that Boat, wherein, all while my shoes had hitch'd, but how I recover'd wholly, I never could remember, only that, as I came to my self, I was flat on my Back, safe
						and well. I know, who those ministers were, of whose kinder Orders they Obey'd obeyed, and thanked them, and Him, Friend: beging Him 100 times over: O pray don't let
						it be found out &amp;c. Which, however remarkable, never was. </p>
					<p> I was this Gentlemans* <add place="margin">The parish vicar</add> fond Companion also, and often<note>In the memoir, the phrase "the parish vicar" is written in pencil in a
							different hand</note> Slid unobserv'd to him, when he was retir'd to private Devotion sometimes I kneel'd behind, and at other times close by his side, that
						I might be a partaker of those influences, which I beleiv'd, he enjoy'd. </p>
					<p> As I Grew older, I had more liberty among the Servants, who endeavour'd to seduce me and bring me into all manner of Wickedness, as much as they could, But finding me
						frighten'd, and fearing I should tell, they threaten'd me hard, what they would do to me, if I did. This brought me more particularly to my own Hearts Friend, and
						they let me alone for sometime; till one evening, I went into a back Garden, where a Company of them wo got, but I did not know nor think of them, till I was almost
						shock'd to death, and could scarce stagger into <add place="above">the House</add>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">door</hi>, when, even in the very Passage, the Lord met me, Comforted me, and gave me the Assurance in my Heart, "He would preserve me for himself
						for ever." This Promise has always been a secret Comfort to me, all my Course through, yea even, when in the highest of my Folly in the World. I was near 8 years old,
						&amp; made a memorandum of that important Day. I was kept more close to my learning, and was instructed in all the Principles of the Church. I also got Courage to discover
						those notorious deceivers, without their knowing it was me Yet my Heart departed from its dearest Object, and I became as Formal and vain as any Body; I saw myself a fair
						Candidate for the World; but also, Ruin, Destruction, and eternal death stood as fair before me. This made me go on heavily, but I could tell no one: And as I was under
						Preparation for the H. Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> I was the more distress'd; Sometimes in dispair and sometimes desperate. In this Situation I went to Evening
						Prayers, but I could neither pray, nor desire. I was so condemn'd; But in the Begining of the last Prayers, my Heart became as melting Wax, and as such a Wretch I
						turn'd again to my Friend, and begg'd for mercy and got Confidence to trust and rely on him. I had sometime before privately made it out in my own mind, that, as
						Oppertunity should serve, I would privately retire to a Cloister, and in that especiall manner dedicate myself to the Lord Forever. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-03.jpg"/>
					<p> In my 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year it was thought proper by my Friends, that I should go to London for further Improvement. I was receiv'd with the greatest
						heartiness, and every one was kindly officious in bringing me to public Places, and shewing me the Curiosities of the Town. I saw the Glory's of the World - and loved it -
						and concluded, as I had often been told, I was made for the World, for it suited my Inclination and tast every way; And I had well nigh set through all Convictions, Though at
						the Bottom I had a Condemn'd heart and guilty Conscience. My Mother being in London at this time took me with her, to see a Friend of hers in Bedlam, and surveying the
						many Shocking objects there, she tumed to me and said. "This is the <add place="above">sad</add> effect of Love and Pride." I made her no answere; but ispairingly
						despairingly thought: and this will one day be my unhappy Case unless God exert his Almighty Power in rescuing me. </p>
					<p> I soon followed my Mother privately to Reading, giving all my Acquaintance the Slip; But was soon surrounded with my old Friends and Acquaintance who were very desireous to
						hear news, and learn more particularly the Fashions of the Town. I told them, I was quite tired of all those things, and therefore resolv'd soon to retire from all, and
						come and live in a quite different way: If any of them w<hi rend="strikethrough">h</hi>ere inclin'd to make one of the Company, when I came to settle at home, it could be
						made out. </p>
					<p> From this time I had no rest for my poor distresst Heart &amp; mind Therefore in my 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> year I left London the Last time, to put in practice what I
						had so long purposed, renewing my Acquaintance with the most solid and religious Part of my Friends. I followed as near as I could. Step for step, with my Mother &amp; Brother,
						who had begun some time ago a more religious Course of Life; But, alas! I grew faint hearted and tir'd: And seeing all my Works, Prayers and Duties, good for nothing at
						all, and I myself that same de- plorable Creature as ever I was, I cry'd out in the Bitterness of my Soul: O Lord Jesus Christ' if this is the way to Heaven, I shall
						never come there! My distress still increased, being more &amp; more Sensible of my Degeneracy; But above all did my base ingratitude to my once so tender Lover fill me with
						horror and Dejection. </p>
					<p> We had heard of the Awakening in Oxford, where my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> went, got acquainted with several, and brought M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Kinchin<hi rend="strikethrough">g</hi> to our house; and afterwards M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wesleys, Hutchins, Whitfield &amp;c. I was much perplex'd in my own mind at
						this rash (as I thought then) proceeding of my Brothers, fearing a Schism in the Church. But being convinced of the truth of their Doctrine, was soon Zealously attached
						thereto. But the Preaching being in our House, it made a great stir in the Town, and caused us much Trouble and disgrace; So that my Mother hearing of it in London, came home,
						and put an intire Stop to it. <note type="catchword">Hereupon</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-04.jpg"/>
					<p> Hereupon my Brother went to Bristoll, and I, and a well disposed singled Woman took a house in the Town; but the Preaching was given up. By these means got the ill Will of all
						my Friends and Relations My Acquaintance also shun'd me, and every one's Face was set against me. Thus forsaken of all, and destitute of my best Friend, I grew
						dejected, and quite malancholy. </p>
					<p> In 1740 I visited Kingswood and Bristol; but could not be reconcil'd to those Agitations among the Methodists at that time. Here I had happiness of seeing first our d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bro<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Toellshig, who seeing my concern, help'd me much. I soon return'd to Reading exceedingly
						distress'd, And finding my dear Companion so happy in our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and myself so wretched, I gave up all hopes of ever being sav'd. But here
						in one moment did my most gracious Saviour reveal Himself to me, forgave me all my sin, and in an instant I was dispossess'd of every Pain: I could hardly tell if I was in
						the Body or not. For my heart saw nothing but Jesus. I felt after Sin; but behold! there was no Sin. I felt after my own guilt and Distress, but there was no Place found for
						them, and nothing but light surrounded me. I had not enjoy'd this happiness long, before my venerable Companion fell happily asleep on the Bosom of her eternal Bridegroom. </p>
					<p> At my return the former Disturbances were reviv'd. many were distresst concerning their Salvation; And the Clergy being greatly perplex'd, endeavour'd to put me
						to Trouble; But our Saviour kept me stay'd upon Him and deliver'd me safe out of their Hands. I gave up my House, and went again to Kingswood, where M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Whitfield, my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and others were separated from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wesleys, and had begun more regular
						Society, and gave me the care of the Single Women, with whom I labour'd as well as I could; But knowing my own Insufficiency, and seeing many Irregularities creeping in among
						the Young People, I told my Bro<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> this was not what suited me; and therefore I came to Reading, where a Widow Quaker Gentlewoman had long and often
						desir'd I would stay with her and <hi rend="underline">take</hi>
						<add place="above">use</add> her House as my own. I did so, And all my Quaker Friends were exceeding kind to me, and earnestly wish'd me to settle amongst them; I would
						have done it, but had no leave from our Savr in my own Heart. My Mind was secretly Hankering after a Cloister: But my Bro<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> desiring my Assistance at
						Tetherton, I went to him, and with all the Money I had, Goods &amp; Furniture, engaged with him, and the Peace of God ruled &amp; rested upon us. </p>
					<p> In 44 I went on a Visit to London, where our late S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stonehouse brought me aquainted with my ever dearest Anna Johanna, with whom my Heart was
						tenderly united, as was hers to me. <note type="catchword">I had</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-05.jpg"/>
					<p> I had heard of the Order among the Single Sisters, and that it was something like a Nunery, which exacted my enquiry and I wish'd once to see such a Choir. My Bro<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> had already contracted a large Acquaintance with the Brethren, and sometime after gave our Societies into their care and went on a Visit to Hhaag,
						and from thence to Ireland. In his Absence I had the favour of a Visit at Tetherton from our late d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Disciple and Discipless, Christel, Anna Johanna
						&amp;c. The Discipless was particularly hearty with me to, whom, at first, I was somewhat reserved; But coming upon Heart Matters, I was quite openhearted, and she spoke to me
						in the most Comfortable and encouraging manner, telling me, how tenderly She and her Company felt towards me, and assuring me of our Saviours Thoughts of Peace concerning me. </p>
					<p> My Brother soon after return'd, who told me yet more about the single Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>, and how earnestly he had Pray'd our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> to bring me into their happy Circle, That he knew it was just a Regulation as would please me. Upon duly weighing the matter before our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, I wrote to my much respected Friend, the d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Discipless for leave to visit the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> in Germany, who readily
						granted me the favour. My Mother also at this time, was well inclin'd towards to Bre<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>; But meeting with some unhpy Circumstances, she was
						turn'd quite against them: And tho' I was much Staggered, yet our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> preserved me, and gave me Courage of persevere in my Purpose. Yet I
						had it hard to get away, and was forc'd to leave her against her Will. </p>
					<p> In March 1747 I arrived with many more English Brethen and Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> together with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; Sis Teltschig in Hhaag, where I
							m<hi rend="strikethrough">e</hi>et with the most cordial reception from our d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Disciple &amp; Discipless. The Congregation and its regulations I
						saw with wonder and delight; Especially that of the S. Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. My first Intention only was to Visit the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>, and not to
						become a Member thereof; But in London, on my way h<hi rend="strikethrough">e</hi>ither, being a Spectator at the Holy Communion, I was so affected that I forgott my
						Resolution; Till by Occasion, soon after my arrival, I grew Suspicious, till I was quite confus'd. But having an unreserved Confidence to the late d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Discipless, I told her all my Concern, who with the greatest tenderness &amp; Frankness clear'd up those matters which had given me so much pain. I now became
						quite happy and saw the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> in a right light, and the Beginning of that happy Period, which the H Ghost had so many years been preparing me for. </p>
					<p> I had the Grace to be received into the Congregation the same year, Was soon after Confirm'd and in Jan 1748 was made a happy Partaker of the Lords Body and Blood in the H
						Communion. Here also I had the Grace to be admitted into the Class of Intercessors, and soon after set out with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Boehler &amp;c. for England. Our D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Papa, Mamma, the Mother, Anna Johanna &amp;c. accompanied us to Francfort, </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb n="6" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-06.jpg"/>
					<p> where, after many Blessings, the rest day we proceeded on our Journey in the Peace of God, and blessing of the Congregation. </p>
					<p> After staying sometime in London, I was sent to Fulneck, where I was one of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Servants, Choir Servant &amp; Helper. In June 1750 I was
						called to London, where I enjoy'd many blessings in the Dear Disciples House in Bloomsbury Square. From whence I was sent to Dublin to have the Care of the S. Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> There and in the north of Ireland. The same year I visited the North, and the Year after was sent there; where also, as in Dublin our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> accom- panied, blessed and prosper'd me, gave me the Hearts of the Sisters, for whom I have ever retained the tenderest affection, and shall
						to my latest Breath. So that, notwithstanding the many heavy Circumstances, I enjoy'd the still Communion with my Hearts best Friend; Nor were my many Faults, weaknesses
						and mistakes a hindrence thereto. </p>
					<p> In Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 1758 I got a Call to the Disciple House, from my dear Anna Johanna. And the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> arriv'd S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mary, S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ripley and Matty Haley, who were most heartily receiv'd by all, and especially by our own d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> little Choir in Ballunderry. </p>
					<p> The 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mary Spoke the Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> to the Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> and in the
						Afternoon we partook of the same. Particular meetings were appointed in all the Plans for the Reception of the above two Sisters, which with other meetings and matters lasted
						to the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> when we viz: B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Watson, S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Mary, Marg<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Graham a Widow, myself, My dear little Neice Betsey Cennick, and Betsey Mortimer, set off from Ballunderry, and came to Bellfast the same evening
						where we were detain'd till the 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> when in our way down to the Vessel S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mary got a sad fall; we got on board
						however the same evening. On the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> a Voilent Storm arose and we were given up for lost. this was a trying Circumstance to me, after I had gone
						through so many trials before; But I immediately turn'd to my best and <add place="above">only</add> Friend, thought perhaps I was the Jonas and therefore became a sinner
						before Him on all accounts, and in 5 minutes all were well between Him and me, and my heart rejoice'd that I should so soon see him. the WW<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of
						the Day was. Rom. 14, 8. "Wether we live, we live unto the Lord, or wether we die, we die unto the Lord." "Must a ling'ring Death await us, This Text ever
						will stand Good: He in Glory to translate us, Purchas'd all Things by his Blood." The 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> we got among the sandbanks. The 29 we landed in
						Liver Pool safe and well. Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> we came to Fulneck abt 4 o'Clock. After Tea S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
						Hendrengen took care of the Children, </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb n="7" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-07.jpg"/>
					<p> And in the evening S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mary sent to invite me into her house, where I enjoy 'd many Blessings; till in Jan. 59 B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
						&amp; Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Houptmann received their Call to Bedford, I embrace'd this Oppertunity of going with them from hence to that Place, where I was
						receiv'd with the greatest love and heartiness. I soon went to London, when, after waiting along while, and meeting with many hindrences, however on the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of May I arrived with several more Brethern &amp; Sisters to my exceeding great Joy, having that long wish'd for happiness of seeing my dear
						Papa, Mamagen and Anna Johanna once more. The 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I was brought to Annenhoff, where I enjoy'd many inexpressible Blessings. The 1<hi rend="superscript">4th</hi> I was receiv'd as Acoluth and ordained a Deaconess. Here I had the favour of Staying till the Close thereof, a time, I shall never forget.
						July the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I set out from Zeist with the respectable B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> H<add place="above">ei</add>nrichs von Reuss &amp; Salome Gross came to Gnadenthal August the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> the 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to Kleinwelke, &amp; the
							12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to Hhuth, where I enjoy'd a real Sabatic season, Continuing in the most tender Comunion with my eternal Friends; and in heartiest
						Fellowship with all. At the latter end of this year our dear Disciple House arrived to the universal great joy of all here; I had the Blessing of being present at the S. Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Synod to the end; as also at that memorable Conclusion of the faithfull Labour of those two eminent Witnesses the d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
						Disciple &amp; Disciples of Jesus in May 1760. That Peace of God, which came more espeically upon the Cong<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi> at that time, I also partook of in a
						particular manner In which happy Sensation I left Hhuth Sep<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Teltschig and came to Kleinwelke; the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to Barby; there I enjoy'd many particular Blessings. The 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> we proceeded on our Journey, and came to Zeist on the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. From thence we came to London Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, And the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I came to Bedford, where I was receiv'd most heartily and it went blessed<add place="above">ly</add> for a time, but afterwards not so; Therefore I was sent to Lembster to B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rice to
						have the Care of some young Women, Collected from several Parts, there being only two Natives. As to outward Circumstances it was morally impossible to come thro' in a
						manner suitable to an Oeconomy; But the principle thing in the whole was <add place="above">the</add> want of hearts, and the true Spirit of Love and Harmony amongs't us
						all. I shall not enter into Farther Particulars, They being of too painfull a nature. </p>
					<p> In Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1764 I receiv'd a Call from the General Synod at Marienborn, by the Hand of my dear Bror Johann, to asist </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="8">
					<head type="page">8</head>
					<pb n="8" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-08.jpg"/>
					<p> Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mary Vogls<hi rend="superscript">ng</hi> in Caring for the S. Sisters and Great Girls of the Country Cong<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi>. I
						receiv'd my Call with awe &amp; real bow- edness of heart. I wrote to S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mary on that account, who answer'd me as a Priestess of God. In
							Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. I set out with a B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. and his Daughter a great Girl, who had lived with me, for ockbrook, where she was to
						reside. We arrived there safe and well after a heavy Journey, and I stay'd to refresh myself for several days among my old Acquaintance and then set out for Fulneck. On
						the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. I came to Leeds where our late B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Shultze was waiting to bring me to Fulneck
						the next Day, and presented me with a very hearty Congratulatory Letter from my D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mary We arrived at Fulneck ab<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Noon on the 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> and met with a very hearty Reception from all my d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> old S. Sisters, and
						stay'd till the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Jan; when I was brought to Gumersall Oeconomy be S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mary and Ann Birkby. I felt well as
						soon as I enterd the House. Early the next morning the <add place="above">two</add> above mentioned Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> took their leave of us. I got alone into
						my little room and kept a hearty Band with my Best Friend, and with many tears devoted myself afresh to him: Put Him in mind of his Promise viz: That He would once bring me
						into an Asylum, where I should enjoy a real Sabatic sea- son and Bridal Intercourse with Him, preparatory to his taking me into His arms and Bosom. </p>
					<p> He shewed me something more concerning my present call, than I found, Some others knew, and was to remain a sceeret between Him and me, I soon found myself at Home, and that he
						would bring me safely thro'. I felt also that the Hearts of the Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> were tenderly inclin'd towards me; so that we soon became one Heart
						and one Mind, and a Blessed Period commence'd, tho' under many Difficulties. Not long after, a certain Sabbatic mood and most intimat inter- course, between me and my
						Friend took Place; So that my Labour among the Souls, was my Delight, it per adventure I might happily gain some, to become lovers of this my so favourite Object. My Journeys
						were long and heavy, to go to the different Cong<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi>, and I being very weakly made me oft secretly sigh and weep be fore my Friend: For it being just
						the depth of the winter that I come here, made walking in those bad roads almost impracticable; But here I must mention with the greatest gratitude &amp; humility the more then
						Brotherly &amp; Sisterly love and Faithfullness of my good, old, venerable Hearts Watsons; Happy for me they were at this time <note type="catchword">living</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="9">
					<head type="page">9</head>
					<pb n="9" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-09.jpg"/>
					<p> living here in Gumersall, and had the Care of Wyke Plan also, they therefore most Chearfully help'd me always, when, and where they could with their horse &amp;c. In
							Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> following, we had the misfortune to loose them; For they went to Mirfield: Here also they faithfully assisted me in every respect, and that
						same genuin look &amp; heartiness still subsisting between us especially my good S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Watson our hearts became joined and united in the heart of our
						wounded Friend, To be Separated no more for ever. As I have always mostly travel'd on foot My walks however have been made to me liturgic Walks, and my Friend has so made
						perfect <add place="above">his strength</add> in my weakness, that, when I have been well nigh fainting and thought I could get no farther, I have been so Comforted
						refresh'd and Strengthened that I have not been sensible of pain and weakness, and oftentimes stood still to consider whereabout I was, and with surprize found myself
						nearer my Journeys end, then I could have thought or imagin'd. My Garden has been like a little Paradise, wherein I have admir'd, worship'd and ador'd my
						Dearest Heart, the Great Gardener of the universe, and He has always attended me in my meanest employ<hi rend="strikethrough">ment</hi> therein. He has made my Labour truly a
						Liturgy. And how he and I have Been engaged together. Some few Verses made on a Garden &amp; Flowers, some of which are here inserted, Do more emp<add place="above">h</add>atically express, </p>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>1</l>
							<l>Josephs Garden here's intomb'd my Lover</l>
							<l>Hollw'd Cave! here lies my Gain</l>
							<l>Here I sing in this cool silent Power</l>
							<l>Bout the Man! my Pleasing strain</l>
							<l>Softest Musick, gently soothing sorrow</l>
							<l>While thy Love sick spouse her spices gather</l>
							<l>From thy Corpse so pale &amp; wan</l>
							<l>Which she's fondly dotting on</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="2">
							<l>2</l>
							<l>Red and white my Jesu's wounded Body</l>
							<l>As <add place="above">in</add> Gardens Flowers excell</l>
							<l>Lylies fair and full Bloom roses Ruddy</l>
							<l>Yeild their Odoriferous smell</l>
							<l>engrav'd upon thy Corpse so sweetly</l>
							<l>Wounds like roses fresh and set compleatly</l>
							<l>And some smaller holes between</l>
							<l>Just like Buds twist Jesemin</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="3">
							<l>3</l>
							<l>Lovly Picture Beauty most transcendent</l>
							<l>Matchless he! My paradice</l>
							<l>Thou my Garden fertile fragrant pleasant</l>
							<l>Thou my food My tree of Life</l>
							<l>Sweet inlaid among thy Clothed Tresses</l>
							<l>From the Thorns Pomgranates have their place</l>
							<l>Fruit and flowers, these compose</l>
							<l>My Belov'd my Sharons rose</l>
						</lg>
						<note>In the memoir, the fourth stanza is placed after stanza 8 in the right column</note>
						<lg type="stanza" n="4">
							<!-- in the mansucript, stanza 4 is in the right column and a line indicates where it should be inserted in the left column above stanza 5-->
							<l>4</l>
							<l>Edens Garden my love planted for me</l>
							<l>favour'd place he brought me there</l>
							<l>Was himself still with me so delight'd</l>
							<l>I with him. Ah happy pair</l>
							<l>Short liv'd Joy I got there in a surfeit</l>
							<l>Every comfort was the fatal forfeit</l>
							<l>Rudly ravish'd from my Love</l>
							<l>Morn'd my Widow'd with Dove</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="5">
							<l>5</l>
							<l>Long I wander'd in the Howling desert</l>
							<l>left my first my Virgin Spouse</l>
							<l>Got new lovers seeming fair &amp; pleasant</l>
							<l>Join'd in league with my Love's for</l>
							<l>In Gethsemeny I saw the Combat</l>
							<l>When he fought for Me his faithless Consort</l>
							<l>And on Calvary with his Life</l>
							<l>Rejoic'd in his Dear Lov'd Wife</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="6">
							<l>6</l>
							<l>Here it is that I with Brides Affection</l>
							<l>To those places oft </l>
							<l>With my Bridegroom in his own Affliction</l>
							<l>Here each other we admire</l>
							<l>Softt Sensations is the pleasing Coverse</l>
							<l>As there Gardens on together traverse</l>
							<l>Mutual Kisses we impart</l>
							<l>To and from each others Heart</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="7">
							<l>7</l>
							<l>Oft we stood and seiz'd with Admiration</l>
							<l>How intent and fond he's been</l>
							<l>With what diligence and warm affection</l>
							<l>He has nurs'd some Little thing</l>
							<l>Hardly worth another thought or notion</l>
							<l>This has been to him the very Christ</l>
							<l>All the finest flowers he's left</l>
							<l>And this one more in his Breast</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="8">
							<l>8</l>
							<l>Yes I know him exquisite his test in</l>
							<l>What even Gardners count above</l>
							<l>These in nosegays raisd to higher Graces </l>
							<l>He will in his Bosom wear</l>
							<l>Publick Grandour once demonstrating</l>
							<l>When the Marriage will be Consumating</l>
							<l>Ever Greens and flowers rare</l>
							<l>Grow old with these shall then appear</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="10">
					<head type="page">10</head>
					<pb n="10" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-10.jpg"/>
					<p> My little Room has been a Cabinet of Jewels to me, Therefore I have long concluded, that if our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> took me home here in Yorkshire, I would die in
						my nest, and so slip away, as it were incognito Since our dr B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Boehlor's Visitation here, our Family has been brought again into the injoyment
						of our Choir Graces with our Choir to our very great abasement. </p>
					<p> For this Year last past, I have felt that my time was out in Gummersal, and last summer thought I should get a Call after the Synod; but could never find out any Place where I
						could be sent to. I once kept a hearty Band with my Friend about it, at the Conclusion of which, and summing up the whole, I said to Him: "Now would it not be better thou
						tookst me home to thy <add place="above">own dr</add> self." I had no room to suspect any thing of the kind, from what I felt from him at that time; But July last, As I
						was in the Chaple <add place="above">Garden</add> at Work, He drew near To me in an extraordinary manner, and discover'd to me Such an Union &amp; oneness between Him
						&amp; me, as is altogether unutterable, tho' I did attempt to express something of it in a few Verses. </p>
					<p> From this time I had often gentle hints of a Change, of something that would take place, which should entirely suit me. </p>
					<p> In August last I got it Voilent Cold, which grew worse &amp; worse, And found my Lungs were infected. In the Beginning of Sept last, I felt myself strangly ill; so as I had
						never been before, which lasted some few nights &amp; days; And during the whole time, I was most happily Comforted with my Friends nearness, Insomuch that I felt no illness at
						all, only that I was weak and drowsy. One night, unasked for, He came Close to my Bedside, and stood there. My Heart saw Him, And my Soul adored Him! He dispersed intirely in a
						moment every painfull thought and Sensation, inwardly and outwardly I felt after one Wound and another sore; But behold! they were all healed. I felt after Sin, and there was
						no sin. I felt after misery and Dejection, But there was none to be found; And thus I was made sound and whole, except those pleasing Wounds of Love, which He had made long
						before in my enamour'd Heart, But now more Deeply impress'd. </p>
					<p> Now it was, He gave me, the soft impression of his Gracious intention Concerning me; while I silently worship'd before Him. On the 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> my d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lorel called on us in her return from Duckenfield, and was quite alarm'd at my seeming bad state of Health,
						would not rest, But insisted on my going to Fulneck, To stay there for some time which I did; where I assisted in seeing the Sisters for the Communion, and could not forbear to
						drop a word now and then concerning something, the very obscure of my happy Situation. On the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I return'd to Gummersal, where my Disorder
						increased, And my Friend confirmed more <note type="catchword">strongly</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="11">
					<head type="page">11</head>
					<pb n="11" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-11.jpg"/>
					<p> Strongly what he had made allready manifest to me. I was very well seemingly, fix'd and suited; But my d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.
						Lorel could not be reconcil'd to my staying at Gumersel, and I must own shew'd more then Mothers Faithfulness and Affection: In these Circumstances she could not be
						prevailed upon to be Satisfy'd, unless I came to Fulneck. </p>
					<p> I therefore set out in mere faith, with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Samuel Fowler and Joseph Peal Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
						<add place="margin">1769</add> and arriv'd here safe, and meet with a very hearty Reception. The first d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Heart which saluted me, was my most
						dear and venerable Heart Anna Johanna; I was also made happily sensable of that genuine Love and hearty affection of the Choir in general, And more especially <hi rend="strikethrough">of</hi>
						<add place="above">from</add> all those in Office; so that that peace of God, and that Sabbath, which I never had heard any one possessing, at least so long before their
						Departure, accompanied me here also in the clearest manner, which begun at the time above mentioned, when our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> manifested Himself to me in such
						an especiall manner. But here I must mention some essential things, which I forgot to mention in their proper places, viz. After all that the Lord had done for me, and I was
						clear and well establish'd in it: One Day, as He &amp; I were solacing ourselves in each others love, it came into my mind; But that oneness &amp; union which I had
						possessed in Him. I was not so clear in at this time: He shew'd me, I was wholly in Him and He in me, and that we were One as he and the Father are One. I saw myself
						cloathed upon in Him, and possessed of all the Bridal Ornaments of the Bridegroom. I must therefore ascribe all the Honour and Glory alone to my own d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. eternal Slaughter'd Lord and Saviour and conclude my Narrative with the Greatest truth in all the World: viz. That, Where Sin hath abounded, Grace hath
						abounded Much more. </p>
					<p> Our venerable and Happily departed Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sarah Cennick, Has in some measure Specify'd How varioussly her Election of Grace has <add place="above">been</add> manifested w<add place="above">h</add>ere-ever her happy Lot Has been cast, during Her Course through this vale of tears. </p>
					<p> Her Strong Capacity, Great Gifts, and quick sensations, was Iluminated by such extraordinary Grace from the H. Ghost As evidently Signalized Her a peculiar Person of Blessed
						remembrance to the Hearts of many Souls. </p>
					<p> Yet amidst all those great Endowments, she had the Happiness, through the infinite Mercys of God, to be throughty Convinced of her great depravity in Soul and Body, and which
						truly as a monument of uncommon Mercy and Grace, was preserved, in her Earlyest years, From the dangers and vain Foibels of her natural Inclinations, and as her own words has
						spoke it, she counted it the highest Dignity <note type="catchword">to</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="12">
					<head type="page">12</head>
					<pb n="12" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-12.jpg"/>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza">
							<l>to be rank'd amongst the Chiefest of Sinners, and has with particular</l>
							<l>clearness expresst her mind in a few verses on this subject, in the</l>
							<l>Beginning of her last Sickness, as follows</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg type="stanza">
							<l>Thou Feast of worms &amp; atoms</l>
							<l>Repast of Sinners poor</l>
							<l>Who on thy Godheads Bottom</l>
							<l>Stands sav'd for evermore</l>
							<l>What signified to Thee</l>
							<l>Our vast depravity</l>
							<l>Thou Abyss of Perfection</l>
							<l>Thou loves immensity</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza">
							<l>Inseperable union</l>
							<l>Devotions fragrant Source </l>
							<l>Most Heavenly Comunion</l>
							<l>Devinest Intercourse </l>
							<l>Soft Gentle soothing Hum</l>
							<l><hi rend="strikethrough">Effectual</hi> aninum</l>
							<l>for evermore to Solace </l>
							<l>The Spirit&amp; Bride say, Come.</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p> By these Veres somithing may be understood of that truly Evangelical intercourse, which our late happy Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> had with her Souls Bridegroom; She has
						certainly been favour'd with a more than common union and nearness from her Friend &amp; Lover. Her Soul magnify'd the Lord, and her Spirit daily rejoiced in God her
							Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> whom she recommended on all Occasstions, with such energy, as is not to be expresst in words, which bears an Indelible Signature of
						Blessing in her Choir. During her last Sickness we have seen many Blessed Testemonies of this Kind, wherein she has plainly shown, that her very Soul was animated with new life
						whenever our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> or his matters was named, Especially with regard to the General and Individual Intercourse which our dear Lord should have in the
						Choir. On Consideration of our dear Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Situation, and Circumstances in Sickness at Gumersall, At our desire she remov'd to end her days in
						the midst of her Choir at Fulneck, yet she retained the same Love and Concern, for her dear Gumersall Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>, to whom we perceiv'd on all
						Occassions, she had the tenderest attachment And her hearts Connexion with the Fountain of Love defus'd it self thro' the whole Choir. For notwithstanding her great
						weakness, she desir'd to see the Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Room by Room, took a most tender and solemn farewell of them all; Like wise Little Moore &amp; Gumersall
						Oeconomies, The Latter of which, she desir'd to see once again, when her Dissolution was perceptably hastening, which was a most moving scene, To Behold and feel with what
						power and grace, she gave her last Benediction to that dear Oeconomy Where she had finishe' her faithfull Labour in this Crosses Kingdom <note type="catchword"/>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="13">
					<head type="page">13</head>
					<pb n="13" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-13.jpg"/>
					<p> Here Below. And blest each with impossion of hands in the most maternal and feeling manner. </p>
					<p> From this time her weakness increas'd more sensibly, which Excited a more Eager desire to see her Class, which Oppertunity was most thankfully embraced to have once more a
						LFeast with her, And her aspect testify'd what her heart injoy'd on this Occasion to have the great priviledge to declare in our midst, that the Peace of God our
						Saviour, was so preceptably felt to rule and preside By one Spirit among'st us, to the Great Comfort and astonishment Of her heart, which she confess'd m<hi rend="strikethrough">e</hi>et her at the first entrance at our Doors. She pray'd fervently, that this Peace and blessed Harmony in our Choir, and particularly in this
						her Class, might daily increase &amp; Prosper to the Honour of his holy name, and the Blessing on the whole Choir, which made a latting impression on all present; And at the
						Close took a most Affecting leave, and like a Handmaid and Priestess of God, sencerely recommended her fellow Helper Lorel Seidel to the Special blessing of the Lord in her
						future Course &amp; Labour in the Choir. The 23 in the evening she Complain'd of a pain in her Side, but had a Tolerable good night, and took her Breakfast in the Moming,
						with More relish then usual, but felt very weary. </p>
					<p> About 9 o'Clock on S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lorels entering the Room she call'd Her to her bedside, And with uncommon firmness of mind <add place="above">said</add> Lorel this very day. I'm determin'd to go home and repeated it again with the greatest fervency, Saying, I have been speaking with my Friend about it,
						See to it, that you have my mansion ready (the Corpses Chamber), and then was still for some moments, a Sister Continuing by her Bedside whom she ask'd, what she was
						reading so devotly in Her Countenance. The Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Answer'd, it's the near Approaches of your Desolution, which engages my attention in an
						unutterable manner. She smiling made no answer and remained still for some time, and then ask'd, what it was that she now perceiv'd come with a little noise from her
						Breast said is it Death! answer'd by the Sister I beleive it is, then she haistyly reply'd, Pray then call Lorel. At whose entrance into the Room, she fixt her eyes
						upon her and said, Dont took so anxious This Ruttling in my Breast is no pain to me, I am quite easy and shall very soon be with him, in whose heart centers all my wishes. </p>
					<p> She retain'd a Strong presence of Mind, and during her Whole Sickness to her last Moments, was Carried on with remarkable Serinity and ease, Traceing many intimations from
						some Months past of her Gracious Lords intentions with her By this sickness, And that no pains should interrupt that <note type="catchword">Sweet</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="14">
					<head type="page">14</head>
					<pb n="14" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_68Cennick-14.jpg"/>
					<p> Sweet Comunion that her Soul injoy'd with its Beloved Bridegroom Which was truly verify'd to the end. </p>
					<p> About an Hour before she departed it was perceivd her Lips moved very quick, beleiving she call'd some one by name, On being ask'd if it was so, she reply'd
						it's possibly. But I was conversing with my Friend and lover: Continuing in this way about 3 quarters of an hour, And then wanted very much To Speak, Her Fa<hi rend="strikethrough">l</hi>iltering Tongue could no more be understood only Christ &amp; Cry &amp;c. a few moments would now end the Period of her time, upon which Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lorel laid her hand upon her head and she look'd once more up. And then Closs'd her eyes to Sleep in the Arms of her everlasting
						Bridegroom. during The Blessing of her Choir, with a most powerfull feeling of Grace, from the sensible near presence of our dearest Lord, Which will never be forgotten by
						those who had the favour To be present, at this important Event </p>
					<p> Her Corpes had a most lovly Aspect. She has spent in this Dying Life 57 Years, 7 Months, and some Days. <note>In the margin in pencil, next to the last line, is written
							"1770"</note>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>