<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Elizabeth Coffin: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin">Elizabeth Coffin</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin-04.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Elizabeth Coffin</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-17" who="#JAKA1">Converted for semantic markup</change>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-09" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Elizabeth Coffin</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin-01.jpg" />
					<p> Our late S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Eliz<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Coffin was born <add place="above">near</add>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">at</hi> Elledmere, on the borders of Wales, <add place="above">A.D. 1777</add> her father being an extensive farmer. Of her earlier years, very little
						is known to us; as our late S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> left no memoranda of her course thro&apos; time. It appears however that her religious impressions were received
						early in life; &amp; she was accustomed to refer to one youthful experience as a turning proint in her <hi rend="strikethrough">experience</hi>
						<add place="above">course</add>. </p>
					<p> Whilst attending the parish Church, some particular sentence in the morning prayer come home to her heart with such power, that she felt the love of Christ as accomplishing her
						redemption. She was <add place="above">thus</add> persuaded of her interest in his atonement, &amp; it is remarkable in the religious experience of our late S<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi>, that her course was not so subject to change &amp; deviation as </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin-02.jpg" />
					<p> that of the majority of the Lord&apos;s children. As far as her X<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> experience is known to us, she has alway spoken of his life of faith as a happy
						one; she knew no periods of gloom &amp; tasted not the bitterness of the soul from whom the Lord&apos;s comforts are with drawn. </p>
					<p> As the age of 17 or 18, she removed to London, and entered the family of our late S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Vowel <hi rend="strikethrough">with</hi> whom she lived till
						that lady&apos;s death. It was during her residence there, &amp; during B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Montgomry&apos;s service of the Congn that she joined the Church of the
							B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>, of which she has been so many years a consistent member </p>
					<p> After S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Vowel&apos;s departure, she remained with the 2 M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Youngs, the nephews <add place="above">of the deceased</add>
						till her own health began to fail. </p>
					<p> About the year 1820, she removed to Bristol, where she became an inmate, of the sisters house, during </p>
					<cb />
					<p> B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Okelys&apos; ministry. Her stay in Bristol was but short, &amp; the subsequent years of her life, up to her last removal in Fulneck, appear to
						have been somewhat un settled as to her abode. She lived in Fulneck S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> House for a few years; &amp; also spent some time again in London, &amp;
						with more than one family of her relatives. </p>
					<p> In July 1831 <add place="above">i.e about</add> 24 years ago she settled finally on Fulneck, a place which seems above others to be that of her choice. Her walk among us here,
						her peculiarities her cheerful nature, her activitz &amp; especially her great love for the meetings for family &amp; public worship these are well known to many who this day
						see her mortal remains conveyed to their last resting place. </p>
					<p> Being so long an invalid, her thoughts were often busied <add place="above">concerning</add>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">upon</hi> her own </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin-03.jpg" />
					<p> health whilst she inquired sympathisingly after she welfare of others. </p>
					<p> About a year ago, when speaking of a recent attack of illness, she remarked I had sometimes the feeling that she Lord would take me to himself. Being asked whether she felt
						herself prepared for the last change she replied in her quick characteristic manner &amp; quite cheerfully -- It would be a great shame if I were not ready for it; for it is
						now 50 years since I first knew the Lord; &amp; since that time he has enabled me to serve Him It would be ungrateful in me to think he would not accept me at the last.&quot; </p>
					<p> For the last twelve month s her health was perceived to her failing considerably tho&apos; she would not, till near the last, hear of seeking medi cal advice. Tho&apos; she
						most often have been suffering from weakness &amp; pain she was still seen as her </p>
					<cb />
					<p> place in the Prayer Hall &amp; Chapel where the meetings were always a source of spiritual enjoyment <add place="above">To her</add> &quot;As long as I can I must go&quot; she
						would say &quot;for soon I may not be able&quot; </p>
					<p> Towards the close of last week, a<hi rend="strikethrough">s</hi> perceptible change was noticed in her &amp; it be came evident to her friends, tho&apos; not as first to
						herself, that her time here below was drawing near it close. When her labouress alluded to the approaching end, &amp; asked her whether she felt ready for our Saviours coming,
						if it should please Him to take her now, she answered, that she would like to feel Him nearer, but she had no fear. </p>
					<p> On Sunday, the last day of her life, tho&apos; growing very feeble, she retained a clear conciousness &amp; on unshaken faith. In reply to a question as to her spiritual
						support in this trouble she answered with energy &quot;I will trust Him tho&apos; he slay me.&quot; And again she said &quot;I care not what pain </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_46Coffin-04.jpg" />
					<p> I have, if I have only <hi rend="underline">Him</hi> with me </p>
					<p> For the attention of the Sisters &amp; friends to her in her illness, she was truly grateful, &amp; expressed herself surprised at the display of love which she witnessed. </p>
					<p> On Sunday evening when her Laboress told her <hi rend="strikethrough">she</hi> our Savr <hi rend="strikethrough">might</hi>
						<add place="above">would probably</add> very soon come &amp; take her to himself, she seemed still somewhat surprised that her end should be so near; but was free from all
						apprehension of the event. Her feeling appeared to be that of the conviction &amp; confidence expressed in the Hymn 1184. 2 Thou knowst &amp;c. </p>
					<p>
						<!-- This following section is inserted (on memoir document it is marked at the bottom of page 4, right-hand page --> She regretted B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Libbay&apos;s
						absence from the Congn at this time, much wishing to live to see him again; as at the first, she appeared not right to have under stood him in his Conversat with her. </p>
					<p> When asked if she wished to par take of the H. Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> again, she replied somewhat doubtfull, -- I do not rest on <hi rend="underline">that</hi> - You
						know <hi rend="underline">He</hi> is my Bread of Life. </p>
					<p> The same evening she received the blessing of the Congn. imparted by B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Okely after a fervent prayer for the nearness &amp; support of Jesus in this
						hour of trial - She was not only perfectly conscious during this transaction but expressed also the enjoyment &amp; benefit she had derived from it. </p>
					<p> About 10 o&apos;cl. the same evening <add place="above">Jan 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> /55</add> whilst supported in the arms of some </p>
					<cb />
					<p> the sisters the hour of her departure came; the silver cord was loosed, &amp; she gently breathed her last, her ransomed spirit departing to be with that Lord whom she had long
						here followed in faith tho&apos; in feebleness &amp; <add place="above">with the sense of</add> much unperfection. <add place="above">Her age was 77 years.</add> May our end be
						as tranquil &amp; happy, &amp; as full of confidence in our unseen but present &amp; faithful Redeemer! </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
