<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://cwrc.ca/templates/css/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader><fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Sarah Craven: Memoir</title>
<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <address>
<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
        </address>
        <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
        </principal>
<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
            <address>
                <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
            </address>
            <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
        </principal>
<respStmt>
<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Project Manager</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Developer</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
        <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
        <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
        <resp>Encoder</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
        <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
        <resp>Encoder</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
        <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
        <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
    </respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
    <edition>
        <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
        <address>
            <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
            <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
        </address>
    </edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
    <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
    <availability>
        <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
    </availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
    <msDesc>
        <msIdentifier>
            <repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
            <msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah">Sarah Craven</msName>
            <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-01.jpg"></msName>
           <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-02.jpg"></msName>
           <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-03.jpg"></msName>
<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-04.jpg"></msName>
<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-05.jpg"></msName>
        </msIdentifier>
    </msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc><xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
</rdf:RDF></xenoData><profileDesc>
    <particDesc>
        <person role="subject">
        <persName ref="#">Sarah Craven</persName>
                </person>
    </particDesc>
    <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
    </langUsage>
</profileDesc></teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-01.jpg" n="1"/>
			<p>
				
					The Life of the Single Sister Sar<hi rend="superscript:true;">h</hi> Craven
					who departed 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <hi rend="strikethrough">Nov</hi> 1790</p>
<p>
					 I was born at Bothwell near Leeds in
					the ???? Nov 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1717. I lived with my
					Parents till my Father died who belonged
					to the Church of England. When I was a
					Child  I often wished to die, for I thought at
					that age I should be saved; but if I lived to
					grow up to be a Woman I should come into
					things which would hinder me from attaining eternal happiness. When I came into
					riper years, I followed the World with eagerness, tho' not with satttisfaction; for I often
					felt ureasy in my mind but put if off,
					resolving to grow better, but still went on
					in my old way. After my Father's death
					I went to live with my Uncle &amp; was with
					him when Mr Ingham came into those
					parts but soon after went to live with my
					Mother; she asked me to go with her to
					hear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ingham preach, but I declined it
					for this reason, I believect if I was one of
					his followers I must denounce the World,
					which was my chief Object at that time,
					soon after he came again to preach nearer
					to our habitation) will Mother urged me to
					go with her which I could not now help
					complying with, tho spiritually clear-
					<del>&amp;</del> the discourses had no effect &amp; I wondered
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-02.jpg" n="2"/>
			<p>
				
					what induced people to run after him:
					my Mother invited him to preach at our
					House but he did chuse to do it except we
					would have a Society setted to which she
					consented. In the mean time my Mother
					spoke very closely to me about the state.
					of my Soul; thus prepared I went to hear
					him again. During his Sermon, I was made
					sensible of my lost condition, I wished I could
					alter &amp; thought I had better be deprived of
					this Worlds pleasure then lose my immortal Soul. I thought I could part with every
					thing I had in the World to be assured of
					may salvation, but feared it was impossible 
					In this miserable state I continued a long
					time, &amp; came into selfworking by degrees
					my misery wore off &amp; concluded this was
					the right way to do all the good that was
					in my power so my confidence was to be
					appeased, but being of a hasty temper &amp;
					sometimes overcome with passion my good
					opinion of myself vanished &amp; I became miserable again. In the year 1740. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ingham &amp; B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Tellsheg came to our house. the
					latter could not speak English, but his look
					made a particular impression on me &amp; I
					believed him to be indeed a Child of God.
					In a short time after his visit our Society,
				
			</p>
<cb/>
			<p>
				
					was dispersed, which troubled me very much
					One of them &amp; myself desired desired to be
					admitted into another Society, which was
					the case soon after with a small company
					at Hollbeck near Leeds. But not having
					the pleasure to see B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> often, I grew dry
					in my heart Upon being asked to be a
					Servant in a Family, I at first refused but
					being earnestly intreated, I at last accepted
					&amp; went to the place. I was soon uneasy in it
					for I found I had no freedom to mix with
					worldly company, but was obliged to stay
					my time out. The night before I left my
					place I <del>opened</del> drew that Verse &amp; When I
					was lost &amp; far had strayed Into a Desart
					wild etc. The day after when I was with
					my Mother, some Sisters came to see me,
					I told them what had passed, they act advised
					me to make a new begining, &amp; then our
					Saviour &amp; the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> would forgive me. These
					words comforted me for I did not expect
					to hear such of them. The first meeting
					after their visit that I went to, B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Tellsheg
					kept on the following words, ye cannot
					serve two Masters. it seemed as if he directed his discourse to me alone and 
					no determined have our Saviour for
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-03.jpg" n="3"></pb>
			<p>
				
					my Master &amp; him alone. The short time
					after I was advised to live with two Sisters
					in Hollbeck I did so, but my sittuation was
					not at first agreable to me, I did not
					remain long with them, being desired by
					B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Teltsheg to go to Leeds to wait on a
					Sick Sister, but soon became sick myself
					as I had then no money left to help me the
					future I was persuaded to live my Mother 
					with whom I remained till she died.</p>
<p>
					The day before her departure, a Sister
					visited her &amp; asked her where she would
					like to have me sittuated; she replyed
					amongst Sisters, But after her Death
					I felt such a strong attachment to my
					Relations that I thought I could not part
					with them which brought me again into trou
					ble, &amp; quite at a loss what to do. When I was
					by myself, my faithful Moniter convinced
					me once more that I was not in my right
					place to stay there would be dangerous
					for my Soul. I immediately set off to acquaint my former Labouress, &amp; disclosed
					my whole case. She recommended me to
					another Family in Hollbeck, this was in
					the year 1750. I attended the Preaching
					in Fulneck every Sunday, B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> LaTrobe
				
			</p>
<cb></cb>
			<p>
				
					Sermons were a real blessing to me, &amp; I
					frequent imagined, that he know my inmost thoughts. I had no rest day, nor
					night, on account of the burden of my
					sins. One day as I was by myself earnestly entreating our Saviour to manifest himself unto me, he granted my request &amp; gave me a full assurance of the
					forgiveness of my sins which came with
					such power, that it melted me into tears
					from this time &amp; particularly during my
					stay in that Family, I received many
					blessings form our Saviour. This was also
					a particular period with the Brethren's
					Congregation, their enemies in these parts
					were not affraid to prognosticate their
					ruin, notwithstanding this I wished for a
					still closer union with them, &amp; importuned
					to be admitted a Member of the Congregation.
					The two S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> with whom I lived having departed
					this life it was thought proper for me to
					leave Hollbeck, &amp; I was placed at last to my
					great joy in the Single Sisters Oeconomy at
					gummersall, May 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1755 &amp; was soon at
					hone with them, tho' it proved a new school
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-04.jpg" n="4"></pb>
			<p>
				
					for my heart. The 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of March 1756 I was in
					formed would be a general Congregation Day
					I got an impression that on that day I should
					have the favour to be added thereto. I there
					fore kept a band with our Saviour, sensitive
					of my poverty &amp; helplessness, yet comforted
					with his nearess. In this sittuation of mind
					according to my impression, I was received
					into the Congregation on the above mentioned
					day which proved a great blessing to me
					Thus for her own account</p>
<p>
					April 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1756 our late Sister removed
					from Gumersal to live in the Choir House
					here. March 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1757 she partook with
					the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> of the holy Comunion for the
					first time. It was evident, notwithstand
					ing all human imperfections that she
					had found her peace in our Saviour.</p>
<p>
					She knew in whom she believed and was
					persuaided that he was able to keep
					that which she had commited to Him.
					which helped her through evry trying
					circumstance she met with. her call
					to belong to a Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> of those she valued
					highly and often spoke of it with the greatest
				
			</p>
<cb></cb>
			<p>
				
					greatest gratitude. It was a particuliar
					pleasure to her to serve her Sisters in
					any little matters she was able to do,
					which she did with great faithfullness
					so long as her Strength wou'd admitt
					of it. The begining of this year an
					Asthmatick complaint which she had
					labourd under many Years, grew very
					troublesom to her, so that she was obliged
					in Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> to moove into the sickroom,
					when her longing to be at home with our
					Saviour increased daily. It gave her much
					pain when two of her companions in the
					sickroom was called home before her.
					She suffer'd much in her Sickness which
					made her sometimes rather impatient
					and think the time long, but she wou'd
					soon recolect herself again, and intreated
					our Saviour to give her a childlike resig
					nation to his will that she might not
					grieve him by her impatience.</p>
<p>
					the night before her departure, she said
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/FUL_SS_41_Craven_Sarah-05.jpg" n="5"></pb>
			<p>
				
					said, I am waiting for our Saviour to
					come and fetch me, he will not be long
					now before he comes, I shall then see
					him for myself sickness &amp; Sorrow will
					have an end, he will wipe all tears
					from my Eyes, that night She spent
					in great Weakness, but in converce
					with her best Friend, Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
					the happy moment came when she
					departed in a soft and easy maner
					to her dear Redeemer with the
					blessing of her Choir, half past
					10 oClock in the forenoon, during
					a Sincible feeling of our dear Lords
					presents, in the 72<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Year of her
					Age.
				
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>