<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>John Darnbrook: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="#mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn">Name</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-05.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#mlper000549">John Darnbrook</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2019-07-08" who="#jschaumberger">Finished markup</change>
			<change when="2019-07-03" who="#jschaumberger">Started markup of the memoir</change>
			<change when="2019-07-02" who="#JAKA1">Created John Darnbrook memoir file</change>
			<change when="2019-06-10" who="#JAKA1">Updated header</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>John Darnbrook</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-01.jpg" />
					<p> Course of Life of the S <roleName type="honorific">Br</roleName>
						<persName ref="#mlper000549">John Darnbrook</persName>, the first part of which he himself has wrote down, &amp; the latter dictated. I was born at
							<placeName>Moreley</placeName> in the <placeName>Parish of Battley</placeName>
						<date type="birth" when-iso="1720-06-20">June the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1720</date>. my first 13 Years I lived with my Parents, which took care to instruct me in
						what was religious, to the best of their knowledge, particularly my Mother, whom I remember, when M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
						<persName ref="#mlper000536">Ingham</persName> and other awakened Men first began preaching, she went frequently to hear them, &amp; a Sermon of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
						<persName>Whitfield</persName>&apos;s being then published, she got it to read. I read the same, it treated so much of the Sufferings of our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi
								rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>, that if brought me into some Concern about my Salvation, <date when-iso="1725" cert="medium">I was then about 5 years old </date>
						&amp; this was the first Conviction, I had, as much as I can remember At the End of my <date when-iso="1733" cert="medium">13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year</date> I was
						put an <name occupation="apprentice">Apprentice</name> to a very religious Man in the same town, a Dissenter, in which Way I had been brought up. Half a Year afterwards my
						Father departed this Life. This struck me pretty much of first, but I soon for- got it. the The 3 first years of my <name occupation="apprentice">aprenticeship</name> I spent
						among young Company as much as I could, &amp; indeed in that time I got seduced to many bad Things. One Day, when I was at Work by myself in the Field, a sudden thought came
						into my Mind that I must once die &amp; appear before <persName type="deity">God</persName> to give an decount of my Life &amp; I thought, if I died in that Condition, I
						certainly must go to Hell. I immediately left of my Work &amp; went a kneeled down under a Tree &amp; prayed to <persName type="deity">God</persName> to forgive me. This was
						the first Time. I ever prayed, except such as the <roleName type="honorific">Lords</roleName> Prayer &amp; others learned out of Books. From this time I began to be vary
						religious. I read many religious Books &amp; prayed 6 or 7 times a day, I entirely broke <add place="above">off</add> from all my old Companions, who despised me very much but
						the religious people praised me greatly, &amp; this made me very proud. But all this availed me nothing, all my reading, &amp; praying brought no Peace to my Heart. I was a
						bound Slave to <persName type="deity">Satan</persName>, &amp; when Sin presented itself, I had no Power to resist Some times I used to be a fortnight of 3 weeks without coming
						into any extraordinary great Sin, this made me think, I had now </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-02.jpg" />
					<p> made <persName type="deity">God</persName> amends. But I soon perhaps came into see very Prick of that Sin, which I thought Ihad conquered. This made me think, <persName
							type="deity">God</persName> was displeased with me, &amp; all my Prayers &amp; Readings were of no Signification, I must begin anew &amp; be more watchfull, than I had been
						hitherto. But with all I could do, Sin had the rule over me. I think, I spent near 2 Years in this miserable Course.</p>
					<p> At <date when-iso="1754-04-14" cert="medium">Easter in the year 1754</date> (as well as I can remember) I thought, I would go a hear the <orgName>Moravians</orgName>, tho&apos;
						I had no liking for them, because I believed them to be <orgName>Roman-Catholicks</orgName>. However I went &amp; heard <roleName type="honorific">B<hi rend="superscript"
								>r</hi></roleName>
						<persName>La Trobe</persName> to my great Astonishment Such a <name event="religious">Sermon</name> I never had heard in all my Life before, I thought directly, this is the
						true way to be saved. I went home, &amp; what I had heard of the Sufferings of <persName type="deity">Jesus</persName>, &amp; how that Salvation could be obtained no otherwise,
						than by his ments, Death &amp; Bloodshedding, This wrought much on my Mind all the Week following. When on Sunday I went again; I was so overcome, that I afterwards could not
						go any where else. I soon got acquainted with <roleName type="honorific">B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>
						<persName>Lorde</persName>, &amp; got a great Love for him, but he soon after went from <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>. I was <name event="reception"
							>received into the Society</name>, attended the <name event="religious">Preachings</name> on Sunday constantly &amp; was often so affected with what I had heard, that I
						many Times in my Way home retired into a Wood near <placeName>Tong</placeName> &amp; <name type="emotion">wept</name> before our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi
								rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>, that I might enjoy what I had heard. But I did not rightly prosper; for I had got some thing else in view besides my
						Salvation.</p>
					<p> I had got an Intention to travel, &amp; this engaged my Mind pretty much, &amp; I put this in Execution, as soon as my Prentice ship was out. There happened just at that Time
						two Persons Who come from <placeName ref="#mlpla000054">London</placeName> to see their Relations at <placeName>Moreley</placeName>, &amp; I took the Opportunity to go with
						them at their Return, The one being a married Person, took me to her House, &amp; it was my Home, till I got a Place which I did in ten days time, but it was very hard, so that
						I left it in 3 months &amp; got another place, which I left in about the same Time on account of some differences, I went to my first lodging &amp; stayd there out of Place
						fill <name occupation="doctor">Doctor</name>
						<persName>John Holstead</persName> returned from the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, where he had been as <name occupation="surgeon">Surgeon</name> of a Ship I visited him
						&amp; told him, I should like to go to Sea. He said, he would recommend me to <roleName en="captain">Captain</roleName>
						<persName>Hornsby</persName>
						<add place="above">bound for <placeName>Greenland</placeName></add>; if he has any Place that would suit me (this <roleName en="captain">Captain</roleName> was a Person he
						himself had been with at <persName>Greenland</persName>, before he went to the <persName>West Indies</persName>). <note type="catchword">Accordingly</note>
					</p>
					<p> Acordingly on his Recommendation the <roleName en="captain">Captain</roleName> took me as his <name occupation="steward">Steward</name> I went on Board, but all Things were
						very awkward, having never been on Board of a Ship before &amp; I knew no more about my office than a Child, but I soon got to understand, that the chief mate was in that
						Office the Voyage before. So I made if my business to get acquaint- ed with him <add place="above">and he</add>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">with a bottle or 2 of Rum for he Loves Liquor</hi> then told me every thing, what I should do &amp; what belonged to my office. Thus I got into the Way
						pretty well. We sailed from the River <add place="above">the</add> latter end of March, &amp; we were not long out at Sea, before I was sick &amp; confined so for 15 Days. I
						thought many Times, if I was on Shore, they should be Sai- lors who would for me, But when I got better, I came thro&apos; pretty well, as I had no ship&apos;s duty to do. It
						was a very cold uncomfortable voyage for about 4 months we returned very unsuccessfull, having got no more than one fish; I got from the Ship as soon I could, weary enough of
						my first Voyage.</p>
					<p> A few weeks after by Accident I went to the <placeName>East India House</placeName> &amp; met with a <roleName en="captain">Captain</roleName> who was <hi rend="strikethrough"
							>a</hi> shipping people, I asked him if he  wanted people? He said, he did &amp; gave me an Order to go on Board. I immediately went on board &amp; met with a Company of
						very wicked, curs- ing &amp; swearing <name occupation="sailor" memoirSubject="no">sailors</name>. However we got ready &amp; put to Sea; About 2 months after our Ship&apos;s
						company was seized by turns with a <name health="disease" type="fever">violent Feaver</name>. I also fell sick &amp; it brought me very near my Dissolution. While we were so
						sick, we hung altogether by ourselves, It was one of the most shocking Times, I have had in all any Life, most of them died cursing &amp; swearing, they all at one Time died,
						that were sick &amp; left me alone. I prayed heartily to our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>, that if He would spare me &amp; bring me
						home again, I would be his &amp; live for him, But when I got better I soon forgot all his goodness &amp; went on a wicked Course with the Rest of the Sailors, &amp; I some
						times swore. But amidst all, I had many Convictions, &amp; I often could not sleep, but <name type="emotion">wept</name> in my Hammock on account of the Course I had entered
						into. When we came to a Port there was generally nothing seen but Wickedness. I remember very were some times, that I was <name type="emotion">grieved</name> in myself, has I
						could not be so bold in Wickedness, as the Rest of my company, &amp; when I thought, that I would be so wicked as they, I generally had such Convictions, that I could not do
						like them. We had a good Voyage but with Regard to Externals we had it hard some times, &amp; were about 6 Months without Bread living on Rice. On Account of the Length of the
						voyage we also </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-03.jpg" />
					<p> were obliged to take in old Stores in the <placeName>East Indies</placeName> which were very bad &amp; rusty thro &amp; thro. But after 2 years &amp; 3 months we arrived at
							<placeName>Spithead</placeName>; &amp; there made myself sick to spare myself from the ??? . When the people were all preots, I got on Shore and came by so force. I lived
						there with my Friends till the ship was paid off. &amp; then according to my Resolution of going to Sea no more, I began to look for a Place where I could earn my Bread &amp;
						by the Help of a Friend I got a good one in <placeName>Cheapside</placeName>, where I lived very agreeably 6 moths &amp; I found they had great confidence towards me.</p>
					<p> But the ship beginning to be fitted out again, <hi rend="strikethrough">where</hi>
						<add place="above">which</add> I had her with before, it made me very unsettled in my Mind &amp; I got a desire to go to Sea again. But I did not know, what Exuse to make, to
						get away from the Place, as had no fault to find with any thing I had Recourse to <placeName>Stratagem</placeName>. I ordered one of my companions, that he should come dressed
						like an officer of a Man of War, &amp; enquire for me, that it might appear, as if he had an Intention to press me. I ordered it so that he should come at an exact Hour, in
						order that I might be out of the Way. Accordingly he came. As soon as he was gone, then my Master called me &amp; told me, that he was afraid, the officer would re- turn again.
						I told him, I was under some Apprehension of being pressed. He desired that I would get ready, &amp; should go away &amp; not be pressed, if possible. When he settled with me
						about my Wages, he gave me 1/2 a guinea more than was due to me. So I came <add place="margin">by which means I came</add> away with many good Wishes. Yet I was condemned for
						acting so unuprightly, besides that I had left my Place &amp; did not know, whether I could get voyage of not to the East. Indies, I went to the <placeName>India
							House</placeName> &amp; spoke to <roleName en="captain">Captain</roleName>
						<persName>Wilson</persName>, with whom had been before, &amp; desired him to recommend me as <name occupation="midshipman">Mid-shipman</name> to <roleName en="captain"
							>Captain</roleName>
						<persName>Jackson</persName>, that was to succeed him. He was very friendly I promised that he would do it. &amp; he was as good as his Words. I then began to get ready
						suitable for that Station, as well as I could. And when I had got my Necessaries I had not much Money to spare, to trade with. A gentle Woman, that wanted some Things from the
							<placeName>East. Indies</placeName>, advanced me 6 Guineas in hand, which I laid out in such Merchandises, as I thought, would suit the best in
						<placeName>India</placeName>. He soon got ready I had a very prosperous voyage from <placeName ref="#mlpla000072">England</placeName> to <placeName>Madras</placeName> in 4
						Months, where I disposed of my Effects to good Advantage., I then bought such Commodities, which I thought would suit for <placeName>China</placeName> which likewise turned out
						to <note type="catchword">good</note>
					</p>
					<p> good Advantage &amp; what Money I had, I laid out in China-goods &amp; in would of brought them home, After18 months we arrived again at <placeName>Plymouth</placeName> where I
						escaped the bressing &amp; came by Land to <placeName ref="#mlpla000054">London</placeName> (when the ship has round to London Spaind, I found that I had 10 pounds to receive
						for Goods that a Person had disposed of in the Passage. I afterwards went on Board from Day to day &amp; some Times sold from Board &amp; brought on shore till got off all my
						effects. I found myself worth a considerable Sum of Money. That made me think of no other way of life, than Seafaring Life as I had such a good success <hi rend="strikethrough"
							>prtazpreeadee, etenne, an</hi>
						<hi rend="underlined strikethrough">aypraan to gave amndin and of</hi>
						<hi rend="strikethrough underline">urantiraf its Shad subled</hi> After I had settled all my Affairs with the Ship for that Voyage, I paid a Visit to <placeName
							ref="#mlpla000084">Yorkshire</placeName>, to see my Mother where I went on Sunday to <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>, &amp; was so laid hold of in the
						Preaching, that I had gladly staid, if I had known, how I should got my Living. In about 5 Weeks I returned to <placeName ref="#mlpla000054">London</placeName>, where I went to
						see about the Ship, &amp; found, it would be some Months, before she would be fitteded out again. I waited the Time, but then some Objections arose between the <roleName
							en="captain">Captain</roleName> &amp; me, &amp; I resolved positively, that I would go to Sea no more I acquainted my Friends with my Resolution &amp; advised with them,
						what I should take to? I had then spent all my Money. They agreed to advance me 30 pounds, that I could procure me a little Shop, for which I had to give then Bond &amp;
						Judgment. We soon met with a little Shop, in which I entered. Soon afterwards I was arrested by a person, that I owed 40 shillings to, &amp; went to the <placeName>Sponging
							House</placeName>, where I wrote a Letter to my Friend &amp; told him any Circumstances. He went directly &amp; put the Bond &amp; Judgment in Force, &amp; took all I had
						&amp; came to me next Morning &amp; paid the Money, for which I was arrested, &amp; set me at Liberty. I had now no home, but went some Times to one Friend&apos;s House, &amp;
						some times to another, where I had been formerly acquainted. But this I could not do very long, &amp; it came so far, that I suffered till to the Bareness of Life. One Day I
						met in the street one of the Family, that I had the Money from, he invited me to go to their House, &amp; they were hearty &amp; friendly with me, &amp; seemed to pity my
						Circumstances, I served in their Shop a few Weeks, &amp; then they hired me as a yearly <name occupation="servant">Servant</name>. I lived there very agreeably, &amp; some
						years ago, they did write to me to <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>, that I should come <add place="above">again</add> &amp; live with them. After some Time I
						called at a <placeName>Barber&apos;s Shop</placeName> to get shaved pretty late in the Evening; while I sat there, I thought I </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-04.jpg" />
					<p> was going to die. I got up &amp; said, I was very bad; but no Body gave me any Answer. I stood at the Door, till some Body, who was before me, was shaved; then I got in &amp;
						was shaved, I went home very heavy &amp; told our people, <name health="disease">I was not well</name>. They advised me to get some Supper, which might help me, I went to Bed
						&amp; in the Morning still found myself the same. I begun to re- flect on my present State, for I had not minded Religion for a long Time; I thought, it was a Punishment from
							<persName type="deity">God</persName> for my bad Course. Accordingly to make Amends, I thought, I would go once on Sunday to some Place of Worship; but the other Part of
						the Sunday I would walk about a take my Pleasure, asI had done before, I want on so for some Time, but it did not help me. Then I thought, I would go both the Forenoon &amp;
						Aftemoon to Worship, yet still I found no Ease. I begun to be so terrified, that I thought, I should be in <placeName type="biblical">Hell</placeName> every Moment. When had a
						Pen in my Hand to write a Bill of Parcel, I flung it away when I had done with it, &amp; thought, I should be in <placeName type="biblical">Hell</placeName>, before I should
						want it any more. When I went out, I often thought, I should drop down dead in the Street. It came so far, that my Appetite left me &amp; I could get no Sleep, I used to awake
						in Frights &amp; get up. I read some Times in the <name type="religion">Bible</name>, but I thought every Word seemed a Sentence against me; I thought, I had sinned against the
							<roleName type="honorific">holy Ghost</roleName>; therefore I had nothing to expect but <placeName type="biblical">Hell</placeName> &amp; Judgment. I was in that Distress
						in more than 2 Months. One Sunday I went to <placeName ref="#mlpla000004">Fetterlane Chappel</placeName>. When I heard some Courses of Lives similar to my own, it gave me great
						Hopes, when I heard how they were redeemed by the Blood &amp; Wounds of <persName type="deity">Jesus</persName>, I went Home full of Hope, that I should soon be released. Next
						Day in the Forenoon, when I was going thro a narrow Passage near <placeName>Spitalfields Church</placeName>, it came into my Mind, that there was Mercy in <persName
							type="deity">Jesus</persName> for every believing Soul. In that Moment I believed, &amp; the Love of <persName type="deity">God</persName> was <add place="above">shed</add>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">spread</hi> abroad in my Heart. I saw <persName type="deity">Jesus</persName> in his crucified form quite clear, who had redeemed me from all my Sins.
						I dont know, how I afterwards got home, Every Body was dear to me I I loved every one, I would gladly have imparted unto them of what I enjoyed. I went on in that Enjoyment for
						some Time &amp; thought, since I was come to the knowledge of our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r,</hi></roleName> that I should no more feel the
						Depravity of my own sinfull Nature, But I found my sinffull Nature still, &amp; was obliged to apply to our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript"
							>r</hi></roleName> for his Grace to preserve me, which he did from time to time <note type="catchword">I began</note>
					</p>
					<p> I began to have a longing desire, to become acquainted with the <orgName>B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></orgName>, as I believed, they were the only people, which I belonged
						to. Accordingly I began to go frequently on Sundays to <placeName ref="#mlpla000004">Fetterlane</placeName>. I went so long, till <roleName type="honorific">B<hi
								rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>
						<persName>Brodersen</persName> took Notice of me in the Preaching &amp; made it out with one of the S. <roleName type="honorific">B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></roleName>,
						that he should speak with me at the first Opportunity. Accordingly he bid me a good Day after the Preaching &amp; asked me, where I was agoing? I told him I was agoing towards
							<placeName>Bishopsgate Street</placeName>. He said he was agoing that Way too &amp; desired my Company. He said, he had observed, that I frequented their Preachings for
						some Time, &amp; inquired, if I knew any thing about the <orgName>B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></orgName> &amp; I told him, yes. I knew the <orgName>B<hi rend="superscript"
								>rn</hi></orgName> in <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName> &amp; I knew <roleName type="honorific">Br</roleName>
						<persName>Brodersen</persName> too, &amp; had spoken with him formerly. I told him, I had often fixed a Day, that I would go &amp; speak with him again. He asked, if I should
						rule to speak with him, &amp; if it would suit me that time, if I had an Opportunity for it? I answered: yes, I had no objection to it So we turned back both together &amp;
						went to Roll&apos;s Buildings. As soon  as we got into the House, we met <roleName type="honorific">B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>
						<persName>Brodersen</persName> in the Passage, &amp; he took me into his Room &amp; we had some pretty Conversation together. The Choir Liturgy was going to begin, &amp; he
						gave one Leave to be at it. I was so melted, that I wept all the Time, often spending some part of the Evening with the S. <orgName>B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></orgName>. I
						returned home very thank- full for the kind Reception, that I met with. From that Time, I went every Sunday to the S <orgName>Brn</orgName>, which was the chief Opportunity
						that I had. Some Time after I petitioned for <name event="reception">Reception</name> into the <orgName>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></orgName>, which Blessing was granted
						me <date when-iso="1766-01-13">January the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1766</date> I entered into a Covenant that time with our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi
								rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName> to be his for ever I spent my time for the most part in a very happy Track of Grace, considering my Situation, wherein I was, &amp;
						I had many near Visits of our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>, which made my Time very pleasant. Tho&apos; I felt naturally my depraved
						human Nature, but I applied to him &amp; got preserved. When <roleName type="honorific">B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>. <persName>Abraham</persName> returned from
						the <name event="religious">Provincial Synod</name> at <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>, he acquainted me that they had made it out in a Conference that if I
						did accept of it, I should go to <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName> &amp; be employed in the <placeName>Con<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> Shop</placeName> I told
						him I had no Choice in it , I would go anywhere. Accordingly, as soon as I could make things suitable, I left my place &amp; set out from <placeName ref="#mlpla000054"
							>London</placeName>
						<date when-iso="1764-02-17">Feb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1764</date> &amp; arrived at <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>
						the <date when-iso="1764-02-22">22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> of the same month</date> to <name type="emotion">my great Joy</name>.</p>
					<p>Thus far his own Words. By dictating his Course of life, he <add place="above">often</add> said, I thought there was some </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_42_DarnbrookJohn-05.jpg" />
					<p> Thing in the World, which I must experience, but I found, there was nothing but fantom, Now often have I thought of <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName> &amp;
						wished me to be there, when I was uneasy, which was very often.</p>
					<p>
						<!-- This is where the voice changes from John Darnbrook to the person writing the memoir --> His Course here was solid, he served faithfully in the Shop &amp; was legitimated
						among <orgName>B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></orgName> &amp; Strangers. His Connexion &amp; Converse with our dear <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript"
							>r</hi></roleName> was real, but in Stilness. He was admitted here to the <name event="sacrament">holy Sacrament</name>
						<date when-iso="1767-05-23">May the 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 1767</date>, which was a real Grace to Him. &amp; as often as he fed afterwards with the <orgName>Cong<hi
								rend="superscript">n</hi></orgName> on the Body &amp; Blood of <persName type="deity">Jesus</persName> in the <name event="sacrament">holy Sacrament</name>, he enjoyed
						it as a poor Sinner who thought himself very unworthy of this great Grace, but felt at the same time that he stood very much in Need of it, &amp; that he could not do without.
						And so, he always got new Strength &amp; Life out of the Wounds of <persName type="deity">Jesus</persName>. When he was spoken with previous to the <name event="sacrament">holy
							Sacrament</name> he was not of many Words, but one perceived clearly, that his Heart did live in the Sufterings of <persName type="deity">Jesus</persName>. All the Meetings
						he en- joyed both in the <orgName>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></orgName> &amp; his <orgName>Choir</orgName> proved a Blesting to him; the Doctrinal Day we had last
							Novemb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, was very blessed to him &amp; he afterwards told, that he enjoyed a particular Nearness of our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi
								rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName> at the <name event="religious">Cup of Covenant</name>. <date when-iso="1769">Last Year</date> he was made <hi rend="strikethrough"
							>and</hi> a Candidate for the <placeName>East Indies</placeName>, which he accepted of: for he was very willing to serve our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi
								rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>, wheresoever his Service should require it, tho&apos; on Account of his weakly Constitution he had but <name type="emotion">little
							Hopes</name> to be of any Use in the Service of our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName> among the Heathen. That time he came among the
						Intercessors, which was very weighty to him. But our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>, who was pleased with his Willingness to serve him,
						had other thoughts about him, <name health="disease">He grew weaker from time to time</name>, &amp; <date when-iso="1769-12">in the Beginning of Decemb<hi rend="superscript"
								>r</hi></date> he was obliged to move into the <placeName>Sick Room</placeName>. First we did not think, that he would go home of this Opportunity, but he soon thought
						so &amp; was quite set upon going home. Here he had a sabbatical time in the Nearness &amp; converse with our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript"
							>r</hi></roleName>
						<add place="above">tho; it was a Shool-Time for him too, inwhich he had to learnmany Lessons &amp; to speak thoroughly with our d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <roleName
								type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>. about many Things.</add> Once he said: tho&apos; our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript"
								>r</hi></roleName> has had so great a Mercy upon me, yet I feel myself often so indifferent towards Him, which is <name type="emotion">the greatest Pain</name>, I have
						in the <placeName>Sick Room</placeName>; at which he wept very much. But he soon was comforted again &amp; cheared by a gracious Look of our <roleName type="honorific"
							>Saviour</roleName>. He himself dictated his Course of Life to <roleName type="honorific">B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>
						<persName>Martens</persName>, &amp; when he had done therewith, <hi rend="strikethrough">to</hi> which was last Friday, he made Haste to meet his etemal Bridegroom. He had it
						very easy in his <name health="disease">Sickness</name>: the day before his going home he once complained, saying: Dear <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript"
								>r</hi></roleName>! it is too hard for me; but he soon got it easier. He was present to himself to the last Moment, when the Blessings of his <orgName>Choir</orgName>
						&amp; the <orgName>Congreg<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></orgName> was imparted unto him during a sweet <add place="above">feeling</add> of our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi
								rend="superscript">rs</hi></roleName> Nearess, &amp; soon after his Soul departed into the arms &amp; Bosom of <persName type="deity">Jesus</persName>, <date
							type="death" cause="disease" when-iso="1770-02-06">last Tuesday about 7 o&apos;Clock in the Morning, viz Feby the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1770</date> in the 34<hi
							rend="superscript">th</hi> year of his Age. Praise to thee, our God, be brought for this Sinner redeemed with thy Blood. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
