<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Anna Georgina Edwards: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards">Ann Georgiana Edwards</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-05.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-06.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-07.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-08.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-09.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-10.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-11.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-12.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Ann Georgiana Edwards</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-18" who="#JAKA1">Converted for semantic markup</change>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-10" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Ann Georgiana Edwards</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-01.jpg" />
					<p> When all thy mercies O my God My rising soul surverys, Transported with the view I&apos;m <add place="above">lost</add> In wonder, love, and praise. Looking back upon days
						which are gone, a long life which has passed away as a tale which is told. -- What cause do I find for deep humiliation and daring gratitude to my gracious God and Saviours who
						thro&apos; all the changes, and chances of this mortal life, has helped me to this hour, and given me a good hope through grace; I would fain leave a poor but grateful
						testimony </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-02.jpg" />
					<p> of his love, mercy, &amp; forbearing goodness to me, His poor erring child In London I first saw the light, 1783. One of four, two only survived My Father one of a numerous
						family was early cast upon the world to obtain his own bread married early My dear old Grandfather I well remember, he had at that time some situation in the India House having
						lost all his property humanly speaking through the carelessness of a female servant. Being then in good trade in Kent she instead of cutting off a </p>
					<cb />
					<p> candle she wanted, burns it off and not taking time to observe whether the wick of the separated part was extinguished, left it, it is supposed still burning. In the night a
						fire broke out, &amp; everything was consumed, nothing being ensured, all was lost As soon as they could came to London, through whom he obtained this situation I know not, but
						that he appeared to me a very dear old man My Father was at this time in the employ of the Right able Hon<hi rend="superscript">able</hi> I Sheridan a noted political
						character, who for his second wife married </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-03.jpg" />
					<p> a Lady related to the late Lady Elizabeth Whitbread Mother of my beloved M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Waldegrave Part of this lady&apos;s fortune was expended to purchase an
						estate in Surry to be settled upon herself and children While we were yet young my Father undertook to be land stewart on to be Bailiff of this estate -- we all removed to the
						country &amp; dwelt in a pretty cottage on the borders of a romantic common Even now the remembrance is sweet and I seem to sink at the fragrance of the beautious Moss roses in
						the little garden before the house. </p>
					<cb />
					<p> Yet there my precious time was wasted there my false views of life were nursed up Our dear parents were strictly moral we went to church and learned catechisms but of the
						depravity of human nature I had no knowledge of vital religion we might be said to be almost as <hi rend="underline">ignorant</hi> as the heathen. I had exalted ideas of what
						human nature might be and aimed with all my might to be what I called good I read with eagerness works of <hi rend="underline">fiction</hi> loved to dwell upon those characters
						who were represented as overcoming all difficulties by their own generosity of heart and nobleness of mind </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-04.jpg" />
					<p> I might spend much time in enumerating the trouble this caused me not finding man whose ideas presumed as mine and constantly failing to execute all I intended to do I sighed
						mourning turned back upon myself-indulging a morbid sensibility, finding no rest for the sole of my foot. My gracious God and Saviour in His love and mercy intend that I should
						yet become acquainted with His love and mercy manifested in the redemption of a lost world. About this time the lady of the mansion haveing a dear little boy now old enough to
						comment at least learn A,b,c took a </p>
					<cb />
					<p> fancy to me, requested to have me to care for this little boy, promising to care for me as her own. To the utmost of her power she performed this, but it would surprise many,
						to hear of the straits to which she was too often reduced, by the thoughtless extravagance of her husband having some qualities she admired, my selfrighteous delusions were
						strengthened After a few years upon the marriage of <del>our</del>
						<add place="above">my</add> dear departed sister to Mr Whitb<del>read</del><add place="above">urn</add> son of a substantial farmer of Ripley, a neighbouring village, I
						returned home. This match was thought so good that there was </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-05.jpg" />
					<p> much rejoicing but in a few years came a sad reverse my brother in law&apos;s affairs became embarrassed and alas! he concealed the embarrassment from my sister till the last
						moment, from mistaken feelings of shame and tenderness and thus put it out of her power to help to avert the impending ruin His friends helped him but a dealer in cattle he
						failed to a large amount in the end my sister and her two dear boys returned to the parental roof and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Whitburn went out to the Cape of Good Hope
						with letters of recomendation from the late lamented M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Whit </p>
					<cb />
					<p> bread the faithful friend of all whose cause he un dertook, and I again left home going to the sister in law of the lady whose little boy I had cared for. This lady travelled a
						great deal and had some time before offered to pay a person to stay with my mother if my Mother would spare me which <hi rend="underline">then</hi> she did not, but now we
						think it providential, we did. We saw a great deal of the countty but grieving over the troubles of my family I enjoyed much less than I might have done; and at the end of two
						years thought myself </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb n="6" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-06.jpg" />
					<p> highly favoured, when I heard that the eldest daughter of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; the Lady Elizabeth Whitbread was going to be married to the Hon<hi
							rend="superscript">be</hi> Cap<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> now Earl of Waldegrave and that the Lady Elizabeth wished to present me to her daughter the character of the
						lady I greatly admired, what I heard of the gentleman prepared me to honour him For the Lady Elizabeth and M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Whitbread I felt an idol sort of
						admiration they had tried to aid my brother in law and my father, I felt grateful </p>
					<cb />
					<p> and devoted myself enthusiastically to their daughter. In 1812 came into Bedfordshire, after my brother in law left England we heard of his safe arrival at the Cape-- of
						(letters) having obtained a situation but he had had two fits of sickness was then going some hundred miles up the country, promising to send remittances, but we heard unsure
						and the constant state of anxiety under mined the health of my beloved sister had some wholesome regulations being made at Somerset House so that no person </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb n="7" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-07.jpg" />
					<p> could any longer hold a situation in that office who did not fulfuill the duties of it in person obliged my father who had longheld one employing a deputy unless he gave it up
						to remove his family to London which was a great pleasure to me as we sometimes came to London but at Cardington I was treated with the great est kindness and confidence I went
						among the villagers searching for and relieving their wants doing all I could for them with the approbation of Cap &amp; my beloved M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Waldegrave
						whose Aunt the lady St. John </p>
					<cb />
					<p> being a member of the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> Church invited me and my friend M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Weir to go to the chapel at Bedford in the evening of
						Easter day 1813 we were pleased but no particular impresion was made upon either on the Easter Sunday following Lady St John invited me to the love feast I was pleased and in
						the meantime becoming more intimately acquainted with S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Thomas Smith late S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hannah Brown resident at Cardington &amp;
						whose family had joined the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> my Knowledge of the Brethren and attach ment to them increased often has she refreshed </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="8">
					<head type="page">8</head>
					<pb n="8" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-08.jpg" />
					<p> my soul by accounts she has brought of sermons &amp; meetings: and now my Father being much embarrassed by the derangement of the affairs of the characters before alluded to,
						it was but the prelude to a train of sorrow more keenly felt <hi rend="underline">because</hi> in <add place="above">thy</add> persons of those near and dear to me. In 1815 we
						lost our mother and I driven by the departure of from Cardington an enlightened curate, often accompanied the dear family of our worthy B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp;
							S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown to the Moravian Chapel finding comfort and one Sabbath </p>
					<cb />
					<p> morning B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Harke preached when he gave out the Hymn (in the old HB.) the true good Shepherd God&apos;s own son when he came to the 2nd verse For <hi
							rend="underline">thee</hi> He shed His precious blood <hi rend="underline">and how His own doth claim</hi> I was as it were transfixed to my seat what I felt I can not
						describe then surely the Lord gave me the first intimation of His will in this matter yet tho deeply impressed I heeded not this intimation as I ought to have done. Yet I was
						during this time fervently praying Lord thou hast blessed me by these people bless me with them I began to consider </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="9">
					<head type="page">9</head>
					<pb n="9" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-09.jpg" />
					<p> how strong the claims which my dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Waldegrave had upon me not only for her kindness to <hi rend="underline">me</hi> but from the nurturing
						consider ation with which she and her honoured parents had in every way endeavoured to aid us in the troubles of our family. I found too that to attend to the
						Cha<del>p</del>pel as I wished I could not fulfill my duties to her and then meeting with Newton&apos;s <hi rend="underline">four</hi>
						<hi rend="underline">letters</hi> an apology for the Church of England. gave up going to Chapel - satisfied myself with what I heard at Church certainly believing myself right
						as far as I then ??? in principle. </p>
					<cb />
					<p> My beloved mother departed in May. The lamented M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Whitbread in July the same year - woe upon woe for I took a near interest. My sister my Mary
						came to see me - attended business in Biggleswade - nothing seemed to prosper her mind ultimately gave way under accumulated trouble my own received a shock which only the Rock
						of Ages held from shattering me. her youngest boy obtained a presentation to Christ Hospital his elder brother went to sea under the guidance of Captain Waldegrave who after
						the death of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Whit bread during the minority of his son held the his seat in parliment. On his coming of age and taking his seat </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="10">
					<head type="page">10</head>
					<pb n="10" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-10.jpg" />
					<p> Cap<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Waldegrave took his family on the continent we went thro&apos; France into Italy we had scarcely been fifteen days in France when we lost their
						dear eldest daughter of dysentry which was then prevalent at St Quinten the eldest boy was nearly gone but Sir Charles Brown an english physician who proved to be a friend of
						the late Earl of Waldegrave <del>came to</del> was providentially led thro&apos; the town and met by Cap<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Waldegrave came to the inn prescribed for
						him and he was spared The dear little girl was tenderly attached to me. I think </p>
					<cb />
					<p> I could not have loved any one more. The moment she was dressed she left her home &amp; we generally passed our time together sad was the journey to me, after she left. My mind
						constantly drawn to Bedford, hoping to retreat to the S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> house there, but detained from mentioning my desire, by a sense of obligation to beloved
							M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Waldegrave, and the grief I knew it would cause her, if we parted. so there was the desire, pent up in my own bosom, and shaking. On our
						return in 1820, really in 1819 the house </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="11">
					<head type="page">11</head>
					<pb n="11" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-11.jpg" />
					<p> was found too small for the family and they removed first to stocks Hartfordshire and ultimately to a family seat in Somersetshire. I saw them through all this and after many
						trials and conflicts which I need not detail on the 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of October 1821 was received in the S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> House at Bedford with
						true sisterly kind ness by S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brogden S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Harke and the sisters dwelling in the house. </p>
					<cb />
					<p> I went a learner and am a learner still Many changes have I seen and passed through among the Brethren and have had much to learn and <del>an</del> in a way I little
						anticipated. Holding an office in our schools is particularly trying to those who join the church in mature years who have not being brought up among them But I bless the Lord
						for my call of grace and </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="12">
					<head type="page">12</head>
					<pb n="12" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_56Edwards-12.jpg" />
					<p> rejoice with humiliation to be numbered with his people and among the flock of his fold As individuals &amp; especially myself we do I fear come far short of what we ought to
						be. O may He graciously pour out His Holy Spirit upon us so that quickened to new life we may love Him more and serve Him better. Soon I may through <hi rend="underline"
							>abouding won</hi>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<hi rend="underline">drous mercy</hi> see His gracious face -- and would acknowledge the tender sympathy and kindness which during this season of weakness I have received from
						my beloved Brethren and Sisters in the Lord. May He bless keep and guide them into eternal life. </p>
					<p>
						<hi rend="underline">Saturday</hi>. February 14 1852 Ann. Georgeana Edwards. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
