<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Sarah Fletcher: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher">Sarah Fletcher</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-05.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-06.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-07.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-08.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-09.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-10.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-11.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-12.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-13.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-14.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-15.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Sarah Fletcher</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-08-28" who="#JAKA1">Created memoir file</change>
			<change when-iso="2019-10-22" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Sarah Fletcher</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-02.jpg" />
					<p> I was born <date type="birth" when-iso="1820-07-02">July 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1820</date> at <placeName>Mapperley</placeName>, a small village in
							<placeName>Derbyshire</placeName>. My dear Mother being a decided child of <name type="deity">God</name> endeavoured to bring her chldren up in the nurture and admonition
						of the <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName>; and I do not <hi rend="strikethrough">rember</hi> remember the time when my thoughts were not <add place="above">wont
							to</add> dwell upon serious things; but alas they were too much of a reasoning <add place="above">sceptical</add> nature. Very little took place during my childhood that is
							worth<hi rend="strikethrough">y of</hi> recording; I had the priviledge of attending a small School, that was kept by the daughters of a most worthy and excellent <name
							occupation="minister" memoirSubject="no">Independant Minister</name>, whose loving and affectionate manner will ever be sweet to my memory. I attended their School untill I
						was in my <date when-iso="1834">14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Year</date> when my dear Mother placed me in the <placeName>Srs House</placeName> at
							<placeName>Ockbrook</placeName>. where, after a few weeks I became exceedingly happy and comfortable the life of a <placeName>S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
							House</placeName>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">House</hi> being well adapted to my nature </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-03.jpg" />
					<p> cheerful, yet somewhat <add place="above">reserved</add>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">timid</hi> disposition. In the beginning of <date when-iso="1837">37</date> I received with several others of my companions, instruction for
						confirmation, or rather in my case for <name event="baptism">Adult baptism</name>, my dear Mother being a baptist I had consequently not received that <name event="sacrament"
							>sacrament</name> in infancy; but I cannot say that either the instructions or the rite itself made any lasting impressions upon my mind; I enjoyed the instructions, as I
						did, imbibing knowledge of any kind that came in my reach. Unaware almost to myself, I formed my own views on <hi rend="strikethrough">religous</hi> the way of Salvation, and
						as might be expected stumbled upon many errors, At one time instead of simply going to <placeName type="deity">Jesus</placeName>, I was seeking the <hi rend="underline"
							>fruits</hi> of the Spirit and at another I was fully impressed with the idea, that tho&apos; I was very very far from what I ought to be as a <name religion="Christian"
							>christian</name>, yet I must wait the <roleName type="honorific">Lord&apos;s</roleName> time to make me different, I could do nothing. At this </p>
					<pb />
					<p> time &quot;<title>Baxters Saints Rest</title>&quot; fell into my hands, which by the blessing of the <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> made a very deep impression on
						my mind and showed me that there was much for me to do, viz an earnestness of spirit, and a determination to give the <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> no rest till he
						was graciously pleased to reveal himself to me. From this time I was much more in earnest, but my adorable <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> was not my all in all;
						consequently the way seemed long and <add place="above">hear I</add> often felt inclined to exclaim &quot;who is sufficent for these things! In the year <date when-iso="1850"
							>50</date> I received a call to be the <name office="warden">Warden of the <orgName en="single sisters choir">Single Sisters</orgName></name> in <placeName
							ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>, and tho&apos; deeply conscious of my own insufficiency for such a post, I felt such a strong conviction that it was from the
							<roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> I dared do no other than accept it. In the first year I had many trials and difficulties caused in a great measure by my own
						inexperience, but afterwards my working very pleasant, and light to me. The Year after I came to Fulneck, the texts for </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-04.jpg" />
					<p> my birthday struck me very much on looking at them sometime before. The daily word was &quot;In the Lord shall all the seed of Israel be justified and <add place="above"
							>glory</add> shall 45<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Isaiah &amp; 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> verse, and the doctrinal text was, the second of Acts &amp; the latter
						part of the 47<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> verse &quot;And the Lord added to the church daily such as should be saved.&quot; I felt to hope that these texts had a reference
						to some that were very near &amp; dear to me, who were not added to any christian church, and over whom my heart had often yearned. I never once thought of them in connection
						with myself, I thought I was added to the church, and of the <hi rend="underline">real meaning</hi> of the daily word I had at that time very little knowledge, oh how possible
						it is to deceive ourselves and others. On the morning of my birthday, I found three verses on my table which had been drawn and placed there by a very dear and worthy sister,
						as was her custom, the three were very striking, but the text of one was <hi rend="strikethrough">love</hi> &quot;Lovest thou me&quot; </p>
					<pb />
					<p> to <add place="above">which</add> was added the verse </p>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>Lovest thou me I hear the Saviour say,</l>
							<l>Would that my heart had power to </l>
							<l>answer yea: </l>
							<l>Thou knowest all things, Lord in heaven above</l>
							<l>And earth beneath, thou knowest that I love</l>
							<l>But &apos;tis not so in word, in deed, in thought</l>
							<l>I do not cannot love thee as I ought,</l>
							<l><hi rend="underline">Thy love</hi> must give that power, thy love alone </l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p> On reading the last line <add place="above">with clasped hands</add> I exclaimed, oh my beloved Saviour that is the very thing why <add place="above">didst</add> thou not show
						me that before. it is indeed <hi rend="underline">thy love</hi> that must give <hi rend="underline">me</hi> power to love thee in return, there is indeed &quot;nothing worthy
						of thee but thine own Oh do thou grant that &quot;with the love wherewith thou lovest me </p>
					<p> Reflected on thyself I <hi rend="strikethrough">would</hi>
						<add place="above">may</add> love thee My dear Saviour had that instant drawn me to himself but when he put his holy spirit into my heart, oh the sink of iniquity I saw there
						&quot;sin did indeed revive and I died&quot; Rom 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ch 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> verse. So heavy was the </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-05.jpg" />
					<p> weight of guilt upon me, that I often felt I must sink under it, or that I should lose my senses; I stood a guilty hell deserving sinner, and felt that I must be lost, if my
						Saviour had not died for me; but I could take no comfort, the promises were as tho&apos; I had never heard them, except occasionally a text such as <note>Line is crossed out in
							pencil, what is written above is illegible</note>&quot;I will not always strive with <note>Line is crossed out in pencil, what is written above is illegible</note>man least
						the Spirit which I have made should fail before me&quot; was as a little gleam of sunshine, and then the cloud passed over again. I remained in this state of mind some Weeks,
						till one sunday evening the text was from some part of John&apos;s first Epistle, but what chapter or verse I have no recollection from the distressed state of my mind. During
						the sermon I earnestly besought the Lord to reveal himself to me, And he did, the peace and joy that I felt that night, none but a pardoned sinner can have any conception of I
						had not a shadow of a doubt of my acceptance in the Beloved. And tho&apos; God has not at all times </p>
					<pb />
					<p> been in my thoughts, yet my beloved Saviour has never suffered my feet to slide O thou who hast begun a good work in me, do thou perfect it unto the end. Oh do thou empty me of
						myself, and fill me with thyself be thou my all in all 185<hi rend="strikethrough">7</hi>
						<add place="inline">5</add> I again devote myself body soul &amp; spirit unto thee dear Saviour, but oh do thou keep me, thou know&apos;st how weak and frail I am, how prone to
						stray from thee, and how contrary I continually act to thy mind. </p>
					<p>
						<note>The remainder of this version of the memoir is written in a different hand.</note> Thus far her own In addition to what our late Sister has stated her fellow laborer adds
						the following on behalf of herself &amp; the choir, &amp; can truly say, that both she and every inmate of the house, feel that they have lost in our late Sister, a sincere and
						valued friend &amp; conscientious Christian. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-06.jpg" />
					<p> Upright in principle &amp; faithful in business, she did all she had to do, with a single eye to the interest of the concern she was entrusted with, &amp; never for an hour,
						would sacrifice duty to pleasure.</p>
					<p> To be unexpectedly called upon to part with a friend so faithful &amp; untiring in her exertions for the good of the whole household, does indeed fill all our hearts with
						sorrow, We deeply mourn our loss, but we cannot but say, that our loss is her eternal gain. She knew in whom she believed, &amp; when the summons came for her to lay by her
						earthly duties, she was enabled to say: &quot;Thy will be done!&quot; And we doubt not would hear the welcome: &quot;Well done good &amp; faithful servant, enter thou into the
						joy of thy Lord!&quot;</p>
					<p> As a fellow laborer &amp; member of our Elders&apos; Conference, our dear S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fletcher was much esteemed by us all, for the candour of her mind,
						&amp; her </p>
					<pb />
					<p> strictly conscientious discharge of her official duties. She would ever openly &amp; clearly state her views on any subject she was interested in, &amp; in case of a difference
						of opinion firmly &amp; faithfully maintain her cause, without however in the least being self opinionated or obstinate.</p>
					<p> Her warm interest in the Lords work &amp; the spread of His kingdom, both at home &amp; abroad, she quietly, yet continuously manifested, not only unto the Searcher of hearts,
						who delights to hear the prayers of his people, when they plead with him for the furtherance of his gospel, but also unto man, by the lively &amp; intelligent interest she
						always displayed in conversations on the subject of missionary labours, &amp; by her untiring &amp; successful endeavours, to collect subscriptions for such objects, as the
						Foreign &amp; Home Missions, the Bible Society &amp; so forth. The local committees of these associations, will miss in her a valued member, &amp; a successful collector. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb n="6" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-07.jpg" />
					<p> We were often struck with her correct memory of men &amp; things, relating to Missionary enterprises, especially those connected with our own Church, of which she was a very
						consistent &amp; attached member. </p>
					<p> She also took her place as a teacher in our Sunday school, &amp; by her prayerful &amp; careful preparation for her work, succeeded in securing the love &amp; gratitude of her
						scholars, to whose hearts her memory is much endeared by her valued instructions in spiritual things. </p>
					<p> She now rests from her labours, &amp; her works do follow her. Whatever she did, she did unto the Lord, &amp; this imparted real worth to her activity. Her memory is dear to
						us. </p>
					<p> When the Minister of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> saw her on the evening of the so called &quot;Sisters&apos; coming in day,&quot; she was remarkably calm &amp;
						cheerful in her mind, &amp; resigned to the Lord, who had laid her on a bed of sickness, </p>
					<pb />
					<p> while the other inmates of the house, were holding their festive meetings in the adjoining prayer hall. For the visit paid to her &amp; the prayer offered up by her bed side,
						she expressed her thanks in a very cordial &amp; lively manner. Little did the Minister think, that on his return from Crook, whither duty called him away for several days, he
						should no longer be permitted to see her among the living.</p>
					<p> To a fellow laborer who visited her late on Sunday evening, &amp; who engaged in spiritual conversation &amp; prayer with the dear patient, she remarked on his enquiry, if she
						felt her Saviour near, that He was her only real comfort &amp; true support: &quot;for what should I do <hi rend="underline">without him</hi> now?&quot; And truly He was with
						her in her last hour. Her own memoir tells us, that she knew in whom she believed. Trusting in his merits, &amp; saved by his bloods hedding &amp; death, she gently fell asleep
						in Jesus to be for ever with the Lord </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb n="7" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-08.jpg" />
					<note>This begins a second version of Sarah Ann Fletcher's memoir</note>
					<p> Memoir of S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sarah Ann Fletcher who departed at Fulneck on the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 1869</p>
					<p> I was born July 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1820 at Mapperly, a small village in Derbyshire. </p>
					<p> My dear mother being a decided child of God endeavoured to bring her children up in the nurture &amp; admonition of the Lord; &amp; I do not remember the time when my thoughts
						were not wont to dwell upon serious things; but, alas! they were too much of a reasoning, sceptical nature. Very little took place during my childhood that is worth recording.
						I had the privilege of attending a small school, that was kept by the daughters of a most worthy &amp; excellent Independent Minister, whose loving &amp; affectionate manner,
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="8">
					<head type="page">8</head>
					<pb n="8" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-09.jpg" />
					<p> will ever be sweet to my memory. I attended their school until I was in my 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year, when my dear Mother placed me in the S<hi rend="superscript"
							>rs</hi> house at Ockbrook, - where, after a few weeks, I became exceedingly happy and comfortable, the life of a S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> house being well adapted
						to my naturally cheerful, yet somewhat reserved disposition. </p>
					<p> In the beginning of 1837 I received, with several others of my companions, instruction for confirmation, or rather in my case for adult baptism. My dear Mother being a Baptist
						I had consequently not received that sacrament in infancy. </p>
					<p> But I cannot say that either the instructions, or the rite itself, made any lasting impression on my mind. I enjoyed the instructions, as I did imbibing knowledge of any kind
						that came in my reach. </p>
					<p> Unawares almost to my self, I formed my own views on the way of salvation, &amp; as might be expected stumbled upon many errors. At one time I was seeking <hi rend="underline"
							>fruits</hi> of the Spirit, instead of </p>
					<pb />
					<p> simply going to Jesus, &amp; At another time I was fully impressed with the idea, that though I was very very far from what I ought to be as a Christian, yet I must wait the
						Lord&apos;s time to make me different, I could do nothing. At this time &quot;Baxter&apos;s saints&apos; rest&quot; fell into my hands, which by the blessing of the Lord made a
						very deep impression on my mind, &amp; showed me that there was much for me to do, viz. an earnestness of Spirit, &amp; a determination to give the Lord no rest, till he was
						gra ciously pleased to reveal himself to me. From this time I <hi rend="underline">was</hi> much more in earnest, but my adorable Saviour was not my all in all; consequently
						the way seemed long &amp; heavy &amp; I often felt inclined to exclaim: &quot;Who is sufficent for these things!&quot; </p>
					<p> In the year 1850 I received a call to be the Warden of the S<hi rend="superscript">le</hi> S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> in Fulneck, &amp; though deeply conscious of my own
						insufficiency for such a post, I felt </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="9">
					<head type="page">9</head>
					<pb n="9" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-10.jpg" />
					<p> such a strong conviction that it was from the Lord, that I dared do no other than accept it. </p>
					<p> In the first year I had many trials and difficulties, caused in a great measure by my own inexperience, but afterwards my work was very pleasant &amp; light to me. </p>
					<p> The 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> year after I came to Fulneck, the texts for my birthday struck me very much, on looking at them some time before. The daily word was:
						&quot;In the Lord shall all the seed of Israel be justified &amp; shall glory. Is. 45.25 &amp; the doctrinal text was, the second of Acts &amp; the latter part of the 47<hi
							rend="superscript">th</hi> verse: &quot;And the Lord added to the Church daily such as should be saved.&quot; I felt to hope, that these texts had a reference to some, that
						were very near &amp; dear to me, who were not added to any <hi rend="strikethrough">Church</hi> Christian Church, &amp; over whom my heart had often yearned. I never thought of
						them in connexion with myself, I thought I was added to the Church, &amp; of the <hi rend="underline">real meaning</hi> of the daily word I had at that time very little
						knowledge. O! how possible it is it is to deceive ourselves &amp; others!. On the morning of my birthday </p>
					<pb />
					<p> I found three verses on my table which had been drawn &amp; placed there by a very dear &amp; worthy sister, as was her custom, the three were very striking. The text of one
						was "Lovest thou me?" To which was added the verse </p>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>"Lovest thou me? I hear my Saviour say,</l>
							<l>"Would that my heart had power</l>
							<l>"to answer, yea, </l>
							<l>"Thou knowest all things, Lord in</l>
							<l>heaven above </l>
							<l>"And earth beneath, thou knowest</l>
							<l>that I love! </l>
							<l>"But &apos;tis not so, - in word, in deed,</l>
							<l>in thought </l>
							<l>"I do not, cannot love thee as I ought;</l>
							<l>"<hi rend="underline">Thy love</hi> must give that power; thy love alone!</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p> On reading the last line I exclaimed with clasped hands, Oh my beloved Saviour, that is the very thing Why didst thou not show me that before. It is indeed <hi rend="underline"
							>thy love</hi> that must give <hi rend="underline">me</hi> power to love thee in return, there is indeed, &quot;nothing worthy of thee but thine own&quot; O do thou grant
						that &quot;with the love wherewith thou lovest me, reflected on thyself I may love thee!&quot; My dear Saviour, had that instant </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="10">
					<head type="page">10</head>
					<pb n="10" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-11.jpg" />
					<p> drawn me to himself but when he put his Holy Spirit into my heart Oh the sink of iniquity I saw there Sin did indeed revive &amp; I died Rom. 7:9. So heavy was the weight of
						guilt upon me, that I often felt I must sink under it, or that I should lose my senses. I stood a guilty hell deserving sinner, &amp; felt that I must be lost if my Saviour had
						not died for me, but I could take no comfort; the promises were as though I had never heard them; except occasionally a text such as &quot;For I will not contend for ever,
						neither will I be always wroth: for the spirit should fail before me &amp; the souls which I have made&quot; Is 57.16 was a little gleam of sunshine, &amp; then the cloud
						passed over again. I remained in this state of mind some weeks, till one Sunday evening, the text was from some part of John&apos;s first Epistle, but what chapter or verse I
						have no recollection from the distressed state of my mind. During the sermon I earnestly besought the Lord to reveal himself to me, &amp; He did. The peace &amp; joy that I
						felt that night, none but a pardoned sinner can have any conception of I had not a shadow of a doubt </p>
					<pb />
					<note>This is page one of a two page insertion into the text of the memoir</note>
					<p> In addition to what our late Sister has stated her <hi rend="strikethrough">Choir</hi>
						<add place="above">fellow</add> labourer adds the following on behalf of herself and the Choir can truly state that both she and every inmate of the house, feel that they have
						lost in our late Sister, a sincere and valued friend, such a Conscientious Christian Upright in principle, &amp; faithful in business, She did all she had to do with a single
						eye to the interest of the concern she was intrusted with, and never for an hour </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="11">
					<head type="page">11</head>
					<pb n="11" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-12.jpg" />
					<note>This is page two of a two page insertion into the text of the memoir</note>
					<p> would sacrifice duty to pleasure. Every inmate of the house must and did feel that when it unexpectedly called to part with her, she had lost a true and valued friend. But
						while we <add place="above">deeply</add> mourn her loss we cannot but say our loss is her Eternal gain She knew in whom she believed, and when the summons came for her to lay
						by her earthly duties she was enabled to say Thy will be done and we doubt not would hear the welcome Message <add place="margin" n="right_horizontal">Well done</add>
					</p>
					<pb />
					<p> of my acceptance in the Beloved. And though God has not at all times been in my thoughts, yet my beloved Saviour has never suffered my feet to slide. </p>
					<p> O thou who has begun a good work in me do thou perfect it unto the end. O do thou empty me of myself, &amp; fill me with thyself be thou my all in all. </p>
					<p> 1857 I again devote myself, body soul &amp; spirit unto thee dear Saviour, but Oh do thou keep me, thou knowest how weak &amp; frail I am, how prone to stray from thee &amp;
						how contrary I continually act to thy mind </p>
					<p> Thus far her own In addition to what our late Sister has stated, her fellow laborer adds the following, on behalf of herself &amp; the Choir, &amp; can truly say that both she
						&amp; every inmate of the house, feel that they have lost </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="12">
					<head type="page">12</head>
					<pb n="12" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-13.jpg" />
					<p> in our late Sister, a sincere &amp; valued friend &amp; conscientious Christian. </p>
					<p> Upright in principle &amp; faithful in business, she did all she had to do with a single eye to the interest of the concern she was entrusted with, &amp; never for an hour
						would sacrifice duty to pleasure. </p>
					<p> To be unexpectedly called upon to part with a friend so faithful &amp; entering in her exertions for the good of the whole household does indeed fill all our hearts with
						sorrow, we deeply <hi rend="strikethrough">fe</hi> mourn her loss but we cannot but say that our loss is her eternal gain. She knew in whom she believed &amp; when the summons
						came for her to lay by her earthly duties, she was enabled to say: &quot;Thy will be done!" </p>
					<pb />
					<p> And we doubt not would hear the welcome Well done good &amp; faithful servant enter thou into the joy of thy Lord </p>
					<p> As a fellow labourer and member of our Elders&apos; Conference our dear Sr. Fletcher was much esteemed by us all for the candour of her mind, and her strictly conscien tious
						discharge of her official duties. She would ever openly &amp; clearly state her views on any subject she was interested in, and in case of a difference of opinion firmly and
						faithfully maintain her cause, without, however, in the least being self opinionated or obstinate. Her warm interest in the Lord&apos;s work and the spread of his kingdom, both
						at home and abroad, she quietly, yet continuously manifested, not only unto the Searcher of hearts, who delights to hear the prayers of his people, </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="13">
					<head type="page">13</head>
					<pb n="13" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-14.jpg" />
					<p> when they plead with him for the furtherance of his gospel, but also unto man, by the lively &amp; intelligent interest she always displayed in con versations on the subject of
						Missionary labours, and by her untiring and successful endeavours to collect sub scriptions for such objects, as the Foreign and Home Missions, the Bible Society, and so forth.
						The local Committees of these Associations will miss in her a valued member, and a successful Collector. We were often struck with her correct memory of men and things relating
						to Missionary enterprises, especially those connected with our own church, of which she was a very consistent &amp; attached member. </p>
					<p> She also took her place as a Teacher in our Sunday School, and by her prayerful and careful prepa ration for her work succeeded in securing the love and gratitude of her
						Scholars, to whose hearts her memory is much endeared by her valued instructions in spiritual things. She </p>
					<pb />
					<p> now rests from her labours, and her works do follow her. Whatever she did, she did unto the Lord, and this imparted real worth to her activity. Her memory is dear to us. </p>
					<p> When the Minister of the Congreg<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. saw her on the evening of the so called Sisters&apos; Coming in Day, she was re markably calm and cheerful in her
						mind, and resigned to the Lord, who had laid her on a bed of sickness, while the other inmates of the house, were holding their festive meetings in the adjoining Prayer hall.
						For the visit paid to her, and the prayer offered <add place="above">up</add> by her bedside she expressed her thanks in a very cordial and lively manner. Little did the
						Minister think, that on his return from Crook, whither duty called him away for several days, he should no longer be permitted to see her among the living. To a fellow laborer,
						who visited her late on Sunday Evening, and who engaged in spiritual conversa tion and prayer with the dear patient, </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="14">
					<head type="page">14</head>
					<pb n="14" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_53Fletcher-15.jpg" />
					<p> she remarked on his enquiry, if she felt her Saviour near, that He was her only real comfort and true support; for what should I do <hi rend="underline">without Him</hi> now?
						And truly He was with her in her last hour; her own Memoir tells us, that she knew, in whom she believed. Trusting in his merits, and saved by his bloodshedding and death, she
						gently fell asleep in Jesus to be for ever with the Lord. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
