<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Thomas Grinfield: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>Fulneck Archive, UK</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas">Thomas Grinfield</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-05.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-06.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-07.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-08.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-09.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-14" who="#JAKA1">Semantic encoding</change>
			<change when="2019-09-04" who="#JAKA1">Created memoir file</change>
			<change when="2019-06-10" who="#JAKA1">Updated header</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Thomas Grinfield</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						<hi rend="underline">Memoir of the late Rev. Thos. Grinfield</hi> The very thought of writing any thing like a memoir of myself the poorest among the Lords poor ones has
						produced a thrilling senssation, so that after its composition, I have more than once consigned it to the fire. But as my high Calling of God in Christ Jesus, &amp; the events
						previous to my fellowship with the Bre threns Church and strikingly marked with the divine finger, I durst not refuse to record to the Glory of God a brief narration of the
						special circumstances that principally bear on these two points. </p>
					<p> It pleased God that I should draw my first breath in the house of my parents at Salisbury Apr 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. 1748. Much as I wish to honour the memory of my
						dear father &amp; mother, yet from the most credible information they canot be considered in any other view than as refined deists. Moral as was their character before men;
						they were immical to divine Revelation &amp; its doctrines; &amp; as a consequence at times showed their aversion to all in every demonination who professed the simple doctrine
						of </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-03.jpg" />
					<p> of the Gospel. The question may now be asked, how could the children of parents thus disposed expect to be brought up in the fear &amp; nurture of the Lord? Much as they might
						wish to instil morality on their sinful minds, their general education would have been according to the Philosophical axioms so prevalent at that period. I was the youngest of
						three brothers; the eldest went early to Winchester school, being designed for the Bar. The second to Westminister for the army. From seven years old, I was a day scholar at
						the Cathedral Grammar school, &amp; had my father lived till I had reached twelve years was to go to Winchester College. </p>
					<p> I must now revert to the awful events which under Providence led to the opening of the Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> gracious purposes with me. In 1759 it pleased God to
						remove both my honoured parents within 9 weeks of each other, my mother of a consumption in July; my father in Octr of a gouty spasm on the heart while conversing with me after
						dinner on my going to Winchester next Easter <note type="catchword">Such</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-04.jpg" />
					<p> such awful bereavements are frequently Mendid with incalcuable loss to minors, but my all merciful God, caused them in the signal to work for my educational gain. For <hi
							rend="underline">He who knows the end from the beginning</hi> saw me (a poor orphan) <hi rend="underline">lying on my blood</hi>, (spiritual death) without any to pity my
						forlorn case. Thank God, I am now in my 76<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year, &amp; enabled to believe that my time of love was come. This thoughts of peace concerning me were
						gradually to be fulfilled, that my lost &amp; dead soul should live by faith to Him on her earth &amp; when his good work in me should be finished, live with Christ in his
						glorious kingdom. O most unworthy am I of these ever blessed prospects. Since the call of an immortal soul from death to life &amp; from darkness to light in the most important
						by all events, no incident combined with its spiritual progress, trivial as it may appear to carnal wisdom will be deemed so by by him, who has ears to hear &amp; eyes to see,
						with a heart to understand the mysteries of the kingdom of God. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-05.jpg" />
					<p> In my father&apos;s will to guardians were appointed, his only brother &amp; one of my mother&apos;s Brothers. The first immediately entered on the change. The whole landed
						property was left to our eldest brother with small fortunes to the younger children. My uncle aware that mine was by no means sufficient to pursue my honoured father&apos;s
						intention for the Church determined to take me to one of the most respectabile schools at Bristol. His friends in this city mentioned the late Rev. W. Foote, who taught latin
						&amp; greek before in the mornings. After dinner Writing, Arithmetic, &amp; the rudiments of Geometry were taught by the Usher. Here I was entered about Michaelmas following. </p>
					<p> The leading reason of my being settled here instead of London, was that my excellent &amp; truly pious Aunt Anne, resded in Bristol &amp; was on the point of joining the
						Moravians. In this event the divine finger is most evident. In Eternity I shall have abundant cause to thank &amp; praise my faithful Shepherd for having brought me his poor
						straying <note type="catchword">lamb</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-06.jpg" />
					<p> lampb under the fostering care of this worthy Lady. </p>
					<p> The Sunday&apos;s and half yearly vacations were generally spent under her roof. My Aunt occasionally touched in a very delicate manner &amp; suited to my capacity on divine
						vine subjects, particularly of the histories of Joseph &amp; Samuel. My ears were then quick to hear the words, new as they seemed, yet the dulness &amp; hardness of my heart
						prevented me from comprehending their spiritual import. </p>
					<p> After many months she pressed me to accompany her to the Chapel. Unpleasant reports of the Moravians had been instilled into my ears by the elder boys of the school. These
						added to the natural enmity of my heart to serious subjects urged me to refuse to go anywhere except to the parish church. Near two years had elapsed before my Aunt, having
						some ladies belonging to the Brn, in her house, requested me to attend her now &amp; then to Maudlin lane. The gratitude felt by me for her constant kind attention pre- </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb n="6" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-07.jpg" />
					<p> vailed over all antipathies. The sermon was preached by the late Revd Mr Nyberg. The evangelical style was so new to my ears, &amp; the place &amp; people so contrary to Church
						regulations, that I scarcely understood the drift of the sermon, nor was I pleased with the mode of worship. My Guardian seriously thought of my learning the Italian method of
						Book keeping to prepare me for a merchants Comfiting house. In 1762 he placed me with an excellent Master who was to devote 2 or 3 hours a day in hearing me read the Classics
						in which I had made good proficiency. This Gentleman&apos;s academy was near the chapel I began to attend very frequently with the children of the principal members. In a few
						months I had leave the attend the Society meetings on Mondays &amp; Fridays, on the latter courses of lives were generallyread, concluding with the beautiful old hymn O head so
						full a bruises &amp;c sung from the Organ gallery. One evening the narrative of boy older than me was read. Previous to his blessed end, he had been deeply exercised with the
						fear of death <note type="catchword">chiefly</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb n="7" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-08.jpg" />
					<p> ly caused of the inattention to the warnings of the Holy Spirit &amp; from a desire to rise in the world, deferring the salvation of his soul to a future period, ignorant how
						suddenly the thread of mortal life may be snapped by God in whose hand are the timer. His tears &amp; heartrendings accompanied with the deep sense of being fovever lost,
						caused him to be humbled before God &amp; in real earnest to call upon the Saviour for the remission of all his sins &amp; follies in his all cleansing &amp; purifying blood. A
						short time before his departure, the good &amp; faithful Shepherd graciously assured him of an interest in the great mediatorial sacrifice. By this manifestation his spirit
						became comforted &amp; resigned his redeemed soul into the hands of his Creator &amp; Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. The deep impression made by the Spirit of truth on may
						poor cold heart beggars all description. It was as though an arrow from the Lord had entered into my loins wounding me to the quick. The meeting was no sooner ended than I
						hastened to my chamber </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="8">
					<head type="page">8</head>
					<pb n="8" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_01_GrinfieldThomas-09.jpg" />
					<p> &amp; fastening the door kneeled down by the bedside, with incessant tears, I stammered forth my finest prayer from the heart, beseeching the compassionate Sav<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi> to show mercy to me a poor orphan wandering in the wilderness, that when my time should come, I might be prepared to go in peace to my eternal
						home. O! was my petition that I might live the life &amp; die the death of the righteous. </p>
					<p> Have I not just cause for considering this important event as my first conviction of sin &amp; insight into the precious doctrine of the atonement. But like the blind man in
						consequence of the spittles first touch, <hi rend="underline">I saw men</hi>
						<hi rend="underline">like trees walking</hi>. These glimmerings of spiritiual light led me gradually to the Savr the fountain of every blessing &amp; to be move cordially
						attached to the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>. It would not have been an hour to have sacrificed every earthly advantage rather than deny the Lord who first showed his
						impression, or quit the fellowship of these dear people, then much despised. I am </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
