<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Sarah Gurney: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney">Sarah Gurney</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-05.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-06.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-02.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Sarah Gurney</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-18" who="#JAKA1">Converted for semantic markup</change>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-10" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Sarah Gurney</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-03.jpg" />
					<p> Sarah Gurney. I was Born in Mimms Middlesex, Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1745. My Parents <del>was</del>
						<add place="above">were</add> of the Church of England wherein I was Baptiz&apos;d &amp; brought up. In my Childhood I was convinced of sin &amp; felt I was not right &amp;
						alreadly then believed that I must attain to something at yet unpossess&apos;d, or I could not be saved. My natural dissposition was flighty so that what tender impressions I
						had in my heart, <del>was</del>
						<add place="above">were</add> of short duration. When I was 13 years old a Discenting Gentlewoman took me into her family, where I was instructed in <del>those</del>
						<add place="above">the</add> principles <add place="above">of that denomination</add>; I read their Bookes &amp; particularly Backesters Call to the unconverted, which
						frighten&apos;d me exceedingly, for I felt I fell short of all righteousness, &amp; therefore endeavour&apos;d to reform my life by more strict observance of my duty,
						especially by reading, praying &amp; frequenting the meetings, which I prefer&apos;d before those of the E. Church, because I thought these people were more sincere. In 1730 my
						Father being sick I visited him &amp; was greatly concerned for his Salvation, &amp; therefore kneel&apos;d down by his bed, read &amp; pray&apos;d by him, putting the Bible
						into his Hands, when he open&apos;d to that portion of Scripture, Remember thy Creator in the days of thy youth, that when thou art old he may not be hid from thine Eyes. This
						so Affected me that I immediately rose up, giving up all the concern I had for my dear Fathers happiness, trusting to this Lord for his Salvation, taking those words as a
						demand from God upon me; nevertheless the loss of so affectionate a Parent affected me so, that I wish&apos;d to be buried with him, believing I shou&apos;d never care for life
						any more. In 1733 my Lady also departed &amp; I return&apos;d to London, where I waited on 2 young Ladies, who with their Mother Lady Askew <del>was</del>
						<add place="above">were</add> of the E. Church but lived in all the gayeties of this world. Here I forgot my former resolutions, I went into all manner of those so called
						innocent diversions viz Cards, Dancing, plays &amp; yet not without strong convictions which at times caused me very heavy reflections. In this family I was in the way of many
						&amp; great temptations, so that at length I was obliged to leave my place, &amp; got another in Putney, where all my convictions return&apos;d, &amp; a deep sense of my
						miserable condition caused a melancholy to overwhelm me, which notwithstanding the advise &amp; admonitions of Ministers &amp; who endeavor&apos;d to persuade me that I enough
						yet I was convinced of the contrary &amp; wanted to find out a of God, for I firmly believed there were such in the world &amp; that they <note type="catchword">could</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-04.jpg" />
					<p> could help me. The housekeeper in the family being a relation of the late B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williams, <del>she</del> invited him one day to Tea, which gave me an
						oppertunity (when she went out) to ask him what religion he was of? He told me the Church of England; I being concern&apos;d &amp; he appearing the same to me, I took the
						freedom to ask him of he always went to the Church, he ans&apos;<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not always; I desir&apos;d to know where then; he told me there was a religious
						Society in Fetter Lane. I ask&apos;d him if I might have leave to come? he said yes, as also told me the time of they meetings &amp; promis&apos;d (it being winter) to come for
						me, which he faithfully did the next Sunday at 5 in the morning. Here I heard B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown preach from the Text. He was wounded for our transgressions,
						he was bruised for our iniquities: the chastisement of our peace was upon him, &amp; with his stripes we are healed. We had not set long before the people from without peltered
						us with stores &amp; bricks breaking the windows &amp; doing much mischief, so that I was very much frightened &amp; not able to attend to the Sermon. The late S<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi> Loyd by whom I sat bad me be compos&apos;d, for she had that confidence in the Lord that he would not suffer us to be hurt, &amp; when the
						preaching was over ask&apos;d me how I had lik&apos;d it? I ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> I could not tell, for altho&apos; I was very desirous to to sav&apos;d, yet I
						believed I shou&apos;d never come any more there, for I was terribly frighten&apos;d, &amp; thought that thereby I risk&apos;d my life, consequently I went no more for 3 years,
						during which time I was wishing much to get into a Nunery, &amp; did all in my power to attain to the same, but as I was informed that I must go to France, for which I had not
						ability otherwise then as a servant, which I did not chuse, as I was informed they would use me as their slave, <add place="above">I dropt that scheme</add>; At this time there
						was to be a confirmation in the Church, when I consequently with many other young women was confirm&apos;d by the Bishop, &amp; the Sunday following partook of the Lord&apos;s
						Supper during which I felt the Lord blessed me. After all this I got an inclination to go again to Fetter Lane &amp; found there was a Congn settled &amp; all stillness, where
						I again met with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Willams &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Loyd whom I knew, I was directly assured in my heart that they were Child<hi
							rend="superscript">n</hi> of God, &amp; that to them I belonged. I was priviledged with going to all the meetings on that day, whereby I was more devinely assur&apos;d of
						my heavenly calling. The following week B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williams sent me a note to come the next Sunday, </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-05.jpg" />
					<p> when I should see some pilgrim B<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>, I did not understand his meaning, yet when I was present at a meeting,
						held to the S. Women by the late <del>Disciple</del>
						<add place="above">ordinary of the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></add> in German which B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Spaningburg interpreted &amp; at which was present Anna
						Nitchman, Benigna &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Anna LaTrobe I soon understood they were the pilgrims that I was come to see. My coming to the B<hi rend="superscript"
							>rn</hi> was kept secret from the family for 3/4 of a year till at length they got intelligence that I went after a religious sect of people, which bore an indifferent
						character, &amp; they fearing the consequence sent for the Minister which had me confirm&apos;d, he questioned me very strictly about the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>, &amp;
						ask&apos;d me whether I realy knew that I was going among a pearcel of strolers. I told him he must be mistaken for I was convinc&apos;d they were Child<hi rend="superscript"
							>n</hi> of God; he said how had I come to this knowledge? I told him I had felt it in my heart, that there was no salvation but in the Gospel they preached thro&apos; faith
						in our Saviour to the forgiveness of sins; upon which he wish&apos;d me to say what sins I had committed, I ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> him I felt myself full of sin,
						altho&apos; I had been preserved from outward transgressions &amp; knew I must have forgiveness otherwise I cou&apos;d not saved. He ask&apos;d me many more questions, so that
						at length I grew quite weary went &amp; fetch&apos;d him all the Books that I had then in my possession of the B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> &amp; desir&apos;d him to read
						them atentively &amp; then return them again; with this I left him at that time but in a few days he sent for me to his House return&apos;d me the Books and saying he would
						have me consider it well over before I left the Church. I told him, I knew what I was about, as also the people &amp; wish&apos;d he knew them as well. After this conversation
						he came to our House &amp; desir&apos;d my M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> to part with me, I being a very dangerous person &amp; enough to infect her whole House. I felt an
						exceeding great love for the B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> people &amp; wish&apos;d more earnestly for a nearer connection &amp; beg&apos;d our Saviour to make known his
						love in my heart, &amp; from this time was convinced had no righteousness, therefore ceased not to pray our Saviour for forgiveness &amp; that he wou&apos;d cloth me with his
						righteousness, which soon after I felt in my heart &amp; was as a new born child so free; it was as if our dear Saviour had shed his blood alone for me, I was quite happy &amp;
						every way well. This happiness lasted about 3 months, </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-06.jpg" />
					<p> but not knowing my own poverty &amp; weakness &amp; that I stood in need of renewed Grace every moment, I grew dark &amp; miserable &amp; reason&apos;d against our Saviour
						feeling an unwillingness to be stript of everything &amp; saved alone by him, I was often frightened at the sight of my self &amp; was wretched to the last degree: but the dear
						H. Ghost ceased not that work which he has begun in my heart but as I afterwards found all was unmerited grace &amp; favor. I took the Hymn Book up in my distress &amp;
						open&apos;d to that Verse ye wounds of Jesus bless me now &amp; blood of Jesus flow me thro&apos; &amp;c. &amp; I found again confidence to our Saviour. I came again to London
						&amp; was hirred in M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Raymonds family. 1747 I was rec&apos;<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> into the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> which was
						really blessed to me &amp; felt a longing desire to partake of the H. Sacrament, but a deep sense of my own unworthiness &amp; the feeling of my wretched nature made me afraid
						to venture on so sacred a matter, therefore waited 2 years longer, when I had a particular favorable opportunity with Anna Nitchman &amp; A. <add place="above">Johanna</add> in
						Red Lyon Square who advis&apos;d me to leave my place, which I readily did &amp; came to live with S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stonehouse, I was soon admitted to the H.
							Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> which made a lasting, impression on my heart for I knew &amp; felt I fed on the Lords body &amp; blood, but nevertheless I often
						hinder&apos;d myself of many blessings thro&apos; unfaithfullness which occasioned often hours of distress, but the dear H. Ghost often represented to my heart the sufferings
						&amp; dying love of Jesus to procure my peace which made me truly ashamed &amp; a real <add place="above">humble</add> sinner. After my M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> decease
						I I was sent by our dear A. Nitchman to the Boys <del>Oeconomy</del>
						<add place="above">Nursery</add> in Mile end where I enjoy&apos;d a very happy period &amp; sabatic season. 1754 I came to S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larish in Linsey House
						from whence in May 1755 we set out for Hhuth where we arrived July 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> here I was with my whole heart which made my time pass the better with my
						much respected S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larish. After her happy Departure I had the favor to go to the C <add place="above">Choir</add> house, where I have enjoy&apos;d
						many unspeakable blessings for my poor heart, particularly in the C C<add place="above">hoir</add> meetings which the late Count <del>Disciple</del> kept in Bethelsdorf to
						which I went. In this <add place="above">Choir</add> House <add place="above">at</add> Hhuth I learnt to know myself better, which has prov&apos;d a wholesome school to me,
						&amp; for which I shall feel greatful to my latest breath. March 1758 I was admitted among the Intercessors which <del>opportunities</del> has prov&apos;d salutary &amp;
						blessed to me after which I liv&apos;d 4 years in the Child<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> Oeconomy &amp; then rec&apos;d a call to Fulneck to be among the Child<hi
							rend="superscript">n</hi> there where, I also remain&apos;d 4 years, &amp; then came to live and the C <add place="above">Choir</add> House here where, I have been ever
						since thousand, thousand thanks be rendered to my gracious Lord &amp; Saviour who has led me thus far, &amp; assured me of my everlasting happiness in him. Since </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_72Gurney-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						<del>Continuation of the life of Sarah Gurney</del>
						<del>I have to add the following</del>: Since I came into the single sisters house at Fulneck the Holy Ghost took me into his school, &amp; showed me that I ought to love our
						Saviour more than I did &amp; that I had not that earnest desire which I should have for the manifestation of his love to me. Though he had followed me from my infancy, yet now
						he discovered my depravity poverty &amp; helplessness returning my abode in the sisters house in a particular manner, I was in darkness sometimes through unbelief &amp; the
						feeling of my misery, &amp; if it one not for his love &amp; pitty he would have taken his grace from me but he did not, but from time to time helped me, letting me see clearly
						that without him there is no happiness, I felt my lost estate but he drew me near to himself &amp; did not let me rest till I could by faith apply his <add place="above"
							>Atone</add> ments <add place="above">to myself</add> &amp; know that I was his &amp; he was mine. If I had been more faithful to his leading I should have experienced more
						happiness &amp; have been more to his honor. I am still his poor child. I see &amp; feel my sinfulness &amp; that so very slowly toward the mark I press, but Jesus comforts me,
						who out mercy free me all my guilt with patience in the accursed tree. Now my hearts inclination is a deep prostration for my Saviours pain, To be therby melted so that each
						one felt it how I love that Man. May his love be be all my own &amp; may I in future love him with my whole heart <del>from here to eternity</del> though I shall fall short in
						time &amp; eternity. I can never praise <add place="above">him</add> sufficiently for what he has done to me his worthy child. His Holy Spirit often reproved <add place="above"
							>me,</add> but when with contrition I <add place="above">owned all</add> to him, he forgave me again, In short I live by his forgiveness. He <del>I was</del>
						<add place="above">cared</add> for me with <add place="above">the</add> tenderness of a Mother. O that I could praise my heavenly Father and my Saviour <del>&amp; I could</del>
						better than I do! O that I <del>did</del>
						<add place="above">might</add> never forget his mercies to me <del>which alas I have often done</del>
						<del>by he</del>
						<add place="above">and tho&apos; I have often to my great loss been forgetful, yet he</add> my great Saviour still remained the same For <del>was</del>
						<add place="above">which I now</add> will praise him as well as I can, &amp; <del>will</del>
						<add place="above">shall</add> do it better when I see him. <del>Thus far her own words, to which her Sisters added the following.</del>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
