<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Philip Molther: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="#mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry">Philip Molther</msName>
						<!-- <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-03.jpg" />-->
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#mlper000561">Phillip Molther</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2019-07-10" who="#jschaumberger">Finished markup of the text</change>
			<change when="2019-07-09" who="#jschaumberger">Started markup of the text</change>
			<change when="2019-06-10" who="#JAKA1">Updated header</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>name</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-01.jpg" n="1" />
					<p> Life of <roleName type="honorific">brother</roleName>
						<persName ref="#mlper000561">Philip Henry Molther</persName> who departed at <placeName ref="#mlpla000025">Bedford</placeName>
						<date type="death" when-iso="1780-09-09">Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 9. 1780</date>. extracted from his own manuscripts. I was born in the <date type="birth"
							when-iso="1714-12-28">year 1714 Dec the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date> at <placeName>Imsheim</placeName> in the vicinity of <placeName>Bussweiler in
							Elsatia</placeName> where my father was the <name occupation="minister">parish minister</name>. <date when-iso="1722" cert="medium">Being 8 years old</date>, I was sent to
						the school at <placeName>Bussweiler</placeName> with a view to lay the first foundation for studying divinity. I felt already in my infancy that the friend and Redeemer of my
						soul was drawing me by his grace. Tho&apos; I had many bad examples before me, I remained in inocent simplicity till in my <date when-iso="1728">14<hi rend="superscript"
								>th</hi> year</date>, when I was seduced into sin by one of my school fellows. Sin begat death, and my conscienc was repeatedly alarmed with this dreadful sentence:
						&quot;Thou art doomed to death&quot;, which caused me to feel unceasing <name type="emotion">anxiety of heart</name>, &amp; imbittered the sinful pleasures of life to me, <note
							type="catchword">serving</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-03.jpg" n="2" />
					<p> serving, through the kind care of the lover of my soul, as a barrier, which prevented me from rushing into misery. <date when-iso="1734">In the year 1734</date> I was sent by
						my parents to <placeName>Metz</placeName> in <placeName>France</placeName> in order to learn the french langua <roleName type="honorific">Our Saviour</roleName> pursued me also
						here by his Grace in many ways. Being once in company with my french master, I accompanied him at night to his lodgings seemingly in good health. The next morning I was
						thunderstruck at hearing that he was dead, as my conscience forced immediatly this question upon me: what would have be come of you if this had been your case? I hastened to my
						room <name type="emotion">trembling, and throwing myself on the ground, and prayed</name> to an unknown <persName type="deity">God</persName> for Grace and conver sion of heart
						from sin. But sometime after I fell again into a dilatory track. In the <date when-iso="1735">year 1735</date> I went to the university <note type="catchword">at</note>
					</p>
					<p> at <placeName>Jena</placeName>, on which occasion I prayed to <persName type="deity">God</persName> with a concerned heart to preserve me from seduction and convert me. This
						prayer I repeated very often as I knew how hurtful bad the time was spent by the major part of the students, being afraid of falling into the same trade Soon after my arrival
						the late <roleName type="honorific">brother</roleName>
						<persName>Daer baum</persName> went with me to the meetings of edification, held by the <roleName type="honorific">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></roleName> M<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi>
						<persName>Brumhards</persName> Here I heard for the first time of <persName type="deity">Jesus</persName> readiness to receive the poorest and most miserable sinners which
						proved to me, a word worthy of acceptation. After the meeting I went to my lodgings and cast myself at the feet of the friend of sinners, entrea ting Him with <name
							type="emotion">many tears</name> to have mercy upon me, and to assure me of my being accepted of him by delivering me from the dominions of sin in soul and body which had
						been on for some time a most grievous burthen to me. He caused me to look in <note type="catchword">that</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-05.jpg" n="3" />
					<p> that moment believingly to Him, in a manner as I had never been able to do, and I felt that sin had been laimed maimed and lost its force. Declining the proposal of my Father,
						to return home and to accept of a living, he withdrew his asistance, which on the one hand obliged me to find my support by teaching frensh but set me on the other hand at
						liberty from accepting my father&apos;s proposal con trary to the dictates of my heart. <persName>Christian <add place="above">Renatus de</add> Zinzendorf</persName> coming in
						the year <date when-iso="1737">1737</date> under the care of <persName>John Nitchman</persName>, to <placeName>Jena</placeName>, I had the pleasure <name occupation="teacher"
							>to be his teacher in music and the frensh language</name>. About easter the same year the late ordinar travelling through <persName>Jena</persName>, he had an enteview
						with all those who were employed to teach his son, and asked every one, after he had first spoke with each of us separately: Wether we were willing to devote ourselves <note
							type="catchword">to</note>
					</p>
					<p> to our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> and the <orgName>Congregation</orgName>, and <add place="above">were</add>desirous to be prepared for serving our <roleName
							type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> Every one said yes. But the question being put to me, I answered: &quot;I am convinced that I ought to devote myself to our <roleName
							type="honorific">Saviour</roleName>, and to be converted to him with my whole heart, for not doing it will render me an unfortunate man. But to be devoted to the
							<orgName>Congregation</orgName> I do not understand.&quot; He replied: &quot;It is very well, this matter is only for such as understand it, meanwhile you may continue to
						instruct my son&quot;. In <date when-iso="1737-06">June of the same year</date> our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> was pleased to convince me, in a most striking
						manner of my call of to the brethren&apos;s church, which time I never shall forget. Till now I thought as is common in my circumstances, that I was bound in duty to serve my
						native country, which had prevented me from to <note type="catchword">see</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-07.jpg" n="4" />
					<p> see or attend to our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName>&apos;s views with me. Previous to my going to <roleName>doctor</roleName>
						<persName>Hamburgers</persName> lectures upon natural philosophy, I meditated about myself and prayed to our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName>, who was pleased to
						speak to my heart and to lead me into a serious consideration concerning my past and future course. The following questions were brought home to my heart: &quot;What will
						become of you at last and in what manner will your studies terminate? You can&apos;t stay always at the university. If you become a <name occupation="minister">minister</name>
						in your native country what benefit will it be of to you on others; for if you go without being sent by me, you will be an unprofitable servant, and it may terminate with you
						as with other awakened students who did not prosper.&quot; It you will save your soul take refuge to the <orgName>brethrens congregation</orgName>&quot; &amp;c. These and <note
							type="catchword">other</note>
					</p>
					<p> others considerations came with such clearness into my heart as if our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> was pre sent and speaking to me, and I was enabled to
						acquiesce and say amen to all, with my whole heart. Now I knew what I was about, heard and saw every thing in another light, and my eye being single the whole body was light,
						so that I could not help wondering at the change wrought in me. I moved with the consent of <persName>John Nitchman</persName> in the <date when-iso="1737-07">month of
							July</date> into the <add place="above">house</add> of of the young count, and which was exceedingly happy in the company of the brethren. <persName>John
							Nitchman</persName> was betrued and respected as a father among us, and cared for the good of our souls with much love and faithfulness. Our main view was to become like
						little children, and such a spirit of love and zeal prevailed among us, that we sat many a night <note type="catchword">till</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-09.jpg" n="5" />
					<p> state of our souls and singing praises to him, who had chosen us from before the foundation of the world, and called us from among the confusion of the learned world to his
						people, and to whom we now wished to devote ourselves, with heart felt joy as living sacrifices. In the <date when-iso="1733">year 1733</date> we went with the <persName
							ana="John Nitchma">young count</persName> to <placeName>Berlin</placeName> where his father resided, having about 70 pilgrims with him. This was a blessed time for me. The
						singing of the <orgName>brethren</orgName> and <orgName>Sisters</orgName> and the discourses of the late ordinary were attended with unction and the demons tration of the
						spirit of <persName type="deity">God</persName>. <date when-iso="1733-2-08">Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date> I was <name
							event="reception">received into the cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></name> and the <date when-iso="1733-02-22">22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></date> I was admitted to
						the <name event="communion">Lord&apos;s supper</name>. Tho our lord had givin given me striking proofs of his Grace, I was yet subject to many changes. This true foundation
							<note type="catchword">was</note>
					</p>
					<p> was laid in my heart, and I was delivered from sin. But being ignorant of the previledges our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName>&apos;s patients are intitled to, I
						perplexed myself often at feeling my innate depravity and did not know how to look upon it. But now it pleased the friend of my soul to remove this by granting me the favor to
						cast a believing look upon Him as my all sufficient <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName>; for being at the comn Liturgy in deep and grateful meditation concerning the
						great favor I had enjoyed in eating and drinking the flesh and blood of the son of man sacramentally, and sighing to him, to make me quite happy; he appeared in<add
							place="above">such</add> a most striking manner to my heart as my bleeding and suffering <roleName type="honorific">Redeemer</roleName>, that I melted into tears like wax
						before the fire. From that time I proceeded from grace to grace and the connexion with Him any beloved <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> whose <note type="catchword"
							>love</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-11.jpg" n="6" />
					<p> love had captivated my heart became daily more confident, and my gracious call<add place="above">of Grace</add> to belong to the congn more impor tant and precious. Having
						stayed 5 months at <placeName>Berlin</placeName> we returned to <placeName>Jena</placeName> where the testimony of <persName type="deity">Jesu&apos;s</persName> Blood approved
						itself as the power of <persName type="deity">God</persName> to salvation upon many students and others. In the year <date when-iso="1739">1739</date> we were called to
							<placeName>Wetteravia</placeName>, which proved a means to bring me to the <orgName>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></orgName> at <placeName>Marien</placeName> born. <date
							when-iso="1739-06-01">July the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></date> the late Ordinary arrived from <placeName>S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Thomas</placeName> in the
							<placeName>Westindies</placeName>. As soon as he had saluted me he said: &quot;My brother I have spoken to our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> concerning you,
						whilst I was at sea. He has ordered me to mention to you in his name, that you are to go to <placeName>Pensylvania</placeName> to preach the gospel in the whole country.&quot;
						I replied: "Here I am may he do with me what is wellpleasing to him.&quot; Soon after I was <name event="religious">ordai <note type="catchword">ned</note></name>
					</p>
					<p> dained a <name occupation="minister">Minister</name> of the brethren&apos;s Church, and went in company with the late ordinary to a <name event="religious">Synodal conf<hi
								rend="superscript">ce</hi></name> held at Ebersdorf. Shortly before my setting out on my intended post, he put me to a very severe but blessed trial by saying <add
							place="above">before all present</add> &quot;Our <roleName type="honorific">brother</roleName>
						<persName>Molter</persName> is now going to <placeName>Pensylvania</placeName>, there he&apos;ll perhaps meet with books wrote against us, or hear many bad things concerning
						the <orgName>congregation</orgName> which will confuse his mind and then he will go from us&quot; &amp; I answered: &quot;I can not boast of myself and make fair pro misses;
						but <del>one thing</del>><add place="above">this</add> I can assertain, that before I prove unfaithful to the <orgName>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></orgName>, I must first
						loose sight, and entirely for get our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName>, nothing else can seperate me from the congregation&quot;, At this declaration I could not
						refrain from tears. my answer removed his thoughtfulness concerning me, and he dismissed me with the a kiss of love and many blessings. I now <note type="catchword">went</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-13.jpg" n="7" />
					<p> went to <placeName ref="#mlpla000001">Herrnhut</placeName>, where I was much struck with the primitive simplicity of the place and the singing of all the single brethren who
						were just going in procession through the place when I arrived. Having enjoyed many blessings during my abode there I returned to <placeName ref="#mlpla000057"
							>Marrienborn</placeName>, where every thing relative to my future plan was settled and I was <name event="marriage">married</name> to <persName>Johanna de
							Seydewir</persName> on the <date when-iso="1739-09-05">5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></date>. As circumstances required my setting out
						without her, she it was resolved that she should follow me, with the next company that was to go to <placeName ref="#mlpla000070">America</placeName>. <date
							when-iso="1739-09-23">Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></date> I sat out and arrived at <placeName ref="#mlpla000054">London</placeName>
						<date when-iso="1739-10-18">Oct. the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>. As no ship was to sail <add place="above">to <placeName>Pensylvania</placeName></add>till the
						middle of Jany I endeavoured to spend my time as useful as I could, and kept meetings to a member of Germans who had been awakened by means of the testimony of <roleName
							type="honorific">brother</roleName>
						<persName>Richter</persName>, who <del>was</del><add place="above">had</add> de parted this life at Algier. to the english <note type="catchword">brethren</note>
					</p>
					<p>
						<orgName>brethren</orgName> and <orgName>Sisters</orgName>. I kept meetings in the Latin language, having some body who inter pacted what I said into english, till I after
						sometime ventured to deliver discourses in the E. language. There was at that time a Society at <placeName ref="#mlpla000004">Fetterlane</placeName> which was begun by
							<roleName type="honorific">b<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>. <persName>Peter Boehler</persName> and was then cared for by the <roleName type="honorific">Rev<hi
								rend="superscript">d</hi></roleName>
						<persName>John</persName> &amp; <persName>charles Wesly</persName>. As these people did not rightly know what they were at they were come into a strange fanatical way, so that
						I did not know what to think when I came for the first time into their meetings and heard them sigh grown and howl in a very strange manner, which they called the demonstration
						of the spirit and the power of <persName type="deity">God</persName>. at speaking with the individuals of this society, I found many deeply concerned for their souls. As
						deficient as I was in expressing myself in the E. Language, they pressed me so <note type="catchword">hard.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="8">
					<head type="page">8</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-15.jpg" n="8" />
					<p> Seeing that he could not obtain his aim he declined all further fellowship with the Society, and <del>stood</del>
						<add place="above">rising</add>from his seat with He walked out with the words: &quot;To me, all that are the <roleName type="honorific">Lord&apos;s</roleName>&quot;. Some few
						followed him. Some brethren <add place="above">who</add> gave me an account of what had happened, I advised to be still, and to leave the isue to our <roleName type="honorific"
							>Saviour</roleName>. In <date>August</date><!-- I dont know the year -->, I had the joy to welcome my wife here in <placeName ref="#mlpla000054">London</placeName>, on her
						way to <placeName ref="#mlpla000070">America</placeName>. It was left to me to let her proceed or keep her with me; but being convinced in my heart that it was the will of our
							<roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> that she should go thither, and finding her willing to go, I accompanied her on board, where we prostrated in prayer before our
							<roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> and covenanted with each other to be and remain his, after which we took an affectionate leave. In
						<date>September</date><!-- I dont know the year --> I was recalled <note type="catchword">from</note>
					</p>
					<p> from <placeName ref="#mlpla000054">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="#mlpla000057">Marrienborn</placeName>, where having stayed for some time, I was commissioned to travel
						into <placeName>france</placeName>
						<name office="visitor">in order to look for such as were awakened</name>. In <placeName>Paris</placeName> I found some godly persons who were mysticks and valued the writings
						of M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. <persName>Boerignor</persName> and Mrs <add place="above"><roleName>Lady</roleName></add>
						<persName>de Guion</persName>. I also learned that there were a great many more of the same people who did not venture to make them selves known. From thence I went to
							<placeName>Lyon</placeName>
						<placeName>Geneve</placeName> by way of <placeName>Lyon</placeName>, here I stayed with the late Ordinary till <date>May</date><!-- I dont know the year --> and enjoyed many
						blessings. On my road from thence to <placeName>Holland</placeName>
						<name health="disease">I fell sick</name>, which necessitated me to stay 10 weeks with my mother. I had no patience to wait till I was recovered, and before I reached Holland
						the <name health="recovered">fever had left me</name>. In <date>Septr</date><!-- I dont know the year --> I arrived at <placeName>London</placeName>, full of hopes and joy to
						pursue my destination to <placeName>Pensylvania</placeName>, but I was again seized <note type="catchword">with</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="9">
					<head type="page">9</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-17.jpg" n="9" />
					<p> with <name health="disease">another illness</name>, so that my fellow travellers entered upon their voyage without me.  Tho&apos; it did not appear as if I should recover, I
						was informed by a letter that in case of my recovering I was to go against to <placeName>Geneva</placeName>
						<name office="visitor">to serve the awakened souls in that place</name>. After <name health="disease">9 weeks illness</name> I sat out for <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, where
						I <add place="above">arrived</add> after an agreeable stay of some days at <placeName ref="#mlpla000057">Marienborn</placeName>, in <date when-iso="1742-02">Feb of the year
							1742</date>. I had not been there above a fortnight when I was ordered by the magistrates, who were dissatisfied with my stay there, to quit my private lodgings, and to
						move to an inn. Taking a journey in the country <name health="disease">I fell sick again</name> &amp; was received and treated as a servant of <persName type="deity"
							>Christ</persName> at the house of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <persName>Elie Prendhomme</persName>, to whom I was recommended by his brother. It proved a great joy to
						me to see afterwards him and  <note type="catchword">his</note>
					</p>
					<p> his whole family, to whom I was is much  indebted, to become children of <persName type="deity">God</persName> our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName>. This was also
						the <add place="above">case</add>with the family of old father <persName>Pindent</persName>, who at another time served me in the same kind manner. About this time I ventured,
						in reliance upon the help of our <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName>, to translate our Hymns into the frensh language and in about a years time I got 70 of them printed.
						In <date when-iso="1743-04">April 1743</date> I returned to <placeName ref="#mlpla000057">Marienborn</placeName>, where I  found my wife, who was arrived from <placeName
							ref="#mlpla000070">America</placeName> a few days before me. I received her as if she was given me quite anew by our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName>. After
						some time we travelled toge ther to the <name event="religious">Synod</name>, which was held at <placeName>Hirschberg</placeName>. there we were <name office="visitor"
							>appointed to visit the awakened souls</name> in <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>. This journey proved very agreeable to us both. When we were tired of walking we sat
						down in a lonely spot and sung a verse, feeling excee <note type="catchword">dingly</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="10">
					<head type="page">10</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-19.jpg" n="10" />
					<p> dingly well thereat. In a town called <placeName>Speyer</placeName> where the whole frensh armee was quartered, we had a narrow escape of being killed, being nearly trodden
						under foot, by the horsemen who came from both sides upon us when we were just under the gate. In the critical moment, when nothing seemed to offer for our relief, I espied a
						little space between the horses, and snatching my wife into my arms I slipped through, wondering at and thanking our <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> for his kind
						protection. <date when-iso="1743-11-13">Nov 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date> I settled the in habitants of <placeName>Montmirail-house</placeName> into a cong<hi
							rend="superscript">n</hi> but after some time it was broke up again, as we met with opposition in <placeName>Switzerland</placeName> and were even forbid to reside any more
						at <placeName>Geneva</placeName>. We now returned again in <date when-iso="1745-07">July 1745</date> to <placeName ref="#mlpla000057">Marienborn</placeName>. In about the time
						of a year we went again into <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, and <add place="above">where besides my former office</add> I had also to care for the housekeeping, besides
							<note type="catchword">this</note>
					</p>
					<p> this and the journies into the country I was employed in translating the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> accounts into the frensh language, as also with revising the hymns I
						had translated sometime ago and adding more hymns to them, which labour proved a refreshment to my heart. As circumstances required again our removal from
							<placeName>Montmirail</placeName>, we met in the hall for the last time to thank our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> for all the grace he had given us to
						enjoy in this place. I arrived at <placeName>Herrnhaag</placeName> (in company of the frensh <orgName>brethren</orgName> and <orgName>Sisters</orgName> from <placeName
							ref="#mlpla000014">Montmirail</placeName>) in the last days of <date when-iso="1748-09-30">sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> of the year 1748</date>. My stay here was not
						agreeable to me, as I did not like the then course of that cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. I therefore kept retired and in stillness. These circumstances caused me to search
						my own heart thoroughly, the conclusion of which was, that our <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> was pleased to give me a renewed impression of my <note
							type="catchword">election</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="11">
					<head type="page">11</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-21.jpg" n="11" />
					<p> election of grace. In <date when-iso="1749">1749</date> we were in <placeName>Holland</placeName> and <placeName ref="#mlpla000072">England</placeName> with the late ordinary,
						in whose house we spent the time very blessedly In <date when-iso="1750">1750</date> we went to <placeName ref="#mlpla000022">Barby</placeName>, in hopes that the frensh
							<orgName>brethren</orgName> and <orgName>sisters</orgName> who were obliged to emigrate with the rest of the b<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> and s<hi rend="superscript"
							>rs</hi> from <placeName ref="#mlpla000014">Herrnhaag</placeName>, would find it practicable to settle there. Meanwhile the <persName>Count of Neuwied</persName> altered to
						receive them in his Dominions and to grant them liberty of conscience. The late Ordinary having had an interview with the <persName>count of Neuwied</persName>, previous to his
						arival at Barby, he acquainted me, that he had found a place for the frensh b<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; s<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> and viz: Neuwied, and told me
						to prepare for my journey thither. In <date>sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></date> I went to <placeName ref="#mlpla000014">Herrnhaag</placeName> and from thence with some of
						the frensh <orgName>brethren</orgName> and <orgName>sisters</orgName> to <placeName>Neuwied</placeName>, where we arrived <date when-iso="10-16">Oct the 16<hi
								rend="superscript">th</hi></date>. Soon after the remain <note type="catchword">der</note>
					</p>
					<p> der of them <del>frensh</del>
						<orgName>brethren</orgName> &amp; <orgName>Sisters</orgName> arrived with us, after which we all partook of the <name event="communion">holy Com<hi rend="superscript"
							>n</hi></name> at which our <roleName type="honorific">Saviours</roleName> grace was power ful among us. We lived at first together in one house as one family. Love,
						simplicity, and grace and truth ruled among us, and He who regardeth the ready and poor, walked in our midst and the peace of <persName type="deity">God</persName> rested upon
						this cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. What trials of faith and patience we had to experience during the first 4 years is only known to our <roleName type="honorific"
							>Saviour</roleName>, but his faithfulness and support was our only dependence. These trials were the consequence of our moving to <placeName>Neuwied</placeName> before
						matters had been finally settled with the <persName>count of Neuwied</persName>, for a deportation which treated afterwards with him in behalf of the unity returned after a
						stay of 3 weeks without being able to conclude upon anything, and we were left upon a very uncertain lasting <note type="catchword">mean-</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="12">
					<head type="page">12</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-23.jpg" n="12" />
					<p> meanwhile occurred the wellknown hard trials in <placeName ref="#mlpla000072">England</placeName>, so that the brethren had no time to think of our settling here upon a sure
						footing, and upon all the letters we wrote during the space of 18 months, we received no answer All the newspapers were filled with the most bitter speeches against us, which
						were often repeated at our windows by persons who were evil inclined. We laid our heavy circumstances before our Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> who formed the unanimous
						resolution to hold our with courage and patience as long as possible. In the <date when-iso="1753">spring of 1753</date> the late ordinary sent a letter to the <persName>count
							of Neuwied</persName> importing, that his present circumstances made it im practicable for him, to assist the establish ment of a frensh Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>
						at <placeName>Neuwied</placeName>, and <del>that</del>
						<add place="above">the</add> people who had moved thither with that intent would probably be obliged to return to <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>. <persName>The
							Count</persName> expressed <note type="catchword">his</note>
					</p>
					<p> his compassion <add place="above">for</add><del>with</del> us and encouraged us by saying: &quot;<persName type="deity">God</persName> can still give this matter a favourable
						turn and bring it to bear.&quot; In <date when-iso="1753-11">Nov.</date> It was resolved in a <orgName>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Council</orgName> to send a deputy to
							<placeName ref="#mlpla000054">London</placeName>, who was to procure a final resolution wether we were to stay here or to move away; but our deputy falling very ill at
							<placeName>Teist</placeName> we were obliged to be patient. In <date when-iso="1754-07">July 1754</date> we received the long wished for message, wich put an end to all our
							<add place="above">concern</add> that the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> was to stay at <placeName>Neuwied</placeName>, to build proper habitations and was to be
						augmented. The word of the day when I received this account form <placeName ref="#mlpla000054">London</placeName> (viz. <date when-iso="1754-07-22">July the 22<hi
								rend="superscript">d</hi></date>) was: &quot;The glory of the <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> shall be revealed, and all flesh shall ice it together: for the
						mouth of the <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> has spoken it.&quot; It is not possible to describe what joy this account occassioned in the Cong<hi rend="superscript"
							>n</hi>. All praised and adored the <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName> for his kindness towards us. Our concession being drawn, up <note type="catchword">and</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="13">
					<head type="page">13</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-25.jpg" n="13" />
					<p> and signed in <date when-iso="1755">1755</date>, we began to prepare for building and in 3 years time the hall and 2 Choir houses for the s<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> b<hi
							rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; s<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> were finished and sundry houses and gardens bought. The congregation encreased so fast that the number of
						souls amounted at the end of <date when-iso="1760">1760</date> to 202. <date when-iso="1758-12-10">December the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1758</date>. the cong<hi
							rend="superscript">n</hi> was settled by <roleName type="honorific">brother</roleName>
						<persName>Johannes</persName>, &amp; the meeting hall concecrated. <del>and</del> In <date when-iso="1761-04">April 1761</date> having been releas&apos;d from my office by
							<roleName type="honorific">brother</roleName>
						<persName>Risler</persName>, we sat out for <placeName ref="#mlpla000001">Herrnhut</placeName> where we<add place="above">arrived</add> after a difficult journey. Thus far our
						late <roleName type="honorific">brother</roleName>. He stayed with his wife about a year in <placeName ref="#mlpla000001">Herrnhut</placeName> from whence he was called to have
						the care of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at <placeName>Dublin</placeName>, where they arrived in the som summer of of <date when-iso="1762">1762</date>, previous to
						which they had brought their 3 sons to <placeName>Cathrinenhatt</placeName>, to be educated in the <orgName en="œconomy">childrens Oec<hi rend="superscript">y</hi></orgName>.
						In <date when-iso="1767">1767</date> he was called to <placeName ref="#mlpla000025">Bedford</placeName> to be the <name occupation="minister">Minister</name> and <name
							office="helper">Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> helper</name> in that Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> It is sufficiently known from the reports of <note
							type="catchword">that</note>
					</p>
					<p> that Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> with wat what unction and grace he served it. In <date when-iso="1755">1775</date> he was called to the <name event="religious"
							>Synod</name> at <placeName ref="#mlpla000022">Barby</placeName> and <name event="religious">consecrated</name> a <name office="bishop">Bishop</name> of the brethren&apos;s
						Church. Before he returned to <placeName ref="#mlpla000025">Bedford</placeName> he visited his children in <placeName>Uper Lusatia </placeName>and
							<placeName>Silivia</placeName> and the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at <placeName>Neuwied</placeName> (where his former services are still remembe red with gratitude).
						He returned from thence by way of <placeName>Teist</placeName> to <placeName ref="#mlpla000025">Bedford</placeName>, where he arrived <date when-iso="1755-12-12">dec the 12<hi
								rend="superscript">th</hi></date>. From that time his <name health="disease">strength decayed and he grew mostly blind</name>. In <date when-iso="1779">1779</date> he
						got a <name health="disease">stroke of the palsy</name> which lamed his right side. <date when-iso="1780" cert="medium">about a year</date> after he had <name health="disease"
							>another attack of the same disorder</name> which showed plainly that he was mean his end. He behaved himself under all these afflictions as a servant of <persName
							type="deity">Christ</persName> and expressed his joy at the prospect of being soon at home with the <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName>, in short he was in last
						illness an edificiation and blessing to <note type="catchword">all</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="14">
					<head type="page">14</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_04_MoltherPhilipHenry-27.jpg" n="14" />
					<p> all around him till he fell asleep in the <roleName type="honorific">Lord</roleName>
						<date type="death" cause="disease" when-iso="1780-09-09">septr the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1780 in the 66<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date> year of his age. He lived
						41 years in the married state and has had 7 children, of which 2 sons and one daughter are still alive. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
