<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>James Oates: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_53_OatesJames">James Oates</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_53_OatesJames-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_53_OatesJames-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_53_OatesJames-03.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">James Oates</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-11" who="#JAKA1">Checked standard, converted to semantic markup</change>
			<change when-iso="2019-08-28" who="#JAKA1">Created memoir file</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>James Oates</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_53_OatesJames-01.jpg" />
					<p>
						<add place="margin" n="right">Departed June 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 1761.</add> The great Boy <hi rend="underline">James Oates</hi> was born at Norwood Green in 7<hi
							rend="superscript">t</hi>h Parish of Halifax Sept the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1745, was baptized in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Church of England, but has been
						amongst y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> from a Child, during which State he <del>was</del> always bore y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Character
						of plain downright &amp; honest, was beloved by y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Labourer of the Plan wherein he lived &amp; <del>of those</del> who visited him from time to time
						for his genuine Simplicity. <add place="margin" n="right">by the Childns Father</add> He was rec&apos;d into the great Boys Choir Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> y<hi
							rend="superscript">e</hi> 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1760, after which it was obvious, that the getting a true acquaintance with the Man of Sorrows lay very near his
						Heart. When he was visited &amp; spoke with from time to time by his Choir Labourers they always found him y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> same Simple &amp; openhearted course,
						andently desiring to become a Joy to that Heart which broke in Death for him; for which reason the Close of his Conversation with them was generally about coming into y<hi
							rend="superscript">e</hi> Choirhouse, where he might spend his time uninterrupted by in a true Devotion of Soul &amp; Body to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> humanity of
						Christ, the Boys Choir heads &amp; Prince. Accordingly this favour was granted him Apr. y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1760 to his
						inexpressible Joy. The Business which he followed in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Choirhouse was that of a Stuffweaver, which he began with his father while at home
							<del>principally</del> and exercised great Diligence thereat principally with a View to come soon into y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Choirhouse &amp; that there he might
						be as little burthensome as possible. He shewd as much Diligence at his Work here as one could well expect of a Boy in his Years, but being naturally of an active turn of mind
						&amp; strong in body he often sollicited to be put to another business which required harder Labour &amp; more Ex- ercise. But this being not convenient according to our
						Circumstances, he was told to pursue that business which he had learnt. Herein he shewd such an unfeig- ned obedience as was exemplary to all of other Boys. (However by his
						continual sitting &amp; faithfulness at his work it is supposed the Disorder he got in his Bowels was contracted.) About a Year ago he first begen to complain of a Pain in his
						Bowels which sometimes was so violent th as obliged him to leave of Work &amp; keep to his Room, wherein obedience he made use of all Medicines given to him by our Physician,
						but his Desire to be again amongst y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Boys at his Work, was sometimes y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Motif for his saying he was well when it was
						not entirely so. However his Disorder seemingly left him, &amp; he began to gather Strength, but secretly his Thoughts were principally set upon going home, which he often
						utter&apos;d to his Labours with longing tears &amp; even was so sure of this Point, that he desired his Companions in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Shop to take notice that
						he would be at home with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; his tabernacle laid in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> burying Ground before next Midsummer. This he also
						told the Boy Wm Ashley when he was waiting for his last kiss last last October, <del>that he would be with him before Midsummer.</del>
						<add place="margin" n="right">In this situation he went on, improving in the knowledge of himself &amp; acquaintance with that Heart who confesses himself to the poor &amp;
							needy; Confident and clear admist all the Sensations of his own Poverty &amp; often weeping after the Soul of Christ whose Comunucation he found to be his life.</add> He
						was rec&apos;d into the Congn March y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> last, to his great Joy &amp; Abasement, for he often said when others were
						rec&apos;d he was not worthy of such a great Grace; Soon </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_53_OatesJames-02.jpg" />
					<p> after which he began to sicken with his old Disorder &amp; was obliged to betake himself entirely to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Sickroom. His first Thoughts were: now I
						shall go home notwithstanding which he was obedient to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Physicians in taking every thing he prescribed &amp; soon became such a Compainion to his
						Sickwaiter as he Scarcely ever had before for his Sinerlikeness, gratitude, clearness of heart &amp; constancy in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> enjoyment of our Sav<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi>. His Patience in his Sickness &amp; Pain was astonishment to everybody, which was alleviated by nothing but his heart living in the Torments Pain
						&amp; Anguish of his beloved, whose Nearness &amp; Converse was the Occupation of his Soul by Day &amp; Night. If any Br or Boy wanted to refresh himself he know not how to do
						it better than by visitng our d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ja<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Oates, who was always found conversing most intimately with our Sav<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi> with Clearness &amp; Serenity &amp; oftentimes with Tears. In his Sleep this happy converse was not interrupted, but went on in the same track as
						when awake, being often heard speaking with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> by those who watch&apos;d with him <!-- These two lines are inserted from left margin -->
						<add place="margin" n="left">saying: my good Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> , my dear Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> , my best Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>!</add> There
						was nothing at all of falsehood or obliquity to be found in him, but that same downright honest openhearted &amp; genuine Simplicity Shun in all his Words &amp; Actions
						constantly panting for the last kiss.</p>
					<p> May the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> he was all the Day in an Extali, continually occupied with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; his coming so that the Hearts of
						many B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> who heard him were melted &amp; their Eyes overflowd. He often enquird about John Morgan, who lay ready for y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>
						departing kiss with him in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> same room &amp; express&apos;d his Concern for him, wishing him safe with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. He
						also mentioned something of the Band he kept with J<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Morgan in the begining of his Sickness &amp; declared of himself how it had been with him
						&amp; how he had spent his time before he came to y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> knowledge of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, that since that time our Sav<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi> slept before his heart he had loved him with all his might, but was ashamed his Love was not stronger, Since the friend of his Soul had done so
						much for him &amp; earn&apos;d his Soul &amp; Body a thousand times over. Upon being asked whether he would choose to go to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> now or wait
						untill He came to visit the Congn, his answer was, I cannot stay, he has charmed my Heart, but if it pleased our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> I would do either; often
						uttering at Intervalls On the first Sight of him persenally! &amp; frequently call&apos;d out Sleepd &amp; waking: My Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> come soon!</p>
					<p> While the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> were enjoying the Lords Course in the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Hall about 5 Minutes before J<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.
						Morgan went home (tho&apos; he knew nothing of Morgans Situa- tion) he burst out in this prophetic Strain, saying to himself. &quot;Yes, yes, my Sav<hi rend="superscript"
							>r</hi> "I now see thou will come soon, Yes I know thou wilt, Ay, Ay, thou will, oh yes "I see it very plain, I see thou art a-coming, Ay, Ay, thou at there a-smiling,
						"Thou art coming just now &amp;c.&quot; When he was told our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> had taken Jo. Morgan to himself, he said, I am glad of it &amp; thank him with
						Joy; now I only wish he <note type="catchword">would</note>
					</p>
					<pb />
					<p>
						<l>would soon come &amp; pay me such another Visit, the sooner the better.</l></p>
					<p> The 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> The Boys of his Room visited him, he was very lively &amp; told them how happy he was &amp; how much he longed to be at home; he
						wish&apos;d none might withold their hearts from our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, for his sufferings deserved a thousand times more then what they were able to give him,
						and sayd how happy it would be it each of them might obtain the favour which he was a Candidate for. On being told that perhaps our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> had some
						Views with some of them for which they must stay yet longer here below, he replied, &quot;it is very probable, but may they then be "good Hearts, give him Joy &amp; execute his
						views, as for me it is my happy Lot to "go home.&quot; He then made his Observations upon some of y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Boys, &amp; lastly they sung several Verses for
						him, a happy melting feeling attended the whole. <add place="margin" n="right">A B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. who had the Watch with him observing the Boy in a gentle
							looking with Surprise found the Boy awakd, who call&apos;d him &amp; ask&apos;d him, who that was that came into the Room &amp; awoke him. The Br. replied, I saw nobody.
							Yes, says the Boy, there somebody did awake me, &amp; I believe it was our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</add> The 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> when the Meeting was
						over in which the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> had been singing&quot; O Jerusalem above &amp;c (tho unknown to him) he sent for the Labourer &amp; said I only wanted to
						tell you, I think it cannot be long before our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> comes &amp; takes me with him, I have such a feeling of him as I cannot express, only he is very
						near. This he utter&apos;d with a most tender feeling &amp; Tears on both Sides Then a Band was kept. The Conclusion was: I have the best Prospect before me, I have not long to
						continue here, I perceive plainly my Friend draws nearer &amp; nearer.</p>
					<p> The 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> He was uncomonly pretty, talk&apos;d charmingly about our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; his happiness in him. Awaking from Sleep
						he called out to his Sickwaiter &amp; said: Well Charles, now it is all over, now I have no more pain, for I have seen our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> , have been with
						him, kiss&apos;d his Wounds, &amp; he told me he would come again very soon, &amp; take me with him to himself. This he utterd with such a Countenance is captivated the
						Sickwaiter. He then desired his Labourer might be call&apos;d, a when he came into the room he lifted up his weak head &amp; said with a Smiling pleasant Mien: I have been with
						our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> , &amp; there was a most Charming Company with him, &amp; bonnily did they sing, ay bonnily, right bonnily, &amp; pretty it was, I never
						heard such bonny singing before. Being ask&apos;d what they sung, he answerd with a broken Voice: The Wounds, the Wounds of our dear Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; all
						abou this Blood &amp; how he suffer&apos;d, &amp;they also sung, that it was all done for me, &amp; a great deal more, but I cannot tell it you all; I am sure if you had heard
						it you would say so too, I know he&apos;ll not be long before he comes again &amp; that will be a fine coming for me.</p>
					<p> Monday June the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> morning early Br Ab<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> took his leave of him before he set out upon
						his Journey for Lindsey house. He lay the whole day in a happy Sabathu stillness, looking out for his Friend &amp; chearing the Minds &amp; Hearts </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_53_OatesJames-03.jpg" />
					<p> of everyone who visited him. The 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> In the Forenoon he had another happy Band with his Labourer, about that first Moment when he should embrace the
						wounded feet of his Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; said, I can hold it out no longer, to day my Joy will be compleated. In the Afternoon it appeared evident that his
						beloved Bridegroom drew near his heart with Smiles of Grace, but his Speech failing him it was difficult to understand what he utterd. After the Choir Evening blessing the
						Labourer went up to the Sickroom, found him in a manner absent to all about him, uttering <del>something</del> to himself. My dear Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> , my
						precious Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> , my good Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; as soon as that Verse was sung for him. Now he does get Permission to leave this
						mortal Tent &amp; he lift up his Eyes with such a charming Glance as captivated the minds of all about him, seemingly intimation he look&apos;d for his last Blessing, whereupon
						it was imparted to him during the Singing of that Verse: O thou holy tormented Corpse, do as Elisha did, he is the Child with a penetrating feeling of the precious Nearness of
						the Friend of his Soul, in whose Arms &amp; Bosom he fell softly &amp; happily asleep without any other Signs then of a Person doasing into the most agreeable Slumber with the
						Blessing of his Choir in the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Year of his Age. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
