<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mary Peel: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel">Mary Peel</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-04.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Mary Peel</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-08-28" who="#JAKA1">Created memoir file</change>
			<change when-iso="2019-10-22" who="#cpirmann">corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Mary Peel</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-01.jpg" />
					<p> I was born at <placeName>Northarm</placeName> in the <placeName>parish of Halifax</placeName> in the <date when-iso="1722-05-29"><add place="above">May 29</add> year
							1722</date>. My Parents being very religious endeavour&apos;d to bring me up strictly in the fear of <persName type="deity">God</persName>. they very early perceiving my
						natural turn to be quick livly and active, on that account took the greater care of me takeing me with them constantly to the <name event="religious">Decenters meetings</name>,
						as I at that time did not understand their meaning, I look upon it as being very hardly dealt with, but afterwards saw clearly that their intentions where only to prevent my
						entrance on a very loose course of life which I might have fall&apos;n into, had not their unwearied care &amp; faithfullness, been a great means of preserving me, together
						with an invisible Hand, which I often felt While very young over me without any knowlidge of the meaning thereof for which I shall forever remain thankfull, I went on much in
						this way till <persName ref="#mlper000536">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Inham</persName> came to these parts, to whose preaching the greatest part of the people resorting, I
						went among the rest, being thereby stir&apos;d up &amp; often brought to reflect on my state, but with out any lasting impression. I remember one night being very thoughtfull
						when going to bed, I dream&apos;d that I was to be put to death, at which I was very much perplex&apos;t, I intreated to be spar&apos;d while I was set to die. The earnestness
						I was in awoke me, but the impression of this I never lost, &amp; by means of the <name type="emotion">uncommon feelings</name> I had somtimes I thought surly there was some
						thing to be injoy&apos;d, to which I was as yet a stranger, but was not rightly satisfy&apos;d to be without it. </p>
					<p> In the <date>year 17??</date><note>we do not know what date this is refering to</note>
						<add place="above">came</add>
						<hi rend="superscript">coming</hi> the <orgName>Brethern</orgName> into <placeName ref="#mlpla000084">Yorkshire</placeName> with a<hi rend="strikethrough">n</hi> vein <hi
							rend="strikethrough">intention</hi> to settle societies, accordingly tookdown the names of those who constantly atended the preaching. I therefore was willing to have mine
						taken down, which was no sooner done, but I was amazingly struck, thinking I am now however fast, but did not repent it. I soon found it was not alone the taking down the </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-02.jpg" />
					<p> names but they entended to look more particularly after each one therefore they soon settled Bands to which I was admitted &amp; geting a great love for them they were very
						much blest to me. Some of my Companions being soon after this <name event="reception" memoirSubject="no">receiv&apos;d into the <orgName>Congregation</orgName></name>
						<name type="emotion">it Cause&apos;d me many uneasy hours</name>, as I was left, however I thought to try &amp; get to them though I knew not how to set about it, when almost
						dispairing I often felt exceedingly encouraged and very much strengthened I was not allow&apos;d to go to the <name event="religious">Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>
							meetings</name> this drove me to the determination to make my mind known which I did by a letter to the <orgName>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></orgName>
						<name type="emotion">expressing my greatest desire</name> to be embody&apos;d with them. My request was soon granted our in year <date when-iso="1745">1745</date> this was an
							<name type="emotion">inexpressible grace &amp; favour to me</name> past discribing being then very chearfull I thought I had then got all that could make my happiness
						compleat. In this way I went on for some time. </p>
					<p> In the year <date when-iso="1747">1747</date> the first <orgName en="œconomy">Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Oeconomy</orgName> was settl&apos;d at
							<placeName>Oxhaighs</placeName> I having the favour to be one of the first, I look&apos;d on it &amp; accepted it with a real thankfull heart, &amp; the <name
							type="emotion">blessing which I then enjoy&apos;d</name> will never be forgot by me. This happiness lasted for some time but before I was aware it all vanishd away and
							<name type="emotion">I was left as much distresst as ever</name> being ready to determin to leave the <orgName>Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></orgName> &amp; take my
						thing in the world but my Consionec would not permit me to take such a step on this account <name type="emotion">I often whr&apos;d to a lonly place</name>, which I had found
						quite to my mind, then I often lamented my state without the least hopes of being helpt through, &amp; sav&apos;d at last but my best &amp; faithfull friend notwithstanding my
						negligence followed me endeavouring to bring me to the place where I at all times bught to have a remaind er at his feet, he thererfore an Oppertunity to show me my state by
						nature &amp; convincd me that noself working would avail me any thing, but he was willing to take my care on himself. I was hereby quite overcome, by his asuring me I was his,
						which so worked on me that I was determin&apos;d to be his intirly with soul &amp; body, and as a poor Sinner to receive grace at his hand. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-03.jpg" />
					<p> My longing was now daily increased to become a partaker of the <name event="sacrament">Holy Sacrement</name> which grace was granted me <date when-iso="1747-11">Nov<hi
								rend="superscript">r</hi> 1747</date> after which I believd simply I should yeild more satisfaction to the <orgName>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></orgName> &amp; my
						self. These thoughts brought me into a very loyal way but could not with my best endeavours effect what I wish for, and having no <name office="laboress" memoirSubject="no"
							>Laboress</name> at that time to help &amp; encourage us, I thought to direct myself, but not being able this way only brought me into confusion. At last I was
						convinc&apos;d that even those who were partakers of his body &amp; blood could lay up no store without a daily &amp; hourly supply from the fountain from whence all good
						springs. Therefore I determin&apos;d to be directed and Influenced alone by him who has often approv&apos;d himself as my friend in need. In the year <date when-iso="17478"
							>1748</date> I mov&apos;d to home <orgName en="œconomy">Oeconomy</orgName> where I liv&apos;d a year <name type="emotion">Chearfully &amp; satisfy&apos;d</name> then there
						being a new <orgName en="œconomy">Oeconomy</orgName> began at <placeName ref="#mlpla000052">Littlemoore</placeName>. I was one that was place&apos;d there where I learnd to
						know more of myself and the leading of our <roleName type="honorific">Saviour</roleName> with me then I was sensible of before. In the <date when-iso="1750">year 50</date> I
						mov&apos;d again to the <orgName en="œconomy">Oeconomy</orgName> at <placeName>Conhouse</placeName>, where I thought to live Chearfully with the rest of my Companions. But here
						I must observe <name type="emotion">I was again disturb&apos;d by my own Corruption</name> of which I thought I had sufficient Knowledge <add place="above">before</add> but
						found the depth of my natural Corrupted heart was unfathomable which made me almost conclude it was unpossible for me to be help to the end of days I was often encouraged by
						those about me to believe I was not to bad for our <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName> but to no purpose, till I felt it scals &amp; made
						clear to my heart by my best friend. He often took such oppertunities as these to melt &amp; bow my heart before him anew, &amp; thereby to make my call &amp; diction of grace
						of greater value to me. The same year the <orgName en="œconomy">Oeconomy</orgName> mov&apos;d to <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">fulneck</placeName> there to reside till the
							<placeName>Choir house</placeName> which was their building, </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-04.jpg" />
					<p> was finish&apos;d, into which as soon as it was ready, I mov&apos;d with the first company, at the entrance of which I again renew&apos;d my Covenant with my d<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi>
						<roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName> and partook of the grace which in a particular manner prevail&apos;d at that time. here as well as in all
						other places &amp; during my whole life <add place="above">notwithstanding</add>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">during</hi> all failings wants &amp; defects I was alway follow&apos;d and often comforted by him who has alway approv&apos;d himself as my only
						effectual Comforter &amp; <roleName type="honorific">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></roleName>. So he will Continue to me to the end of my days. he has often been so visibly
						near my heart as if I had seen him with my bodily eyes, yea I could Converse with him as with an intimate friend about every thing. In the year <date when-iso="1760"
							>1760</date> I had a Call to go to <placeName ref="#mlpla000025">Bedford</placeName>, as it was thought best I went out of Obedience at which place I was receiv&apos;d with
						so much love &amp; heartiness as I can&apos;t express but <add place="above">and</add> I <add place="above">have often</add> reflected on it with thankfullness, So far Her own
						words but meeting with difficulties of various sorts, the employment for which I went there not answering the wish for end, and having a great desire to return to fulneck, as
							<name health="disease">my Bodily Health was also much impair&apos;d</name> I made my desire Known, which after Consideration was consented too &amp; I returnd <date
							when-iso="1770-02-16">feb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 16 1770</date>
						<note>From this point on, memoir is in a different hand.</note> Here she liv&apos;d several years in the <orgName en="œconomy">Sist<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
							Oeconomy</orgName> with great faithfullness till thro bodily circumstances she was oblig&apos;d to retire into the <placeName>Choir House</placeName> there but finding Her
							<add place="above">self no better</add>
						<hi rend="strikethrough">weakness increase</hi> She defin&apos;d &amp; obtaind leave to remove back again to <placeName>The Choir House</placeName> in <placeName
							ref="3mlpla000003">Fullneck</placeName> where she arriv&apos;d <date type="death" when-iso="1770-02-16">Feb 16 1770</date>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
