<?xml-model href="../../TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mary Peel: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Jess Hom</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marita Gruner</persName>
               <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sarah Kannemann</persName>
               <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archive, Fulneck</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel">Mary Peel</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-04.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-19" who="#jschaumberger">Started and finished markup</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>name</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head type="page">1</head>
               <pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-01.jpg" />
               <p>I was born at <placeName>Northarm in the parish of Halifax</placeName> in the year <date type="birth" when-iso="1722-05-29"><add>May 29</add> 1722</date>. My Parents being very
                  religious endeavour'd to bring me up strictly in the fear of <persName type="diety">God</persName>. they very early perceiving my natural turn to be <del>???</del> quick livly and
                  active, on that account took the greater care of me takeing me with them constantly to the <orgName>Decenters</orgName> meetings, as I at that time did not understand their meaning,
                  I look upon it as being very hardly dealt with, but afterwards san clearly that their intentions where only to prevent my entrance on a very loose course of life which I might have
                  fall'n into, had not their unwearied care &amp; faithfullness, been a great means of preserving me, together with an invisible Hand, which I often felt while very young over me
                  without any knowlidge of the meaning thereof for which I shall forever remain thankfull, I went on much in this way till <persName>Mr Inham</persName> came to these parts, to whose
                  preaching the greatest part of the people resorting, I went among the rest, being thereby stir'd up &amp; often brought to reflect on my state, but with out any lasting impression. I
                  remember one night being very thoughtfull when going to bed, I dream'd that I was to be put to death, at which I was very much perplex't, I intreated to be spar'd while I was set to
                  die. The earnestness I was in awoke me, but the impression of this I never lost, &amp; by means of the uncom- mon feelings I had somtimes I thought surly there was some thing to be
                  injoy'd, to which I was as yet a stranger, but was not rightly satisfy'd to be without it. In the <date when-iso="1744" cert="low">year 17</date> the <orgName>Brethern</orgName>
                  <del>???</del><!-- see note in Daily Log gogogle doc -->
                  <add>came</add> into <placeName ref="#mlpla000084">Yorkshire</placeName> with a vein <del>intention</del> to settle societies, accordingly tookdown the names of those who constantly
                  atended the preaching. I therefore was willing to have mine taken down, which was no sooner done, but I was amazingly struck, thinking I am now however fast, but did not repent it. I
                  soon found it was not done the taking down the </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head type="page">2</head>
               <pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-02.jpg" />
               <p>ames but they entended to look more particularly after each one therefore they soon settled Bands to which I was admitted &amp; geting a great <name type="emotion">love</name> for
                  them they were very much bless to me. Some of my Companions being soon after this receiv'd into the <orgName>Congregation</orgName> it Cause'd me many uneasy hours, as I was left,
                  however I thought to try &amp; get to them though I knew not how to set about it, when almost dispairing I often felt exceedingly encouraged and very much strengthened I was not
                  allow'd to go to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> meetings this drove me to the determination to make my mind known which I did by a letter to the Cong<hi rend="superscript"
                     >n</hi> expressing my greatest desire to be embody'd with them. My request was soon granted our in year <date when-iso="1745">1745</date> this was an inex- -pressible grace &amp;
                  favour to me past discribing being then very chearfull I thought I had then got all that could make my happiness compleat. In this way I went on for some time. In the year <date
                     when-iso="1747">1747</date> the first <orgName en="œconomy">Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Oeconomy</orgName> was settl'd at <placeName>Oxhaighs</placeName> I having the favour to be one of
                  the first, I look'd on it &amp; accepted it with a real thankfull heart, &amp; the blessing which I then enjoy'd well never be forgot by me. This <name type="emotion"
                     >happiness</name> lasted for some time but before I was aware it all vanishd away and I was left as much distresst as ever being ready to determin to leave the
                     <orgName>Sisrs</orgName> &amp; take my thing in the world but my Consionec would not permit me to such on this account I often whr'd to a lonly place, which I had found quite to
                  my mind, then I often lamented my state without the least hopes of being helpt through, &amp; sav'd at last but my best &amp; faithfull friend notwithstanding my negligence followed
                  me endeavouring to bring me to the place where I at all times bught to have a remaind er at his feet, he thererfore took an Oppertunity to shen me my state by nature &amp; convincd
                  me that noself working would avail me any thing, but he was willing to take my care on himself. I was hereby quite overcome, by his asuring me I was his, which so worked on me that I
                  was determin'd to be his intirly with soul &amp; body, and as a poor Sinner to receive grace at his hand. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head type="page">3</head>
               <pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-03.jpg" />
               <p>My longing was now daily increased to become a partaker of the <name event="sacrament">Holy Sacrement</name> which grace was granted me <date when-iso="1747-11">Nov
                     1747</date> after which I believd simply I should yeild more satisfaction to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; my self. These thoughts brought me into a very loyal way
                  but could not with my best endeavours effect what I wish for, and having no Laboress at that time to help &amp; encourage as, I thought to direct myself, but not being able this way
                  only brought me into confusion. At last I was convinc'd that even those who were partakers of his body &amp; blood could lay up no store without a daily &amp; hourly supply from the
                  fountain from whence all good springs. Therefore I determin'd to be directed and influenced alone by him who has often approv'd himself as my friend in need. Chearfully &amp;
                  satisfy'd then there being a new <orgName en="œconomy">Oeconomy</orgName> began at <placeName ref="#mlpla000052">Littlemoore</placeName>. I was one that was place'd there where I learnd to know
                  mroe of myself and the leading of our <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName> with me then I was sensible of before. In the <date when-iso="1750">year 50</date> I mov'd again to
                  the <orgName en="œconomy">Oeconomy</orgName> at <placeName>Conhouse</placeName>, where I thought to live Chearfully with the rest of my Companions. But here I must observe I was again disturb'd
                  by my own Corruption of which I thought I had sufficient knowledge <add>before</add> but found the depth of my natural Corrupted heart was unfathomable which made me almost conclude
                  it was uppossible for me to be help to the end of days <del>?????????</del>. I was often encouraged by those about me to believe I was not to bad for our Sav<hi rend="superscript"
                     >r</hi> but to not purpose, till I felt it scals &amp; made clear to my heart by my best friend. He often took such oppertunities as these to melt &amp; bow my heart before him
                  amen, &amp; thereby to make my call &amp; diction of grace of greater value to me. The same year the <orgName en="œconomy">Oeconomy</orgName> mov'd to <placeName ref="#mlpla000003"
                     >Fulneck</placeName> there to reside till the <placeName>Choir house</placeName> which was their <del>in</del> building,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head type="page">4</head>
               <pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_79Peel-04.jpg" />
               <p>was finish'd, into which as soon as it was ready, I mov'd with the first company, at the entrance of which I again renew'd my Covenenat with my d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  <persName type="diety">Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> and partook of the grace which in a particular manner prevail'd at that time. here as well as in all other places
                  &amp; during my whole life <del>during</del>
                  <add>notwithstanding</add> all failings wants &amp; defects I was alway follow'd and often comforted by him who has alway approv'd himself as my only effectual Comforter &amp; Sav<hi
                     rend="superscript">r</hi>. So he will continue to me to the end of my days. he has often been so visibly near my heart as if I had seen him with my bodily eyes, yea I could
                  Converse with him as with an intimate friend about every thing. In the year <date when-iso="1760">1760</date> I had a Call to go to <placeName ref="#mlpla000025">Bedford</placeName>,
                  as it was thought best I went out of Obedience at which place I was receiv'd with so much love &amp; heartiness as I can't express but I have often reflected on it with
                  thankfullness, so far Her own words but meeting with difficulties of various sorts, the employment for which I went there not answering the wish for end, and having a great desire to
                  return to <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>, as my <name type="health">Bodily Health was also much impair'd</name> I made my desire Known, which after Consideration
                  was consented too &amp; I refused <date when-iso="1770-02-16">Feb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 16 1770</date> Here she liv'd several years in the <orgName en="œconomy">Sist<hi rend="superscript"
                        >rs</hi> Oeconomy</orgName> with great faithfullness till thro bodily circumstances she was oblig'd to retire into the Choir through there but finding Her <add>no better</add>
                  <del>weakness increase</del> She defin'd &amp; obtaind leave to remove back again to The <placeName>Choir House</placeName> in <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fullneck</placeName>
                  where she arriv'd <date when-iso="1770-02-16">Feb 16 1770</date></p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
