<?xml-model href="../../TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Susan Smith: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Jess Hom</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marita Gruner</persName>
               <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sarah Kannemann</persName>
               <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archive, Fulneck</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan">Susan Smith</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-05.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-06-20" who="#jschaumberger">Started and finished markup</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>Susan Smith</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head type="page">1</head>
               <pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-01.jpg" />
               <p>The <persName ref="#mlper000273">S. S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sus. S<del>h</del>mith</persName> who departed this life <date type="death" when-iso="1814-12-19">Dec 19<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> 1814</date> has left tho following short account concern ing herself: I was born at <placeName>Morton Bank</placeName>, in the parish of
                     <placeName>Bingley</placeName>
                  <date type="birth" when-iso="1746-01-06">Jan. 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1746</date>. <date when-iso="1746-01-08">Two days after my birth</date> my Mother departed this life and
                  I was put to my grandmother to be nursed. My father went to live for some- time in the <orgName en="œconomy">S B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> Oeconomy</orgName> at <placeName>Smith
                     house</placeName> hear <placeName>Wyke</placeName>, and after a few years he moved to <placeName ref="#mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName> where he was married the 3 time, on this
                  occation he took me home again, being then in my <date when-iso="1753" cert="medium">7th year</date>. I often call to mind the blessings I then injoyed in attending the Childrens
                  meetings, particularly once when <persName>Count Zinsendarf</persName> on our Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> day spoke to us much of our <persName type="diety">Sav<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi></persName> love, and when the meeting was over came to ask each of us separate </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head type="page">2</head>
               <pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-02.jpg" />
               <p>if we loved our <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName> which made a days impression on my heart. I my <date when-iso="1761" cert="medium">15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                     year</date> I came to live in <note>In the "Yorkshire Families" refrence doc, there is an event "sisters’ house Fulneck 31.03.1762". This seems to be the same event that is
                     here.</note> the <placeName>Srs house</placeName> here, I entered with thankfulness, as I felt myself very unworthy of such a privile<del>d</del>ge, I found myself soon at home,
                  lived for sometime very <name type="emotion">happy</name>, and with the meetings I was greatly <name type="emotion">delighted</name>. In externals it was difficult, nothing but
                  spinning, however as long as I was satisfied, I did well; but when I deviated from the right path I grew <name type="emotion">unhappy and discontended</name>, this brought me into
                  trouble and dark- ness, reasoning and dispare, I wish'd to injoy privile<del>d</del>ges in the Congn but had to wait 7 years before I was recd Still my <persName type="diety"
                     >Saviour</persName> had thoughts of peace over me, and gave me grace to reflect on the past time, I felt and found that I had not been attentive to the </p>
               <p> voice of his holy Spirit, nor put my trust and confidence in him, this brought me into deep concern, I wept and prayed many nights and days that our <persName type="diety"
                     >Saviour</persName> would pardon my sins and transgressions, and receive me anew as his property, and I thank him this day, for his pardon, mercy and comfort which he then
                  imparted to me. <date when-iso="1768-11-13">Nov. 13th 1768</date> I was <name type="event" subtype="reception">recd into the Congn</name> and <date when-iso="1772-09-08">Sept 8th
                     1772 </date> I had the favour to <name type="event">partake the first time of the H Comn</name> which proved days of solid belssings to me, and I felt again <name type="emotion"
                     >happy</name> and comfort- able, injoyed our <persName type="diety">Saviours</persName> nearness and the priviliges of the Congn proved a great refreshment and incouragement to my
                  poor and needy soul. But alas! I soon again came into a dark and reasoning way, on which account I had many heavy hours, my uneasiness of mind </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head type="page">3</head>
               <pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-03.jpg" />
               <p>was very great, I went to the H Comn often when I felt and knew it would have been better for me not to partake of this heavenly repast. Often I thought I would run away where I
                  might be seen no more, and once I did set off and went to <placeName>Mortenbank</placeName> to a Relation, but feeling no rest there neither, I returned back again. I shall never
                  forget the kindness then shown to me, of which I was so undeserving, but above all the mercy, love and forbearance of my <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName>, who still had not
                  forsaken me; but kept his hand over me his erring Sheep. I stayed now from the H Comn for several times, the <persName type="diety">Lord</persName> had much to do for me, he pardoned
                  my sins and washed them away in his precious Blood, and the <date when-iso="1780-08-13">13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Aug 1780</date> when I had the great favour again </p>
               <p> to draw near to the table of the Lord to partake of his Body and Blood in the <name type="event" subtype="sacrament">Holy Sacrament</name>, it proved to me an injoyment which I
                  never shall forget. Now when I reflect on my ihequered course, I find thousand reasons to fall down at my <persName type="dietey">Saviours</persName> feet, to thank and praise him
                  for his unwearied faithfulness his patience and longsuffering, and tho I have often grieved him and disobeed the voice of his holy spirit; <hi rend="superscript">still</hi> he sought
                  and found me when I strayed from him, and received me with open arms of mercy. "O thou my gesterday to day and ever "most faithful <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName>. I have
                  nothing more to say, as <persName type="diety">Lord Jesus</persName>! I am a poor Sinner, who would fain thro' the Lambs ransom entrance gain." May he now prepare me for his
                     <placeName type="biblical">heavenly Kingdom</placeName>, where I shall praise him for ever, for what </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head type="page">4</head>
               <pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-04.jpg" />
               <p>he has done for me unworthy sinner here below. Thus far she dictated to a friend in <date when-iso="1809-09">Sept 1809</date>. At that time she was in a very <name type="health">poor
                     state of state of health</name>, and thought that her time here below would not be long. However it pleased the <persName type="diety">Lord</persName> to restore her sofar that
                  she could go about again tho in <name type="health">weakness</name> and feeling many <name type="health">infirmities</name>, whereby her faith and patience was often tried. As she
                  has candidly stated herself the various scenes of trials in which <del>the</del> the <persName type="diety">Lord</persName> has helped her thro' we shall not innumerate any thing
                  now; but unite our thanks and praises with hers, to him, who has had patience with her in time of need, and heard her prayers in the accepted time; who has done all things well, and
                  now brought </p>
               <p> her to her desired haven. Within this last year she <name type="health">suffered much with pain and weakness</name>. On <date when-iso="1814-12-11">Dec. 11</date><hi
                     rend="superscript">th</hi> she injoyed the <name type="event">H. Comn</name> with 5 other Sisters in the <placeName>Sickroom</placeName>, she expressed herself after- wards very
                     <name type="emotion">grateful</name>, and said: "What I felt on this occation I shall "never forget, it was a foretaste "of Eternity, O Eternity! when shall "I once be there, with
                  my dear <persName type="diety">Savr</persName> "surely, it cannot be very long. Tho she grew weaker, yet neither she nor we thought her departure <hi rend="underline">so</hi> near.
                  On the <date when-iso="1814-12-18">18</date><hi rend="superscript">th</hi> in a conversation, when amongst other things she was asked if any thing desturbed her mind, and if she felt
                  quit resigned to our <persName type="diety">Saviours</persName> will? She replied: "I have "done with every thing. but you know "dying has always been an aweful "thing to me,
                     <del>but</del>
                  <hi rend="superscript">however</hi> I have that "firm asurance that our <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="5">
               <head type="page">5</head>
               <pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-05.jpg" />
               <p>"will receive me, poor and worthless "as I am; I can say nothing, "but <persName type="diety">Lord</persName> have mercy upon me! In the evening <hi rend="superscript">she was</hi>
                  pretty easy but in the night she grew very restless and her <name type="health">breathing very difficult</name>, and she prayed fervently to our <persName type="diety"
                     >Saviour</persName> to help her, in the mor ning on the <date when-iso="1814-12-19">19th</date> having received the blessing for her departure she <del>bl</del>breathed her last
                  during the singing of that verse. When in the arms of <persName type="diety">Jesus</persName> thy Lips shall pallid grow. Aged 68 years 11 months. -- </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
