<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Susan Smith: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan">Susan Smith</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-05.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Susan Smith</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-08-30" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Susan Smith</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-01.jpg" />
					<p> The S. S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sus. S<hi rend="strikethrough">h</hi>mith who departed this life Dec 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1814 has left the following short
						account concern ing herself: </p>
					<p> I was born at Morton Bank, in the parish of Bingley Jan. 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1746. Two days after my birth my Mother departed this life and I was put to my
						Grandmother to be nursed. My Father went to live for some time in the S B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> Oeconomy at Smith house hear Wyke, and after a few years he moved to
						Fulneck where he was married the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> time, on this occation he took me home again, being then in my 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year. I often
						call to mind the blessings I then injoyed in attending the Childrens meetings, particularly once when Count Zinsendorf on our Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> day spoke to us
						much of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> love, and when the meeting was over came to ask each of us separate </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-02.jpg" />
					<p> if we loved our Saviour? which made a days impression on my heart. In my 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year I came to live in the S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> house here,
						I entered with thankfulness, as I felt myself very unworthy of such a priviledge, I found myself soon at home, lived for sometime very happy, and with the meetings I was
						greatly delighted. In externals it was difficult, nothing but spinning, however as long as I was satisfied, I did well; but when I deviated from the right path I grew unhappy
						and discontended, this brought me into trouble and dark ness, reasoning and dispare, I wish&apos;d to injoy priviledges in the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> but had to wait
						7 years before I was rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Still my Saviour had thoughts of peace over me, and gave me grace to reflect on the past time, I felt and found that I
						had not been attentive to the </p>
					<pb />
					<p> voice of his holy Spirit, nor put my trust and confidence in him, this brought me into deep concern, I wept &amp; prayed many nights and days that our Saviour would pardon my
						sins and transgressions, and receive me anew as his property, and I thank him this day, for his pardon, mercy and comfort which he then imparted to me. Nov. 13<hi
							rend="superscript">th</hi> 1768 I was rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> into the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> and Sept 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1772 I had the
						favour to partake the first time of the H Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> which proved days of solid blessings to me, and I felt again happy and comfort able, injoyed our
						Saviours nearness and the priviliges of the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> proved a great refreshment and incouragement to my poor and needy soul. But alas! I soon again
						came into a dark and reasoning way, on which account I had many heavy hours, my uneasiness of mind </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-03.jpg" />
					<p> was very great, I went to the H. Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> often when I felt and knew it would have been better for me not to partake of this heavenly repast. Often I
						thought I would run away where I might be seen no more, and once I did set off and went to Mortenbank to a Relation, but feeling no rest there neither, I returned back again. I
						shall never forget the kindness then shown to me, of which I was so undeserving, but above all the mercy, love and forbearance of my Saviour, who still had not forsaken me; but
						kept his hand over me his erring Sheep. I stayed now from the H Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> for several times, the Lord had much to do for me, he pardoned my sins and
						washed them away in his precious Blood, and the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Aug 1780 when I had the great favour again </p>
					<pb />
					<p> to draw near to the table of the Lord to partake of his Body and Blood in the Holy Sacrament, it proved to me an injoyment which I never shall forget. Now when I reflect on my
						chequered course, I find thousand reasons to fall down at my Saviours feet, to thank and praise him for his unwearied faithfulness his patience and longsuffering, and tho I
						have often grieved him and disobeed the voice of his holy spirit; <add place="above">still</add> he sought and found me when I strayed from him, and received me with open arms
						of mercy. &quot;O thou my yesterday to day &amp; ever &quot;most faithful Saviour. I have nothing more to say, as Lord Jesus! I am a poor Sinner, who would fain thro&apos; the
						Lambs ransom entrance gain.&quot; May he now prepare me for his heavenly Kingdom, where I shall praise him for ever, for what </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-04.jpg" />
					<p> he has done for me unworthy sinner here below. </p>
					<p> Thus far she dictated to a friend in Sept 1809. </p>
					<p> At that time she was in a very poor state of state of health, and thought that her time here below would not be long. However it pleased the Lord to restore her sofar that she
						could go about again tho in weakness and feeling many infirmities, whereby her faith and patience was often tried. As she has candidly stated herself the various scenes of
						trials in which the the Lord has helped her thro&apos; we shall not innumerate any thing now; but unite our thanks and praises with hers, to him, who has had patience with her
						in time of need, and heard her prayers in the accepted time; who has done all things well, and now brought </p>
					<pb />
					<p> her to her desired haven. </p>
					<p> Within this last year she suffered much with pain and weakness. On Dec. 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> she injoyed the H. Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> with 5 other
						Sisters in the Sickroom, she expressed herself afterwards very grateful, and said: "What I felt on this occation I shall never forget, it was a foretaste of Eternity, O
						Eternity! when shall I once be there, with my dear Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> surely, it cannot be very long." Tho she grew weaker, yet neither she nor we thought her
						departure <hi rend="underline">so</hi> near. On the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> in a conversation, when amongst other things she was asked if any thing desturbed her mind,
						and if she felt quit resigned to our Saviours will? She replied: &quot;I have done with every thing. but you know dying has always been an aweful thing to me, <hi
							rend="strikethrough">but</hi>
						<add place="above">however</add> I have that firm asurance that our Saviour </p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_6SmithSusan-05.jpg" />
					<p> will receive me, poor and worthless as I am; I can say nothing,  but Lord have mercy upon me!" In the evening <add place="above">she was</add> pretty easy but in the night she
						grew very restless and her breathing very difficult, and she prayed fervently to our  Saviour to help her, in the morning on the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> having
						received  the blessing for her departure she <hi rend="strikethrough">bl</hi>breathed her last during the singing of that verse. <lg type="verse">
							<l>When in the arms of Jesus</l>
							<l>thy Lips shall pallid grow. </l>
						</lg>
						<l>Aged 68 years 11 months.</l>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
