<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Edmund Tattersall: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_43_TattersallEdmund">Edmund Tattersall</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_43_TattersallEdmund-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_43_TattersallEdmund-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_43_TattersallEdmund-03.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Edmund Tattersall</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-16" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Edmund Tattersall</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_43_TattersallEdmund-01.jpg" />
					<p>
						
							Dep<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Aug. 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 1761
							Edmund Tattersalls Course of Life, <del>the</del> Part of which was noted
							down from his own Mouth 
						</p>
					<p>
							I was born (in Heyroid, Worley Township) in ye Parish of Hallifax 5/16 Oct. 1691
							(and baptized in my fathers house by a Church Minister)
							My Father departed this Life when I was 6 Years old. My Mother
							took the Tuition of me, because of a small Estate which I had to expect.
							I was sent to School till I was 10 Years old &amp; learnd to read &amp; write
							Afterwards I was put <del>out</del>
								<add place="above">Ap</add> prentice to a Clothier for 10 Years, and saw
							and heard nothing but wickedness &amp; Irreligion. Being free from my
							Prenticeship I married and followed the Worsted Trade and lead a 
							<del>loose</del> Life of Idleness and Drunkiness &amp; The People &amp; Servants which I 
							employed proved bad and unfaithfull, &amp; I was forced to give up Busi
							ness, designing to go to ye Isle of Man, to a Brother in Law &amp; there to
							follow <add place="above">my</add> Trade afresh, was already on Board the Vessel, but <add place="above">was</add> three <add place="above">2</add> times
							brought back because of the Rebellion in England at that time. After the
							Battle at Preston I came back again &amp; settled in Hallifax &amp; wove <del>to weaving</del>
							resolved to break of from my former wicked Course and to become religious. I had strong Convictions in my Mind &amp; prayed often, but without
							understanding. Once I came amongst some Soldiers who wanted
							to trick me putting money into my pocket, but I <add place="above">being</add> a desperate
							Fellow, got off from them. Half a Year after I went <add place="above">as a</add> Volunteer among
							the Kings Dragoons left my wife and Childr<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>, but staid only 13 weeks
							and then got my Discharge again. Two Years after I listed in ye
							same Reigment &amp; staid <del>again</del>
								<add place="above">no longer then</add> 13 weeks, because I saw so much wicked
							ness &amp; got at length my Dismission, which I desired. I returned to
							my wife and Childr<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> and <del>followed</del>
								<add place="above">my Trade</add>
								<del>weaving</del> in Hallifax. It was
							at this time that I earnestly sought to become religious, went
							every Month to the Communiun in the Church &amp; entred into a Society with some Churchmen who in principles were Calvinists
							with them I continued till I was 49 Years old. At that time I was
							seized with a violent fever &amp; during that Sickness I found that 
							I was not in a State of <del>being saved</del>
								<add place="above">Salvation</add>, I had not that Satisfaction
							and rest, which I thought I had. I recognized from that Illess
							and resolved to join no Party, untill I was better Satisfied in
							my Soul. When the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> came to keep Meetings at the Worlds End
						
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_43_TattersallEdmund-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						
							near Hallifax I went to hear them, liked them well, desired also to
							be in their Society, which was granted the 21 Jan.
						</p>
					<p>
							Amongst the Brethren and in their Preaching I found that w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>
							I wanted I loved them exceedingly, because I was convinced
							that ye Lord was with them, I spared no time nor pain to
							go to hear them and to accompany them from place to
							place &amp; discoursed with them, being mostly concerned <del>for</del>
								<add place="above">abt</add> points
							of doctrine. My wife would not go with me at first, because
							she had not much hopes, that I would continue, being so
							cross &amp; peevish with her, for I was of a proud nature and wantted to be Something.
						</p>
					<p>
							From <del>that</del>
								<add place="above">the</add> time that he <del>was</del> joined be ye B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Word
								concerning his Death &amp; Passion often reached his heart, but his
							pride &amp; seeking to fill his head with Knowledge <add place="above">long</add> stifled <del>his</del>
								<add place="above">our</add>
							d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Work <del>long</del>; he was also of a very talkative <add place="above">Disposition</add>
								<del>nature</del>
							and preached to every one in his family &amp; to others, so that
							to became burdensome to his wife and Child: &amp; to every body
							<add place="margin">ye</add>
								<del>besides</del> whereby he <add place="above">did</add>
								<del>had</del> hurt to himself and others
							<del>they saw that his Spirit &amp; conversation was not agreeing.</del>
							His Labourers told him for of it and he was glad and thankfull for their reproofs but he could not help himself &amp;c. He
							<del>was</del> often melted into Tears and confessed his follies to the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>
							His heart grew more and more attached to the wounded Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; he
							felt himself overcome by his Dying Love, wished &amp; earnsstly
							entreated to be under the special Care of the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; to be in a
							Member of the Congr<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> which also was granted on the 13 Aug
							1749. at <del>Gracehill</del>
								<add place="above">Lambs Hill</add> he was exceeding glad of it, delighted to
							<add place="margin">come</add>
								<del>in coming</del> to the Meetings, and <del>in Conversation with</del>
								<add place="above">to converse with</add> the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>
							and went on chearfully &amp; happy, was beloved <hi rend="superscript">much</hi> by the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>
							and loved them as our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> peculiar chosen Inheritance
							He was made a Partaker of the holy Comunion June 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1750
						</p>
					<p>
							<add place="above">He has been</add>
								<del>These many Years he was</del> troubled <add place="above">these many Yrs</add> with an Asthmatic Disorder
						
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						
							which encreased more &amp; more, so that it became very troublesome to
							him to walk &amp; attend the Meetings. Hewever as long as he could
							creep he would not <add place="above">stay away</add>
								<del>miss coming</del> for said he nothing is such a
							Comfort for my heart Soul and Body <del>than</del>
								<add place="above">as</add> hear of my of cruci-
							fied Lamb and to be in fellowship with my d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>. The holy
							Sacrament was to him the highest Festival, which if he could help he 
							would never miss. He borrowd last March <add place="above">was</add> a twelve month a Galloway to
							come to Wike, but <del>so</del> was a good while after so sore in his Limbs, that
							he could come no more. Aug the 4 he was the last time at the
							Starary in Hallifax at the Quarterly Meeting &amp; received <add place="above">at night</add> his Share
							with some others in the holy Sacram<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>, he tried Sept 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to come
							once more, but was obliged on acct of Illness to go home again
							and from that time his Disorder turnd into a Dropsy his Legs began to swell &amp; at last to break &amp; run <add place="above">wch continued</add> ever since. He could not
							lie in Bed, but sat in a Choir by ye fire Side. Our d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; gracious
							Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> took him now into a <add place="above">peculiar</add> school, <add place="above">which was</add> beneficial to his heart, <hi
									rend="strikethrough">but</hi>
							Dec 16 last Y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> when I was with him and the newly published <add place="above">Christian</add> Magazin
							of a man was mentioned he said. I look upon Mount Olive &amp; Calvary with
							my Lord did penance for me and <del>the rest of Man</del>
								<add place="above">all Mankind</add> &amp; hung as a Lamb
							on the Cross wounded all over to be the best Magazin and Storehouse
							<add place="above">for</add>
								<del>of</del> a Christian, I want to know nothing but Him in his dying form
							He was very glad whenever B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> came to see him, &amp; this was done as 
							often as <del>it</del> could be. <del>Febr</del> Last Febr. he complained much of his Pain
							&amp; Distress, in Body, but above all a Dryness in his heart &amp; that he had
							not a feeling Sense of the d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Saviours precious Nearness, and wept fore
							on account of his Impatience and Peevishness. March 10 he kept an 
							open hearted Band with me and told me, that our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> was so gracious as to help him, in his <add place="above">great</add> outward Poverty, <add place="above">he</add> was ashamed
							more of himself than he <add place="above">did</add>
								<del>was</del> not <del>more</del> rely<del>ing</del>
								<add place="above">more</add> upon him &amp; <add place="above">was not</add> thankfull
							to him enough for all the manifest Proofs of his Loving heart. He
							fell sometimes into reasoning thoughts that he was a Burden to every
							one &amp; wished that our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> might grant him <del>to be dissolved</del> his dissolution.
							I told him, that all these things wch he complaind of arose from one cause
							He should speak thoroughly with our d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> abt <add place="above">the state of</add> his heart and beg a
								drop
							of his ll healing Blood for his Soul, &amp; <add place="above">that</add> the Spirit of Jesus <add place="above">shd</add> take full Possession
						
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_43_TattersallEdmund-03.jpg" />
					<p>
						
							of his heart and <add place="above">that he sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></add> make a blessed use of this blessed Passion <add place="above">Season</add>. His
							wife had been his Nurse and dressed his running Legs till the 27<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>
							of April when she by a <del>Palsy</del> fit <add place="above">of the Palsy</add> was disabled &amp; confined to this
							bed, which made his case still nore pitiable &amp; distressed. He
							could <add place="above">have</add> no relief granted from the Parish, but what some charitable persons did in consideration of the great<del>est</del> poverty to <add place="above">which</add> they
							were reduced <del>to.</del> They were visited at least every fortnight, &amp;
							many an openhearted Conversation kept with them both, which
							proved always a Blessing &amp; Comfort to them, especially June 23
							&amp; July 7, when they both after <del>having</del>
								<add place="above">they had been</add> spoken with fully,
							received their share in the holy <del>Comuni</del> Sacrament on their Sickbed. I was these several months quite pleased with the State of
							his heart, he grew weaker &amp; weaker in Body, his Legs began
							to heal in part and our d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Saviour made a blessed End of all
							his Trouble Grief &amp; Woes by taking him home to himself Aug.
							the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> in the forenoon at 11 oCl. when the Text was Lazarus
							our friend Sleepeth. He had groaned in his dying Tabernacle
							69 Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> 10 Months &amp; 17 days. His Corpse had a lovely, sweet
							aspect bespeaking the happy sleep &amp; Rest <add place="above">wch</add> he had entered into.
						
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
