<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mary Taylor: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor">Mary Taylor</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-05.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#"
				xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
				xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#"> </rdf:RDF></xenoData>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Mary Taylor</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-01.jpg" n="1" />
			<p>
				
					The Course of with of the S. Sister Mary Taylor who Departed
					to our Savior <add place="above">at</add> Fulnec Feb<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> 21 1790
				</p>
			<p>
					I was Born at Moberly in the County of Cheshire July 11<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> 1745
					and Baptized in the Church of England. In my Childrens
					Years I felt some dawnings of Grace in my heart, but did know
					how to value it rightly. In my 10<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> Year my Father took me
					with Him to hear the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi>, and I not a deep impression of our
					Saviors love in my heart, which remained with me for some
					Time. But in my 14<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> Year I began to see my lost Condition
					which soon brought me into dispair, and Satan got such
					power over me, that I believed there was no God, or if there
					was I had no right to Him &amp; I thought Hell its self could
					not contain more misery, than I found dwelt in me, so I
					wished I had never been Born, and that I had no immortale
					Soul to live forever; but Since I had, wish'd that it might
					be distroyed, and not remain inthe number of those Souls
					that was immortal. This led me to think wether or no there
					was a God who had made me &amp; who cou'd distroy my Soul: And
					I conclnded that there was a God, &amp; that he could save some that
					believed on Him. But I had no faith, and thought I must be
					lost. In this Situation I went to hear a Brother preach, the Text
					was at the Time of Ignorance God winketh at, but now
					Commandeth all Men every where to repent. I thought
					if I had but been Ignorant, then I might have hopes.
					but I have been told so often of our dear Savior, and what he
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-02.jpg" n="2" />
			<p>
				
					had done &amp; fuffered for poor Sinners, how often has my Father
					entreated me to go alone and to pray to my Maker &amp; Redeemer
					that He wood have mercy upon my Soul, but I had refulod it.
					All this was set before my heart &amp; Eyes in a clear light. But
					my distress I could tell to no one, and kept my misery to myself
					for I thought no one was as bad as I felt myself to be.
					In my 17<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> Year I went again to hear the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi> preach
					and the Text was a great Comfort to my distressed Soul,
					It was the following He which hath begun a Good Work in
					you, will perform it untill the Day of Jesus Chriest, It
					was as if my dear Savior said to me, this is my work. Give
					thine Heart to me &amp; I will give the rest from thy Labour
					Oh how did my Soul rejoice that she Lord could have mercy
					upon me. In the Year 1762 I moved with my Father
					&amp; Mother to be near the Cong<hi rend="superscript:true;">n</hi> in Duckenfield, where I
					soon got a desire to live inthe Choirhouse, and Obtained
					leave in the Year following to my great Joy. But I must
					confess that I spent my Time there very indifferently &amp;
					did not seek in ernest to know my dear Saviors aim with me
					but was satisfied with some dawnings of his Grace.
					Oct<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> 23<hi rend="superscript:true;">d</hi> 1763 I had the favor to be rec'<hi rend="superscript:true;">d</hi> into the Cong<hi
							rend="superscript:true;">n</hi>
					from this Time I fell into a legal self working way
					striving in my own Spirit &amp; strength to become good, but
					in vain. Thus I spent 4 Years in this miserable self
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-03.jpg" n="3" />
			<p>
				
					<add place="above">righteous</add>
						<del>working</del> way of my own, Sometimes I was weary and
					tired out almost, but still could not leave it off. Till in
					the Year 1767, when I had the grace to become a Condidate
					for the Holy Comuinion. this gave me acdearer imight into
					myself than I had ever had before. I now found that all my
					self working was like a Cob web, &amp; all my self nighteousness
					was as felthy, &amp; that Verse was applicable to my condition.
				</p>
			<p>
					A Garment I myself had gained.
					A Staff I had whereon I lean'd
					Which fell when tryed from out my hand
					My Robe I buent it to a brand.
				</p>
			<p>
					I had alonging desire to be<add place="above">come</add> a Partaker of the highest Good
					but was very timoaroay about it. However my dr Savior
					shewed me the way that as a poor Sinner I must go and
					venture upon his mercy. March the 21<hi rend="superscript:true;">st</hi> 1760 on Maunday
					Thursday I partook for the first Time of the Highest Good
					in the Holy Sacrament, during which I got a deep impress.
					ion of our Saviours sufferings &amp; Death, &amp; it was a time
					of real Blessing to me which I hope never to forget; I went
					on in a still and happy Course for near a Year, when my Father
					&amp; Mother &amp; Brothers agreed to <del>force</del>
						<add place="above">get</add> me away from the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi>
					by telling me that they were a deceitful People and that I
					was already deceived, but I could not believe them; but
					as their designs where frustrated, thay contrived a scheme
					to get meto my Father House by a message that if I would
					see my <del>Father</del> Mother alive I must come immeadsately
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-04.jpg" n="4" />
			<p>
				
					but it was <del>all</del> entirely a Falshood &amp; deceit. "I however went
					to see her I found her rather poorly but no ways danger-
					ously Ill, now sheirintentions was to keep me, and
					when I attempted to go back again, they would not suffer
					me to go &amp; when I set off they fetched me bact, and 
					forced me to stay against my will &amp; at night locked
					me in my chamber, &amp; desired the neighbours to watch
					me least I should leave the House, this continued a whole
					week before I could make my escape. At last I found
					an Oppertunity to get off. on a Dark night, I went
					around about way for Duckenfield, that they might
					not ovortakeme if they pursued me. But my two
					Brothers &amp; two other Men, got to Duckenfield before
					me and placed them selves in the roads that led to the
					S S<hi rend="superscript:true;">rs</hi> House, so that I could not get home without meet
					ing some of them. my Brother happined to be in the
					road where I had to pass. He therefore stoped me and
					called the others to assist Him, they intended to take
					me back by force, but being near the S<hi rend="superscript:true;">rs</hi> House, I cried 
					as loud as I could, that they might hear me and come
					to my assistance, which they did, and came to see
					the reason of my cries, and one ofthem asked me if I
					would go back with the Men or not, I answered that
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_61Taylor-05.jpg" n="5" />
			<p>
				
					I would not return with them they then endeavoured to get
					me at liberty, but one of the Sisters was knocked down by
					one of them, which made them fight in good ernest,
					and the S<hi rend="superscript:true;">rs</hi> being almost come out, at length prevailed
					&amp; I escap'd their hands, tho' I was much bruis'd <del>&amp;</del>
					by the hard usage I had undergone. I was thankful
					to my dear Savior, that I could be at rest again in my
					Choir House, but my Stay in Duckinfield was not long
					for I wrote to my Brother in Fulneck of what had
					happened to me, and He spoke to the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi> there about
					me, <del>wishing</del> thinking that it would be better if I re-
					moved to some other Congregation, this was taken into
					consideration, and I Obtained leave to live in Fulnec,
					accordingly on March the 21<hi rend="superscript:true;">st</hi> 1769 I <del>went</del>
						<add place="above">came</add> to live in the
					Choir House here, where I was thankful to be, altho
					onulwardly I had it harder to procure a Maintenance
					than in Duckenfield, but I believe that the Lord will
					make it answer a good and at last. thus far her own
					Account.
				
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
