<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Charles Henry Conrad Von Larisch: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles">Charles Henry Conrad Von Larisch</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-05.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-08.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-09.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-12.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-13.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Charles Henry Conrad Von Larisch</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-11" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Charles Henry Conrad Von Larisch</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Lindsey House Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1754.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p> After the remains of our dear B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larish were intred, the B<hi
							rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
						<lb/> (among whom where many from London) met in the Family Hall <lb/> in
						Lindsey House and then was Sung that Hymn: O Head so full of  <lb/>Bruises
						&amp; After which the Disciple spoke in English as follows. </p>
					<p> I have but a few words to say on this Occasion, the Liturgy of to <lb/> Day belongs to the
						Evening when our Saviour went from us, the pre <lb/> sent Day has besides
						that, the particular character of all Saints, &amp; that <lb/> gives me a
						handle to speak something of the Saints, &amp; of the nature of a Saint.
						<lb/> &apos;Tis a name quite common in the Bible, and if we hear of a good
						Man <lb/> who left the World 2, or 300 Years ago, then we have not much
						against <lb/> his appearing in that Character, and are not shock&apos;d by
						it, <lb/> but the Ideas we have form&apos;d to ourselves of a Saint are
						such, that <lb/> in the Romish Church itself no body can be called so, till
						1000 <lb/> Years after his Departure. The reason is because one fears, <lb/>
						if any one should remain who had seen that Man or <lb/> Woman he would
						Controul his Sanctity, he would <lb/> say something that would lesson his
						Opinion of his Wor- <lb/>thiness. I am sure one is greatly mistaken in this
						Respect, <lb/> but as we are calld to promote the Sinnership we <lb/> are
						not so Curious to receive that Name, Saint, we <lb/> care not if that
						Charactor should be heard of no more <lb/> but for all that I would not have
						it, that we shou&apos;d <lb/> loose the meaning of the Thing together with
						the name <lb/> Title &amp; Charactor, &amp; should we prove careless in that
						point <lb/> I Fear we should be deprived of a great Charactor in the Gos-
						<lb/> pel Train. A Saint in my Opinion is a Christian, <lb/> who thinks very
						little, who perhaps may be oblig&apos;d to <note>think</note></p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-03.jpg" />
					<p> think of many things on Account of his Business &amp; of his <lb/> Office, but when I say
						he thinks not much, I mean that he <lb/> does not care to think much,
						according to the Inclination <lb/> of his Heart. You will scarcely find a
						Saint among the great <lb/> Men, the Rich &amp; learn&apos;d Men, perhaps
						not among the Gen <lb/> try, or what one calls an easy Person in this World,
						the rea <lb/> son is, because all such charge themselves with too ma <lb/>
						ny Superfluities, while the necessary condition of becoming <lb/> a Saint,
						is not to have a great Store of Idle &amp; unnecessa <lb/> ry things about
						him. Simplicity &amp; plainness is the Distin <lb/> guishing, mark of a
						Saint. I confess that if a Person <lb/> of that Character, happens to want
						Education &amp; of <lb/> Course what one calls all manner of required
						Qualities <lb/> hath absoludely not so much notion of the World, as <lb/> to
						deal in an ordinary Way, in a regular Way, then the <lb/> Sanctity of such a
						Man, may not comand that Honour <lb/> that Awe, that Reverence which is due
						to it as long as he <lb/> lives, &amp; it Seems therefore, that I should be
						afraid to tell <lb/> you now by way of Discourse, what I have already Sung
						<lb/> of my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larish, whom I always thought a
						Saint &amp; <lb/> I beleive there are 100 in the Cattalouge on Dypticks of
						old, <lb/> who were by far not his paramounts, not like him, nor so <lb/>
						much of a Saint as He. He was a Person void of all <lb/> manner of
						Education, he had been neglected in all the <lb/> Necessary things of this
						Life, &amp; after having found the <lb/> Secret, to make himself to be
						forgotten in this World, after <note>having</note>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p> having placed himself behind the Congregation at Hhuth, in <lb/> order to lead a Simple
						Civil Life, &amp; absolutely not regard <lb/> ed by any one, which he
						contriv&apos;d so out of a true Humility, <lb/> for He was a Lord, &amp; had
						then many Subjects, &amp; a great <lb/> Territory of his own. When he was in
						that Situation <lb/> he came hither, and met with one of the most Difficult
						<lb/> Tasks which can be imagin&apos;d, nevertheless he atcheiv&apos;d &amp;
						per <lb/> formd it with such surprising Simplicity &amp; wisdom, that <lb/>
						I cant help owning once more, that I should have been <lb/> embarrass&apos;d
						in the highest degree to do the like: And I must add <lb/> that if after my
						Decease one would compare me to that great <lb/> Man, &amp; my Conduct to
						his many Personal Circumstances, as <lb/> well as real Intricacies, which
						would be too long to relate <lb/> here (the Saviour knows them, &amp; part
						of us are not Igorant <lb/> thereof,) it would be mere Courtesey. B<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi>. Larish fullfill&apos;d <lb/> his Task with
						Honour, &amp; has not left one leaf of his Book <lb/> unfinish&apos;d. His
						end was like to that of all truly great Men, a <lb/> little while before he
						had not the least thought of going home <lb/> he was Sick, &amp; a very long
						time knew his sase almost incurable <lb/> but drew no Consequence from it
						for in approaching Dissolution. <lb/> When he was acquainted of the Turn his
						Sickness had taken <lb/> &amp; of the approaching Dissolution, &apos;twas
						very well, &apos;twas <lb/> all the same to him. Those Days passed away in
						the same <lb/> Strain as the foregoing. He treated that awful matter as
						simple <lb/> Natural &amp; unconcerndly fill the last gasp as usual, that
						<lb/> none of the Heroes of this world, nore of the great Geniuses <lb/>
						needed to be asham&apos;d of the same Exit, Considering the thing in
							<note>itself</note></p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-05.jpg" />
					<p> itself &amp; without that difference, which makes his case so <lb/> much happier than
						theirs, as for that, He will never <lb/> change his Exit for that of any
						Hero of this World, of <lb/> any great man or Philosopher whatsoever that is
						quite <lb/> out of Question, all I have to say on that part is, <lb/> that
						he departed this Life like a Hero. </p>
					<p> Every one enabled from above to see the hidden Side <lb/> of things, their real Charactor
						to extricate the real <lb/> point out of appearances, will never Contradict
						my opinion, <lb/>about his abode here, having been like his Departure <lb/>
						I wish with all my Heart, that so many brave B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>
						&amp; S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
						<lb/> so many wise ones so many well Educated, so many truly <lb/> learned
						ones. And which is the best of all so many of our <lb/> Sinnerlike good
						People may obtain. </p>
					<p> His Natural &amp; Simple Charactor that they who <lb/> had not the good fortune to have
						known him personally <lb/> may be encouragde thereto by his pretty End. </p>
					<p> What I have said is only Introductory to that little <lb/> Hymn which I have Compos&apos;d
						on his Account &amp; which <lb/> perhaps will be Translated. </p>
					<p>
						<hi rend="underline">Next follows some Account of his Life &amp;
							Departure</hi>
						<lb/> Our dear B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charles Henry Conrad von
						Parish, was born <lb/> Sept 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1711 in
						Gradenwiz near Cosel in upper Silesia. He <lb/> was descended from the
						Ancient Famous Family of the Courts <lb/> &amp; Lords of Larish, also of the
						Lineage of great Nimsdorff <lb/>
						<add place="above">one</add> of whom, in the Service of our Sav<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi> is already a grain of  <note>what</note></p>
					<cb />
					<p> Wheat in Surinam. He inherited from his parents the Lord- <lb/> ships of Shossloehiz Lomniz
						Zonade &amp; Rodewiz. In his <lb/> tender Youth he became acquainted with
						Abbot Steinmez &amp; o- <lb/> ther Servants of God, by means of the well
						known great Just <lb/> ness awakening, &amp; he was concern&apos;d about his
						Salvation very <lb/> much, this continued for some time, &amp; on this
						account he staid a- <lb/> while in <del>Neustad</del>
						<add place="above">Mandel</add> with Abbot Steinmetz, was at Werningrode
						<lb/> Halle &amp; other Places, where he thought perhaps he might get a
						<lb/> Blessing for his Heart. Since 1731 he has been acquainted <lb/> with
						the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> as well in Jena as in other Places &amp;
						came <lb/> from time to time to Visit the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>
						in Hhuth, where the <lb/> Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> came ever nearer
						to his Heart. He found no true rest <lb/> from all his good Performance, nor
						was delivered from his An <lb/> xiety till he resolv&apos;d in the Year 1739
						to become the intire <lb/> Reward of the Smart of Jesus, at the same time he
						got <lb/> a Conviction to let every thing be as it was, &amp; to betake him-
						<lb/> self to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> to stay there;
						accordingly he did so, with <lb/> a true Blessing for his Heart, &amp; he
						had at that time true- <lb/> ly blessed times for his Heart with the Single
							Br<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> assist- <lb/> ed also quite faithfully
						in Building their Choir House <lb/> there. He was also soon received into
						the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; partook <lb/> of the Corps &amp;
						Blood of Jesus in the Sacrament with <lb/> the Cong<hi rend="superscript"
							>n</hi>. </p>
					<p> In May 1742, He came over to Engl. were he staid for some <lb/> time especially in
							Yorks<add place="above">hire</add> &amp; was edifying to the Cong<hi
							rend="superscript">n</hi> in his <lb/> Servants office in the Hall which
						he perform&apos;d very faith-  <note>fully</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-08.jpg" />
					<p> faithfully &amp; with his whole Heart from thence he returned in com- <lb/> pany with the
						Dr Disciple &amp; Mother to Holland &amp; so on to <lb/> M-born &amp; was
						there May 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1743. Married to our S<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi>. Diana <lb/> Raymond after his marriage her
						his Wife were 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Deacons in <lb/> Engl &amp;
						conducted it with true Simplicity &amp; many Bles- <lb/> sings afterwards he
						made Several Journeys to Hhuth &amp; <lb/> Hhaag, in this Year also he
						visited his Lordships &amp; found him- <lb/> self not only not in a Capacity
						to execute what he had in- <lb/> tended, but found also such an Entanglement
						in his worldly <lb/> Affairs, that he thought it best to sell his Estates,
						to pay <lb/> he Debts, &amp; to give the rest to the Diaconate of the Enity
						<lb/> which at that time was much streighten&apos;d, for wch in the <lb/>
						Year 1740 the New House calld Lichtenburg was made over to <lb/> him &amp;
						fitted up, but because his comfort did not like to tarry <lb/> at Hhaag, he
						went with her first to Zyest &amp; in the last <lb/> Year again to Engl;
						&amp; enjoyed by his abode in each Place of <lb/> those Cong<hi
							rend="superscript">ns</hi> much Grace &amp; Blessings for his Heart,
						&amp; all <lb/> the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; S<hi
							rend="superscript">rs</hi> lov&apos;d him, he had a longer attachment
						&amp; faithful <lb/> Heart full of love to our Sav<hi rend="superscript"
							>r</hi> &amp; his Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; amidst the va-
						<lb/> rious Circumstances w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> his weak
						constitution mostly occasi- <lb/> ond. He was never put off from his point,
						but his Heart al- <lb/> ways long&apos;d after him, whom he can now see
						bodily &amp; kiss his <lb/> Wounds. </p>
					<p> The latter Years of his mortal Life he was very Sickly &amp; had <lb/> many disorders in
						his Body, but especially since the Winter <lb/> 53 yet as long as it was
						possible he came to the Opportunities <lb/> in the Disciples House very
						diligently &amp; with great Chearfull-  <note>ness</note>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p> cheerfulness. According to the Nature of His Disease and frequent casaul <lb/> ties of all
						sorts He thought nothing at first of going home, till just <lb/> after his
						Birthday this year when the Watchword was untill the <lb/> glance extend
						throughout &amp; then he came upon it very happily <lb/> himself, and he was
						heard to say when by <del>by</del> himself, to our <lb/> Saviour: My Dear
						Saviour be thou my all in all &amp; round a- <lb/> bout me, I am indeed
						weak, but thou knowest well how to make <lb/> it better, and he said: I am
						indeed spent or very weak, but I <lb/> shall soon go into the Regions of
						health. Another time, when <lb/> he was in great pain he comforted himself
						with the sufferings <lb/> of our Saviour, &amp; rejorced at the sweet hour
						of his release, &amp; <lb/> only wish&apos;d that our Saviour wo&apos;d take
						him to himself in <lb/> sleep. As he pressd very much to have all his
						Temporal affairs <lb/> concerning him and his regulated while he was here,
						therefore <lb/> the Synodal Conclusion of 1753, was thro&apos; the
						interposition <lb/> of the Disciples House but a few days before his end in
						<lb/> the name of our God brought into the form customary <lb/> here, and
						tho&apos; all the necessary forms are yet wanting from both <lb/> the
						Married parties, yet the Deed is delivered to the satisfac- <lb/> tion of
						all sides. Oct 26 He got a new disorder &amp; said: that now <lb/> he was
						ready to waite for the last kiss, when the Brn at his <lb/> desire sung him
						some verses he rejoyced and said O that <lb/> has strengthned me, &amp; so
						continued in continual thought <lb/> of going home till the 28 of Octo<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi> when he said: to this Ser- <lb/> vant Bro<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi> Summerskill, this Ev&apos;ning or Tomorrow
						<lb/> morning the expected hour will <add place="above">come</add> &amp;
						often asked, is it not yet <lb/> time he sent also 2 or 3 times in the night
						for B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Johan <note>to</note></p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-09.jpg" />
					<p> to come and bless him, and when Joh came to him, and sung: pale <lb/> Lips kiss him upon
						the Heart, he said; o yes, and to that Verse and <lb/> when thy Mouth
						expiring &amp;c. He said even to Day. </p>
					<p> Oct 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Towards Morning he took leave of his Wife and said:
						<lb/>My dear I kiss thee on thy Heart, here I have been thy Hus <lb/> band
						and thy Heart, we was both one Body but now no <lb/> more, I an going to our
						dear Saviour and shall expect <lb/> thee with my Bridegroom with Joy:
						Afterwards he <lb/> said to B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Summerskill and
						his Wife, my dear Children for <lb/> give me every thing and I thank you for
						all the Love and <lb/> faithfulness that you shew&apos;d me here and the
							B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> will think <lb/> on you for it,
						thereupon he said to his Maid (who is no <lb/> Sister) adue I thank you also
						for all you have done for me, I <lb/>wish you well in the World, about Six
						o&apos;Clock in the <lb/> Morning he desired Brother John<hi
							rend="superscript">s</hi> to be called <lb/> again, because he was very
						weak but re- <lb/> cover&apos;d himself as soon as he saw him w<hi
							rend="superscript">ch</hi>
						<lb/> he did several times before; The rest of the <lb/> Time he was mostly
						as if he was a- <lb/> sleep, &amp; had thereby sometimes such an <lb/>
						extraordinary lovely &amp; smiling look <lb/> that the eyes of the Brethren
						&amp; Sisters <lb/> round about him overflowed. Hutton <lb/> said once, such
						a look is worth more <note>than</note>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p> than 100 Guineas, at last he awoke, rais&apos;d <lb/> himself and said to Brother Johannes
						<lb/> now Bless me, &amp; then he took his hand &amp; <lb/> laid it himself
						upon his forehead, &amp; <lb/> so Johannes Blessed him with that <lb/>
						Verse: &amp; let his Mouth expiring on <lb/> thy dear Breast recline &amp;c.
						to <lb/> which our dear happy heart said yes <lb/> powerfully: Ater the
						Blessing <lb/> he look&apos;d about once more, when <lb/> he saw Bro<hi
							rend="superscript">r</hi>. Johannes, Wallerville <lb/> Hutton &amp;
						others standing round <lb/> him, he threw them a kiss, &amp; said: <lb/>
						<add place="above">Fare you well</add> Adue sweetly the holy Ghost has <lb/>
						impress&apos;d upon all upon my heart <lb/> thy committed to him many Sa-
						<lb/> lutations <add place="above">&amp; kisses</add> to the Saviour and
							<note>the</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb n="6" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-12.jpg" />
					<p> the Church above made perfect <lb/> &amp; perticularly our dear Blessed <lb/> Christle, and
						he promissd it <lb/> with a plain Yes. His last <lb/> Words were: We all
						live unto <lb/> him &amp; then he shut his eyes <lb/> again and slept &amp;
						so accord- <lb/> ing to his wish his Spirit was <lb/> kiss&apos;d away in
						Sleep &amp; the Brn <lb/> &amp; Sisters round him <add place="above">sung
							him</add> quite into <lb/> his rest. His Tabernacle displayed <lb/> a
						very happy look with which <lb/> the Brethren &amp; Sisters present <lb/> in
						Sarons hall delighted them- <lb/> selves </p>
					<cb />
					<p>
							<hi rend="underline">Made by the dear Disciple on Br L. Departure</hi>						
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>1.<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Thou venerable Child of Grace </l>
							<l>Go in thy white and Blood wash&apos;d Dress</l>
							<l>To live there henceforth without Sin</l>
							<l>where many a Soul &apos;fore thee hath been :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="2">
							<l>2.<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> on all Saints Day thy Corpse is laid</l>
							<l>In God&apos;s green pretty Sharon&apos;s Bed</l>
							<l>Where it shall sweetly rest, till He</l>
							<l>Thinks fit to Change it Gloriously :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="3">
							<l>3.<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> from the Disciples House there are</l>
							<l>Already Sevral Grains Sown there, </l>
							<l>Marigens and her little ones</l>
							<l>* Kleists, Millers, &amp; Golds Little Sons</l>
							<l>and Christels Bones <note type="foot">Or * Kleists, Millers, Gold's Child's mortal Bones and my own son's</note></l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="4">
							<l>4.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> That Corpse is now laid in the Grave to </l>
							<l>On whose account no doubt we have,</l>
							<l>But he who did inhabit it</l>
							<l>Will fetch it Back when quite made fit :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="5">
							<l>5.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Now thou that Body&apos;s noble Guest</l>
							<l>Who us so edified hast</l>
							<l>Because thy Farewell was like that</l>
							<l>which we of Fredrick Whilhelm Great</l>
							<l>Commemorate</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Or *Kleists, Millers, Gold&apos;s Child&apos;s mortal Bones</l>
							<l>and my own Son&apos;s</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb n="7" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-13.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="6">
							<l>6.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Thou wert presentis Animi</l>
							<l>Ev&apos;n in thy Farewell Agony</l>
							<l>Some Days thou&apos;st ready for Adieu</l>
							<l>So that thy our Friend &amp; Mother too</l>
							<l>their Pleasure view</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="7">
							<l>7.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I saw it when that Angel dear</l>
							<l>Who waited on our Larish here</l>
							<l>Went to his B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>. He did say</l>
							<l>Beloved only think I pray :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="8">
							<l>8.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I thought I waited on a Sheep</l>
							<l>Which happen&apos;d on his Path to keep</l>
							<l>But in its Exit turn&apos;d at length</l>
							<l>To Heroism that little Strength :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="9">
							<l>9.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> This last Act finds so much Applause</l>
							<l>That Ev&apos;n a Christle hath no cause</l>
							<l>To blush at it, when Ludwig shall</l>
							<l>So clear and chearful leave his Call</l>
							<l>O very well.</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="10">
							<l>10.<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>h Should one ask seriously: How so? </l>
							<l>What is it that makes Larish go</l>
							<l>So nobly, &amp; afford a Sight</l>
							<l>of which God&apos;s House hold w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Delight</l>
							<l>Saith. That is right?</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="11">
							<l>11.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I answer Larish may be stil&apos;d</l>
							<l>In all Respects a simple Child</l>
							<l>A Child, as Scripture teaches us</l>
							<l>Is otherwise Synonimous</l>
							<l>with Genius.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="12">
							<l>12.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Swift&apos;s Wit did end in Lunacy</l>
							<l>A Clark doth loose his Forced Esprit</l>
							<l>Ev&apos;n Newton turns a Simpleton</l>
							<l>But Larish, when ripe to be gone</l>
							<l>a Solomon.</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="13">
							<l>13.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Thou Partner of this Man, attend</l>
							<l>And ponder well his happy End</l>
							<l>Let thyself in Child&apos;s Mould be cast</l>
							<l>To shall you be right nobly grac&apos;d</l>
							<l>and shine at last</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="14">
							<l>14.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> All ye who&apos;re Saints because the Lamb</l>
							<l>Did take upon him your Sins Shame</l>
							<l>Salute him ye who&apos;re gone to Christ</l>
							<l>You here; turn Children be advis&apos;d</l>
							<l>and so Baptiz&apos;d</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
