<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Anna Margretta Walker: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta">Anna Margretta Walker</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta-05.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#"
				xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
				xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#"> </rdf:RDF></xenoData>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Anna Margretta Walker</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta-01.jpg" n="1" />
			<p>
				
					Anna Margretta Walker was Born in fulneck <add place="above">went home</add> Apl 23<hi rend="superscript:true;">d</hi> 1770
					Sept<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> 20: 1763, and was soon after Baptised by Br<hi rend="superscript:true;">o</hi>
					Latrobe, the was a lively and healthy Child till she
					was nine Months old, when she got the hooping Cough
					which left something upon her Stumoc of a Consumptive nature
					which remained with her to the very last, soon after she
					begun to speak she took great, delight in Learnong verses
					the first of which was I am a little Child you see etc.
					and what verse soever she learnt She always Learnt
					the right Tune along therewith, for which she had a
					special gift, her most faverit verses were, heartily
					Love I she Lamb etc. The Lord I love with Tender awe etc
					look on me Lord till I do weep etc Grace how good how
					cheap how free etc The Saviours Blood and Righteousness
					and many more which would be too tedeous to Mention
					a year and half ago when a School was begun in the Sis<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> house
					for the girls in the place, She Rejoised greatly there at
					and has so much as her health wou'd admit of always gone
					and it has been observd it has been special Blessing
					to her, last Novembr She got a Fever which brought
					her very weak but after wards Recovered prety well
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta-02.jpg" n="2" />
			<p>
				
					Derectly after which she took the small pox, but came
					very well thro, and was for a short time more healthy
					than she used to be, and went in the School again, and
					when any of the girls or Sisters went home and She
					saw their Corps, it maid a great impresion upon her,
					and she could not speak enough of their buty, and
					often spoke how much She Longed to be like them
					and tould some of her Companions that they should
					come and see her when she was a Corps, and spoke
					often with her father and Mother how they Should dress
					her when she was a corps, and what she would
					have in the coffin with her, but her greatest care
					was about the watch word which was on her Birthday
					for this year the Sisters in the School having writ of
					her on apice of printed paper, when she Brought
					it to her. Father, she said. I will have this put in 
					my hands in the coffin with me,* She has complained
					for these three Months last frequently of head ace, and
					in pasion week She went one night to the meeting in 
					the hall and Spoke with a peculiar delight of being
					at great Sabbath and took care to have at her clothes
					Clean for that day, but on Tusday in the night She
					was shakon with a vilant pucking and headach
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta-03.jpg" n="3" />
			<p>
				
					which Continualy increased, and altho' she took
					medcin, yet neither that nor any thing els would
					rest upon her Stomoc. So that it was plain that our dear
					Saviour intended to take her into his Eternal Security
					when She was askd at any time what she wanted she
					always answred, I want our Saviour to come, when askd
					if She would grow Better, She always said I will go to
					our Saviour and would hear of nothing als
					on Ester Sunday night she begun to have Convelsions
					So that we though She would Soon go home, but on the Monday
					the doctor aplied something which gave her a little ease
					till Friday night, when her convulitions Returnd again
					So that one Expected her going home every houre, but She
					still continued all that day and night, and Sunday having
					Convultions continually, during the whole week
					She was frecquantly visited by the Sisters both day and
					night, which is hereby acknowledged with thankfulness
					on Sunday in the night the convulsions left her and she 
					Lay quite Still till half an hour past 5 on Monday morning
					when her happy soul took flight into the wounds of her beloved
					Saviour with the Blessing of the Cong and her choir aged 6 years
					7 Months and 3 days
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_16_WalkerAnnaMargretta-05.jpg" n="4" />
			<note>The text of this insertion is denoted to be part of the text of page 2 of this document.</note>
			<p>
				
					*The text on her Birth Day was on the 20<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> of Sept
					my flesh and my heart faileth, but god is the 
					Strength of my heart, and my position for ever.
					There's nought, that me can part from Jesus in
					life or death vicissitude; I lay my hand in his side
					precious and say, thou'st my Lord and my God."
					The S<hi rend="superscript:true;">rs</hi> observe as to her disposicon she was of a lively &amp; acttive
					turn though sometimes when her own will
					showed it self it gave her and her Sisters some
					trouble but when she was reminded of it she
					soon was a sinner and beged us to forgive her
					which we readyly did for she was tenderly beloved
					by her Sisters and School companions
				
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
