<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>George Wood: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_52_WoodGeorge">George Wood</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_52_WoodGeorge-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_52_WoodGeorge-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_52_WoodGeorge-03.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">George Wood</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-16" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>George Wood</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_52_WoodGeorge-01.jpg" />
					<p>
						
							Departed Feb 3, 1761
							Personalia of the single B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> George Wood, who in his sick room
							left the following Acc<hi rend="superscript">t </hi>of himself.
						
					</p>
					<p>
						
							I was born at Holbeck in the Parish of Leeds August 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1735
							My Father was a native of Ireland &amp; my Mother a Yorkshire Woman.
							When I was about 2 years old my Father left my Mother to Care
							for herself &amp; Children &amp; went into Ireland. My Mother brought
							me up as well as she could, but on Account of Poverly was not
							able to give me any Schooling, the Loss of which I have experienced
							the most since I come amongst the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>; for as I had not learn&apos;d to 
							read, I was deprived of that Opportunity which my B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> have, of
							entertaining themselves, with reading something agreeable about
							our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, in their sabbatic Hours: But this Loss has been sufficciently restored by our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> in granting me his precious
							Nearness, whenever I wept for him!
						
					</p>
					<p>
						
							In my Youngest Years, I was a Child of a quiet Disposition,
							and liked best to be alone because when I happened to come into
							the Company of other Children, something generally occurred
							about which my Mind was uneasy afterwards, I therefore kept
							chiefly <hi rend="superscript">by</hi> to myself &amp; often took a Walk alone, feeling my Mind
							most easy and chearful in this Course.
						
					</p>
					<p>
						
							In my 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Year, I was put apprentice to my Uncle Stancliff
							who was then amongst the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>, to be a Clothier &amp; the first Sunday
							he took me with him to Grace Hall, on which Day I felt something
							powerful in my Heart from our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>., What I heard &amp; felt had
							such an Effect that I could not miss one Meeting afterwards
							to which I was allowed the Priviledge of going. I soon got acquainted with dear B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Held, who gave me Leave to go to all the
							Childrens Meetings, Bands &amp; Classes, which proved a real Blessing
							to my Heart. &quot;When I was about 14 Years old I was rec<hi rend="superscript">d </hi>amongst
							the great Boys by B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charlesworth from which Time I attended
							the Boys Meetings diligently &amp; with Pleasure not obtaining any
							Thing particular in Mind or Body to what I had done in my
							Childrens Years, but felt our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> near my Heart, &amp; was well
							in the Meetings of the Boys; yet during all this time tho&apos; I felt
							very well, I had not a real &amp; solid Connexion &amp; Conversation
							with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> as a Sinner, which afterwards was made clear to me.
						
					</p>
					<p>
						
							In any 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Year I begun to perceive my natural Depravity and
						
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_52_WoodGeorge-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						
							Corruption pretty strongly, promting me to things which I know very
							well were against the Mind, <del>of</del> &amp; Heart of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, but has <add place="above">not</add> sufficient
							acquaintance with Him &amp; Foundation in my own Heart to make the
							right Use of him in these new Circumstances, &amp; was therefore brought
							into Darkness &amp; great Perplexity of Mind, so that I was sometimes
							very dubious how it would at last End with me, yet <del>the</del> in the
							bottom of my Heart I had a real desire to be helped into a happy
							clear Track but my greatest Misfortune was a false shame, which
							caused me to conceal <del>the</del> my true Condition &amp; the Cause of my Differences
							from my labourers, but being frequently visited <del>by</del> at that time
							by B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Renatus, he perceived I was not so clear &amp; lively as usual &amp;
							wanted to know the cause, but which I avoided telling, till I could
							hold out no longer, being compelled by the great Misery of my Heart
							to disclose every thing wherewith I was bound &amp; entangled, &amp; which
							indeed proved very happy for me in its Consequences. I then could
							&amp; did speak with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> in a sinnerlike, confident Manner, &amp; often
							times fell on my Face before <add place="above">him</add> &amp; wept bitterly, till He melted my
							Heart with his Nearness &amp; rich Forgiveness, &amp; cheared me with his
							friendly look. I then resolved to devote my Soul &amp; Body just as
							it was to him, &amp; to speak quite openheartedly with my Labourers
							about all my Circumstances for I felt the sweets of it, &amp; since I
							made that Resolution it has been my constant practice to my surprising ease &amp; Blessing. From this time, I have had a happy Connexion with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, I went every Night into the Fields after I
							had donemwork to speak with the Friend of my Soul, whom incomparable Nearness &amp; presence always met me, so that my Eyes &amp; Heart
							were often overflowing with gratitude, on Account of what he had
							done for &amp; manifested to me. My concern about the Preservation
							of my Soul &amp; body was often the Subject of my Conversation with Him
							&amp; therefore I pray&apos;d him with Tears to make a Way for me to the Choir House
							for I felt no place else in all the world could satisfy me. Some Weeks,
							after I was loose of my Apprenticeship, I had the Joyfull
							News brought me that our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> had given me Leave to come I live
							in the Choir House which Grace I accepted of with thousand thanks
							to my dear Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, who thus graciously heard &amp; granted my Request
							&amp; soon after I came with Joy &amp; gratitude of heart into my beloved
						
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						
							Choir house in my 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year July the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1756, and Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: the 22<hi rend="superscript"
									>d</hi> the
							same year had the Grace to be rec&apos;<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> into the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> to my inexpressible
							Joy, and went the first Fine to the holy Communion with my clear Single
							B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> at a Choir Communion June 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1757 whereby my highest Wish
							next to that of seeing &amp; embracing him bodily was granted me, &amp;
							which I shall never forgot.
						
					</p>
					<p>
						
							About Easter in the Year 1759 a <del>gathered</del> Humour <del>came</del>
								<add place="above">fell</add> into
							one of my Feet &amp; broke out in a running Ulcer whereby I was
							incapable of earning my bread for a long Time. I made Use of
							many things &amp; also by Advice went to the how, not without long
							&amp;effect the areal here was not wrought by any thing I tried of
							did for tho it healed one quarter it broke out the next &amp; now a Consumption <del>came</del>
								<add place="above">added</add> thereto, so that I have a near Prospect of soon
							kissing the Points in Hands and feet for my Grace Election
							I wait in my Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hands &amp; Friendship with ardent Desire
							the happy End of all Complaint when I shall grow pallid
							in Jesus Arms &amp; Lap.&quot; So far his own account.
						
					</p>
					<p>
						
							To which we will only add, that his course amongst us from
							first to last has been as a <add place="above">youth</add> of God, solid, steady &amp; annointed.
							and his Heart past has <del>has</del> lived in a tender uninterrupted connexion
							with the Man of Sorrows, so that it was always a pleasure to keep Band
							with him. We kept his Hearts object constantly in View &amp; suffered
							nothing to disturb him in the Enjoyment thereof, so that we have
							had no Grief, but always Joy over him, &amp; some Years <add place="above">since</add> when the
							<add place="above">situation of</add>
								<del>it looked precarious with</del> many of our young Single B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>
								<add place="above">seemed very precarious</add> he was
							not in the least disturbed thereby in his happy Track, but cleaved
							the more closely to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; was heartily glad of &amp; thankful
							for his election.
						
					</p>
					<p>
						
							<add place="above">From the time that</add>
								<del>After the above mentioned</del>
								<add place="above">His</add> Sickness would not permit him to receive
							<del>work</del> any longer <del>at</del> he busied himself with such little
							Matters as he could do in the House &amp; which he did with Faithfulness
							&amp; Pleasure as long as he could, &amp; till he betook himself entering 
							to the Sick Room. Here he enjoyd a perfect Sabbath in the Nearness
							of his bleeding Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. It was a Pleasure to visit him &amp; speak with
							him abt. our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. He never liked to hear any thing about his reco-
							very but wish'd <add place="above">that</add> his happy Hour <add place="above">might soon</add> strike. He was patient in his Sickness
							to Admonition for said he, our Savr&apos;s Nearness makes my Sickness tolerable &amp; Happy.
						
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_52_WoodGeorge-03.jpg" />
					<p>
						
							&amp; <add place="above">was</add> thankful to his Brn, as also to to his Sick Waiters for every Thing he
							enjoyed. <del>At</del> the last <add place="above">time he was spoken with</add>
								<del>Speaking</del> before the Communion he said I think 
							this will be the last Time I <add place="above">shall</add> enjoy His Corpse Blood here &amp; when 
							it was brought to him he enjoyd it with great Devotion &amp; a particular
							aweful Feeling attended it.
						
					</p>
					<p>
						
							The 2 last times he Class was kept he decided it might be in his 
							Sick Room, which was granted. he told his Class B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> that his longing 
							to be with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> was the only Concern he now had and entreated
							them to beg our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> to hear him soon. Feb 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> he was so very
							weak that we expected him soon to go Home. His Heart&apos;s Situation and
							Longing to go home was charming and pretty: Love verses were sung
							for him &amp; tho he could speak no more yet he gave signs with a 
							most lovely childlike Aspect &amp; said at the end of every Verse, moor.
							Feb the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> betwixt 3 &amp; 4 in the Morning he called to his Sick Waiter
							&amp; wanted to get up. Upon being ask&apos;d Why? he answered, &quot;I am not
							yet at Home, I want to go home to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.&quot; He was told that
							our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> would soon come &amp; take him to himself which he 
							was <add place="above">much</add> pleased to be assured of, &amp; thus he continued quite unfit
							to his last Moment when about 8 o&apos;Clock his Friend beckon&apos;d
							to him, &amp; he grew pale in Arms &amp; Legs wiht the Blessing
							of his Choir during the singing the Word &quot;And now his 
							Mouth expiring on thy dear Breast recline &amp;c and with 
							these fine Tents, <hi rend="underline">The Sparrow hath found an House, and </hi>
							<hi rend="underline">the Swallow a Nest.</hi> lit: Tent. <hi rend="underline">With my Spirit within me</hi>
							<hi rend="underline">I seek thee early. My Saviour, Ah! was I with Thee.</hi>
							The Feeling attending his Separture was inexpressible, &amp;
							caused the Eyes of the B<hi rend="superscript">rn </hi>presant to overflow, our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
							was indeed there tho our Eyes could not see Him yet the
							Feeling testified it sufficiently.
						
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
