<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Liley_Robert_Ful_3_70</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Our Br Robert Lilley was born in the Month of Octr.</l>
					<l>1697 at High Town in the Parish of Berstal and was</l>
					<l>educated in the established church. His Parents being</l>
					<l>poor, he was put out Apprentice very young, and suffered</l>
					<l>during that time a deal of Hardship. Having learned</l>
					<l>the Clothiers Bussiness and being now 26 years of age,</l>
					<l>he entered into the married State with the present Widow,</l>
					<l>which Marriage our dear Lord Blessed with 1 Son and</l>
					<l>2 Daughters. One of the latter went happily to our</l>
					<l>dear Savr before him, out at the S. Srs House here. His</l>
					<l>only Son James is an inhabitant of Fulneck Congn.</l>
					<l>and the other Daughter is married in the World.</l>
					<l>During the time of the great awakening here in</l>
					<l>Yorkshire, when Mr Ingham and others preach&apos;d the Word</l>
					<l>of Reconciliation to poor Sinners, he not only went to</l>
					<l>hear as others did but he was soon convinced of </l>
					<l>the great need he stood in of a Savr. Being now</l>
					<l>concerned for his Happiness in time and Eternity he,</l>
					<l>as a Parent of his Children, Husband of his Wife, and</l>
					<l>Father of a Family, was equally concerned for the</l>
					<l>Salvation of his whole House, and was not satis-</l>
					<l>fied untill they all heard with him the precious</l>
					<l>Gospel from whence he expected life everlasting.</l>
					<l>According to that first Love and Zeal, which prevailed</l>
					<l>among the awakened souls in those Days he was also</l>
					<l>a Sharer of that well known great Love Feast at</l>
					<l>Fieldhead. And becoming now more and more sensible</l>
					<l>of his undone Condition, notwithstanding his having</l>
					<l>already experienced some comfortable Feelings of our</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Saviours Grace, he once during a Preaching of Mr</l>
					<l>Inghams became particularly happy, thro&apos; the holy Ghosts</l>
					<l>applying the Word to his heart. When Mr Spangenberg</l>
					<l>went about settling Societies in these Districts he became</l>
					<l>a Member of the same. He having a great Love for the</l>
					<l>Church he was brought up in and being now more clear in</l>
					<l>what one went properly to divine Service for, he continued</l>
					<l>going to Church for a long while believing that our Savr</l>
					<l>blessed him there like wise. But as his Heart could be</l>
					<l>no more satisfied without Fellowship, and he not meeting</l>
					<l>with it there, this determined him to follow solely and</l>
					<l>alone the Track our dear Savr Might lead him among</l>
					<l>the Brn, in which Resolution he was very steady, untill</l>
					<l>he was recieved into the Congn, which came to pass Augst 13th</l>
					<l>1748 on account of which Grace he was very much melted</l>
					<l>and thankful. In the same Year, namely the 13th of Novr</l>
					<l>he went with the Congn to the holy Comunion for the first</l>
					<l>time, and as he has never enjoy&apos;d it before in his Life</l>
					<l>time out of a profound Respect he had for the same, His</l>
					<l>Heart was so much the more bowed on account of this</l>
					<l>great Grace and concerning which he said: No Tongue</l>
					<l>is able to express the feeling of my Heart, that such</l>
					<l>a poor Worm as me, is permitted to enjoy this highest</l>
					<l>Treasure. This Awefull Impression of the holy Sacrament</l>
					<l>abade with him to the End of his Life. An accidental</l>
					<l>Circumstance proved the Occasion to determine him and </l>
					<l>his Wife to spend the Remainder of their Days in Fulneck</l>
					<l>and having obtained Leave to move thither, He was soon</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>there with all his Goods without ever enquiring</l>
					<l>beferehand where he was to have his dwelling, which was</l>
					<l>May the 12th 1759. His Grace Election was very important</l>
					<l>to him and which he kept continually in his Eye, and when</l>
					<l>he had the Favour to become Congn Disceple, which Dignity</l>
					<l>he was twice invested with, his heart was so humbled</l>
					<l>and broken because of the Sense of his unworthiness that</l>
					<l>he went to his Son James, entreated him to assist him</l>
					<l>in praying our dear Savr that His Intention with him</l>
					<l>might be obtained. In his Course and Walk, this in</l>
					<l>a Measure unobserved, he enjoy&apos;d much of our Savrs</l>
					<l>Love and Grace, and so as he grew weaker and</l>
					<l>feebler in his Body his Tenderness towards his</l>
					<l>Redeemer encreased, and his Longing to be soon with </l>
					<l>him grew more ardant. He was often seen weeping</l>
					<l>when by himself, and if asked what was the Cause</l>
					<l>of at, he said: These are not Tears of Sorrow, but</l>
					<l>Tears of Love to my Saviour. When he was the </l>
					<l>last time at the holy Comunion in the Hall, he had</l>
					<l>an Intimation of it that this would be the last time</l>
					<l>he should enjoy that greatest of Blessings here below;</l>
					<l>But heartily wished that he might have no long and </l>
					<l>serious sickness in order not to give his Brn any</l>
					<l>trouble, which Request be clear Lord granted him</l>
					<l>like wise: for when on the 16th of Dec. he went to</l>
					<l>Bed about 9 o&apos;Clock in the Evening, he slept till about</l>
					<l>1 o&apos;Clock in the Morning, and at 2 o&apos;Clock his Soul</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>had alreadly taken its Flight into the Enjoyment</l>
					<l>of everlasting Bliss. His dieing Life lasted 75 Years.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
