<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Allot_Mary_Ful_SS_12</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1051.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Mary Alott</l>
					<l>Was born at Barksland in the Parish of</l>
					<l>Elland. On the 12th of Decr 1734 N S.</l>
					<l>When she was about Three years old her</l>
					<l>Father dyed &amp; she liv&apos;d with her Mother &amp;</l>
					<l>her Aunt (Namely Betty Midgley) who</l>
					<l>jointly Nurs&apos;d &amp; Maintain&apos;d till she was</l>
					<l>about seven, then her Mother being again</l>
					<l>Married her Aunt left them took a Room</l>
					<l>&amp; design&apos;d to live by herself, But not being</l>
					<l>at all willing to be left behind often begg&apos;d </l>
					<l>her Aunt to take her with her, which </l>
					<l>accordingly in a few weeks after she Willlingly</l>
					<l>did, &amp; Cared for her as her own.</l>
					<l>When she was about Nine years old she</l>
					<l>by the Drawing of the Holy Ghost was inclin&apos;d</l>
					<l>to hear the Gospel which she of her own free</l>
					<l>accord begun &amp; Continued Constantly to do. </l>
					<l>Some time after her Aunt had a mind for</l>
					<l>the more Convenince of hearing the Brn</l>
					<l>to live nearer Smith House &amp; she made it</l>
					<l>out with the Brethren that Mary should also</l>
					<l>come &amp; remain with her which she was very </l>
					<l>glad off.</l>
					<l>In July 1748 they Both of them together got</l>
					<l>leave to live with the Single Sisters in Clack</l>
					<l>Heaton &amp; she remain&apos;d there &amp; in the same</l>
					<l>Oconomy at Tyre-sell-Hall till we came</l>
					<l>in the Choir House (Which I shall take</l>
					<l>Notice of afterwards)</l>
					<l>In the year 1751 on the 5th of April she</l>
					<l>was receiv&apos;d in the Congregation which Pleas&apos;d  </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1052.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>her very much. In 1753 on the 25 of February</l>
					<l>she after many a Hearty wish &amp; Earnest longing</l>
					<l>for it was addmitted to the Lords Supper</l>
					<l>In the same year was Receiv&apos;d from the Great Girls</l>
					<l>to the Single Sisters Choir.</l>
					<l>She has since about 10, or 11, Years Old,</l>
					<l>carried about a Very Sickly &amp; Weakly Tabernacle</l>
					<l>which she bore without Complaint, &amp; being of an </l>
					<l>exceeding shill quiet, but also very solid &amp;</l>
					<l>sensible Dispossition she was seldom</l>
					<l>heard to speak about any thing except when</l>
					<l>spoken to: But however as we now have found she</l>
					<l>took good Notice of ever thing &amp; Ponderd them in </l>
					<l>her Heart.</l>
					<l>In February this present year she had the</l>
					<l>Small-Pox which not only went very hardly</l>
					<l>with her But also left that remaining on her</l>
					<l>which Render&apos;d her Much more Weak &amp; Sickly</l>
					<l>than before a Consumption appearing thro&apos; her</l>
					<l>Whole Constitution: It was manifest to all about her</l>
					<l>she could not hold it out long, tho she herself wod</l>
					<l>commonly say when ask&apos;d about it &quot;that she was</l>
					<l>pretty well Nevertheless what she inwardly felt</l>
					<l>also </l>
					<l>Brought her upon the thoughts &amp; consideration </l>
					<l>of going to Our Saviour (as she afterward, de</l>
					<l>clar&apos;d with Joy.)</l>
					<l>In July she was a little Better but the disor</l>
					<l>der Presently return&apos;d more strong than ever:</l>
					<l>Yet she continued to walk about till the 22d of</l>
					<l>November, then she entirely took her to her</l>
					<l>Room &amp; soon after to her Bed.</l>
					<l>Now she freely acknowledgeing that she</l>
					<l>had all this summer last, been in a Continual</l>
					<l>meditation &amp; Consultation with her Dear Saviour</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>all</l>
					<l>about her going to him, having all along been Senscible</l>
					<l>of it for herself that she should not stay here</l>
					<l>but the Reason why she would not confess it</l>
					<l>openly was because she was affraid she should</l>
					<l>not go as soon as she wish&apos;d for.</l>
					<l>She was now exceeding Bad, but quite Brisk</l>
					<l>in Spirits &amp; chearful in Heart &amp; Soul, &amp; as before</l>
					<l>even Ever since we have known her she has</l>
					<l>been us&apos;d to speak very little, so Now to the Con</l>
					<l>trary, spoke a great deal especialy to these</l>
					<l>with whom she had had an intimiate acquaintance</l>
					<l>&amp; Perticularly with Our dear Sister Mary</l>
					<l>who very faithfully visited her all the time</l>
					<l>On the 12th instant she had her Birth-Day</l>
					<l>(being 20; years old,) when many Sisters who vis</l>
					<l>ited her Express&apos;d their Hearty wishes for her</l>
					<l>which she receiv&apos;d, &amp; answer&apos;d with much satis</l>
					<l>faction: In the afternoon her Class made</l>
					<l>her a Very Pretty Love-Feast which rejoice</l>
					<l>ed her Exceedingly &amp; in which she spoke of</l>
					<l>her Departure with such Pleasure &amp; Delight</l>
					<l>as she never had done before; she spoke with</l>
					<l>sister Mary &amp; Made out Ev&apos;ry thing that was in </l>
					<l>her Mind about her Burial, as well as all</l>
					<l>the Hearty wishes &amp; desires of her heart for</l>
					<l>her Class &amp; c. In short she said that this had</l>
					<l>been to her the Happiest day she ever had</l>
					<l>had in all her life. This day &amp; forward she </l>
					<l>unbosom&apos;d &amp; declar&apos;d what she had (Perhaps)</l>
					<l>kept Treasur&apos;d up in her Heart to this Opper</l>
					<l>tunity for some years Past, She spoke of her </l>
					<l>various Troubles &amp; Anxieties in Particular Circum</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1053.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Circumstances, such as no body had perciev&apos;d on her</l>
					<l>with a Chearful &amp; Thankful Heart, being</l>
					<l>bowed with Shame before him will whom she</l>
					<l>had spent many happy Moments, days &amp; years</l>
					<l>About the 15th it being Two years since</l>
					<l>we came in Choir House she told Sister Mary</l>
					<l>Ev&apos;rything how she had been &amp; was in Tyre-</l>
					<l>sell-Hall at that time, What Anxiety &amp;</l>
					<l>Concern she felt about coming in the Choir House</l>
					<l>fearing Least she should not have leave to </l>
					<l>come &amp; how she had in Shillness Pray&apos;d &amp; wept</l>
					<l>before her dear Lamb, that he would give</l>
					<l>her Leave to come &amp; that if she should have </l>
					<l>that favour that he would grant her the feel</l>
					<l>ing &amp; nearness of his Wounds that she might</l>
					<l>be faithful to him therein &amp;c. Nay his almost</l>
					<l>incredible, how quick &amp; active her Memory</l>
					<l>was over this matter she not only gave Sisr</l>
					<l>Mary an account of herself but of all the </l>
					<l>Sisters in Tyre-sell-Hall at that time, she </l>
					<l>(unperceiv&apos;d) had taken Notice of ev&apos;ry One,</l>
					<l>conduct words &amp; behaviour, But to return</l>
					<l>she also Express&apos;d herself in a very Lively</l>
					<l>manner with grace &amp; Understanding how</l>
					<l>Exceedingly she was Rejoiced when she was</l>
					<l>assured she should come here. She at the </l>
					<l>same time viz&apos; the 15th or 16th Instant spoke wth</l>
					<l>with an inly Tender feeling about the Choir</l>
					<l>&amp; Choir Grace what she has felt since</l>
					<l>she was Receiv&apos;d in the Single Sisters Choir</l>
					<l>&amp; what her dear Bridegroom has done from</l>
					<l>time to time on her therein, &amp; Perticularly</l>
					<l>in this Present Year, together with the Esteem</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>&amp; Satisfaction she has had for, &amp; in the Choir House</l>
					<l>this she did from time to time Repeat And</l>
					<l>also she would allways take notice of many</l>
					<l>Sisters whom she saw &amp; Reflected on their</l>
					<l>Situation at Present and time Pass &amp; when</l>
					<l>Sister Mary came to her then she would sell</l>
					<l>her all her Mind about them &amp; Especialy the</l>
					<l>concern she had had, about her Class under</l>
					<l>some heavy Circumstances some Months agoe</l>
					<l>&amp; being ask&apos;d why she did not speak at such</l>
					<l>time what she had in her mind? She answer&apos;d</l>
					<l>&quot;that she always thought herself too mean</l>
					<l>&amp; too insignificant to Speak Her mind about</l>
					<l>any thing, But she had instead of that gone</l>
					<l>somewhere in a Corner &amp; Wept for them be</l>
					<l>fore her dear Saviour &amp; Pray&apos;d him that he</l>
					<l>would Bless Preserve &amp; keep them &amp; Her</l>
					<l>&amp; that they Might all become a Joy to Him</l>
					<l>Once in Sister Mary&apos;s Presence after having</l>
					<l>fully spoken &amp; Open&apos;d all her Mind to her a</l>
					<l>bout Many things, she took Notice that her</l>
					<l>Aunt (who faithfuly tended &amp; Nurs&apos;d</l>
					<l>her all the time of Sickness) was a Cry</l>
					<l>ing: So she demanded the Reason of her why</l>
					<l>she wept, telling her she had no Ocassion</l>
					<l>to weep for her since &quot;says she&quot; I am fully</l>
					<l>Satisfied &amp; Reconciled both with My Lamb &amp;</l>
					<l>&amp; with all my Sisters &amp; have spoke my mind </l>
					<l>about Everything &amp; Now am Ready to go </l>
					<l>whenever he Pleases</l>
					<l>Thus she Continued under a Deep Sense</l>
					<l>&amp; Speaking of herself &amp; her Choir &amp; Often</l>
					<l>Expressing her Desire to go. But yet she</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1054.jpg' n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>would Secretly sometimes say to her Aunt that</l>
					<l>she believ&apos;d she should live till Christmas, but</l>
					<l>If our Saviour Pleasd to take her before, she</l>
					<l>would be glad</l>
					<l>Sunday Last about 11 or 12 in the Evening</l>
					<l>she was Siez&apos;d with the monst Violent pain</l>
					<l>So that Sister Mary who at the same time</l>
					<l>watch&apos;d with her Perceiv&apos;d such a Senscible</l>
					<l>Alteration not only by her Excessive Pains</l>
					<l>but also by the Motion &amp; Alteration of all</l>
					<l>her Faculties that she thought she Realy would </l>
					<l>go, &amp; thereupon ask&apos;d her if she was now quite</l>
					<l>Ready. She with Pleasure &amp; Serenity answerd</l>
					<l>&quot;yes! I am Quite Ready now &amp; shall be glad to</l>
					<l>go to my Lamb as soon as he Pleases&quot;</l>
					<l>However she reviv&apos;d a little &amp; then desired</l>
					<l>2 verses which she named to be sung for her</l>
					<l>viz Appear as her Protector who turns to</l>
					<l>Joy all Tears &amp; When she shall get Per</l>
					<l>mission to leave this Mortal Tent, From Pains</l>
					<l>&amp; Griefs Dissmission Thy self Just then present</l>
					<l>And then says she &quot;Sing Hush stir not up</l>
					<l>the friend of Christ, Wake not the lovely</l>
					<l>Bride &amp;c</l>
					<l>She was very Bad all Night &amp; Lay like</l>
					<l>one Expireing till towards Night on Monday</l>
					<l>Yet she Bore her Pains with Much more</l>
					<l>Patience any one could Expect who did but</l>
					<l>see how she was Munday night she was some</l>
					<l>waht Easier &amp; appear&apos;d to ys as if she might</l>
					<l>Possibly continue a few days, But if she heard</l>
					<l>any one take notice of the near approach </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Christmass &amp; of the Joy we Expected in the Birth</l>
					<l>day of our Saviour She would readly answer</l>
					<l>them that if our Saviour only was Pleas&apos;d to let</l>
					<l>her go to him before or in the Holidays She</l>
					<l>should have a far Better Christmass than </l>
					<l>We and that she would be glad of.</l>
					<l>Tusday Night she Alter&apos;d again &amp; on Wed</l>
					<l>nesday Morning was much Worse. In the</l>
					<l>Forenoon we thought again she would Certain</l>
					<l>ly Depart, But she continued and lay severly</l>
					<l>Oppresse&apos;d with the Most Excessive Pangs thro&apos;</l>
					<l>Ev&apos;ry Limb &amp; Fibre, Speaking very little, But</l>
					<l>Panting in Stillness for the Happy Moment</l>
					<l>when she should get the Departing Kiss, And </l>
					<l>when Sometimes her Tabernacle seem&apos;d to be</l>
					<l>almost Rack&apos;d in Pieces with the most shock</l>
					<l>ing &amp; Excessive Pain as almost could be thought</l>
					<l>Unpossibl a Human Creature could Bear. she </l>
					<l>would say &quot;Ah! how </l>
					<l>shall I hold it Out Why does he not fetch me</l>
					<l>Sis Mary then would remind her of the Hard</l>
					<l>Toil &amp; Conflict of our Saviour which he bore</l>
					<l>in his Humanity Saying My dear Heart it</l>
					<l>is but a few Minutes &amp; you will be with </l>
					<l>him, She that Moment was again in a </l>
					<l>Calm Serenity  &amp; Peace Said O! yes he soon</l>
					<l>will fetch me to his Embraces, Which she</l>
					<l>Obtain&apos;d Under these Words, The Lamb wth</l>
					<l>all his Grief &amp; Smart Remains the Pleasure</l>
					<l>of the Heart Long as it Moves in Thee</l>
					<l>And Now when Here it Beats no more</l>
					<l>There where the Spear His Side did </l>
					<l>bore thou Last thy Place Etneraly and</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1055.jpg' n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>so she sweetly went to sleep in the Arms of </l>
					<l>her Lover about 5 o&apos;clock in the Evening </l>
					<l>on Christmas Day.</l>
					<l>It is to be Oberv&apos;d that this dear Heart</l>
					<l>was the Only One Great Girl in all the </l>
					<l>Oconomies was One of the first that was</l>
					<l>Receiv&apos;d in the Congregation The Only One</l>
					<l>that came in the Choir House at first</l>
					<l>She was the first that was admitted to the</l>
					<l>Sacrament. And Now the first that is gone</l>
					<l>to Our saviour. Where she Rests from all her</l>
					<l>Pain: And has Left behind her the Char</l>
					<l>acter of an Honest Upright Unaffected</l>
					<l>&amp; Enamour&apos;d Virgin Heart She has been</l>
					<l>Known by those who have liv&apos;d with her from</l>
					<l>among us </l>
					<l>her first Commg to this Her Dissalution to be</l>
					<l>an Example of Patience of Steadfastness &amp;</l>
					<l>Constancy in her Love to him who first gave</l>
					<l>her Confidence to believe in his Wounds she</l>
					<l>never Once having been Perceiv&apos;d to Draw back</l>
					<l>or to Slight her Calling in Joy or in Smart,</l>
					<l>and Now at last her Mouth has made a</l>
					<l>a Brief Confession of Him Whom her Heart</l>
					<l>has Loved Felt &amp; Believ&apos;d on. </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
