<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Astley_Ful_3_47</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1735.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Mirfield April the 18th 1770.</l>
					<l>The Life of the Md Br. Jno Astley</l>
					<l>who went home Apl 18 1770</l>
					<l>My Dear Brn &amp; Sisters</l>
					<l>It will without Doubt be Expected, that Some</l>
					<l>Thing Should be Said of the Life of our departed Brother</l>
					<l>John Astley, for it is usual amongst us but as he</l>
					<l>has left nothing from under his own Hand, and beside;</l>
					<l>has told me little or nothing by Word of Mouth, therefore</l>
					<l>I want Materials. He told one: that the was Born in </l>
					<l>Lower Wyke in the Year 1712. and there learnd the </l>
					<l>Trade of a Shoemaker. and there like wife he Married</l>
					<l>The presant Widow, being a Wild Wicked young Man &amp;c.</l>
					<l>But by the Preaching of our Late Br Delamott:</l>
					<l>(who was invited in to Yorkshire by Mr Ingham) he was</l>
					<l>Brought upon Serious thoughts, &amp; a Hearty concern</l>
					<l>about his Salvation, and that in this Situation of</l>
					<l>Heart &amp; Mind he fell early in to the hands of the Brn</l>
					<l>who soon after his awakening came in to Yorkshire, and</l>
					<l>that by that Means, he was not only Happily preserv&apos;d</l>
					<l>from relapsing into his Former Course but also by the Simple</l>
					<l>and Evangelical Preaching of the Brns, he became convinced of</l>
					<l>our Savrs unmeasurable love &amp; Grace for Sinners; and became</l>
					<l>more, &amp; more acquainted, and Confident toward Him, and </l>
					<l>Therefore began to value, &amp; love the Fellowship of the Brethren</l>
					<l>and beg&apos;d for reception in to the Congn He &amp; his Wife, had this</l>
					<l>their Hearty desire Grented them as near as he could guess</l>
					<l>in the Year 1747. and were soon after admitted to the Holy</l>
					<l>Communion, for the first time. He thought </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1736.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>It was the First communion which was kept in Fulnek Hall</l>
					<l>however be that as it will, it was the first to him in That Place,</l>
					<l>and Numbred with Him; amongst his particular Hours of Grace!</l>
					<l>From that Day: He has maintain&apos;d His communion with the</l>
					<l>Brn to his Dying Hour, tho&apos; it was often times, but slenderly &amp;</l>
					<l>and with difficulty yet it never ceas&apos;d realy.</l>
					<l>They were Married in the year 1733 in Febr and had</l>
					<l>a 11 Children 5 of whom are in the Burying Ground in Fulnek; </l>
					<l>one in Hartshed Church yard, one Daughter, a Dukenfield, and one</l>
					<l>at Ockbrook Choir House. and the other three i.e. one Son, and</l>
					<l>two Daughters don&apos;t belong to us. they had once a little oeconomy</l>
					<l>of Single Brn at their House in Hartshed, but this was not their own</l>
					<l>but the Brns Projecting, but as it did not answer our Savrs &amp; the Brns purposes</l>
					<l>it was soon Given up again.</l>
					<l>He has been her Some years, a pretty good steward</l>
					<l>and Servant of the little Congn in Mirfield, and so has also</l>
					<l>His present Widow, and therefore his Memory must remain</l>
					<l>Dear to us. He was a Child of Grace indeed, yet his life</l>
					<l>was Chequer&apos;d o&apos;er with Grief and need.</l>
					<l>His Domestick  affairs have bore a very indifrent</l>
					<l>Trace these Many years, by which Means his credit was</l>
					<l>reduced considerably; and this not only with Strangers,</l>
					<l>but partricularly So among our own People, therefore</l>
					<l>I am rather inclin&apos;d to Draw a vail over the Most part</l>
					<l>of his Life. than to Expose it to Publick view.</l>
					<l>However: all is Well, what Ends Well. altho the beginning</l>
					<l>and Middle had Some thing deploreable yet the end was</l>
					<l>adoreable. I have labour&apos;d upon it from the beginning</l>
					<l>of his Sickness to get his Mind off from all Eaternal </l>
					<l>concerns, as he could Mend nothing in it, &amp; entreated Him</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>all</l>
					<l>to Fix his heart and Eyes on our Savr and on his atoneing</l>
					<l>Sacrifice, which advice he took Child-likely and became quite composed,</l>
					<l>and Chearlul in his Mind. we visited him pretty often in order</l>
					<l>to keep this Matter alive in his heart which has happily Succeeded</l>
					<l>on Easter day he Send for me, accordingly I wwent with 2 more Brethren</l>
					<l>Pray&apos;d heartily by Him, kept a little liturgy, by his Bedside, &amp;</l>
					<l>gave him my last Blessing, thinking he could not live till I could</l>
					<l>come again. this little visit was attended with a most blessed feeling,</l>
					<l>So that I left him with a Heart quite Satisfy&apos;d.</l>
					<l>on Easter Tuesday, I and my Wife went to See him once more</l>
					<l>I was quite Edify&apos;d with his look &amp; Spoke tenderly to him, and</l>
					<l>Sung Some Suitable verses for him, in which he join&apos;d with us</l>
					<l>which we could see by the moving of his lips, this was the last</l>
					<l>happy little visit, for: the next Monday Early, he fell Softly</l>
					<l>and Happily asleep in his 58th year.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
