<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Beck_John_Thompson_Ful_3_115</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>3. John Thompson Beck, aged 22 years/</l>
					<l>Previous to his illness he gave no indication of</l>
					<l>spiritual life; for tho&apos; a moral character, his mind was so</l>
					<l>fixed on earthly pursuits, that it produced a degree</l>
					<l>of hardness of heart and feeling not often found in one</l>
					<l>so young. All his affections were enlisted in the acqui</l>
					<l>sition of money, after for which he panted with fearful </l>
					<l>eagerness. In this state he continued for a considera</l>
					<l>ble time after he was confined to the house, and even</l>
					<l>long after it was apparent that he would no get better.</l>
					<l>So hard were his feelings that it was painful to visit</l>
					<l>him, and so severe was the conflict on his mind when</l>
					<l>he saw that death would soon put an end to al his</l>
					<l>schemes, that it was truly distressing. The mental</l>
					<l>struggle and his fond clinging to life, reeked and tor</l>
					<l>tured his soul. Many times have I left the house</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>with the most painful feelings, and had I not been con</l>
					<l>vinced that the Word of reconciliation can soften</l>
					<l>the most obdurate heart, I should have desponded. Fre</l>
					<l>quent and fervent were my prayers, that the Lord</l>
					<l>would open the eyes of this young man. Still no signs</l>
					<l>of spiritual life appeared; my conversations with</l>
					<l>him, the reading of the scripture, and Hymns, see</l>
					<l>med to fall on a rock. At length the grace of God</l>
					<l>triumphed, and this unhappy state gave way to sen</l>
					<l>timents and feelings of a different kind.</l>
					<l>The first symptoms of a sounder state of mind</l>
					<l>appeared some months ago. He became an humble</l>
					<l>inquirer and listened to the instructions given him</l>
					<l>in spiritual things; and the silent tears rolling down</l>
					<l>his cheeks, proved that degree of light was spin</l>
					<l>ning up in his soul. His friends observed the</l>
					<l>change with pleasure; but I thought it was</l>
					<l>prudent to take no notice of it, but his alteration</l>
					<l>should be diverted from the great object of his</l>
					<l>faith and absorbed in himself and his feelings.</l>
					<l>He now loved the Lord Jesus; he loved to hear</l>
					<l>of His sacrifice and death. His confessions showed</l>
					<l>much humility and a hope of happiness groun</l>
					<l>ded in the atonement of Christ.</l>
					<l>One day, about a fortnight after this change</l>
					<l>had taken place, when he was more communi</l>
					<l>cative than he had been before, I ventured to</l>
					<l>remark, that he had different thoughts and </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>feelings now from what he had had a few</l>
					<l>weeks before ago, he ascented, expressing his</l>
					<l>thankfulness that this was the case. To my</l>
					<l>question, &quot;When did you begin to think more</l>
					<l>seriously on these things, and what led you to it?&quot; </l>
					<l>he replied; &quot;Do you remember the evening</l>
					<l>when you and my uncle were here, and conversing</l>
					<l>about the love of Jesus, our Saviour, in giving His</l>
					<l>life a ransom for sinners, suffering and dyeing on</l>
					<l>the cross for our sins, and of His mercy in saving</l>
					<l>all who come to Him in faith? That conversa</l>
					<l>tion I could not forget, and for three hours after</l>
					<l>I went to bed, I was thinking about it. I prayed</l>
					<l>for grace to believe; I prayed for pardon and</l>
					<l>I felt a hope that I should not be lost, that Jesus</l>
					<l>would save me. Since then my mind has at</l>
					<l>times been very comfortable, when I think of</l>
					<l>my Saviour and pray to Him.&quot;</l>
					<l>From that day the operations of the Holy</l>
					<l>Spirit on his heart became more evident, and</l>
					<l>showed their blessed effects by a complete surrender</l>
					<l>of himself to the Lord, and submission to His will;</l>
					<l>and by being delivered from the fear of death, and</l>
					<l>bearing his severe suffering with exemplary pa</l>
					<l>tience, often saying, &quot;It is the Lord&apos;s will, let Him</l>
					<l>do with me what He pleases.&quot; He was mercifully</l>
					<l>preserved from any reasons of gloom or darkness</l>
					<l>of mind, and to the last confined in a tranquil</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and peaceful state. He had buried his hopes on</l>
					<l>the Rock of ages, and in a childlike manner fixed</l>
					<l>his mind on the suffering of the Lamb of God. In</l>
					<l>consequence of this, tho&apos; his frames and feeling varied,</l>
					<l>he was kept in perfect peace. Eight weeks ago,</l>
					<l>when racked with the most excruciating pains of body,</l>
					<l>his soul was graciously supported by inward conso</l>
					<l>lations. Peace beamed in his countenance, and</l>
					<l>joy glowed in his expressions. &quot;Don&apos;t weep for me&quot;</l>
					<l>Addressing those present he said, &quot;Don&apos;t weep</l>
					<l>for me; it will soon be all over; my Saviour is</l>
					<l>great; He will not leave me.&quot; Subsequently</l>
					<l>his pains were partially relieved; when he never</l>
					<l>failed to impress the importance of eternal things</l>
					<l>on all who visited him.</l>
					<l>On Sunday August 13<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> he was he was asur</l>
					<l>ably to his earnest desire, acknowledged a member</l>
					<l>of our Church, and commended to the sympathy</l>
					<l>and prayer, of the cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>. and in the evening</l>
					<l>the H. Communion was administered to him</l>
					<l>and his parents, in the presence of the other mem</l>
					<l>bers of the family and a few friends. Du</l>
					<l>ring this solemn act the peace of God was power</l>
					<l>fully felt by all present, and he himself testified</l>
					<l>by his look, his the heavenly joy that filled his</l>
					<l>soul. When the service was over he exclaimed,</l>
					<l>&quot;this has been a blessed meeting; nothing but</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>heaven can exceed this.&quot; His bodily sufferings</l>
					<l>were forgotten, and the happenings of his soul seemed</l>
					<l>almost too great for his weak frame to enterain.</l>
					<l>The day after, speaking to one of his sisters of his en</l>
					<l>joyment, he was unable to express himself in</l>
					<l>language sufficiently strong, saying, &quot;O what a</l>
					<l>meeting that was! If you had felt as I did, you</l>
					<l>would never forget it.&quot;</l>
					<l>The last week of his life was one of very severe</l>
					<l>suffering, but of inward peace. In the midst of his</l>
					<l>sufferings he frequently exclaimed; &quot;Glory, glory be</l>
					<l>to God! I shall soon be with Him. I am going fast;</l>
					<l>my Saviour will soon come to fetch me home. I </l>
					<l>shall soon be with him in Heaven; there I shall</l>
					<l>see Him face to face; I shall be near Him and shall</l>
					<l>see the wounds He bore for my sins.&quot; At one of my</l>
					<l>last visits to him, when he appeared very near</l>
					<l>his end, he said, turning his face to me, &quot;You will</l>
					<l>soon have to preach my funeral sermon. I wish</l>
					<l>the young people may take warning by me, and be</l>
					<l>led to give themselves to the Lord.&quot;</l>
					<l>The Satturday before he died, he was much exhau</l>
					<l>sted by pain, and could say very little; but seemed to</l>
					<l>derive comfort from the words addressed to him.</l>
					<l>When about to leave him he exerted himself to say</l>
					<l>something, the substance of which was, that he enjoyd</l>
					<l>sweet comfort and peace by in feeling our Saviour&apos;s pre</l>
					<l>sence, and in meditating on His sufferings &amp; death, ad</l>
					<l>ding, &quot;O how I long to go and see The Lamb of God, who</l>
					<l>died for me &amp;c.&quot; On shaking hands with him he said with </l>
					<l>a smile, &quot;All will be well at last.&quot; He departed the following Tuesday.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
