<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Benade_Samuel_Ful_3_78</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Narrative of my pilgrimage</l>
					<l>thro&apos; the vale of tears.</l>
					<l>They that sow in tears, shall reap in</l>
					<l>joy. He that goeth forth and reap weepeth</l>
					<l>bearing precious seed, shall doubtless</l>
					<l>come again with rejoicing, bringing</l>
					<l>his sheaves with him.</l>
					<l>All they, who weeping now go forth</l>
					<l>And bear the precious seed,</l>
					<l>May in our Savior&apos;s walk on earth:</l>
					<l>Pattern and comfort read.</l>
					<l>Samuel Traugott Benade</l>
					<l>Having, while I lived on earth, among</l>
					<l>other favors and privileges conferred upon</l>
					<l>me, thro&apos; the unmerited &amp; undessed grace</l>
					<l>of my Lord and Savior been honored with</l>
					<l>the appointnient of a Minister of the Gospel</l>
					<l>I deem it my bounden duty, once more</l>
					<l>thro&apos; this narrative of my earthly pilgri-</l>
					<l>mage, to bear testimony to the power and</l>
					<l>efficacy of a living faith in a crucified</l>
					<l>Redeemer, as experienced by me to the</l>
					<l>saving of my Soul and the rejoicing of</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>of my heart. And Oh! the may this feeble testi-</l>
					<l>mony prove an encouragement to my fellow</l>
					<l>pilgrims who as yet have not reached their</l>
					<l>heavenly home, but are still laboring to enter</l>
					<l>into that eternal rest, which God, the faith-</l>
					<l>ful covenant keeping God, has prepared for</l>
					<l>his people. To All, that shall hear or read this</l>
					<l>narrative, I solemnly declare, that my salva-</l>
					<l>tion has been from beginning to end, the work</l>
					<l>of God, and a succession of miracles, wrought</l>
					<l>by the grace of God, for my deliverance as well</l>
					<l>as for the promoting of my happiness, &amp; for</l>
					<l>the completion of my heavenly calling &amp; election.</l>
					<l>Ever since I came to the knowledge of my natu-</l>
					<l>ral depravity and sinfulness &amp; knew experi-</l>
					<l>mentally the truth of that declaration, &quot;that</l>
					<l>those is neither health nor help in ourselves&quot;,</l>
					<l>scarcely a day has passed, but I had occasion</l>
					<l>to weep and to mourn, yea to abhor myself.</l>
					<l>and scarcely a day, but I experienced some ma-</l>
					<l>nifestation of my Savior&apos;s redeeming grace &amp;</l>
					<l>power, for my comfort &amp; encouragement </l>
					<l>On revising my own works, it is no compli-</l>
					<l>ment to say, that I find no ground for glorying;</l>
					<l>but calling to mind the Lord&apos;s mercies, I find</l>
					<l>abundant cause for everlast&apos;g thanks &amp; prayer.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Hear then, what the Lord has done for my</l>
					<l>Soul!</l>
					<l>I was born the 28th of October 1746 at</l>
					<l>Milkel in Upper Lusatia about to 10 E. miles</l>
					<l>from Bautzen the Capital. My Father was</l>
					<l>the Minister of the place, and my Mother</l>
					<l>Christiana, whose maiden name was Faber</l>
					<l>a Minister&apos;s daughter. These my dear Pa-</l>
					<l>rents were eamestly concerned, to bring</l>
					<l>up their Children, of whom they had 6 living,</l>
					<l>in the fear and nuture of the Lord, and</l>
					<l>to prerserve them from this present evil world</l>
					<l>&amp; from the spirit of seduction. Wherefore,</l>
					<l>getting acquainted with the Brethren,</l>
					<l>who frequently passed thro&apos; the village</l>
					<l>in going from Kleinwelke to Uhyst, they</l>
					<l>soon embraced that opportunity, to place</l>
					<l>us, one after another, in the Seminaries</l>
					<l>of the Brn, and thus in my eigth year</l>
					<l>I came to live in the Oeconomy at Uhyst.</l>
					<l>It was high time for me to be then brought</l>
					<l>to a place of safety; for young &amp; little as I</l>
					<l>was, the evil propensities of the heart began</l>
					<l>already to unfold themselves and would have</l>
					<l>even without the aid of seduction, rushed</l>
					<l>into activity, if they had not been restrained.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Numberless times in the sequel I have</l>
					<l>thanked our Savior with tears, that he in</l>
					<l>good time plucked me as a brand from the burn-</l>
					<l>ing, and planted me as a tender plant in the</l>
					<l>Brs Church, &amp; thereby preserved me from</l>
					<l>running headlong into Sin.</l>
					<l>Being then under the Brns care, I spent</l>
					<l>the remainder of my childhood in a happy</l>
					<l>manner receiving early and deep impressions</l>
					<l>of Jesus dying love, which excited me to love</l>
					<l>him again; tho&apos; my innate self love &amp; self</l>
					<l>complacency did not fail to show itself from</l>
					<l>time to time.</l>
					<l>In 1756 the Boys Oeconomy moved from</l>
					<l>Uhyst to Niesky, where my love to our Sa-</l>
					<l>vior and fellowship with him was much</l>
					<l>further&apos;d by the faithful care of the late Br</l>
					<l>Bryant, and by his edifying manner of</l>
					<l>treating his Pupils, making it his chief busi-</l>
					<l>ness, to lead them into acquaintance with</l>
					<l>our Savior. </l>
					<l>While here, one of the most signal visita-</l>
					<l>tions of grace was experienced by me on the</l>
					<l>13th of November at the meetg for prostration;</l>
					<l>my Soul was overcome and melted by an inex-</l>
					<l>pressible Sense of our Savior&apos;s love wch con-</l>
					<l>strained me, to devote myself with soul</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and body to Him as his eternal property</l>
					<l>This blessed event I have always remember&apos;d</l>
					<l>with particular gratitude; and to this very</l>
					<l>day the remembrance of it is as fresh and lively</l>
					<l>to my mind, as if it had occured but yesterday.</l>
					<l>In my 13th year I was placed in the Pae-</l>
					<l>dagogium at Hennersdorf, with a view to</l>
					<l>prosecute my studies. At that time the vi-</l>
					<l>sits and discourses of the late Count Zinzen-</l>
					<l>dorf were much blessed to my heart; &amp; I was</l>
					<l>deeply affected, when that Servant of God</l>
					<l>was called to enter into the joy of his Lord.</l>
					<l>After his departure the Paedagogium was trans-</l>
					<l>ferred from Hennersdorf to Niesky</l>
					<l>As I advanced in years, my natural depra-</l>
					<l>vily and siful propensities appeared more</l>
					<l>and more, and I should have been carried</l>
					<l>away by the torrent of corruption, if through</l>
					<l>grace a good foundation had not been laid in</l>
					<l>my soul, and if I had not been under the care</l>
					<l>of faithful Tutors.</l>
					<l>Our Savior continued the good work he had</l>
					<l>begun; and when I on the one hand wept &amp;</l>
					<l>mourned over myself, he on the other com-</l>
					<l>forted and supported me by repeated manifesta-</l>
					<l>tions of his love and kindness. I was enabled,</l>
					<l>to look by faith to a crucified Redeemer, and</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>perceived virtue going out of him whenever</l>
					<l>I touched him by faith.</l>
					<l>In 1759 I was received into the Congn. &amp;</l>
					<l>in 1761 admitted to the H. Comn. This divine</l>
					<l>repast has been of blessed reality &amp; help to me</l>
					<l>in my younger years, as indeed at all times</l>
					<l>It always proved a new encouragement to </l>
					<l>me, and revived my faith, love and confidence</l>
					<l>in such a manner, that I could run with pa-</l>
					<l>tience the race set before me; wch however</l>
					<l>would not have been the case, if I had not</l>
					<l>been in the habit of looking unto Jesus in</l>
					<l>my daily wants and necessities.</l>
					<l>On 1764 I came with 6 others to Barby</l>
					<l>to finish our Studies in the Seminary.</l>
					<l>The celebration of the 13th November, wch</l>
					<l>happened the next day after our arrival.</l>
					<l>proved a blessed welcome and introduction</l>
					<l>to us. My three years stay there was attended</l>
					<l>with much benefit and blessing. I proceeded</l>
					<l>gradually both in the knowledge of myself</l>
					<l>and of my Lord and Savior Jesus Christ,</l>
					<l>and learned to apply his precious merit to</l>
					<l>the healing of my sin sick nature. It was</l>
					<l>there likewise that I received a divine con-</l>
					<l>viction and assurance, that my blesed Creator</l>
					<l>&amp; Redeemer, had made me, a poor worm, an</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>object of his divine, infinite and unbounded</l>
					<l>love, and that it was the gracious purpose of</l>
					<l>his love, to grant me a full portion of that sal-</l>
					<l>vation, which he has purchased for all and</l>
					<l>this impression has never left me since, proving</l>
					<l>a powerful support to me under various trial</l>
					<l>and tribulations. </l>
					<l>In my 22. year I was appointed Teacher</l>
					<l>in the Paedagogium at Niesky, where I spent</l>
					<l>4 years very pleasantly; my labor among</l>
					<l>the youths, whom I dearly loved, being easy</l>
					<l>and agreeable to me, and my fellowshep with</l>
					<l>our Savior childlike and familiar. During</l>
					<l>that time I had a very painful fit of the gout,</l>
					<l>occasioned by an obstinate cold, wch I had</l>
					<l>neglected in the beginning.</l>
					<l>Upon this truly delightful period followed</l>
					<l>a time of trial and distiess, wch. I brought</l>
					<l>upon myself by indulging a mistaken notion</l>
					<l>that I should to more useful in our Savior&apos;s</l>
					<l>cause, if I went out of the common track,</l>
					<l>and that my faith would carry me through</l>
					<l>all difficulties. When I afterwards discovered</l>
					<l>the fallacy of my conceptions, &amp; the true source</l>
					<l>from wch they had spiring, the pride of my</l>
					<l>heart, and a desire to render myself eminent &amp;</l>
					<l>conspicuous; I was exceedingly distresed,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and at time so cast down that it required</l>
					<l>strong and repeated consolations, to lift me up</l>
					<l>again. Under these circumstance the Holy</l>
					<l>Ghost created me with matenal tenderness</l>
					<l>and attention, discovering to me on the one</l>
					<l>hand more than ever the deep depravity of</l>
					<l>my heart as the source of all Evil, and on the</l>
					<l>other the unchangeable love &amp; friendships</l>
					<l>of my Savior; administering at the same</l>
					<l>time the balm of divine consolation to my</l>
					<l>broken and contrite heart. It was then that</l>
					<l>I made a blessed experience of that precious</l>
					<l>truth, that all things must work together</l>
					<l>for good to them that love God. For this</l>
					<l>trial not only served to confirm my faith,</l>
					<l>but also to prepare me for my future calling</l>
					<l>to preach the Gospel and to labor in the</l>
					<l>Lord&apos;s vineyard.</l>
					<l>In the year 1772, having been accepted an</l>
					<l>Acoluth in the UEC, I was appointed to the</l>
					<l>service of the Boys Oeconomy at Fulneck</l>
					<l>in Yorkshire. As I had to travel alone, and</l>
					<l>part of the way thro&apos; England, unable to </l>
					<l>speak the language, I experienced new proofs</l>
					<l>of a gracious providence watching over me</l>
					<l>for good, and answering the prayers of a lone-</l>
					<l>ly traveller.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='9'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The first year of my service at Fulneck</l>
					<l>was extremely heavy to me, as I found the</l>
					<l>circumstances of the Oeconomy so difficult</l>
					<l>and embarrassed, that I could see no remedy</l>
					<l>either one way of another. Nevertheless, I put</l>
					<l>my trust in the Lord, and firmly believed,</l>
					<l>that he in his own good time would bring</l>
					<l>things into a better course, wch also came to</l>
					<l>pass, when Br. Traneker came as Congn</l>
					<l>Helper to Fulneck and undertook the ma-</l>
					<l>nagement of the Oeconomy.</l>
					<l>In the second year after my arrival in</l>
					<l>England, I was appointed to preach occasion-</l>
					<l>ally in country places about Fulneck, which</l>
					<l>indeed was a difficult task to me, both on</l>
					<l>account of my insufficient knowledge of</l>
					<l>the language, and on account of my natural</l>
					<l>timidity and bashfulness. But He, whose</l>
					<l>strength is made perfect in weakness, and</l>
					<l>who regards the poor and needy, supported</l>
					<l>me in every time of need, and if I felt po-</l>
					<l>verty of spirit it was for the blesing of my</l>
					<l>own heart.</l>
					<l>Amidst all outward difficulties I had a</l>
					<l>blessed time at Fulneck. I counted it grace,</l>
					<l>to advance in the knowledge of my deep de-</l>
					<l>pravity, as it was a powerful inducement</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='10'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>to me, to come with prayer &amp; supplication</l>
					<l>to the Savior of Sinners, and to claim the</l>
					<l>healing virtue of his precious blood, wch I </l>
					<l>also experienced according to my faith:</l>
					<l>At times indeed I felt the power of sin &amp; </l>
					<l>the strength of unbelief to such a degree,</l>
					<l>that I was prompted to despair of a com-</l>
					<l>pleat deliverance; but even then &quot;he delivered</l>
					<l>my soul from death, mine eyes from tears,</l>
					<l>and my feet from falling&quot;, and granted me </l>
					<l>again a time of refreshing from his presence</l>
					<l>Once on such an occasion I was most bless-</l>
					<l>edly relieved by a divine assurance, that not</l>
					<l>withstanding all my sinfulness I should</l>
					<l>yet attain to that supreme happiness, to</l>
					<l>love my Savior with all my heart, with all</l>
					<l>my strength and with all my undesrstandg</l>
					<l>and to be perfectly renewed into his image.</l>
					<l>The labor among the Children appeared to</l>
					<l>me highly important, &amp; I found much</l>
					<l>occasion, to ask for grace and wisdom to</l>
					<l>do justice to the several duties incumbent</l>
					<l>upon me. I trust my labor has been of be-</l>
					<l>nefit to some of them; but at any rate it has</l>
					<l>been made a blessing to my own heart.</l>
					<l>As I have found, in the course of my mi-</l>
					<l>nistry, that some people form to themselves</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='11'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>erroneous ideas of the way and manner, in</l>
					<l>which our Savior manifests himself to the</l>
					<l>soul, and are apt to look for some extraordi-</l>
					<l>nary &amp; striking event. I will here mention</l>
					<l>some instances, among many, of his gracious</l>
					<l>manifestations experienced by me in the com-</l>
					<l>moon course of things.</l>
					<l>Once being in violent pain, wch for 3 days</l>
					<l>&amp; nights had continued without any intermis-</l>
					<l>sion; I began with a murmuring spirit, to</l>
					<l>reflect on the goodness of God, that he would</l>
					<l>leave his creatures in pain, the he could so</l>
					<l>easily relieve them. But I was soon ashamed</l>
					<l>of this ungrateful thought, and led to consider</l>
					<l>the way of divine, wch are so conpicuous</l>
					<l>even in our afflictions, but most of all that</l>
					<l>manifestation of his unspeakable love, that</l>
					<l>He himself became a man of sorrows and</l>
					<l>acquainted with griefs, bearing our griefs and</l>
					<l>carrying our sorrows, wch consideration so</l>
					<l>over came and melted my heart, that I for the</l>
					<l>present forgot my pains, and afterwards could</l>
					<l>endure them patiently.</l>
					<l>Another time being at Scarboro&apos; on a high</l>
					<l>rock close to the sea, on wch the castle stands,</l>
					<l>from whence there is an extensive view of</l>
					<l>the sea, the town below and the adjacent country</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='12'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>the ships below appearing as small as</l>
					<l>cockle shells and the men like crawling</l>
					<l>insects my mind was uncommonly struck,</l>
					<l>with the sublime and awful scene, and im-</l>
					<l>pressed with an overpowering Sense of the</l>
					<l>immensity of that universe, of wch the earth</l>
					<l>with all its water wide and deep, and with</l>
					<l>all its stupendous mountains, is but a speck,</l>
					<l>a mere atom. How great then, thought I,</l>
					<l>how immensely great must He be, who</l>
					<l>has called the whole creation into existence,</l>
					<l>and who upholds all things by the word of</l>
					<l>his power. And do you really believe, said I</l>
					<l>to myself, that this great Builder of the Uni-</l>
					<l>verse: &quot;who dwelleth on high, &amp; humbleth</l>
					<l>himself, to behold the things, that are in</l>
					<l>the</l>
					<l>heaven and in earth&quot;, should have appeared</l>
					<l>in the world in the form of a Servant, &amp; died</l>
					<l>on the cross, that he might redeem fallen man,</l>
					<l>and raise him to glory!? Reason answered</l>
					<l>no it is far too much to be believed: it is im-</l>
					<l>possible; but my heart, with a clear wit-</l>
					<l>ness of the Spirit within, and melting under</l>
					<l>a sense of the love of God, said, yes, I must</l>
					<l>believe it from what I have experienced,</l>
					<l>lost and undone should I be, if it were not so</l>
					<l>but in my great Creator I have found my</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='13'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Savior and Redeemer, who has delivered my</l>
					<l>Soul from the pit of corruption, and is become</l>
					<l>to me a never failing source of comfort, peace</l>
					<l>and joy. Thus a grand view of nature proved</l>
					<l>the occasion of an animating manifestation of</l>
					<l>of divine love.</l>
					<l>Another instance is this. For a consider-</l>
					<l>able time my heart had been as cold as ice, and</l>
					<l>dead as a stone, altho&apos; I was not particularly</l>
					<l>by tempitations, or the workings of my corrupt</l>
					<l>nature, and tho&apos; I was well convinced, that this</l>
					<l>was a lamentable state, I had neither power</l>
					<l>nor inclination to pray for a change, &amp; for</l>
					<l>a return of my former blessed &amp; tender feeling.</l>
					<l>In this state I took a solitary walk into a</l>
					<l>wood, and laid myself, dead &amp; cold as I was</l>
					<l>at the feet of my Savior and cried: &quot;Lord,</l>
					<l>have mercy upon me.&quot; It was not long before</l>
					<l>such a transition took place, as if I had been</l>
					<l>translated from darkness into light, &amp; from</l>
					<l>death into life, God revealed himself to me</l>
					<l>in his unspeakable love. And O! how often</l>
					<l>has he by an unexpected touch, without any</l>
					<l>particular occasion, melted my heart, how</l>
					<l>often has he drawn me with chords of love.</l>
					<l>when I was least aware of it, yea, how often</l>
					<l>has he laid his hand upon me, when I was</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='14'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>on the point of deviating from the right</l>
					<l>path and going astray, and if at any time.</l>
					<l>my frail nature had swerved beyond the</l>
					<l>proper bounds, he soon created in me a god-</l>
					<l>ly sorrow on account of it, and then again</l>
					<l>filled my heart with peace and comfort.</l>
					<l>During my stay at Fulneck I experienced</l>
					<l>a particular prresenation of my life. Being</l>
					<l>one Sunday sent to Baildon to preach, I</l>
					<l>took a short road, where I had to cross a small</l>
					<l>river, wch, in dry weather is fordable on step-</l>
					<l>ping stones, but was now so swelled by the rain</l>
					<l>that it could only be crossed over in a boat.</l>
					<l>The ferryman having gone to Church, a</l>
					<l>stout looking boy offered to ferry me over &amp;</l>
					<l>we set off, but when we had got into the</l>
					<l>middle of the stream, he found it so rapid</l>
					<l>that he lost the command of the boat, &amp; was</l>
					<l>obliged to let it go down with the current,</l>
					<l>which carried us into a mill race, &amp; brought</l>
					<l>us to the very edge of the mill dam, from</l>
					<l>which the superfluous water was precipitatg</l>
					<l>itself into a bed of stones. We now expected</l>
					<l>to go down the fall and to be dashed among</l>
					<l>the stones wch had happened to others in this</l>
					<l>place, who lost their lives, and indeed the</l>
					<l>people came running from the mill &amp; the</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='15'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>adjacent houses, to see what would be come</l>
					<l>of us. But when we came to the edge of the</l>
					<l>fall, the boat instead of going down with</l>
					<l>the torrent, gliding gently along close to the</l>
					<l>edge, safely passed the waterfall, two young</l>
					<l>men from the mill then got into the boat,</l>
					<l>and ferried me safe over the river. Having</l>
					<l>thus received, as it were, my life anew out</l>
					<l>of the hand of God, I dedicated it anew to</l>
					<l>him, to spend it in his service &amp; to his glory.</l>
					<l>In the year 1770 I was called to Dublin,</l>
					<l>these to have the care of the single Brn and</l>
					<l>Boys, including the Children, as also to</l>
					<l>assist in preaching. Previous to my setting</l>
					<l>out I was ordained a Deacon of the Brns</l>
					<l>Church by Br. Johannes de Watteville then</l>
					<l>on a visit at Fulneck.</l>
					<l>During my 5 years service in that Congn,</l>
					<l>I experienced much patience, long-suffering</l>
					<l>&amp; forbearance, but also much grace &amp; favor</l>
					<l>from my bountiful Lord. Many temptations</l>
					<l>indeed from the side of an evil world presented</l>
					<l>themselves to my view &amp; I had no power</l>
					<l>in myself to resist, but rather found my</l>
					<l>treacherous heart but too ready and prone</l>
					<l>to engage in unprofitable things; but I cried</l>
					<l>to the Lord in my distress, &amp; he heard my cry</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='16'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and delivered me in every time of need,</l>
					<l>As the Congn. at that time was desirous, that</l>
					<l>a Boys day school should be instituted under</l>
					<l>the Brns direction and management, I was</l>
					<l>glad of being servicable in establishing and</l>
					<l>promoting said institution, wch indeed in</l>
					<l>the beginning afforded but an unpromising as-</l>
					<l>pect, but in process of time began to prosper</l>
					<l>beyond our expectation and was attended with</l>
					<l>the Lord&apos;s blessing.</l>
					<l>In August 1783, that is, 11 years after my</l>
					<l>arrival in England, I received Call, to be</l>
					<l>one of the Writers to the U.E.C., wch I accepted</l>
					<l>from the conviction, that it came from the</l>
					<l>Lord. But it lasted till February following,</l>
					<l>before I could set out on my passage to Ger-</l>
					<l>many. Several occurrences render&apos;d this jour-</l>
					<l>ney very remarkable. First I lost all my</l>
					<l>goods, when the Ship, in which I was send-</l>
					<l>ing them from Dublin to London, was wrecked</l>
					<l>on the Welsh Coast, wch loss however did not</l>
					<l>affect me much as my immediate wants</l>
					<l>were relieved by the Brn &amp; Srs in Dublin</l>
					<l>according to their wonted liberality. The</l>
					<l>next difficulty arose from the hard winter</l>
					<l>then prevailing. The landing in Holland</l>
					<l>had been render&apos;d very difficult &amp; expensive</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='17'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>by the ice living the coast, and requiring</l>
					<l>ice boats to land the passengers, it was but</l>
					<l>just cleared of the ice when I had to go over.</l>
					<l>The ice having been stopped both in the</l>
					<l>Rhine and in the Elbe, dreadful inunda-</l>
					<l>tions had ensued, wch rendered the roads im-</l>
					<l>passable, and when I left Zeist it was with</l>
					<l>the first post waggon that could travel, &amp;</l>
					<l>still in several places the road was intersected</l>
					<l>by the water. Thus I saw a hand of provi-</l>
					<l>dence in it, that my setting out from Dublin</l>
					<l>had been so long delayed. But when I had</l>
					<l>reached the borders of Germany, the winter</l>
					<l>set in again, it snowed day and night and</l>
					<l>the roads were rendered nearly impracticable.</l>
					<l>One night we actually stuck fast in the snow</l>
					<l>and we could not have been extricated, if there</l>
					<l>had not been another carriage in company,</l>
					<l>whose horses joined to ours rescued us from our</l>
					<l>disagreable situation. In short, I had so</l>
					<l>much to suffer from cold, sickness and fatigue</l>
					<l>that when at last I reached Barby in the</l>
					<l>beginning of April, my heart was full of</l>
					<l>thanks and praises for my presentation, and</l>
					<l>I found my faith and confidence in divine,</l>
					<l>providence much strengthened, and indeed</l>
					<l>it was a wonder to me, that I had been kept </l>
					<l>safe and sound.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='18'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>In August 1784 I was married to my late</l>
					<l>wife Johanna Eleanora Gaertinor, &amp; in Septr</l>
					<l>moved with the U.E.C. to Herrnhut. Here in</l>
					<l>consequence of the hardships I had suffered on</l>
					<l>my journey from Holland, as before described</l>
					<l>I had to indure a severe illness, and was brought</l>
					<l>nigh unto death, but it proved a salutary effort</l>
					<l>of nature, under the divine blesing, to bring</l>
					<l>about a better and more durable state of health</l>
					<l>than I had enjoyed before. I shall never</l>
					<l>forget, what comfort and encouragement</l>
					<l>I received during this illness when once in</l>
					<l>a sleepless night, my mind laboring under</l>
					<l>great distress, the watchman passing under</l>
					<l>my window, began to sing with a charming</l>
					<l>voice:. Herr Jesu, unser Flehen etc.</l>
					<l>Hear our prayer, gracious Savior Jesus,</l>
					<l>Friend of Soul so dearly bought!</l>
					<l>Let thy grace prevail and bless us,</l>
					<l>Far beyond our feeble thought!</l>
					<l>Lead us ever with thy favor</l>
					<l>That we may in times succeeding</l>
					<l>See from grace to grace proceeding.</l>
					<l>My appointment as Writer to the U.E.C.</l>
					<l>was exceedingly pleasant to me, tho&apos; very</l>
					<l>laborious, and I was sorry to be soon called</l>
					<l>to another station. For in the year following</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='19'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I was appointed Minister of the Congn</l>
					<l>at Neusalz, and having been ordained a</l>
					<l>Presbyter by Br Spangenberg, I arrived there</l>
					<l>with my wife, who was then pregnant, the</l>
					<l>23d of March, after a difficult and hazardous</l>
					<l>journey, the snow being uncommonly deep.</l>
					<l>The state of the Congn whom we came to</l>
					<l>serve, was such, that we might have been</l>
					<l>discouraged from undertaking the office</l>
					<l>if our Lord had not supported us with the</l>
					<l>believing hope, that he would be with us,</l>
					<l>&amp; bless our service which hope was in the</l>
					<l>sequel realised beyond our expectation.</l>
					<l>In 1785 the Lord blessed us with the birth</l>
					<l>of a Son, whom we dedicated unto Him</l>
					<l>as his blood bought property.</l>
					<l>But now began a scene of domestic distress,</l>
					<l>wch under a various changes &amp; vicissitudes,</l>
					<l>lasted till the happy departure of my be-</l>
					<l>loved wife, who during a period of 6 years</l>
					<l>had to endure one sickness after another,</l>
					<l>&amp; even in the intervals did not enjoy any</l>
					<l>comfortable state of health. The early de-</l>
					<l>parture of our little Son who for half a</l>
					<l>year labored under a gradual decline, con-</l>
					<l>tributed much to the injury of her frame,</l>
					<l>as she took it much to heart.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='20'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>During this period I was often harrassed</l>
					<l>by such a variety and multiplicity of distresses</l>
					<l>and perplexiting circumstances, that I should</l>
					<l>have been quite unfit for the duties of my office</l>
					<l>and the service of the Congn, if our Savior</l>
					<l>had not supported me in an extraordinary</l>
					<l>manner, next to wch the love and kindness</l>
					<l>we experienced from our Brn &amp; Srs was also</l>
					<l>a great help and benefit to us.</l>
					<l>In the beginning of 1789 we were called</l>
					<l>upon to officiate during the Synod at Gna-</l>
					<l>denfrey, while both the Congn Helper &amp; the</l>
					<l>Minister of that Congn were attending the</l>
					<l>Synod. My dear wife was but just recovering</l>
					<l>from a severe illness, and still so weak, that</l>
					<l>she could not cross the room without help</l>
					<l>nevertheless we accepted the call in reliance</l>
					<l>upon our Savior&apos;s support, who graciously</l>
					<l>answered our prayers on that occasion.</l>
					<l>Our short residence at Gnadenfrey was in-</l>
					<l>deed attended with much labor and fatigue,</l>
					<l>but we also experienced much of our Savior&apos;s</l>
					<l>help in time of need, &amp; were strengthened by</l>
					<l>the mutual support of our fellow labourers</l>
					<l>and the general love of the Brn &amp; Srs, so that</l>
					<l>our hearts overflowed with thanks and praises </l>
					<l>when in the spring 1790 we set out for England,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='21'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>having been appointed by the Synod La-</l>
					<l>borers of the London Congn.</l>
					<l>We arrived in London in June following</l>
					<l>Here we had again to pass thro&apos; a variety of</l>
					<l>new &amp; heavy trials; the increasing sickliness</l>
					<l>of my wife soon disabled her from attending</l>
					<l>her office, and terminated at last in a confirmed</l>
					<l>decline. This and other distresses had such</l>
					<l>an effect upon my whole frame, that I</l>
					<l>felt sick and was again brought nigh unto</l>
					<l>death. The Lord however blessed the means</l>
					<l>used for my recovery, and strengthened me</l>
					<l>anew, to administer my last help to my dear</l>
					<l>wife now hastening to her dissolution, and</l>
					<l>to wait upon her, till she was permitted to</l>
					<l>enter into her eternal rest.</l>
					<l>At the close of this period taking a retrospect-</l>
					<l>ing view of the various afflicting dispensations</l>
					<l>I had passed thro&apos;, and which at times seemed</l>
					<l>to bear to hard upon me, I could thank our</l>
					<l>Savior with heartfelt gratitude for all the de-</l>
					<l>monstrations of his love and goodness, and for</l>
					<l>causing all things to work together for my good</l>
					<l>I am fully convinced from my own experience</l>
					<l>that He doth all things well, that all his chast-</l>
					<l>enings on love, and that our short affliction</l>
					<l>wch is but for a moment, worketh a far more</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='22'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>exceeding and eternal weight of glory, while</l>
					<l>we look not at the things wch are seen, but at</l>
					<l>the things wch are not seen.</l>
					<l>After the happy departure of my late Wife</l>
					<l>in January 1792 I spent one year as a Wi-</l>
					<l>dower, and our Savior granted me a time of</l>
					<l>refreshing rest. In September the same year</l>
					<l>I received an appointment, to serve the Congn</l>
					<l>at Bedford, but circumstances delayed my</l>
					<l>going thither till the year following.</l>
					<l>On the 2d. April 1793 I was married to the</l>
					<l>S. Sr Jane Dodgson, and soon after we went</l>
					<l>to Bedford.</l>
					<l>Our stay there was upon the whole very</l>
					<l>agreeable, and we richly enjoyed the blessing</l>
					<l>of God, and the love and confidence of our Brn</l>
					<l>&amp; Srs. We had indeed also our share of diffi-</l>
					<l>culties, but the Lord helped us thro&apos; them all.</l>
					<l>When we found ourselves quite comfortably</l>
					<l>settled, we received a Call to Dublin, and ar-</l>
					<l>rived there in December 1794.</l>
					<l>As we both had served this Congn before,</l>
					<l>tho&apos; in different capacities, &amp; pretty well</l>
					<l>knew beforehand, what difficulties awaited</l>
					<l>us to encounter, we felt rather heavy on that</l>
					<l>account, but nevertheless, trusted in the</l>
					<l>Lord, that he would continue to support us,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='23'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>as he had done hitherto. Nor was our confi-</l>
					<l>dence put to shame, and amidst our own</l>
					<l>infirmities, and various trials we had to pass</l>
					<l>thro&apos; we enjoyed much grace and blessing</l>
					<l>from our Savior, and his gracious support</l>
					<l>in every time of need.</l>
					<l>One of the heaviest trials, which occurred</l>
					<l>during this period, was that dreadful re-</l>
					<l>bellion, wch while it lasted, raged with sa-</l>
					<l>vage fury, and more than once threatened</l>
					<l>destruction to the City of Dublin. It was well</l>
					<l>for us, not to know the full extent of the</l>
					<l>dangers we were surrounded with tho&apos; we</l>
					<l>were also frequently alarmed by false reports</l>
					<l>and needless apprehensions. Frequently the</l>
					<l>state of things was such, that our lives seem&apos;d</l>
					<l>to hang by a slender thread, and on several</l>
					<l>occasions it was a serious question, we had</l>
					<l>to put to ourselves, whether we were duly</l>
					<l>prepared to meet the impending fate, tho&apos;</l>
					<l>we should be carried off by a sudden stroke.</l>
					<l>Our hope was in the Lord, who heard our</l>
					<l>humble prayers and supplications for the</l>
					<l>good of the country, and granted a happy</l>
					<l>issue to that awful contest wch, if it had</l>
					<l>terminated in the intended revolution &amp; sub-</l>
					<l>version of the existing Government, would</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='24'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>would have occasioned scenes of unparalled</l>
					<l>cruelty, massacre and devastation. </l>
					<l>We were thankful to the Lord, that we not</l>
					<l>could</l>
					<l>only possess our own Souls in patience, but also</l>
					<l>administer comfort and encouragement to others.</l>
					<l>During that time I also experienced a remark-</l>
					<l>able preservation from bodily harm, having</l>
					<l>my legs nearly crushed by a brewer&apos;s dray drive-</l>
					<l>ing against a jaunting car, in wch I was sitting</l>
					<l>sideways. The injury I received was however</l>
					<l>such, that for a considerable time I was pre-</l>
					<l>vented officiating in the Church. But far</l>
					<l>more important was the preservation of my</l>
					<l>Soul in the midst of so many temptations</l>
					<l>abounding in such a large City, wch I could</l>
					<l>by no means overcome by my own strength,</l>
					<l>but solely by looking unto Jesus the Author</l>
					<l>&amp; Finisher of my faith.</l>
					<l>And let me here observe again, that for</l>
					<l>the most part of my life scarcely a day has</l>
					<l>passed, when I had not some humbling</l>
					<l>sense &amp; symptom of the vileness &amp; depravity</l>
					<l>of my nature, which caused me to mourn &amp;</l>
					<l>to seek help and comfort in our Savior, the</l>
					<l>blessed consequence of wch was, that I also ex-</l>
					<l>perienced the comforts of his pardoning &amp; reviving</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='25'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>grace. This constant need of a Savior, and</l>
					<l>the never failing help and refuge I found</l>
					<l>in Him, proved to me the reality of the</l>
					<l>Gospel, and my sure interest in Christ&apos;s re-</l>
					<l>demption. And as my experience tallied with</l>
					<l>the written word of God, it confirmed my high</l>
					<l>regard and veneration for the sacred oracles:</l>
					<l>or else that stupendous &amp; all conception far</l>
					<l>surpassing fact: God was manifest in the</l>
					<l>flesh, and suffer&apos;d blood and died for Sinners,</l>
					<l>would have utterly confounded my reason</l>
					<l>&amp; understanding and staggered all belief.</l>
					<l>When the Synod of 1801 had come to a close,</l>
					<l>and I had received no intimation of an intended</l>
					<l>change, I concluded, that I should continue</l>
					<l>in the service of the Dublin Congn &amp; therefore</l>
					<l>devoted myself anew to the Lord for that pur-</l>
					<l>pose. But while I was sitting in my room</l>
					<l>in this happy fame of mind, the postman</l>
					<l>brought a letter, contain<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>g</hi> our appointment</l>
					<l>to the service of Fulneck Cong<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>n</hi>. This indeed</l>
					<l>came very unexpected, and was not altogether</l>
					<l>agreeable to our wishes, as we were much</l>
					<l>attached to the Dublin Congn, with whom we</l>
					<l>had shared a great deal of joy, as well as of</l>
					<l>distress and trouble, particularly during the</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='26'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>late rebellion. But having devoted ourselves</l>
					<l>unreservedly to the Lord&apos;s service, &amp; promised</l>
					<l>obedience to his will and guidance, we could</l>
					<l>do no other than accept of that new appointment.</l>
					<l>We arrived at Fulneck Nov. 10. 1801, and on</l>
					<l>the 13th following, on wch day 65 years ago</l>
					<l>I had experienced the first real and abiding</l>
					<l>manifestation of Jesus love and grace, I was</l>
					<l>according to a Synodal resolution, confirmed</l>
					<l>by the Lord, consecrated a Bishop of the Brns</l>
					<l>Church by the Brn Traneker and Moore, on</l>
					<l>wch occasion I was so overpowerd by the grace</l>
					<l>of God, that with purpose of heart, and without</l>
					<l>any reserve whatever, I surrender&apos;d myself anew</l>
					<l>to my Lord &amp; Savior and from a pure motive</l>
					<l>of love and gratitude for his lovingkindness</l>
					<l>and goodness towards me, dedicated my fu-</l>
					<l>ture services to Him in that house &amp; family</l>
					<l>of his own to which He had graciously led</l>
					<l>me in my early youth.</l>
					<l>On this occasion it will not be improper</l>
					<l>for me, to state my views respectg the Brn</l>
					<l>Congn, to wch I have the favor to belong.</l>
					<l>The Church of Christ here on earth appears</l>
					<l>to me like a large and fruitful gardens, con-</l>
					<l>sisting of a number of compartments or divisions</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='27'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>differing indeed both in arrangement &amp; cul-</l>
					<l>ture, but all under the care and managment</l>
					<l>of one &amp; the same Gardener; who appoints</l>
					<l>Laborers for each division of his garden &amp;</l>
					<l>vineyard, instructing them in the proper mode</l>
					<l>of cultivating that part which is exclusively</l>
					<l>committed to them. Now it is well known,</l>
					<l>that different plants require both a different</l>
					<l>treatment and a different soil, &amp; would not e-</l>
					<l>qually prosper in a soil less congenial to their</l>
					<l>texture and nature. So it is with the different</l>
					<l>denominations in the Christian Church. All</l>
					<l>of them, that confess Jesus Christ to be their</l>
					<l>Lord and Master, and walk in the way of his</l>
					<l>precepts and commandments deriving from</l>
					<l>him wisdom, righteousness, sanctification and</l>
					<l>redemption, and keeping the word of his pa-</l>
					<l>tience, belong to the Lord&apos;s vineyard, &amp; occupy</l>
					<l>different compartments where they receive a</l>
					<l>different treatment under their peculiar</l>
					<l>form and constitution; there they find them-</l>
					<l>selves at home and thrive best. Thus there</l>
					<l>are many excellent Children of God, whom our</l>
					<l>constitution, discipline and outward form</l>
					<l>would not suit, and who would not like to</l>
					<l>be confined within our fold. And thus on the</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='28'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>other hand those whom our Savior has</l>
					<l>called to the Brns Church, &amp; who are genuine</l>
					<l>members of the same, could not foot themselves</l>
					<l>at home in any other denomination, nor be</l>
					<l>so much further&apos;d in their course any where else.</l>
					<l>This at least is my case, conviction and ex-</l>
					<l>perience, and the Brs Church has proved</l>
					<l>to me the most congenial soil for growing in</l>
					<l>the grace and knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.</l>
					<l>It is in this fold, that I have been screened and</l>
					<l>secured from the deleterious influence of se-</l>
					<l>duction, so common among young people when</l>
					<l>left to themselves; it is there that I received</l>
					<l>a careful education, combining the know- </l>
					<l>ledge of spiritual things with useful learning</l>
					<l>of things pertaining to this life: it is there that</l>
					<l>by serving in a variety of situations &amp; passing</l>
					<l>thro&apos; various trials, peculiar to our connection</l>
					<l>with one another, I was qualified both to feed</l>
					<l>the sheep of Christ, and from my own expe-</l>
					<l>rience to lead them deeper into a proper ap-</l>
					<l>plication of the word of life &amp; the merits of our</l>
					<l>Lord Jesus Christ; it is there, that the gifts &amp;</l>
					<l>talents allotted to me, can be more usefully em-</l>
					<l>ployed than any where else, and finally it is</l>
					<l>there, that my heavenly race meets with the</l>
					<l>least obstruction &amp; with the best encouragement.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='29'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>If therefore others have the same special Call,</l>
					<l>let them obey it, and they will find themselves</l>
					<l>in the right place, they will thrive &amp; prosper</l>
					<l>and they will clearly see from their blessed</l>
					<l>experience, that He, who has called them, is</l>
					<l>faithful to perform the purposes of their call<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>g</hi></l>
					<l>and election. And Oh! that our young people,</l>
					<l>who are born and bred in our Congn, and thus</l>
					<l>have a clear Call to it, might duly reflect on</l>
					<l>our Savior&apos;s views with them in regard to</l>
					<l>their course thro&apos; life and be duly concerned</l>
					<l>to inherit the blessing of their Parents &amp; An-</l>
					<l>cestors. And Oh! may the Brns people never</l>
					<l>forget, that the Lord has formed them for him-</l>
					<l>self, to be his witnesses, to confess him among</l>
					<l>men as the only Savior of perishing Sinners,</l>
					<l>to be living monuments of his redeemg grace</l>
					<l>and power, and persevere in their endeavors</l>
					<l>for the conversion of heathen nations; and</l>
					<l>Oh! may they, walking in the fear of the Lord,</l>
					<l>and in the comfort of the Holy Ghost be mul-</l>
					<l>tiplied! Amen.</l>
					<l>But to resume my Narrative. When I en-</l>
					<l>tered upon the service of Fulneck Congn, I was</l>
					<l>well aware of the multiplicity of labor, cares</l>
					<l>and difficulties belonging to it, nor could I think</l>
					<l>myself sufficient for that station, but nevertheless</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='30'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I submitted to every part of my calling in</l>
					<l>reliance upon our Saviors gracious support</l>
					<l>wch. I also richly experienced under a variety of </l>
					<l>heavy circumstances. In the beginning it was</l>
					<l>a great help to me, that our late dear Brother</l>
					<l>Traneker still continued for some time to act</l>
					<l>as Congn. Helper and to take some share in</l>
					<l>the labor, but after his departure I had to en-</l>
					<l>ter fully upon the exercise of all my functions</l>
					<l>as Congn. Helper Minister &amp; Inspector of the</l>
					<l>Schools.</l>
					<l>Every period of the Brns. Church has been</l>
					<l>attended with its own peculiar difficulties</l>
					<l>but what renders the office of a Laborer in</l>
					<l>such a situation now a days more particu-</l>
					<l>larly embarrassing, is the want of proper</l>
					<l>persons for managing the Concerns of a Place</l>
					<l>Congn., and for serving our Boarding Schools</l>
					<l>as Teachers or Assistants, or in any other ca-</l>
					<l>pacity. If therefore a vacancy happens, it is</l>
					<l>no easy matter to fill it up again with a</l>
					<l>proper qualified person. At one time in par-</l>
					<l>ticular this circumstance caused me much dis-</l>
					<l>tress of mind, and I cried day and night to the</l>
					<l>to the Lord for help, till it came from quar-</l>
					<l>ter, from when I had least expected it. On the</l>
					<l>other hand I found abundant cause to rejoice,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='31'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>over the blessing, which the Lord had laid</l>
					<l>upon the Schools. For when I first came to</l>
					<l>Fulneck in the year 1772, as first Teacher of</l>
					<l>the Boys Oeconomy, consisting at that time</l>
					<l>of about I Boys, I found it in such needy</l>
					<l>circumstances, and so low in the estimation</l>
					<l>of others, that it required much patience to</l>
					<l>endure it, and much faith to hope for better</l>
					<l>times. And on my return in the year 1801</l>
					<l>I found a School of about 70 Boys settled</l>
					<l>in a new house built for the purpose, and</l>
					<l>another of upwards of 50 Girls occuping the</l>
					<l>lower apartments under the Chapel, placed</l>
					<l>under our care in easy circumstances This</l>
					<l>was to me a most striking proof, that the</l>
					<l>Lord sees our tears, hears our prayers, &amp; in</l>
					<l>due time grants our petitions, yet doth ex-</l>
					<l>ceeding abundantly above all that we can ask</l>
					<l>or think, for his own name&apos;s sake. My only</l>
					<l>wish and prayer was, that we might be able,</l>
					<l>to do justice to our important calling. And</l>
					<l>in this respect, as all others, I was heartily</l>
					<l>thankful to our Saviors and admired his</l>
					<l>gracious leading, that in my dear wife he-</l>
					<l>had given me a partner, well qualified for</l>
					<l>our station and respective employments</l>
					<l>In the year 1810 I was brought very low and</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='32'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and much reduced by a slow nervous fever</l>
					<l>wch almost incapacitated me for any time</l>
					<l>but still I was not entirely laid up, &amp; could</l>
					<l>transact the most urgent matters.</l>
					<l>Our service in Fulneck, arduous &amp; laborious</l>
					<l>at best, on account of the multiplicity of our</l>
					<l>incumbencies, was in the 2 last years rendered</l>
					<l>still more<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'> so</hi> by the misfortunes, occasioned by</l>
					<l>the spirit of speculation in trade, wch was</l>
					<l>then prevailing throughout the mercantile</l>
					<l>community and was the cause of innume-</l>
					<l>table ruinous failures. The reproach, which</l>
					<l>then, tho&apos; undeservedly; fall upon the Cong<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>n</hi></l>
					<l>and its Servants, and other highly distressing</l>
					<l>circumstances bore heavy upon our minds</l>
					<l>but at the same time we were so stren<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>g</hi>then&apos;d</l>
					<l>by the Lord, and supported by his powerful</l>
					<l>aid, that we were able to bear up under</l>
					<l>all trials and difficulties</l>
					<l>Upon the whole, when we survey our 11</l>
					<l>years residence and labor in Fulneck, our</l>
					<l>hearts are filled with gratitude for the in-</l>
					<l>numerable proofs of the unchangeable love.</l>
					<l>grace and mercy of our Lord and Master, ex-</l>
					<l>perienced both in our private course, &amp; in</l>
					<l>our official labors. Nor is it the least of his</l>
					<l>favors, that he counted us worthy, to serve</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='33'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>not only the Fulneck Congn, but also its</l>
					<l>dependencies, the rest of our Cong<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>n</hi> in York-</l>
					<l>shire, and their numerous Schools.</l>
					<l>In the year 1<hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>7</hi>811 we received our Call to Ire-</l>
					<l>land, where, besides our, joint offices, I was</l>
					<l>to succeed our late Br. Hartley in that of</l>
					<l>Prov. Helper of Ireland, &amp; Minister of Grace-</l>
					<l>hill; but it lasted till October 1812, before</l>
					<l>we could set out for our new post where we</l>
					<l>arrived on the 14th of that month.</l>
					<l>In this new situation I feel again every day</l>
					<l>anew the absolute necessity, to look to Jesus</l>
					<l>the Author and Finisher of my faith, that I may</l>
					<l>not only be prese<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi>ved from sin and the evils of</l>
					<l>a corrupt nature, but also grow up in his like-</l>
					<l>ness in all things. along with an humbling</l>
					<l>sense of the entire depravity of soul &amp; body,</l>
					<l>and the constant need of a Physician, &amp; under</l>
					<l>a deep conviction, that I am not worthy of</l>
					<l>the least of all his mercies, I am favored with</l>
					<l>a high conception of my heavenly calling</l>
					<l>and election of grace, and of the infinite worth</l>
					<l>of that crown of life, which the Lord, the</l>
					<l>righteous Judge, shall give unto all them</l>
					<l>that love his appearing. But oh!, how often</l>
					<l>do I feel an unaccountable listlessness, and</l>
					<l>must blame myself for culpable tardiness</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='34'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>in proving that holiness without which</l>
					<l>no man shall see the Lord. How often do I</l>
					<l>feel irksome, when he applies the refiner&apos;s</l>
					<l>fire and the fuller&apos;s soap to the purifying of</l>
					<l>my sinful nature. tho&apos; I ought to be thank</l>
					<l>ful, that he is so unremittingly engaged with</l>
					<l>my poor Soul, and so constantly intent upon</l>
					<l>carrying on the good work he has begun</l>
					<l>Oh that I could now spend the remainder of</l>
					<l>my pilgrimage to the joy and honor of Him</l>
					<l>who has redeemed me from all iniquity and</l>
					<l>given me power to become a Child of God</l>
					<l>and an heir of eternal bliss and glory.</l>
					<l>What inmumerable escapes &amp; preservations</l>
					<l>of my soul have I experienced in the course</l>
					<l>of my pilgrimage, little known to them</l>
					<l>who were conversant with me &amp; could not</l>
					<l>observe the various temptations, besetting</l>
					<l>me from within and from without, and</l>
					<l>the trials arising as much from my natural</l>
					<l>disposition, as from unpleasant occurences.</l>
					<l>Tho&apos; I am truly thankful for that share</l>
					<l>&amp; confidence, which I have enjoyed in every</l>
					<l>Congn whom I had the favor to serve, and</l>
					<l>that I could live in peace &amp; harmony with</l>
					<l>my fellow laborors. tho&apos; I was perfectly sa-</l>
					<l>tisfied with my situation in life and tem-</l>
					<l>poral</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='35'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>poral circumstances, yea could truly say, even</l>
					<l>in this respect&quot; my lot has fallen to me in a</l>
					<l>pleasant place, and I have got a goodly heritage,&quot;</l>
					<l>tho&apos; in general I have enjoyed a good state of</l>
					<l>health, and was possessed of a variety of tem--</l>
					<l>poral blessings, suited to my taste and natural</l>
					<l>disposition, taking particular delight in works</l>
					<l>of art, and the beauties of nature: yet, with</l>
					<l>all these advantages, the world would have<hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>th</hi></l>
					<l>been to me a true vale of tears, and much</l>
					<l>mourning and weeping has attended me on</l>
					<l>my pilgrimage. But I have also derived</l>
					<l>constant consolation from the suffering life</l>
					<l>of my dear Redeemer; And O! how blessed</l>
					<l>was it for me, that by the afflictions of this</l>
					<l>life I was continually excited, to look forward</l>
					<l>to the end of my earthly warfare &amp; pilgrimage,</l>
					<l>and to the blessed moment, when I shall</l>
					<l>be permitted, to enter into the joy of my Lord,</l>
					<l>and to rest from all my labors.</l>
					<l>It behoves me to mention in this place,</l>
					<l>that besides the reading of the holy Scriptures</l>
					<l>which afforded a rich and delightful pasture</l>
					<l>to my mind, I was also much benefited by</l>
					<l>many hymns in our Collection, especially such</l>
					<l>as tallied with the experience &amp; feelings of my</l>
					<l>own heart; and many sleepless hours in the</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='36'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>night have I spent agreeably in repeating</l>
					<l>or rehearsing such as were familiar to in</l>
					<l>recollection and suitable to my circumstances.</l>
					<l>And how shall I now O Lord thou God</l>
					<l>of my salvation, express unto Thee my infi-</l>
					<l>nite obligations whose mercy towards me</l>
					<l>has been new every morning. Thou didid sepa-</l>
					<l>rate me from my mother&apos;s womb, and set thy</l>
					<l>love upon me, before ever I had heard thy name</l>
					<l>and before I could make the least returns</l>
					<l>Thro&apos; thy kind providence I had both in me</l>
					<l>respected Parents and in my<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'> 6</hi> Teachers faithful</l>
					<l>guides of my youth, and in my early days</l>
					<l>was favored to hear the joyful sound of the</l>
					<l>gospel, and to have a crucified Savior set be- </l>
					<l>fore the eyes of my poor and contrite spirit</l>
					<l>Altho&apos; thro&apos; thy tender care and divine power</l>
					<l>I was preserved from the snares of an evil world,</l>
					<l>from the wiles of Satan, and from the de-</l>
					<l>structive power of Sin; yet thro&apos; the teaching</l>
					<l>of thy holySpirit I was thoroughly convinced</l>
					<l>both of the total corruption of my nature and</l>
					<l>its helpless state, and of the necessity to flee</l>
					<l>for refuge and to lay hold of the hope that is</l>
					<l>set before us. How can I thank Thee sufficiently</l>
					<l>for all the clear evidences &amp; blessed manifestations</l>
					<l>of thy love and goodness towards me, &amp; of the</l>
					<l>healing</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='37'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>healing, sanctifying and guickening virtue</l>
					<l>of thy precious blood, without w<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>ch</hi> I must</l>
					<l>have perished in the leprosy of sin. What</l>
					<l>a poor unhappy mortal should I have been</l>
					<l>continually harrassed and tormented with</l>
					<l>pride, ambition, envy and jealousy, and</l>
					<l>destroying myself in the service of Sin, if</l>
					<l>I had not found in Thee deliverance, peace</l>
					<l>of mind and rest of soul. Thro&apos; thy grace</l>
					<l>it was my happy lot, to live content under</l>
					<l>all the various dispensations of thy kind</l>
					<l>providence, and in every place of my</l>
					<l>earthly residence. Thou hast taken great</l>
					<l>pains to train <hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>my</hi> me for thy service, and</l>
					<l>to qualify me for every situation in thy</l>
					<l>house, to wch I was appointed, but ah!</l>
					<l>how short did I fall of that Zeal &amp; activity,</l>
					<l>wch I ought to have shown in the perform-</l>
					<l>ance of my duties! To glorify Thee with all</l>
					<l>the faculties and abilities of spirit, soul and</l>
					<l>body, because they were bought with a price,</l>
					<l>and preserved from the destructive power of</l>
					<l>sin, should have been my constant study</l>
					<l>by day and night. Thy rich forgeveness</l>
					<l>must cover all my short comings, neglects</l>
					<l>&amp; omissions. And O how readily hast Thou</l>
					<l>pardoned thy unprofitable Servant on all</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='38'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>occasions, meeting me half way falling about</l>
					<l>my neck and kissing me, even before I could</l>
					<l>make my humble confession with tears of re-</l>
					<l>pentance and contrtion. However unde-</l>
					<l>serving I may be, still I can rest upon that</l>
					<l>gracious promise of thine:&quot; where I am there</l>
					<l>shall also my Servant be!&quot; And O! how do I</l>
					<l>rejoice with joy unspeakable and full of glory</l>
					<l>at the enchanting prospect before me, to</l>
					<l>enter once into thy blissful presence, to be </l>
					<l>for ever at home with thee, to behold this glo-</l>
					<l>rious countenance, to come unto mount Sion</l>
					<l>and to the City of the living God, the heavenly</l>
					<l>Jerusalem, to an inumerable company of</l>
					<l>Angels, to the general Assembly &amp; Church of</l>
					<l>the firsbom wch are written in heaven &amp; to </l>
					<l>God the Judge of all</l>
					<l>Till then I will lean on Thee, my Beloved</l>
					<l>while walking thro&apos; the wildemess, and live</l>
					<l>by the faith of the Son of God, who has loved</l>
					<l>me and given himself for me. Amen.</l>
					<l>Thus far written in the year 1814-</l>
					<l>S.J.. Benade</l>
					<l>Note. The following occurrence has been</l>
					<l>omitted in the foregoing Narrative, wch how-</l>
					<l>ever belongs to the remarkable incidents of my</l>
					<l>Life</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='39'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Life.-- In the year 1803 two Tahitian youths,</l>
					<l>Meydow and Olai, had been by the London</l>
					<l>mission Society committed to the care of Br Wm</l>
					<l>Okely then Minister of our Congn at Mirfield,</l>
					<l>for their instruction both in the English lan-</l>
					<l>guage &amp; in the Christian doctrine. Their</l>
					<l>moral conduct had been from the beginning</l>
					<l>correct and exemplary, and latterly they gave</l>
					<l>clear evidences of religious impressions &amp; of a</l>
					<l>work of grace in their hearts. Having ex-</l>
					<l>pressed a desire after baptism, and being</l>
					<l>instructed in the spiritual character of this</l>
					<l>holy ordinance, it was administered to them</l>
					<l>by our Lords approbation, in a solemn assembly</l>
					<l>in the Chapel, Meydow receiving the name</l>
					<l>of Joseph and Olai that of Christian; after</l>
					<l>wch within a short period they both fell asleep</l>
					<l>in Jesus, Joseph first, and his brother Christian</l>
					<l>not many days after.</l>
					<l>To myself it was not only a pleasant duty,</l>
					<l>but also a great favor, to be thus made instru-</l>
					<l>mental in administering holy baptisin to</l>
					<l>those two Tahitian Youths and to perform</l>
					<l>the office of a Heathen Messenger in Christian</l>
					<l>country.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='40'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>October.28th 1817</l>
					<l> Seventy one years have now passed away since</l>
					<l>I was born, and fifty years, since I entered into</l>
					<l>the service of the B rethren&apos;s Unity for which</l>
					<l>had been destined and educated from my</l>
					<l>early youth. How precious are thy thoughts</l>
					<l>unto me, O God! how great is the Sum of them&apos;</l>
					<l>If I could count them, they are more in num</l>
					<l>ber than the sand. Bless the Lord, O my Soul</l>
					<l>and all that is within, bless his holy Name!</l>
					<l>From all eternity with love--  unchangeable</l>
					<l>Thou hast me view&apos;d--Ere knew this beating</l>
					<l>heart to move-- Thy tender mercres me pur-</l>
					<l>sued!. Ever may they with me abide-- And</l>
					<l>close me in on every side!&apos;</l>
					<l>Deeply bowed in the dust, yea prostrate at</l>
					<l>thy feet, I adore Thee O Lord, and with a</l>
					<l>flood of tears, I render unto Thee my un-</l>
					<l>feigned thanks and praises for inumerable</l>
					<l>mercies of all kinds, so undesenvedly be-</l>
					<l>stowed upon me during so long a period,</l>
					<l>while passing thro&apos; this vale of tears, under</l>
					<l>so many changes and vicissitudes, trials and</l>
					<l>tribulations. I can bear abundant testimony</l>
					<l>from my own experience, that Thou art</l>
					<l>the Lord merciful and gracious long -suffer</l>
					<l>ing</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='41'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>ing, and abundant in goodness and truth.</l>
					<l>forgiving iniquity, transgression and sin.</l>
					<l>and that thy mercy is new every morning.</l>
					<l>In my forlorn condition. Those Lord, didst</l>
					<l>me receive--Thou savedst from perdition-</l>
					<l>My soul, and badst me live. --With inward</l>
					<l>Spirits ardor --I thank Thee for thy grace,</l>
					<l>Thyself this heavenly fervor-- Of love to</l>
					<l>Thee increase. Oh! that now the few re-</l>
					<l>maining days of my pilgrimage may be</l>
					<l>consecrated to thy service and to thy glory.</l>
					<l>But oh, how do I blush with shame-</l>
					<l>and confusion of face, when I reflect, how</l>
					<l>often I still grieve Thee by unbelief, cold-</l>
					<l>ness of heart, want of love, carnal propen-</l>
					<l>sities, indolence in thy service, and various</l>
					<l>other things, when I reflect, how short</l>
					<l>I fall of those virtues and excellencies, wch</l>
					<l>adorn the Christian character, and wch are</l>
					<l>exhibited to us in thy walk and conversa-</l>
					<l>tion, in thy whole life here on earth. How</l>
					<l>little do I yet discover of that meekness &amp;</l>
					<l>lowliness of heart, wch we are to learn of</l>
					<l>Thee, and of that purrity and holiness, with</l>
					<l>out wch no man shall see the Lord. There</l>
					<l>are indeed hours of grace, when I am par-</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='42'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>ticularly led to meditate, both upon that</l>
					<l>wonderful act of thy bleeding &amp; dying love</l>
					<l>when Thou gavest thyself for my salvation</l>
					<l>and redemption, and upon that tender un-</l>
					<l>wearied care Thou hast taken of me from</l>
					<l>my tender infancy until now, bearing, for</l>
					<l>giving, comforting, upholding, and sup-</l>
					<l>plying my wants in every time of need, and</l>
					<l>when the flame of love kindled in my heart</l>
					<l>burns bright and strong; but ah! how soon</l>
					<l>is it again like smoking flax, &amp; my faith</l>
					<l>and confidence like a bruised reed. How</l>
					<l>soon might the smoking flax be quenched</l>
					<l>and the bruised reed be broken, if thy mercy</l>
					<l>did not sustain me from day to day.</l>
					<l>And what shall I say respecting my poor</l>
					<l>services:? They are not performed with that</l>
					<l>Goal and fervency of spirit, wch ought to</l>
					<l>activate me, whether I declare the counsel</l>
					<l>of God for our salvation in public, of address</l>
					<l>either the Congn. collectively of any Choir</l>
					<l>separately, or when I administer the holy</l>
					<l>Sacraments, or am engaged in any other</l>
					<l>official duties. How often do I act more</l>
					<l>from a sense of duty than from an impulse</l>
					<l>of love. I claim no reward, but I humbly</l>
					<l>implore</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='43'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>implore thy forbearance, patience &amp; pardon</l>
					<l>But O my Savior, what an arduous sta-</l>
					<l>tion hast thou called me to occupy in this</l>
					<l>country. The destitute of the necessary</l>
					<l>means, I am required to afford help &amp; relief</l>
					<l>in different quarters and on various ocea-</l>
					<l>sions, where it is called for. Is it a wonder</l>
					<l>that my faith at any time should seem</l>
					<l>to fail, and my courage to sink! But</l>
					<l>no. I will not cast away my confidence,</l>
					<l>and why should I, after so many striking</l>
					<l>proofs and instances of thy gracious help</l>
					<l>&amp; support in difficult &amp; trying circumstances,</l>
					<l>where human help was in vain, doubt of</l>
					<l>thy further help? I am thy Servant.,it is</l>
					<l>thy cause I wish to serve: it is thy will</l>
					<l>I should have my station here, &amp; it was</l>
					<l>in obedience to thy call, that I came, not</l>
					<l>knowing what awaited me.</l>
					<l>Me thy all- seeing eye</l>
					<l>Hath kept with watchful care,</l>
					<l>Thy great compassion never fail&apos;d,</l>
					<l>Those heardst my needy pray&apos;r-</l>
					<l>This makes me firmly trust,</l>
					<l>Thou&apos;lt lead me farther still-</l>
					<l>And safely guide throughout the way,</l>
					<l>That leads to Sion&apos;s hill</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='44'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>October 28th 1818 </l>
					<l>What shall I say of the year that is now</l>
					<l>gone by. it was indeed a period of many se-</l>
					<l>vere trials of various kinds, but the greatest</l>
					<l>of all was, that on the 6th of August it pleased</l>
					<l>the Lord, to take home to himself my beloved</l>
					<l>partner and faithful helpmate, with whom</l>
					<l>I had lived in the married state 25 years, &amp;</l>
					<l>who not only was a pleasant companion</l>
					<l>to me but also an experienced Assistant in</l>
					<l>the labor, having already previous to our</l>
					<l>marriage served a number of years as a faith</l>
					<l>full handmaid of the Lord among the Girls</l>
					<l>and single Sister. Thus I was now the 2nd</l>
					<l>time placed in the state of a Widower at</l>
					<l>a time of life, when such an agreeable com-</l>
					<l>panion and faithful helpmnate is doubly</l>
					<l>valuable. My desire was now more than</l>
					<l>ever fixed upon things above, &amp; upon being</l>
					<l>at home with the Lord.</l>
					<l>I had also some expectation at the close</l>
					<l>of the Syned held this year at Herrnhut,</l>
					<l>that I should be permitted to lay down my</l>
					<l>offices and enjoy some rest, but was disap-</l>
					<l>pointed and rather found, that by the new</l>
					<l>regulations</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='45'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>regulations agreed upon I should have some-</l>
					<l>additional duties to perform. Nothing there-</l>
					<l>fore remains to me but to commit myself</l>
					<l>anew to the hands of my faithful Lord and</l>
					<l>Savior, relying on his gracious promise</l>
					<l>And even to Your old age I am He, and even</l>
					<l>to fear faits will I carry you; I have made</l>
					<l>and I will bear; even I will carry &amp; deliver</l>
					<l>you. Isas 16! 4. Amen be it so.</l>
					<l>The year 1823 was <hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>an account of the</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>partly syainit prruaiting in the Cangn and</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>exnows tin urnrearcer cosrecfed with its</hi>,</l>
					<l>a trying period to me, and finding, that</l>
					<l>by gouty and rheumatic affections my bodily</l>
					<l>strength was much impaired, and that both</l>
					<l>body and mind were no longer equal to the</l>
					<l>performance of my official duties, I followed</l>
					<l>my conviction, that after a service of 56</l>
					<l>years I might retire from my former acti-</l>
					<l>vity to a more easy situation, and therefore</l>
					<l>resigned all my offices except that of Minister.</l>
					<l>Thus I could begin the year 1826 with</l>
					<l>a chearing prospect of rest and peace from</l>
					<l>within and without, nor was I disappointed</l>
					<l>in my expectation. I really anticipated the</l>
					<l>fulfillment of the prophecy my people</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='46'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>shall dwell in a peaceable habitation, in</l>
					<l>sure dwellings, and in quiet resting placed</l>
					<l>All my mourning was turned into joy, and</l>
					<l>I could thank the Lord even for the afflictions</l>
					<l>I had to pass thro&apos;, as they afforded in the</l>
					<l>end new evidences of his unchangeable love</l>
					<l>and faithfulness. My great concem and my</l>
					<l>earnest prayer and supplication now is, that</l>
					<l>the Spirit of God may prepare me for meeting</l>
					<l>of Savior with joy, and make me meet</l>
					<l>for an inheritance among the. Saints in light,</l>
					<l>is to my present situation I can truly</l>
					<l>testify with the Psalmist; my lines are</l>
					<l>fallen unto me in pleasant places, yea&apos;</l>
					<l>I have a goodly heritage.&quot; Ps 16. 6</l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>July 8th 1827 I ordained Br. Cent Henry</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>Rudolph, then Minister of Dublin Congn.</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>a Presbyter of the Brns Church, and this</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>was the last transaction of my ministe-</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>rial office</hi>.</l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>At he cloyorh they Narnadseihedbvrag.</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>well which u Party ment we palekdirovaoo</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>&amp; appears my thanks &amp; praipr to Had, that</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>his hisend spowurdenaed and fire His go-</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>annaaes Coderlhits ed for proved &amp; save-</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>nations Mr. Bates, du wainpannkracemeuts</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>sstrare.</hi></l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='47'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>does, he sacodrin; kunselad, was sauinad</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>caminsstantud Dntonee anidaraathaddr-</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>iofjunae isananer while saith dstminutf</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>is a Paproingan mine to dvaidare See</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>fine CuSravenang dear navess and</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>aRerenitakiaaieinshnaut ataavinaar</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>idreranaabug far radaavaga&amp; stone</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>was dradaect faPavarynwidaaaie and</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>to sariouartaigkativrasiof taranwant</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>Blatg. a Wratean camprariny The darcnerng</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>stile of ksaaeninul itllthak in ptaarthecody</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>At to sary five savages.</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>The ed hear daruruut hinfarihgg</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>London were an Gaslemads for w &amp; nrucsaik dor</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>on inagea iandiraind sraven to The Sound</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>Nifule Given.</hi></l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
