<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Bentley_Joseph_Ful_3_115</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Obituary Notices</l>
					<l>of several persons, who had died at Bailden in the</l>
					<l>year 1837, communicated by Br. Libbey, who had</l>
					<l>visited them during their last illnesses.</l>
					<l>1. Joseph Bentley</l>
					<l>After the afternoon service on Sunday April 30<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi></l>
					<l>I was informed, that a poor man, labouring under a</l>
					<l>mortal disease, wished to see me. My informant</l>
					<l>added; &quot;He is very ignorant, having never in his</l>
					<l>life attended any place of Worship; but spent it</l>
					<l>in sin and wickedness. At the last York Assizes </l>
					<l>he was tried for felony, but not convicted, the</l>
					<l>prosecutor; from motives of compassion with</l>
					<l>holding the required evidence. He is now suffe</l>
					<l>ring from a blow, received in an affray with</l>
					<l>the gamekeepers on M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> F&apos;s estate, when detected</l>
					<l>with some of his companions in poaching.&quot;</l>
					<l>We  ascertained, that it was not the </l>
					<l>fear of death, which induced him to search for me,</l>
					<l>but that he showed some of persistance</l>
					<l>and contrition of spirit; I went to see him, on</l>
					<l>as my official notice allowed it.</l>
					<l>When I entered his house and begun to speak</l>
					<l>to him I perceived that the wound in his head had</l>
					<l>quite exhausted his strength, and that his mind had</l>
					<l>been bewildered by the presence of so many persons</l>
					<l>who in the course of the day had come to see him. After</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>a few words I asked if he wished me to pray. But</l>
					<l>even this he declined, saying, &quot;So many have been</l>
					<l>here today and prayed with me, that my head is</l>
					<l>quite confused.&quot; I therefore left him, promi</l>
					<l>sing to call again the following day. Feeling an</l>
					<l>increasing interest in his case, I repeated my calls</l>
					<l>almost daily, and somedays saw him more than once. </l>
					<l>The work of the Holy Spirit on his heart was stri</l>
					<l>kingly evident, and being of an open turn of mind</l>
					<l>his candid confession of himself, and the simplici</l>
					<l>ty of his declaration, made the conversations wtih </l>
					<l>him more interesting as the following brief</l>
					<l>notices of my interviews with him each show.</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>May 1</hi><hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>st</hi><hi rend='underlined:true;'>.</hi> He was sitting by the fire, and I took</l>
					<l>my seat by the side of him. I had scarecly sat down</l>
					<l>when he began very freely to disclose him feelings</l>
					<l>and the state of his mind, experiencing very strongly</l>
					<l>fear of death and the judgment. He trembled when</l>
					<l>speaking of the crimes he had committed, and of his </l>
					<l>approaching death. I felt much for him, and in</l>
					<l>silent prayer besought the Lord so to direct my</l>
					<l>words, as to suit his care. Turning to him, I said, </l>
					<l>&quot;I come to tell you good news.&quot; Instanly he exclai</l>
					<l>med, &quot;What is that?&quot; I continued, &quot;The Lord</l>
					<l> <hi rend='underlined:true;'>loves</hi> you.&quot; I shall not easily forget his look,</l>
					<l>when he rejoined, <hi rend='underlined:true;'>That</hi> is impossible! He</l>
					<l>cannot love such a wretch as I am.&quot; &quot;Listen&quot;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>to me,&quot; said I, &quot;while I tell you what He has done</l>
					<l>for you. He came down from heaven, became</l>
					<l>a poor man and, out of love to you and me and </l>
					<l>all sinners, was nailed to the cross, and shed His</l>
					<l>blood to purchase pardon &amp; happiness for us.&quot;</l>
					<l>He <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>was</hi> appeared very thoughtful, which I </l>
					<l>quoted several texts of Scripture on this subject,</l>
					<l>illustrating it by allusion to common things</l>
					<l>Br. I. Terry coming in our conversation was</l>
					<l>interrupted, and I deemed it prudent to with</l>
					<l>draw. He prefered my heart and, with tears in his</l>
					<l>eyes, said; Please, sir, come again, for you have</l>
					<l>done me good.&quot; It proved a great encourage</l>
					<l>ment to me when informed by Br. Terry, that </l>
					<l>on my leaving the house, the sick man sat silent</l>
					<l>for some time and then, turning to Br. T. said, &quot;What</l>
					<l>do you think M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>. Libbey has told me? He told me</l>
					<l>that God loves me; yes, and he has proved </l>
					<l>it too. The Lord died for me on the cross. Is not</l>
					<l>that good news, John?&quot;</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>May 2</hi><hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>nd</hi>. I found his mind dwelling on the subject</l>
					<l>of the love of God; but still perplexed with doubts</l>
					<l>and fears, being not yet able unreservedly to be</l>
					<l>lieve the Gospel. A Divine ray of hope has indeed</l>
					<l>burned into his soul, but at sinner unbelief had</l>
					<l>him in bondate. <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>This caused him</hi> He gave vent</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>to his feeling by short sentences, &quot;O that I could</l>
					<l>believe, that mercy can be shown to such a wretch</l>
					<l>as me! I cannot pray aright: I cannot pray</l>
					<l>enough.&quot; I repeated to him the beautiful de</l>
					<l>clarative of our Saviour, &quot;As Moses lifted up the</l>
					<l>serpent in the wilderness, so must the Son of Man</l>
					<l>be lifted up, that whoever believeth in HIm</l>
					<l>should not perish, but have eternal life.&quot; /Joh. 3.14/</l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>I was</hi> Having explained it to him by referring </l>
					<l>the case of the wounded Israelites, he <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>I</hi> exclaimed</l>
					<l>in the simplicity of his heart; &quot;Am I only to</l>
					<l>look up?&quot; I replied, &quot;To look up means</l>
					<l>to believe, and this is all our Saviour requires</l>
					<l>you to do.&quot; &quot;But,&quot; said he, &quot;my heart is so very</l>
					<l>wicked; O you do not know what a wicked</l>
					<l>man I have been. Since our conversation </l>
					<l>yesterday I have thought more of my sins, than</l>
					<l>I did before, and when I think how good God</l>
					<l>has been to me, to do so mcuh for me, and that</l>
					<l>He has not cut me off in my sins, I see that I </l>
					<l>have been sinning against <hi rend='underlined:true;'>love</hi>; This makes</l>
					<l>me afraid. If I felt as good men feel, then I</l>
					<l>could believe there was mercy for me, but, </l>
					<l>Oh! I have committed so many sins.&quot; To </l>
					<l>this I replied, &quot;If you had committed as many</l>
					<l>sins as all the men in the village, I would yet</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>encourage you to come to Jesus, for it <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>is</hi> stands </l>
					<l>in the Bible; The blood of Jesus Christ cleanses</l>
					<l>us from all sin.&quot; I further showed him, that</l>
					<l>the Israelites were commanded to look to the</l>
					<l>brazen serpent <hi rend='underlined:true;'>because</hi> they were wounded, and </l>
					<l>that they were healed when they did look, &quot;so</l>
					<l>must we,&quot; said I; &quot;we must go to our Saviour,</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>because</hi> we do not feel <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>happ</hi> well and happy in</l>
					<l>our minds, <hi rend='underlined:true;'>beacuse</hi> we are sinners; and then He</l>
					<l>will have mercy upon us.&quot; &quot;Then,&quot; said he,</l>
					<l>&quot;we must <hi rend='underlined:true;'>first</hi> look to Jesus, or believe in Him; </l>
					<l>as we shall be pardoned.&quot; I replied, &quot;Believe </l>
					<l>on the Lord Jesus Christ and thou shalt be saved.&quot;</l>
					<l>The word was blessed to his soul.</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>May 4th:</hi> He expressed some doubts as to his</l>
					<l>acceptance at last; and tho&apos; he was evidently</l>
					<l>enjoying a degree of rest &amp; peace, yet gloomy</l>
					<l>apprehension of death now and then shot across</l>
					<l>his mind. I repeated the words, &quot;Jesus has opened</l>
					<l>the kingdom of heaven to all believers&quot;, adding, </l>
					<l>&quot;He is the Master of the house and the Lord of</l>
					<l>the kingdom, and says, &quot;I have the key of David,</l>
					<l>I open the door and no man can shut it, and I shut</l>
					<l>and no man can open <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>shut</hi> it.&quot; I continued, &quot;you</l>
					<l>are the master of your own house, If I came</l>
					<l>to see you and found the door fastened I should</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>knock; and if you opened the foor I should come</l>
					<l>in. We go by faith to our Saviour and ask to be</l>
					<l>admitted into His kingdom; and He says, &quot;I</l>
					<l>have set before then an open door and no</l>
					<l>man can shut it! Thus hath He opened the</l>
					<l>kingdom of heaven to all believers.&quot; He re</l>
					<l>mained thoughtful, but appeared much more</l>
					<l>composed in his mind.</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>5. May 5th</hi>. I found him in a most delightful</l>
					<l>state of mind. Among other things he said; &quot;When you</l>
					<l>came to see me last Sunday I was as ignorant as a beast.</l>
					<l>Some persons told me to pray to God Almighty <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>but </hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>I did</hi> so to forgive me; but I did not know how to pray</l>
					<l>anymore than the ash in the fire. But now when</l>
					<l>I sit alone, or lie sleepless in my bed, and think</l>
					<l>of Jesus, how He was a poor man and suffered</l>
					<l>for our sins, and how kindly He spoke to the people</l>
					<l>the tears run down my face and I can pray to Him</l>
					<l>in my heart; and I feel something that tells me, He</l>
					<l>loves <hi rend='underlined:true;'>me</hi>, and will not leave me to perish at last.&quot;</l>
					<l>I asked him, &quot;If the Lord should be pleased to call you</l>
					<l>soon out of the world, can you be satisfied, and can you</l>
					<l>rest on what you have heard?&quot; Looking at me</l>
					<l>with a cheerful mien he replied, &quot;To be sure I can;</l>
					<l>what can I want more? Did He not die for me,</l>
					<l>and does He not love me. I am a great sinner; but</l>
					<l>I shall go to heaven.&quot; </l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>May 8th</hi>. I saw him for the last time, tho&apos;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I had then no idea that he was so near eternity. His</l>
					<l>expressions were not so clear and encouraging as the</l>
					<l>preceding Satturday. This I could easily account for</l>
					<l>when he told me, that a great many people had called</l>
					<l>on him the day before, and many had prayed with him</l>
					<l>and spoken so loud, which had so much affected his head,</l>
					<l>that, /to me his own experience/ &quot;I was so weak you</l>
					<l>might have knocked me down with a feather.&quot; However,</l>
					<l>what he said <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>to</hi> of the state of his mind showed that </l>
					<l>he still depended for salvation solely on the merits of</l>
					<l>Jesus. He departed about 2 o&apos;clock the following</l>
					<l>morning. From the testimony of those who were</l>
					<l>with him at the time I have reason to believe</l>
					<l>that the Lord graciously supported him in that trying</l>
					<l>hour, enabling him to make a good confession of faith</l>
					<l>in the God of his salvation. About ten minutes before</l>
					<l>he left this word, he exhorted those present to seek</l>
					<l>the Lord, adding, &quot;I shall soon die; but, oh! how</l>
					<l>bright, how blinded will the last mintues of my life</l>
					<l>be when I am leaving this world of sin and misery,</l>
					<l>and going to see my Saviour!&quot;</l>
					<l>My visit to this poor man excited many serious</l>
					<l>reflections. In his case I saw in vivid colours</l>
					<l>1. The unhappiness and folly of sin. My blood has </l>
					<l>chilled at the recitals of this man, when relating</l>
					<l>the awful course of sin he had led his hairbreadth</l>
					<l>escape from cruel death, and the unhappy state</l>
					<l>of his mind during all this time, and, as he himself</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>expressed it, the heavy load he had had to carry</l>
					<l>warily, the Devil is a hard taskmaster.</l>
					<l>2. The Mercy of God in plucking sinners from ever</l>
					<l>lasting burning. As the good shepherd He had fol</l>
					<l>lowed this dying sheep thro&apos; all his wanderings,</l>
					<l>for it was evident from what he told me, that he had</l>
					<l>not been without convictions and reproof of conscience</l>
					<l>while persuing his wicked ways, and before his last</l>
					<l>illness. On one occasion his remorse of consci</l>
					<l>ence was so strong, that tho&apos; he set out on a Sunday</l>
					<l>morning to join his wicked comerades, the sight <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>meeting</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>accidentally</hi> of a good man, whom he accidentally</l>
					<l>met, so alarmed him, that he turned and leaped</l>
					<l>over a wall, crying like a child. He actually turned</l>
					<l>back, andn tried to pray to God, promising to lead</l>
					<l>a different life. Scenes of folly again diverted his</l>
					<l>mind, and obliterated serious thoughts.</l>
					<l>3. The power of the Word of the Cross, when accompa</l>
					<l>nied by the influence of the Holy Ghost, whose office it</l>
					<l>is to glorify Jesus, by leading poor sinners to faith</l>
					<l>in the atonement.</l>
					<l>4. How the fruits of the Spirit appear in thou, who</l>
					<l>have faith in Jesus, by resignation to the will of God,</l>
					<l>love and thankfulness for His mercy - patience</l>
					<l>under affliction - meekness and forgiving of sin</l>
					<l>and a desire that others should enjoy ??? happi</l>
					<l>ness, and attain to eternal life. </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
