<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Clark_Grace_SS_10</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="#facs_1" n="1"/><p>
            <lb/>Grace Clark
            <lb/>was born in North Ourum in the Parish of Halli
            <lb/>fax April ye 17<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> 1720.
            <lb/>She was awakened in 1746 &amp; received into the
            <lb/>Congregation January ye 6<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> 1745 &amp; became soon after a
            <lb/>Partaker of the Corps &amp; blood of Jesus. Soon
            <lb/>She was admitted into the Single Sisters Oeconomy
            <lb/>at Oxhaise Febr. 24<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> in the same year &amp; in Pudsey
            <lb/>Febr. 27. 1747, when she was made use of with
            <lb/>others, to visit the Single Sisters.
            <lb/>In 1748 she become Voorsteheress of the oeconomy
            <lb/>in Pudsey.  She was always Childlike &amp; faith
            <lb/>ful in what she had to do, &amp; much loved by her
            <lb/>Sisters. In the Beginning of April she began
            <lb/>to be out of order &amp; complained of her Breath
            <lb/>which in a short time made her so weak
            <lb/>that she was hardly able to walk, altho' all possi</p><pb facs="#facs_2" n="2"/><p>
            <lb/>ble Means have been used to the last.
            <lb/>In May she began to speak much of going
            <lb/>&amp; said she should to soon after she had seen the Mother
            <lb/>to the Lamb &amp; would hardly hear any Thing
            <lb/>of being recovering. Her only great concern was
            <lb/>to be buried on Lamb's Hill, which she
            <lb/>desired very often, &amp; firmly believed if
            <lb/>she should live so long till a place was
            <lb/>appointed for her. In her sickness she was
            <lb/>always contented &amp; happy, spoke very much of
            <lb/>the wounds &amp; especially of the Side's Hole, of which
            <lb/>she also dream'd continually, &amp; invited her the
            <lb/>Sisters, who stood about her, to come with her
            <lb/>into that Hole, there was Blood enough for
            <lb/>them all. once she said she had seen the dear Saviour
            <lb/>&amp; he said to her, I am thy Husband, thou art</p><pb facs="#facs_3" n="3"/><p>
            <lb/>&amp; he said to her I am thy Husband, thou art
            <lb/>mine &amp; am thine, but he had a long vest
            <lb/>ment on, so that she could not see the wounds.
            <lb/>She begg'd him ye He would come an other Time
            <lb/>with his wound Holes for she lik'd to see him
            <lb/>best therein, He mind at it &amp; open'd the
            <lb/>cloke so of she could see the Side's Hole, into
            <lb/>which she went &amp; drank plentifully of His Blood.</p><pb facs="#facs_4" n="4"/><p>
            <lb/>Last Friday
            <lb/>June the 23<hi rend="superscript:true;">d</hi> she said often that she should go
            <lb/>Home ye Day, &amp; would go first to the Side's Hole
            <lb/>&amp; also tast the other wounds. Towards Evening
            <lb/>In the evening ab<hi rend="superscript:true;">t</hi> 9 o'Clock S<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> A. Maria
            <lb/>went to her &amp; sung several verses, blessed her
            <lb/>under those words: So go then go my Heart &amp; hide
            <lb/>deep I say deep into the Side, &amp; while She was sing
            <lb/>ing: There where the Spear his Side did bore
            <lb/>thou last thy place eternally here Soul took
            <lb/>it's flight into the Side's Hole, being fetched
            <lb/>away by the kiss of her Husband, which was
            <lb/>plainly to be perceived in her countenance.</p></body></text></TEI>