<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Clark_Elizabeth_Ful_SS_21</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Eliz. Clark</l>
					<l>Was born at Northouram in the</l>
					<l>Parish of Halifax. My Parents being Disenters, I </l>
					<l>was babtiz&apos;d according to their Profession, as my d<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>Mother departed this Life while I was yet very young</l>
					<l>my father being left with 4 Children namely one Son</l>
					<l>and 3 Daughters, and being strictly religous himself, took all </l>
					<l>possible care to preserve us from the seductions of the</l>
					<l>world. this concern of His, togather with my natural thought</l>
					<l>full turn of mind led me to an enquirery after future</l>
					<l>happiness, even in my Childhood, at which time the fear of</l>
					<l>death restrain&apos;d me from injoying my self in the manner</l>
					<l>usual to others at that age, contrary to my inclination</l>
					<l>which was to divert my thoughts, not being able to</l>
					<l>Satisfy my self by those means, as I grew older I took</l>
					<l>the resolution to exert the utmost of my power to shake</l>
					<l>of my former Convictions, and I found even then that my</l>
					<l>best efforts prov&apos;d vain to help my indweling proponsity</l>
					<l>to the alurements of this world, having in private</l>
					<l>often besought the Lord with tears to save me, and still</l>
					<l>found I was as prone as ever to come into the same</l>
					<l>Condemration. I pursu&apos;d this resolution as far as I was</l>
					<l>able and acepting the invitation of others of my Companions</l>
					<l>strove to amuse my thoughts by publick diversions, in</l>
					<l>the midst of one of which asemblies, I was so amazingly</l>
					<l>struck with Horror &amp; Condemnation, that I was forc&apos;d to</l>
					<l>retire, beseeching the Lord to have Mercy upon me I</l>
					<l>resolv&apos;d never to come into the like ocasion again.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>which I also never did, altho still heart was unconverted</l>
					<l>nor had I any desire to engage in Religion, as many of</l>
					<l>my aquaintance would have perswaded me, by oppertunity</l>
					<l>of Mr Ingham&apos;s Preaching who was just then come into these</l>
					<l>parts, my reason was to try If I cou&apos;d find no satisfaction</l>
					<l>more in the world first; but finding by experience that my</l>
					<l>misery pursu&apos;d me more Closely then ever, I gladly made use </l>
					<l>of the offer of the Gospel made by the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi> at their</l>
					<l>first coming into Yorkshire. by whose means I found the </l>
					<l>only way to seek true satisfaction, and lamented with many </l>
					<l>tears my former indifference towards my d<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> who had </l>
					<l>so graciously led me unknown to myself of from all other</l>
					<l>pleasures to seek my happiness alone in Him. The B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi></l>
					<l>soon began how to Settle Bands among the Young Women</l>
					<l>but not having much aquaintance with me thought best</l>
					<l>to refer My reception into their society somtime longer.</l>
					<l>this Circumstance together with my ardent desire for their</l>
					<l>fellowship caus&apos;d me many sorrowfull reflection over</l>
					<l>myself for my past neglect. but as they not only</l>
					<l>visited those in Conection with them, but those whom</l>
					<l>they found adher&apos;d to their Preaching, So among the</l>
					<l>rest I was an object of their care, and by ocasion</l>
					<l>of a Visit of the Late Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>tr</hi> Eliz. Clagget. found</l>
					<l>freedom to deslose the concern of my heart in a hearty</l>
					<l>Conversation with her. She asur&apos;d me that our Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi></l>
					<l>aim was to make me intirely happy, and gave me also</l>
					<l>great incouragement to hope for fellowship with His</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>, this was very Comfortable to me and not long soon after what </l>
					<l>I was admitted to a Band among Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>trs</hi> with whom cou&apos;d</l>
					<l>converse freely Concerning the situation of my heart, to my</l>
					<l>real comfort &amp; blessing. being very much distresd, on</l>
					<l>Such an Ocassion, I spoke very openheartadly of my Misery</l>
					<l>and concern, when the beforemention&apos;d Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>tr</hi> in a feeling</l>
					<l>Manner display&apos;d the loving Condescension of our d<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>in taking upon himself our Guilt &amp; Misery, and by His</l>
					<l>Meritorious Suffrings &amp; death making a full atonement</l>
					<l>for all Sin, procuring thereby peace and pardon for every</l>
					<l>Soul who Concious of their wretchedness turn&apos;d to Him</l>
					<l>with a Simple Confidence in his Mercy. at which I</l>
					<l>was so deeply affected that retiring in my way home I</l>
					<l>earnestly intreated our d<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> to grant me the happy</l>
					<l>experience of His saving power &amp; deliverance from the </l>
					<l>Misery of the Fall &amp; depravity of my own nature &amp; for</l>
					<l>his wounds sake to bestow on me that pardon &amp; peace which</l>
					<l>he had merited for me, I had not gone far in this situation</l>
					<l>of mind before He graciously drew near my heart, and I</l>
					<l>was thereby so overpower&apos;d that all my former Misery</l>
					<l>Vanish&apos;d, instead of which I felt such Peace &amp; Comfort</l>
					<l>that I cou&apos;d scarce recolect how it had been with me, but</l>
					<l>went on my way rejoicing in God my Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> who had regarded</l>
					<l>my lone estate &amp; had help&apos;d me out of all my distress.</l>
					<l>Not long after I was rec&apos;d into the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> in April</l>
					<l>1745 to my great Joy, this abas&apos;d me very much on</l>
					<l>account of the unexpected favour it was to me.</l>
					<l>but I went on Chearfull in my course till Aug<hi rend='superscript:true;'>st</hi></l>
					<l>following, when by opportunity of a visit by some</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi> tho recd Sist<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> were spoken with individualy</l>
					<l>Concerning the aim &amp; intention of reception. This made</l>
					<l>a deep impression on my mind and being apointed to </l>
					<l>be at Pudsy the Sunday following I grew exceedingly</l>
					<l>Concerned about my self least I shou&apos;d not answer</l>
					<l>the end &amp; aim of my Call to the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> being this</l>
					<l>porplext in my way thither my recourse was to</l>
					<l>my d<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> who Comforted and reasur&apos;d me of His</l>
					<l>Love &amp; favour towards me, but upon my arrival at</l>
					<l>Pudsy how great was my Surprize, when the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi></l>
					<l>told me that our Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> had directed them to invite</l>
					<l>me with them to the Holy Com<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>, I was at once so</l>
					<l>struck with Joy and awe that I scarce knew what</l>
					<l>to think, but reflecting on the particular instance</l>
					<l>of His feeling nearness on the road, I was incourag&apos;d</l>
					<l>to Venture my All upon Him, and injoyed this Highest</l>
					<l>good Sacramentally to my great comfort &amp; Blessing</l>
					<l>In the year 1746 the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi> began to regulate &amp; Settle</l>
					<l>Oeconimys, I got permission to move into the first of </l>
					<l>this regulation at Oxhay&apos;s. Where the Manner of </l>
					<l>Life being Quite new to me and expecting in myself</l>
					<l>Something extraordinary, I came so far into my</l>
					<l>own reason that I gren perplext, and tho more</l>
					<l>so as I had gone to the Com<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> which thro&apos; an </l>
					<l>Ocurence not altogether clear to me, I had also</l>
					<l>Misd once</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>this led me so far that I was at last so distressd I </l>
					<l>knew not what to do. in this porplextity I was determin&apos;d</l>
					<l>to take my retreat to my best Freind, with this resolve</l>
					<l>If it must be so, to perish at His Feet casting myself</l>
					<l>thus upon His Mercy I became from that time more than</l>
					<l>ever sencible of the cause of this my dubious state.</l>
					<l>and that it proceeded from my own selfworking &amp;</l>
					<l>Striving, whereby I cou&apos;d not come thro&apos;, as all my happiness</l>
					<l>depended on his free grace alone, &amp; not on any thing</l>
					<l>of my willing or doing, but simply depending &amp; looking</l>
					<l>unto Him in every case &amp; circumstance, this gave me</l>
					<l>the Clearest insight into the poor Sinners happiness</l>
					<l>I ever had before, &amp; prov&apos;d an abiding blessing to</l>
					<l>me thro&apos; all future Viscisitudes I learn&apos;d daily more</l>
					<l>to know the poverty of my own heart and the in</l>
					<l>Sufficientcy of human reason. and as in the year</l>
					<l>1748 I mov&apos;d with other Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>trs</hi> to the Little Moore</l>
					<l>Oeconimy, and was apointed to Visit the Country Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>trs</hi></l>
					<l>it prov&apos;d a blessed school to my own heart, being</l>
					<l>Concious of my unfittness &amp; want of experience, which</l>
					<l>often drew tears from my eyes but gave rise to many </l>
					<l>tender &amp; Sinnerlike Conversations with my souls Friend</l>
					<l>whose Consolation, supported and comforted me on all</l>
					<l>ocassions. my Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>trs</hi> who with me had the grace to be</l>
					<l>Members of the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> and particularly my elder</l>
					<l>Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>tr</hi> was a comfort to me. but as it pleas&apos;d our</l>
					<l>Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>to call her to himself in the year 1749. which was</l>
					<l>a painfull Circumstance to me, as thereby I lost in her</l>
					<l>a tender faithfull heart, whose conversation had been</l>
					<l>usefull and edifying to me upon many Ocassions, but</l>
					<l>as our Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> had aprov&apos;d himself in so many cases</l>
					<l>to my heart as able to comfort &amp; Supply all my</l>
					<l>nescesitys So I again cast myself upon Him anew</l>
					<l>and thereby found a fresh proof of His tenderness &amp;</l>
					<l>faithfullness torwards me, his poor and Bashfull one.</l>
					<l>In the year 1752, the Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>trs</hi> mov&apos;d into their new</l>
					<l>Choir House out of the several Oeconimy&apos;s, but</l>
					<l>as some few still remain&apos;d in the Pudsy-town</l>
					<l>Oeconimy I mov&apos;d thither with another Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>tr</hi> to</l>
					<l>inspect the same Oeconimy. but got permission</l>
					<l>in a few months to Change with one out of the</l>
					<l>Choir House, and came thereby at last to my</l>
					<l>long desir&apos;d home, rejoic&apos;d &amp; thankfull for all the</l>
					<l>kind &amp; gracious leading &amp; dealings of my D<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Lord</l>
					<l>who had brought me thus far</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
