<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Clerk_Esther_Ful_SS_14_2</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Memoirs of the late happily departed Sister</l>
					<l>Esther Cleake who on the 27<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> of May 1791</l>
					<l>at Fulneck enterd into the joy of her Lord</l>
					<l>In the 76<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> Year of her age.</l>
					<l>She has left the following account concerning</l>
					<l>her Pilgrimage here below.</l>
					<l>I think my dear Brethren &amp; Sisters will</l>
					<l>like to hear somthing of my Course through</l>
					<l>this time which I will gladly relate to the</l>
					<l>honour of my dearest Saviour. I was Born at</l>
					<l>Kirton in Lincolnshire, July 8<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1715 my Parents died when</l>
					<l>I was very young, was therefore left an Orphan</l>
					<l>to Providence, or to my dear Creator &amp; Saviour</l>
					<l>for whom I was born &amp; destined surely.</l>
					<l>To tell my dear Brethrening &amp; Sisters of the</l>
					<l>Goodness, the mercy &amp; kindness, the love &amp; faithfulness</l>
					<l>of My dear Lord &amp; Saviour to me a poor Child.</l>
					<l>my weak words fall very short to express the</l>
					<l>praise that is due to him, from me, for his wonders</l>
					<l>have been without end, thanks, thousand thanks</l>
					<l>be to the Lamb for ever &amp; ever. I will now relate</l>
					<l>some of the particulars of the tender lendings of</l>
					<l>My gracious &amp; most faithfull Lord. The first</l>
					<l>impression of grace I remember, was when I was</l>
					<l>about four Years old, when one day kneeling by</l>
					<l>a choir with a book in my hand, in which was those</l>
					<l>words, Seek and ye shall find knock, &amp; it shall</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>shall be append unto You, I felt somthing</l>
					<l>particular at the time, I had a very quick under</l>
					<l>standing for my years, and a very sensible feeling</l>
					<l>of what was right, and wrong I wanted to be a good</l>
					<l>Child that I might go to Heaven, on that account</l>
					<l>I was much praised, which wou&apos;d have been more</l>
					<l>hurtfull to me, but the dear Holy Ghost who had </l>
					<l>begun his work in my heart, pleased me continualy, my</l>
					<l>wicked and sinfull nature, which kept me low &amp;</l>
					<l>consions that I did not deserve that praise, which</l>
					<l>was a grace to me at that time, so it checked my</l>
					<l>Satanick pride, which I felt very sensible, Yet </l>
					<l>from many circumstances I thought God must</l>
					<l>love me, but how it was I cou&apos;d not tell, I have</l>
					<l>I was a sinner, In my 11<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> year I was very thought</l>
					<l>full and distress&apos;d, felt guilt with the impression</l>
					<l>that I did not love God, nor cou&apos;d I promise him</l>
					<l>which one day a little bird was made use of to </l>
					<l>shew me that I cou&apos;d not praise my Creator even</l>
					<l>as a Bird cou&apos;d I had also strange Idea&apos;s about</l>
					<l>him, what kind of a form he had, and was much</l>
					<l>perplexed about it at this time I had a dream where</l>
					<l>in I thought God allmighty was in a parlour in </l>
					<l>the house where I was, and that he was a Man of</l>
					<l>which I was very glad, &amp; thought then One cou&apos;d be</l>
					<l>familliar with him. But not understanding the </l>
					<l>gracious lending of my dear Saviour, I continued</l>
					<l>extremly</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>extremly distress&apos;d, thought I commited Sin</l>
					<l>evry moment by the strange thoughts I had, &amp;</l>
					<l>they was of such a nature, I cou&apos;d not tell them</l>
					<l>to any body, nor wou&apos;d they have understood me,</l>
					<l>but wearied indeed with trying to help myself</l>
					<l>a thought came in my mind, As I can not help</l>
					<l>these thoughts God Almighty has nothing</l>
					<l>against me. In that moment my mercifull</l>
					<l>and compassinate Saviour drew near with his</l>
					<l>love and gave me peace, it was as If he said to</l>
					<l>me, I have nothing against thee, I was amazed</l>
					<l>but did not know how to account for it, to be</l>
					<l>loved by God in such a manner, from that time</l>
					<l>When those thoughts came again I cou&apos;d believe</l>
					<l>he had nothing against me for it, but not under</l>
					<l>standing the right poor Sinners path I came into</l>
					<l>an esteem self rightious course, Striveing with</l>
					<l>all my might to be good by other means then</l>
					<l>Jesus blood, I fasted &amp; prayd, wanting to be as</l>
					<l>good as the Primitive Christians, not likeing any</l>
					<l>one to be better then myself, here my Satanick</l>
					<l>pride show&apos;d itself to a great degree, All how</l>
					<l>unwilling was I to be saved by grace I went on</l>
					<l>for some time in this manner. My Aunt dieing who</l>
					<l>brought me up, I became a Second time an Orphan</l>
					<l>indeed She treated me as If She had known my</l>
					<l>destination. Ah the wonders of My dear Saviours</l>
					<l>love which I did not then understand through</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>His kind providence in My 19<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> year I went</l>
					<l>to London into Lady Scarborough&apos;s Family.</l>
					<l>who had sent for me to wait on her little Neice</l>
					<l>and My dear Saviour put it into her heart from the first</l>
					<l>moment to be remarkable kind to me, and the whole</l>
					<l>family shew&apos;d a great regard &amp; respect for my religious</l>
					<l>turn of mind, which they found was sincere</l>
					<l>(not on account of outward gifts or quatifications)</l>
					<l>but the dear Holy Ghost in whose School I then</l>
					<l>was, gave me a constant sence of My depraved</l>
					<l>nature in all it shapes, and finding I fell so far</l>
					<l>short of what I thought I shou&apos;d be, this kept</l>
					<l>me low and in some sence humble, and kept the</l>
					<l>ballance against that hartfull prais which is</l>
					<l>often given. I served also in several other families</l>
					<l>namely Lord Orrory, Lady Charlott Edan&apos;s &amp;</l>
					<l>the Duke of Buckclugh. My dear Saviour</l>
					<l>and most faithfull Shepherd helped me through</l>
					<l>with all my imperfections so wonderfully</l>
					<l>that If I may humbly say so, I found favour</l>
					<l>with God, &amp; Man, but I nor no body else, thought</l>
					<l>what was prepareing for me. In my 26<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> year I</l>
					<l>return&apos;d to Lady Scarborough who always received</l>
					<l>me with the greatest kindness, At this time I fell</l>
					<l>again into self working fasted &amp; prayed much, till I </l>
					<l>was quite weared finding it did me no good, Once in</l>
					<l>the Year 42 while at prayer I felt somthing very</l>
					<l>blessed, it was quick like the fleeting of a Star</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>but it seemed to me all that was good, it was</l>
					<l>Light Peace, Joy, all happiness in One moment</l>
					<l>I thought it was the Holy Spirit, &amp; praied to</l>
					<l>feel more of it. Soon after I received a letter</l>
					<l>concerning the preaching of the Methodists which</l>
					<l>I had never heard of. I was very much biggote to</l>
					<l>the Church &amp; thought it a shame to go any where else</l>
					<l>I thought how ever I wou&apos;d inquire about them what</l>
					<l>kind of people they wear, it happend at this time a</l>
					<l>Methodist came in My way, and by his conversation</l>
					<l>I was convinced of what I wanted, the knowledge of the</l>
					<l>atonement of our Saviour for My Sins, then all his</l>
					<l>gracious leading was brought to my mind so that I</l>
					<l>knew it was a faith from God, the person lent me</l>
					<l>a Sermon book of Sermons of M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Whitfields</l>
					<l>the more I read the more it was opened to me that</l>
					<l>I wanted a Saviour, for my mind took a turn and</l>
					<l>I found some rest from my labour, and saw that it</l>
					<l>was Christs rightousness that I wanted, I enterd</l>
					<l>with my whole mind into the matter, got all the</l>
					<l>books I cou&apos;d of that kind amongst the rest I got</l>
					<l>the Brethrens little Hymn book which sat&apos;d me</l>
					<l>exceedingly well espicialy One Verse, viz: If I</l>
					<l>glimse in My own breast Feel of a Christian bliss</l>
					<l>Then on the truth of it let me rest. That such a</l>
					<l>Life there is. At length my good Lady found I had</l>
					<l>got Methodist books, but did not think I was so deep</l>
					<l>in the matter, for She had a better opinion of me</l>
					<l>then that I wou&apos;d follow such people, but one time</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>being with her at Court, She caught me reading a</l>
					<l>letter which she took from me, wherein She found I</l>
					<l>had been Once at the Tabernacle, She was much</l>
					<l>concern&apos;d &amp; took the greatest pain possible to diss</l>
					<l>waid me from it, but I was Devinly convinced of</l>
					<l>the truth of the Gospel, my Lady forbid me to go</l>
					<l>to the Tabernacle, I told her I cou&apos;d wou&apos;d not with</l>
					<l>out leting her Ladyship know, I thought I cou&apos;d do</l>
					<l>with books &amp; Stay at Home, at this time the family</l>
					<l>went into the Country, where was a good friend a</l>
					<l>Minister who took great pain to prevent my</l>
					<l>going too deep in my present Ideas, he brought me</l>
					<l>many books but to no purpose, my heart was afraid</l>
					<l>of the truth, We return&apos;d to London and I grew very</l>
					<l>uneasy, found I cou&apos;d not be faithful without</l>
					<l>going to hear the preaching, I therefore desired</l>
					<l>leave, which was not granted. My good Lady was</l>
					<l>now very much distress&apos;d about me, She wanted</l>
					<l>to keep me, &amp; out of Love &amp; kindness she did her</l>
					<l> what She cou&apos;d to perswaid me, She wanted</l>
					<l>me again to be advis&apos;d by some Minsters,</l>
					<l>I chose the Bishop of Oxford (Sacher) for that</l>
					<l>purpose I was so clear in My matter I feared no</l>
					<l>thing, my B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> went with me to the Bishop and</l>
					<l>accused me of leaving the Church, I told him</l>
					<l>it was because they did not preach our Saviours</l>
					<l>Sufferings, &amp; I was fully asured nothing else</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>cou&apos;d save me, this he aprov&apos;d of, as to good work</l>
					<l>I said, when the tree is good, the fruit will be good,</l>
					<l>he was very tender with me finding I was Sincere</l>
					<l>If it was possible I was more confirm&apos;d in my point</l>
					<l>then before, My dear Lady was much dissapointed</l>
					<l>but I cou&apos;d not help it, here She rested, she had</l>
					<l>done all She cou&apos;d but My matter remained to leave</l>
					<l>her, or have leave to to go to the preachings, at last</l>
					<l>I con&apos;d do no longer, therefore went to hear the</l>
					<l>preaching, I was wanted before I came home again,</l>
					<l>My Lady ask&apos;d me where I had been, I told her, She</l>
					<l>said I had gone without leave, I said because her</l>
					<l>Ladyship wou&apos;d not have given the leave If I had</l>
					<l>ask&apos;d upon this She sent me out of the room</l>
					<l>to see me no more, She was affraid to keep me on</l>
					<l>account of the Children &amp; Servants, least I shou&apos;d</l>
					<l>bring them into my way of thinking, &amp; when I went</l>
					<l>with her to Court it was a shame at that time to be</l>
					<l>a Methodest. But My dear Saviour had prepared</l>
					<l>my way for me, I went to bed as composed as if</l>
					<l>nothing had happened, In the morning I rose with</l>
					<l>great chearfulness, like a Bird releas&apos;d from a</l>
					<l>Cage, and agent to the Tabernacle at 6 o&apos;Clock from</l>
					<l>Cavendish Square, which was a wonder of God for I</l>
					<l>had nothing, nor any prospect how I shou&apos;d get my</l>
					<l>bread, had very little money, many hard things was</l>
					<l>set before me, and in myself nothing to depend on, nor</l>
					<l>had I any acquaintance here, Our dear Saviours</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>words became litterally true, seek first the</l>
					<l>Kingdom of God &amp; its Righteousness and all things</l>
					<l>shall be added unto You, I was like a Child</l>
					<l>turn&apos;d out of doors (was again an Orphan) But</l>
					<l>my ever faithfull Lord whose Hand &amp; Eye was over</l>
					<l>me cared for me in evry respect. My Lady gave me</l>
					<l>proof more of her kindness to me, finding I had</l>
					<l>no acquaintance, sent me word that I shou&apos;d lodge</l>
					<l>there till I cou&apos;d find a home the Servants was</l>
					<l>amaized at me, because I was otherwise no person</l>
					<l>of courage, but they did not know that I had found</l>
					<l>the Pearl of great price. I stay&apos;d with my Brother</l>
					<l>in the day time till the preaching time at the</l>
					<l>Tabernacle, my Brother was very shy to me, he was</l>
					<l>sorry for My leaving such a good place. He look&apos;d</l>
					<l>into my books, made a good observation &amp; said all</l>
					<l>professions make the Scriptures there rule, but</l>
					<l>If this inward feeling can be true it must come from</l>
					<l>God. It pleased he to hear him say so much.</l>
					<l>I enquir&apos;d of him for the Brethrens Chapel that I </l>
					<l>might see the people to whom by little Hymn Book</l>
					<l>belong&apos;d (this was in Feb<hi rend='superscript:true;'>y</hi> 1744) He directed me</l>
					<l>but when I came to Fetter Lane there was no preaching,</l>
					<l>I enquir&apos;d at the Chapel House S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Wheeler kindly</l>
					<l>ask&apos;d me to come in Shewed me the Chapel, and what</l>
					<l>She told the at that time of Our Saviour walking</l>
					<l>amongst his People, made such an impression on</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>me that I never shall forget. It Tallied with my own</l>
					<l>experience, I enquired if the Countes of Zinzendorf</l>
					<l>did not want a Servant, but heard She was not in England.</l>
					<l>I went to Speak with M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Whitfield to advise with</l>
					<l>him, and found him at B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> John Syms&apos;s, I told them my</l>
					<l>case just as it was, S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Syms according to her kind way</l>
					<l>in such cases took me into her house, thus I left my</l>
					<l>good Lady &amp; all my old Friends, with greatfull</l>
					<l>thanks for all their kindness &amp; I heartly pray that</l>
					<l>My dear Lady May not loose her reward, I cou&apos;d do no</l>
					<l>other but follow my gracious Lord and Saviour, B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp;</l>
					<l>S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Syms Shewed me great kindness, M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Whitfield &amp;</l>
					<l>his Wife was also very kind to me, but M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Whitfield</l>
					<l>going to George in about six weeks, this connexion</l>
					<l>was ended. B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Syms being atach&apos;d to the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi></l>
					<l>I often went with them to Fetterlane, I had receive&apos;d</l>
					<l>many blessings by going to the Tabernacle, at this</l>
					<l>time B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Syms moved, from which time I left off</l>
					<l>going to the Taber. Now my good Lord led me Step</l>
					<l>by Step as it pleased him both inwardly &amp; outwardly</l>
					<l>in a most gracious manner which brings these lines</l>
					<l>to my mind. With patience immense, And love so</l>
					<l>intense, He hath led me on, I&apos;m lost in amazment</l>
					<l>When thinking thereon. Now being come to my proper</l>
					<l>home, the dear Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> where I have enjoy&apos;d more blessings</l>
					<l>then I am able to express, they have been so many, and so</l>
					<l>great, and my call to the dear Congn is so clear and weighty</l>
					<l>to me, that I can say, next to our Saviour, the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> is the</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>dearest thing to me, I am a Sinner to whom belongs</l>
					<l>nothing but shame &amp; confusion of face, but it has</l>
					<l>pleased him to open to me the treasure of his Love</l>
					<l>&amp; great Salvation, which has been sealed to me by</l>
					<l>his Spirit, by his Word, by his Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> as an eternal truth</l>
					<l>for such was my make that I must know it as a truth</l>
					<l>for myself, was truly convinced of unbeliefs, and my</l>
					<l>enmity against our Saviour, when this came to the</l>
					<l>highest pitch, I thought If there was another Saviour</l>
					<l>I wou&apos;d have him, I felt condemned for the thought</l>
					<l>and in that moment I was overpowerd with the</l>
					<l>love and peace of my dear Saviour, and as If he</l>
					<l>said to me for all this I love thee. The feeling</l>
					<l>and impression of his nearness, bow&apos;d me down in</l>
					<l>the dust before my gracious Lord, with this</l>
					<l>Sensation, The poor Sinners happy feeling, the holy</l>
					<l>shame. But My selfrighteousness still</l>
					<l>troubled me in various shapes, but in that feeling</l>
					<l>the following verse was sealed to me as the greatest</l>
					<l>truth, O precious precious blood, The only Holiness</l>
					<l>that&apos;s good, Still drop, &amp; flow &amp; cover me, it</l>
					<l>cursed Sinner without thee. The Scripture, the</l>
					<l>preachings, the Hymns, where open&apos;d with such</l>
					<l>truth &amp; Life which I can&apos;t describe.</l>
					<l>I left B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Syms with greatfull thanks for</l>
					<l>all their care, and went to live with M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Delamott</l>
					<l>at Black Heath to take care of Betsey Holand</l>
					<l>her Parents being gone to Germany, here I experienc&apos;d</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>something particular in the first place to my shame.</l>
					<l>I was shewn such love and respect from this dear</l>
					<l>family, but what relates particularly to the heart</l>
					<l>was as I have said the preachings had been so blessed</l>
					<l>to me, being now all at once taken from all meetings,</l>
					<l>which I felt much store by, it was amazing to me</l>
					<l>that I now enjoy&apos;d such a Sabatic stillness &amp; a</l>
					<l>Sunshine of peace for that time, that I wanted</l>
					<l>nothing, but was indeed as a Child at the breast.</l>
					<l>I was not Yet in the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> tho&apos; I had defer&apos;d it some</l>
					<l>time. B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Holand how comeing from Germany</l>
					<l>I went with their Daughter to live with them.</l>
					<l>I now thought much about being received into the</l>
					<l>Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>, but I had still to wait some time, which</l>
					<l>was very wholsome for the I was once much comforted</l>
					<l>by these words, Jesus thy affairs will think on,</l>
					<l>as thy ever loveing Head. At length the hour which</l>
					<l>certainly at the right moment, the Divine impression</l>
					<l>to me was, I am now in by Fathers House, this was</l>
					<l>May 18<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1747, and the 2<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> of Sep<hi rend='superscript:true;'>t</hi> following I had</l>
					<l>the unspeakable grace to be a partaker of my dear</l>
					<l>Saviours body &amp; blood in the Holy Sacrament.</l>
					<l>In this period ah! how good &amp; blessd was the Liturgies</l>
					<l>&amp; all the Meeting to my poor heart beyond all expres</l>
					<l>sion, I had the grace to feel that in myself I was</l>
					<l>a poor Creature truely convinced no one worse, had a</l>
					<l>solid feeling what Sin is in all its odious Shapes</l>
					<l>I am sensible that I have given the dear Holy Ghost</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>to keep me low as a sinner, my dear B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi></l>
					<l>will understand what that sensation is a solid</l>
					<l>feeling what is sin, but <unclear>not to touch sin God forbid</unclear></l>
					<l>In this Year I went to live at Mile end with the</l>
					<l>Children here I had new appearings of my dear Saviours</l>
					<l>Love and grace especially relating to my Choir. I</l>
					<l>was drawn to read the Canticles &amp; these Disciples</l>
					<l>of our Saviours love to his Church was opend to</l>
					<l>me with such truth &amp; reallity as I can&apos;t express</l>
					<l>The following verse was much impressed on my mind</l>
					<l>at this time, O thou the fairest of mankind</l>
					<l>Thy beauty strike both heart &amp; mind. But</l>
					<l>nothing is so fair in thee. As thy sweet form</l>
					<l>upon the tree and can thro&apos; his love &amp; grace say</l>
					<l>Nothing has so struck me. As when God&apos;s</l>
					<l>Spirit took me too Golgotha O God be prais&apos;d</l>
					<l>This has a period in the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> of some extravegances</l>
					<l>But can say for myself I am truly convinc&apos;d</l>
					<l>by my own experiance that there was a glory</l>
					<l>from the Lord, indeed too great for earthly minds</l>
					<l>long to bear, but I expect to see it again in</l>
					<l>perfection without a Vail between, and with</l>
					<l>the whole Sinners train surround that Cavity</l>
					<l>where I shall dwell eternally, at this time</l>
					<l>that verse was realised to my heart, To be</l>
					<l>enamour&apos;d I know well, To have the heart quite</l>
					<l>overflowing, For him alone to be so glowing</l>
					<l>Expressions only me here fail. About this</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>this time I also had a new school for my own heart</l>
					<l>concerning the Virgin Station, and found that only</l>
					<l>by partaking of the Nature of the only Virgin man</l>
					<l>one cou&apos;d deserve that Character, this was made</l>
					<l>very clear to me, Fair gifts of my creation, quite</l>
					<l>spirit&apos;d made me disspair for this grace, the</l>
					<l>knowledge of myself (in this particular) I adore &amp;</l>
					<l>thank my dear Lord &amp; his Spirit for teaching me</l>
					<l>the way to turn to his precious blood, which alone</l>
					<l>can cleanse our hearts and make all good, I found</l>
					<l>it an antidote against all those sins that stick</l>
					<l>so close to our nature.</l>
					<l>In the year 1751 I was sent to care for the Single</l>
					<l>S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> in Ockbrook and in Sep<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 1757 I receiv&apos;d a call</l>
					<l>to go to Tytherton for the same purpose, and arrived</l>
					<l>there in the Angels <unclear>????</unclear>, this Jurney I shall</l>
					<l>never forget, it was very much bless&apos;d to me through</l>
					<l>the nearness of my gracious Lord, and the impression</l>
					<l>I had of the aid of his dearAngels, July 19<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1763</l>
					<l>I return&apos;d again to Ockbrook, and Dec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 11<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1772</l>
					<l>I arrived in London where I hope to finish my poor</l>
					<l>&amp; insignificant labour, In all these places my</l>
					<l>best Friend has help&apos;d me through in wholesome</l>
					<l>poverty both internally &amp; externally, and I can</l>
					<l>say with the Deciples, I have lacked nothing, have</l>
					<l>been rich in the midst of poverty, here I desire</l>
					<l>to give my due thanks to My dear Bretheren &amp;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi>, and particularly those of My own Choir</l>
					<l>for their love kindness &amp; patience towards me.</l>
					<l>But ah! how much is due to by dearest &amp; best</l>
					<l>Friend &amp; lover, for his Election of grace &amp; for the</l>
					<l>knowledge of his dear Wounded Person, his precious</l>
					<l>blood, and all what he is to me, I conclude with</l>
					<l>the 30<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> verse of the 43<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> Chapter of Eccleasiastious</l>
					<l>which well express my mind, When You Glorify the</l>
					<l>Lord, exalt him as much as God can; for even Yet</l>
					<l>will he far exceed; and when You exalt him, put forth</l>
					<l>all Your Strength, and be not weary, for You can</l>
					<l>never go for enough. Thus far our late Sisters account.</l>
					<l>Having serv&apos;d the Single Sisters Choirs with great</l>
					<l>faithfulness, and blessing in several Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ns</hi> (had the</l>
					<l>confidence of her Sisters who always found in her a kind</l>
					<l>and Sympathizing friend ready to share with them in</l>
					<l>joy &amp; smart, the prosperity of every One laying very</l>
					<l>near her heart) till her bodily infirmities wou&apos;d no</l>
					<l>longer permit her to do what her heart &amp; mind was</l>
					<l>Still willing for June 20<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1782 She arrived here</l>
					<l>in Fulneck to injoy a Sabath. During the 8 years</l>
					<l>of her abode here, She often express&apos;d her gratitude</l>
					<l>to our Saviour for his kind leadings of her through</l>
					<l>this Vale of tears and that she had the favour to</l>
					<l>enjoy her time of rest in this dear Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>. She had the</l>
					<l>love and respect of ev&apos;ry one that knew her we can with</l>
					<l>truth give her this testimony that She approved</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>herself among us as a real Child of peace.</l>
					<l>At our last Choir Festival She was present at all</l>
					<l>the meetings, which was the last time she was able</l>
					<l>to go out after which She lost her strength very</l>
					<l>perceptably but her longing to be at home with her</l>
					<l>dearst Lord encreased daily, two days before her</l>
					<l>happy departure She said a S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> that was with</l>
					<l>her with great emotion of heart, I go to our Saviour</l>
					<l>as the greatest Sinner, not one so great as I am,</l>
					<l>but this I can tell You, He has pardon&apos;d all my</l>
					<l>transgressions &amp; clothed me in the robe of his</l>
					<l>righteousness, on the 27<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> of May at 11 oClock</l>
					<l>in the forenoon She desir&apos;d to be helped up I see she said</l>
					<l>our Saviour he to here, now he will soon fetch me,</l>
					<l>after which she lay mostly Still, till 7 oClock</l>
					<l>in the Evening when the long wish&apos;d for moment</l>
					<l>came, that She departed softly &amp; happily into the </l>
					<l>joy of her Lord with the blessing of her Choir</l>
					<l>in the 76<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> year of her Age.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
