<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Darnbrook_John_Ful_3_42</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1680.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Course of Life of the S Br John Darnbrook,</l>
					<l>the first part of which he himself has wrote down,</l>
					<l>&amp; the latter dictated.</l>
					<l>I was born at Moreley in the Parish of Battley June the 20<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>th</hi></l>
					<l>1720. my first 13 Years I lived with my Parents, which took</l>
					<l>care to instruct me in what was religious, to the best of their</l>
					<l>knowledge, particularly my Mother, whom I remember, when Mr</l>
					<l>Ingham and other awakened Men first began preaching, she went</l>
					<l>frequently to hear them, &amp; a Sermon of Mr Whitfield&apos;s being</l>
					<l>then published, she got it to read. I read the same, it treated</l>
					<l>so much of the Sufferings of our Sav<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi>, that if brought me into</l>
					<l>some Concern about my Salvation, I was then about 5 years old </l>
					<l>&amp; this was the first Conviction, I had, as much as I can remember</l>
					<l>At the End of my 13th year I was put an Apprentice to a very</l>
					<l>religious Man in the same town, a Dissenter, in which Way I had</l>
					<l>been brought up. Half a Year afterwards my Father departed</l>
					<l>this Life. This struck me pretty much of first, but I soon for-</l>
					<l>got it. the The 3 first years of my aprenticeship I spent among young</l>
					<l>Company as much as I could, &amp; indeed in that time I got seduced</l>
					<l>to many bad Things. One Day, when I was at Work by myself in</l>
					<l>the Field, a sudden thought came into my Mind that I must</l>
					<l>once die &amp; appear before God to give an decount of my Life &amp; </l>
					<l>I thought, if I died in that Condition, I certainly must go to Hell.</l>
					<l>I immediately left of my Work &amp; went a kneeled down under</l>
					<l>a Tree &amp; prayed to God to forgive me. This was the first Time.</l>
					<l>I ever prayed, except such as the Lords Prayer &amp; others learned</l>
					<l>out of Books. From this time I began to be vary religious. I read</l>
					<l>many religious Books &amp; prayed 6 or 7 times a day, I entirely</l>
					<l>broke <hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>off</hi> from all my old Companions, who despised me very much but</l>
					<l>the religious people praised me greatly, &amp; this made me very</l>
					<l>proud. But all this availed me nothing, all my reading, &amp;</l>
					<l>praying brought no Peace to my Heart. I was a bound Slave to</l>
					<l>Satan, &amp; when Sin presented itself, I had no Power to resist</l>
					<l>Some times I used to be a fortnight of 3 weeks without coming</l>
					<l>into any extraordinary great Sin, this made me think, I had now</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1681.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>made God amends. But I soon perhaps came into see very Prick of </l>
					<l>that Sin, which I thought Ihad conquered. This made me think, God</l>
					<l>was displeased with me, &amp; all my Prayers &amp; Readings were of no</l>
					<l>Signification, I must begin anew &amp; be more watchfull, than I</l>
					<l> had been hitherto. But with all I could do, Sin had the rule over</l>
					<l>me. I think, I spent near 2 Years in this miserable Course.</l>
					<l>At Easter in the year 1754 (as well as I can remember) I</l>
					<l>thought, I would go a hear the Moravians, tho&apos; I had no liking for</l>
					<l>them, because I believed them to be Roman-Catholicks. However I</l>
					<l>went &amp; heard Br La Trobe to my great Astonishment Such a Ser-</l>
					<l>mon I never had heard in all my Life before, I thought directly,</l>
					<l>this is the true way to be saved. I went home, &amp; what I had heard</l>
					<l>of the Sufferings of Jesus, &amp; how that Salvation could be obtained</l>
					<l>no otherwise, than by his ments, Death &amp; Bloodshedding, This</l>
					<l>wrought much on my Mind all the Week following. When on Sunday</l>
					<l>I went again; I was so overcome, that I afterwards could not go any</l>
					<l>where else. I soon got acquainted with Br Lorde, &amp; got a great Love</l>
					<l>for him, but he soon after went from Fulneck. I was received into</l>
					<l>the Society, attended the Preachings on Sunday constantly &amp; was</l>
					<l>often so affected with what I had heard, that I many Times in my</l>
					<l>Way home retired into a Wood near Tong &amp; wept before our</l>
					<l>Savr, that I might enjoy what I had heard. But I did not rightly</l>
					<l>prosper; for I had got some thing else in view besides my Salvation.</l>
					<l>I had got an Intention to travel, &amp; this engaged my Mind</l>
					<l>pretty much, &amp; I put this in Execution, as soon as my Prentice</l>
					<l>ship was out. There happened just at that Time two Persons Who</l>
					<l>come from London to see their Relations at Moreley, &amp; I took the</l>
					<l>Opportunity to go with them at their Return, The one being a married</l>
					<l>Person, took me to her House, &amp; it was my Home, till I got a Place</l>
					<l>which I did in ten days time, but it was very hard, so that I left</l>
					<l>it in 3 months &amp; got another place, which I left in about the same</l>
					<l>Time on account of some differences, I went to my first lodging</l>
					<l>&amp; stayd there out of Place fill Doctor John Holstead returned</l>
					<l>from the West Indies, where he had been as Surgeon of a Ship</l>
					<l>I visited him &amp; told him, I should like to go to Sea. He said, he</l>
					<l>would recommend me to Captain Hornsby <hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>bound for Greenland</hi>; if he has any Place</l>
					<l>that would suit me (this Captain was a Person he himself had</l>
					<l>been with at Greenland, before he went to the West Indies).</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Acordingly on his Recommendation the Captain took me as his Steward</l>
					<l>I went on Board, but all Things were very awkward, having never been</l>
					<l>on Board of a Ship before &amp; I knew  no more about my office than</l>
					<l>a Child, but I soon got to understand, that the chief mate was in</l>
					<l>that Office the Voyage before. So I made if my business to get acquaint-</l>
					<l>ed with him(<hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>with a bottle or 2 of Rum for he Loves Liquor</hi>) then</l>
					<l>told me every thing, what I should do &amp; what belonged to my office. Thus</l>
					<l>I got into the Way pretty well. He sailed from the River the latter end of</l>
					<l>March, &amp; we were not long out at Sea, before I was sick &amp; confined so</l>
					<l>for 15 Days. I thought many Times, if I was on Shore, they should be Sai-</l>
					<l>lors who would for me, But when I got better, I came thro&apos; pretty well,</l>
					<l>as I had no ship&apos;s duty to do. It was a very cold uncomfortable voyage</l>
					<l>for about 4 months we returned very unsuccessfull, having got no more</l>
					<l>than one fish; I got from the Ship as soon I could, weary enough of my</l>
					<l>first Voyage.</l>
					<l>A few weeks after by Accident I went to the East India House</l>
					<l>&amp; met with a Captain who was <hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>a</hi> shipping people, I asked him if he </l>
					<l>wanted people? He said, he did &amp; gave me an Order to go on Board. I</l>
					<l>immediately went on board &amp; met with a Company of very wicked, curs-</l>
					<l>ing &amp; swearing sailors. However we got ready &amp; put to Sea; About 2 months </l>
					<l>after our Ship&apos;s company was seized by turns with a violent Feaver. I</l>
					<l>also fell sick &amp; it brought me very near my Dissolution. While</l>
					<l>we were so sick, we hung altogether by ourselves, It was one of the most</l>
					<l>shocking Times, I have had in all any Life, most of them died cursing</l>
					<l>&amp; swearing, they all at one Time died, that were sick &amp; left me alone.</l>
					<l>I prayed heartily to our Sav<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi>, that if He would spare me &amp; bring</l>
					<l>me home again, I would be his &amp; live for him, But when I got better</l>
					<l>I soon forgot all his goodness &amp; went on a wicked Course with the Rest</l>
					<l>of the Sailors, &amp; I some times swore. But amidst all, I had many Con-</l>
					<l>victions, &amp; I often could not sleep, but wept in my Hammock on</l>
					<l>account of the Course I had entered into. When we came to a Port there</l>
					<l>was generally nothing seen but Wickedness.  I remember very were some</l>
					<l>times, that I was grieved in myself, has I could not be so bold in</l>
					<l>Wickedness, as the Rest of my company, &amp; when I thought, that I would</l>
					<l>be so wicked as they, I generally had such Convictions, that I could not</l>
					<l>do like them. We had a good Voyage but with Regard to Externals</l>
					<l>we had it hard some times, &amp; were about 6 Months without Bread</l>
					<l>living on Rice. On Account of the Length of the voyage we also</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1684.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>were obliged to take in old Stores in the East Indies which were very bad &amp;</l>
					<l>rusty thro &amp; thro. But  after 2 years &amp; 3 months we arrived at Spithead; &amp;</l>
					<l>there made myself sick to spare myself from the ??? . When the people were</l>
					<l>all preots, I got on Shore and came by so force. I lived there with my Friends</l>
					<l>till the ship was paid off. &amp; then according to my Resolution of going to Sea</l>
					<l>no more, I began to look for a Place where I could earn my Bread &amp; by</l>
					<l>the Help of a Friend I got a good one in Cheapside, where I lived very</l>
					<l>agreeably 6 moths &amp; I found they had great confidence towards me.</l>
					<l>But the ship beginning to be fitted out again, where which I had her with</l>
					<l>before, it made me very unsettled in my Mind &amp; I got a desire to go to</l>
					<l>Sea again. But I did not know, what Exuse to make, to get away</l>
					<l>from the Place, as had no fault to find with any thing I had Re-</l>
					<l>course to Stratagem. I ordered one of my companions, that he should come</l>
					<l>dressed like an officer of a Man of War, &amp; enquire for me, that it</l>
					<l>might appear, as if he had an Intention to press me. I ordered it so</l>
					<l>that he should come at an exact Hour, in order that I might be out</l>
					<l>of the Way. Accordingly he came. As soon as he was gone, then my</l>
					<l>Master called me &amp; told me, that he was afraid, the officer would re-</l>
					<l>turn again. I told him, I was under some Apprehension of being</l>
					<l>pressed. He desired that I would get ready, &amp; should go away &amp;</l>
					<l>not be pressed, if possible. When he settled with me about my</l>
					<l>Wages, he gave me 1/2 a guinea more than was due to me. So I came</l>
					<l>by which means I came</l>
					<l>away with many good Wishes. Yet I was condemned</l>
					<l>for acting so unuprightly, besides that I had left my Place &amp; did</l>
					<l>not know, whether I could get voyage of not to the East. Indies,</l>
					<l>I went to the India House &amp; spoke to Captain Wilson, with whom</l>
					<l>had been before, &amp; desired him to recommend me as Mid-shipman</l>
					<l>to Captain Jackson, that was to succeed him. He was very friendly</l>
					<l>I promised that he would do it. &amp; he was as good as his Words.</l>
					<l>I then began to get ready suitable for that Station, as well as I</l>
					<l>could. And when I had got my Necessaries I had not much Money</l>
					<l>to spare, to trade with. A gentle Woman, that wanted some Things</l>
					<l>from the East. Indies, advanced me 6 Guineas in hand, which I</l>
					<l>laid out in such Merchandises, as I thought, would suit the best</l>
					<l>in India. He soon got ready I had a very prosperous voyage</l>
					<l>from England to Madras in 4 Months, where I disposed of my</l>
					<l>Effects to good Advantage., I then bought such Commodities, which</l>
					<l>I thought would suit for China which likewise turned out to</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>good Advantage &amp; what Money I had, I laid out in China-goods &amp; in would of</l>
					<l>brought them home, After18 months we arrived again at Plymouth</l>
					<l>where I escaped the bressing &amp; came by Land to London (when the </l>
					<l>ship has round to London Spaind, I found that I had 10 pounds to receive for Goods</l>
					<l>that a Person had disposed of in the Passage. I afterwards went on</l>
					<l>Board from Day to day &amp; some Times sold from Board &amp; brought on</l>
					<l>shore till got off all my effects. I found myself worth a consider-</l>
					<l>able Sum of Money. That made me think of no other way of life, than </l>
					<l>Seafaring Life as I had such a good success <hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>prtazpreeadee, etenne, an</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true; strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>aypraan to gave</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>amndin and of</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>urantiraf its Shad subled</hi> After I had settled all my Affairs with the</l>
					<l>Ship for that Voyage, I paid a Visit to Yorkshire, to see my Mother</l>
					<l>where I went on Sunday to Fulneck, &amp; was so laid hold of in the Preach-</l>
					<l>ing, that I had gladly staid, if I had known, how I should got my Living.</l>
					<l>In about 5 Weeks I returned to London, where I went to see about the</l>
					<l>Ship, &amp; found, it would be some Months, before she would be fitteded out</l>
					<l>again. I waited the Time, but then some Objections arose between</l>
					<l>the Captain &amp; me, &amp; I resolved positively, that I would go to Sea no more</l>
					<l>I acquainted my Friends with my Resolution &amp; advised with them, what</l>
					<l>I should take to? I had then spent all my Money. They agreed to advance</l>
					<l>me 30 pounds, that I could procure me a little Shop, for which I had to</l>
					<l>give then Bond &amp; Judgment. We soon met with a little Shop, in which</l>
					<l>I entered. Soon afterwards I was arrested by a person, that I owed</l>
					<l>40 shillings to, &amp; went to the Sponging House, where I wrote a Letter to</l>
					<l>my Friend &amp; told him any Circumstances. He went directly &amp; put</l>
					<l>the Bond &amp; Judgment in Force, &amp; took all I had &amp; came to me next </l>
					<l>Morning &amp; paid the Money, for which I was arrested, &amp; set me at</l>
					<l>Liberty. I had now no home, but went some Times to one Friend&apos;s</l>
					<l>House, &amp; some times to another, where I had been formerly acquainted.</l>
					<l>But this I could not do very long, &amp; it came so far, that I suffered</l>
					<l>till to the Bareness of Life. One Day I met in the street one of</l>
					<l>the Family, that I had the Money from, he invited me to go to their</l>
					<l>House, &amp; they were hearty &amp; friendly with me, &amp; seemed to pity my</l>
					<l>Circumstances, I served in their Shop a few Weeks, &amp; then they </l>
					<l>hired me as a yearly Servant. I lived there very agreeably, &amp; some</l>
					<l>years ago, they did write to me to Fulneck, that I should come <hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>again</hi> &amp; live</l>
					<l>with them. After some Time I called at a Barber&apos;s Shop to get </l>
					<l>shaved pretty late in the Evening; while I sat there, I thought I</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1686.jpg' n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>was going to die. I got up &amp; said, I was very bad; but  no Body gave me any Answer.</l>
					<l>I stood at the Door, till some Body, who was before me, was shaved; then I got in &amp;</l>
					<l>was shaved, I went home very heavy &amp; told our people, I was not well.</l>
					<l>They advised me to get some Supper, which might help me, I went to</l>
					<l>Bed &amp; in the Morning still found myself the same. I begun to re-</l>
					<l>flect on my present State, for I had not minded Religion for a long</l>
					<l>Time; I thought, it was a Punishment from God for my bad Course.</l>
					<l>Accordingly to make Amends, I thought, I would go once on Sunday</l>
					<l>to some Place of Worship; but the other Part of the Sunday I would</l>
					<l>walk about a take my Pleasure, asI had done before, I want on so</l>
					<l>for some Time, but it did not help me. Then I thought, I would go</l>
					<l>both the Forenoon &amp; Aftemoon to Worship, yet still I found no Ease.</l>
					<l>I begun to be so terrified, that I thought, I should be in Hell every</l>
					<l>Moment. When had a Pen in my Hand to write a Bill of Parcel,</l>
					<l>I flung it away when I had done with it, &amp; thought, I should be in</l>
					<l>Hell, before I should want it any more. When I went out, I often</l>
					<l>thought, I should drop down dead in the Street. It came so far, that</l>
					<l>my Appetite left me &amp; I could get no Sleep, I used to awake in</l>
					<l>Frights &amp; get up. I read some Times in the Bible, but I thought</l>
					<l>every Word seemed a Sentence against me; I thought, I had sinned</l>
					<l>against the holy Ghost; therefore I had nothing to expect but Hell</l>
					<l>&amp; Judgment. I was in that Distress in more than 2 Months. One</l>
					<l>Sunday I went to Fetterlane Chappel. When I heard some Courses of</l>
					<l>Lives similar to my own, it gave me great Hopes, when I heard</l>
					<l>how they were redeemed by the Blood &amp; Wounds of Jesus, I went</l>
					<l>Home full of Hope, that I should soon be released. Next Day in</l>
					<l>the Forenoon, when I was going thro a narrow Passage near</l>
					<l>Spitalfields Church, it came into my Mind, that there was Mercy</l>
					<l>in Jesus for every believing Soul. In that Moment I believed, &amp;</l>
					<l>the Love of God was <hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>shed</hi> spread abroad in my Heart. I saw Jesus in</l>
					<l>his crucified form quite clear, who had redeemed me from all my</l>
					<l>Sins. I dont know, how I afterwards got home, Every Body was dear</l>
					<l>to me I I loved every one, I would gladly have imparted unto them</l>
					<l>of what I enjoyed. I went on in that Enjoyment for some Time &amp;</l>
					<l>thought, since I was come to the knowledge of our Sav<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r,</hi> that I</l>
					<l>should no more feel the Depravity of my own sinfull Nature, But</l>
					<l>I found my sinffull Nature still, &amp; was obliged to apply to our</l>
					<l>Sav<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r</hi> for his Grace to preserve me, which he did from time to time</l>
					<l>I began</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I began to have a longing desire, to become acquainted with</l>
					<l>the B<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>rn</hi>, as I believed, they were the only people, which I belonged to.</l>
					<l>Accordingly I began to go frequently on Sundays to Fetterlane. I went</l>
					<l>so long, till B<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r </hi>Brodersen took Notice of me in the Preaching &amp; made</l>
					<l>it out with one of the S B<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>rn</hi>, that he should speak with me at</l>
					<l>the first Opportunity. Accordingly he bid me a good Day after the</l>
					<l>Preaching &amp; asked me, where I was agoing? I told him I was agoing</l>
					<l>towards Bishopsgate Street. He said he was agoing that Way too</l>
					<l>&amp; desired my Company. He said, he had observed, that I frequented</l>
					<l>their Preachings for some Time, &amp; inquired, if I knew any thing about</l>
					<l>the B<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>rn</hi> &amp; I told him, yes. I knew the B<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>rn</hi> in Fulneck &amp; I knew Br</l>
					<l>Brodersen too, &amp; had spoken with him formerly. I told him, I had often</l>
					<l>fixed a Day, that I would go &amp; speak with him again. He asked, if I</l>
					<l>should rule to speak with him, &amp; if it would suit me that time, if</l>
					<l>I had an Opportunity for it? I answered: yes, I had no objection to it</l>
					<l>So we turned back both together &amp; went to Roll&apos;s Buildings. As soon </l>
					<l>as we got into the House, we met Br Brodersen in the Passage, &amp;</l>
					<l>he took me into his Room &amp; we had some pretty Conversation together.</l>
					<l>The Choir Liturgy was going to begin, &amp; he gave one Leave to be at</l>
					<l>it. I was so melted, that I wept all the Time, often spending some</l>
					<l>part of the Evening with the S. Brn. I returned home very thank-</l>
					<l>full for the kind Reception, that I met with. From that Time, I went</l>
					<l>every Sunday to the S Brn, which was the chief Opportunity that I had.</l>
					<l>Some Time after I petitioned for Reception into the Congn, which</l>
					<l>Blessing was granted me January the 13th 1766 I entered into</l>
					<l>a Covenant that time with our Savr to be his for ever I spent my</l>
					<l>time for the most part in a very happy Track of Grace, considering</l>
					<l>my Situation, wherein I was, &amp; I had many near Visits of our Savr,</l>
					<l>which made my Time very pleasant. Tho&apos; I felt naturally my de-</l>
					<l>praved human Nature, but I applied to him &amp; got preserved. When</l>
					<l>Dr Abraham returned from the Provincial Synod at Fulneck, he</l>
					<l>acquainted me that they had made it out in a Conference that if I did</l>
					<l>accept of it, I should go to Fulneck &amp; be employed in the Cong Shop</l>
					<l>I told him I had no Choice in it , I would go any where. Accordingly, as</l>
					<l>soon as I could make things suitable, I left my place &amp; set out from</l>
					<l>London Febr the 17th 1764 &amp; arrived at Fulneck the 22nd of the same month</l>
					<l>to my great Joy. Thus far his own Words.</l>
					<l>By dictating his Course of life, he <hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>often</hi> said, I thought there was some </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1688.jpg' n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Thing in the World, which I must experience, but I found, there was nothing</l>
					<l>but fantom, Now often have I thought of Fulneck &amp; wished me to be</l>
					<l>there, when I was uneasy, which was very often.</l>
					<l>His Course here was solid, he served faithfully in the Shop &amp;</l>
					<l>was legitimated among Brn &amp; Strangers. His Connexion &amp; Converse</l>
					<l>with our dear Sav<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>r </hi>was real, but in Stilness. He was admitted here</l>
					<l>to the holy Sacrament May the 23<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>d</hi> 1767, which was a real Grace to</l>
					<l>Him. &amp; as often as he fed afterwards with the Cong<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>n</hi> on the Body &amp;</l>
					<l>Blood of Jesus in the holy Sacrament, he enjoyed it as a poor Sinner</l>
					<l>who thought himself very unworthy of this great Grace, but felt at</l>
					<l>the same time that he stood very much in Need of it, &amp; that he could</l>
					<l>not do without. And so, he always got new Strength &amp; Life out of the</l>
					<l>Wounds of Jesus. When he was spoken with previous to the holy Sa-</l>
					<l>crament he was not of many Words, but one perceived clearly, that his</l>
					<l>Heart did live in the Sufterings of Jesus. All the Meetings he en-</l>
					<l>joyed both in the Cong<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>n</hi> &amp; his Choir proved a Blesting to him; the</l>
					<l>Doctrinal Day we had last Novembr, was very blessed to him &amp; he</l>
					<l>afterwards told, that he enjoyed a particular Nearness of our Savr at</l>
					<l>the Cup of Covenant. Last Year he was made <hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>and</hi> a Candidate for</l>
					<l>the East Indies, which he accepted of: for he was very willing to serve</l>
					<l>our Savr, wheresoever his Service should require it, tho&apos; on Account of</l>
					<l>his weakly Constitution he had but little Hopes to be of any Use in the</l>
					<l>Service of our Savr among the Heathen. That time he came among the </l>
					<l>Intercessors, which was very weighty to him. But our Savr, who was</l>
					<l>pleased with his Willingness to serve him, had other thoughts about him,</l>
					<l>He grew weaker from time to time, &amp; in the Beginning of Decembr he</l>
					<l>was obliged to move into the Sick Room. First we did not think, that</l>
					<l>he would go home of this Opportunity, but he soon thought so &amp; was quite</l>
					<l>set upon going home. Here he had a sabbatical time in the Nearness &amp;</l>
					<l>converse with our Savr </l>
					<l>tho; it was a Shool-</l>
					<l>Time for him too, in</l>
					<l>which he had to learn</l>
					<l>many Lessons &amp; to</l>
					<l>speak thoroughly with</l>
					<l>our dr. Savr. about </l>
					<l>many Things.</l>
					<l>Once he said: tho&apos; our Savr has had so great a</l>
					<l>Mercy upon me, yet I feel myself often so indifferent towards Him, which</l>
					<l>is the greatest Pain, I have in the Sick Room; at which he wept very much.</l>
					<l>But he soon was comforted again &amp; cheared by a gracious Look of our Saviour.</l>
					<l>He himself dictated his Course of Life to Br Martens, &amp; when he had done</l>
					<l>therewith, <hi rend='strikethrough:true; fontSize:0.0; kerning:0;'>to</hi> which was last Friday, he made Haste to meet his etemal</l>
					<l>Bridegroom. He had it very easy in his Sickness: the day before his going home</l>
					<l>he once complained, saying: Dear Savr! it is too hard for me; but he soon</l>
					<l>got it easier. He was present to himself to the last Moment, when the</l>
					<l>Blessings of his Choir &amp; the Congreg<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>n</hi> was imparted unto him during a</l>
					<l>sweet <hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;'>feeling</hi> of our Savr Nearess, &amp; soon after his Soul departed into the</l>
					<l>arms &amp; Bosom of Jesus, last Tuesday about 7 o&apos;Clock  in the Morning, viz</l>
					<l>Feby the 6th 1770 in the 34 th year of his Age.</l>
					<l>Praise to thee, our God, be brought for this Sinner redeemed with thy Blood.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
