<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Haigh_John_Ful_3_60</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>John Hugh who Departed May 22d 1772 has dictated the</l>
					<l>folloig concerning his Life</l>
					<l>I was born at Frestrup in the Parish of Pembrokshire Febr 6th</l>
					<l>1741, &amp; lived with my Parents till I was 7 years of Age; about this</l>
					<l>time Br Cennick came into this Country &amp; Preached the Gospel,</l>
					<l>my Mother who went frequently to hear him, took me with her</l>
					<l>which I liked. When a Childrens Meeting was begun, I had the</l>
					<l>Grace to be one of them who attended it, which proved a blessing</l>
					<l>to me, for there I got the first Impression of our Savrs Love.</l>
					<l>Esqr Roach of Clarison being a lover of the Gospel &amp; a friend</l>
					<l>of Children he settled a School, to which I also was taken, but I</l>
					<l>having no Genius for learning, did not bring it far, yet by frequent</l>
					<l>hearing the Versses out of the little Hymn Book which he had bought</l>
					<l>for the Children, I learned many of them by heart &amp; delighted in</l>
					<l>singing them. Our Master who was a very good Man, used to sing</l>
					<l>Verses before &amp; after Meals of which the following made a particular</l>
					<l>Impression upon me: We thank the Lord for this our Food;, but more</l>
					<l>for Jesus Flesh &amp; Blood the Manna to the Spirit giv&apos;n the living Bread</l>
					<l>sent down from Heav&apos;n. At Nights our Master used to kneel</l>
					<l>down with us, &amp; oftens pray&apos;d very heartily that our Savr might</l>
					<l>preserve us from every bad thing &amp; lead us in the way to everlasting</l>
					<l>Life. We Children kept also Meetings among ourselves &amp; when we</l>
					<l>went into the Fields, we sometimes kneel&apos;d down under the Hedges &amp;</l>
					<l>pray&apos;d to our Savr in a Childlike simple manner. When I was about</l>
					<l>12 years of age I went to Service, where I had it very hard, nor did</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I get enough to eat. After 2 Years I went to another place, where I</l>
					<l>had it better in outward respects, but was much exposed to bad and</l>
					<l>hurtful Company, so that I lost those good Impressions which I had</l>
					<l>as a Child, &amp; a Desire for the World &amp; is Vanity took place in me.</l>
					<l>When I was about 19 Years old, one of my former Masters wanted</l>
					<l>me to enter again into his Service, with whom I also agreed, &amp; as</l>
					<l>I learn&apos;d afterwards, a Scheme was laid, that if I had come there,</l>
					<l>I very likely should have settled &amp; been entirely lost in the things of</l>
					<l>this World; but before the time came quite on, I went to see my</l>
					<l>Mother &amp; Sister, who persuaded me to go &amp; work as a Mason on the</l>
					<l>Fortification, which was then to be build, tho&apos; I never had been em-</l>
					<l>ploy&apos;d as a Mason before, but I got Tools &amp; went, &amp; the Lord to</l>
					<l>whom I pray&apos;d, helped me, so that I could go on with the work &amp; there</l>
					<l>by all Dangers, which awaited me, if I had gone again to Service,</l>
					<l>were prevented. Living now with my Mother, she asked me to go with</l>
					<l>her to divine Service, which I did, as I had no particular Choise in</l>
					<l>this Respect. After I had been to hear Br Nyberg several times he spoke</l>
					<l>to me &amp; invited me to call &amp; see him, which I did the Sunday after, when</l>
					<l>we had had some Conversation together, helold me, that now the</l>
					<l>Society would have a meeting &amp; I might be present; As soon as I</l>
					<l>entered the Room, I was seized with an holy awe &amp; the praying</l>
					<l>of the Litany in that Meeting made such an Impression upon me</l>
					<l>that I not only looked upon them as true Children of God, but became</l>
					<l>also seriously concerned about myself. I then went to the Meeting</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>every Sunday &amp; in my return, I oftens pray&apos; d to our Savr to</l>
					<l>make me happy &amp; give me the assurance thereof in my heart.</l>
					<l>I had still some Difficulties on account of my former Connexions</l>
					<l>but my faithfull Savr help&apos;d me thro&apos; &amp; made me free from them all .</l>
					<l>As we lived about 3 Miles distant from Haverforthwest, &amp; my</l>
					<l>Mother was not so well cared for as I could wish, I took a House</l>
					<l>&amp; moved with her to Haverforthwest where we lived happily toge-</l>
					<l>ther. May the 12th 1765 I was received into the Congn which I</l>
					<l>esteemed very highly. In general I have had a very happy time</l>
					<l>&amp; had many a Visit from our Savr in the Converse with him; As well</l>
					<l>in my Sleeping place, as when I took a walk in the Fields &amp; once</l>
					<l>inparticular when I walked by the River Side, He appeared to my poor</l>
					<l>heart &amp; assured me that I should be His &amp; that he has shed his Blood for</l>
					<l>all my Sins; March 31 1768 I was made a partaker of our Lords</l>
					<l>Flesh &amp; Blood in the holy Sacrament, Ah! how thankful mn I</l>
					<l>for all the Grace our Savr has bestow&apos;d upon me, how often has He drawn</l>
					<l>so near to me, that I have melted into Tears, when I have been praying</l>
					<l>or speaking to him, these were happy Times, which I shall never forget.</l>
					<l>Thus far his own words.</l>
					<l>When Br Petrus was in Haverforthwest, he desired &amp; obtained leave</l>
					<l>to come to Fulneck &amp; arrived here Augst 28th 1768. His course here has</l>
					<l>been Edifying &amp; to our Satisfaction, he always expressed a great</l>
					<l>Regard for the Congn, but when he saw or heard any thing unbecoming</l>
					<l>in any one, who lived in the Congn, he did not rightly know how to</l>
					<l>take it, yet our Savr always reminded him to look to himself &amp;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>to dwell upon the faults of others &amp; thereby farther hurt was</l>
					<l>prevented. He oftens expressed a Desire to serve our Savr, &amp; some</l>
					<l>time before his last Sickness begun; he declared to his Labourer:</l>
					<l>That he had devoted himself quite a new to our Savr &amp; his People,</l>
					<l>was quite satisfied as &amp; where he was at present, but if our Savr</l>
					<l>would givehim a Call to any other place or employ, if he but</l>
					<l>knew, it came from Him, he would accept of it with all</l>
					<l>his heart. Last December he got a bad Cold, which turned</l>
					<l>to a severe Cough attended with a Hectic Fever. He expressed</l>
					<l>a Desire to go to our Savr, but said, that he was not clear, if</l>
					<l>it would be now. The Medicine he took had but little affect</l>
					<l>yet we thought, the warm wheather &amp; some gentle Exercise</l>
					<l>might perhaps be a means of his recovery, &amp; when it was prac-</l>
					<l>ticed, it seemed to have a good effect, so that about 3 weeks ago</l>
					<l>he thought still, that he would be able to take a Journey to Wales</l>
					<l>&amp; fixed the day for his setting out, which proved to be the day of</l>
					<l>his happy Departure. Eight Days ago his Sickness took a turn,</l>
					<l>when it appeared, that his time here would be but short, &amp; when</l>
					<l>the Doctor told him so, he was exceeding glad of it &amp; waited with</l>
					<l>resignation for his Desolution; a little before his Departure, a</l>
					<l>Br said to him: that now he would soon be with our Savr and</l>
					<l>appear before him in his Blood &amp; Righteousness, upon which he answered</l>
					<l>Ah! that is pretty, if I had no Savr, what should I do now? In this</l>
					<l>Comfortable Disposition &amp; with a Reconciled heart he went to his Redeemer</l>
					<l>in the 31st Year of his Age.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
