<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Hinchcliffe_Mary_Ful_3_27</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The Course of Life of the </l>
					<l>Married Sister Mary Hinchcliff</l>
					<l>who went happily to our Savr: on the 29th Augst 1770</l>
					<l>She was born at Wibsey in the Parish of</l>
					<l>Bradford Yorkshire in August 1718,</l>
					<l>and was brought up in the Presbyterian</l>
					<l>Religion and in her Youth behaved order</l>
					<l>ly, and living with her Uncle and aunt</l>
					<l>Pollard when they began to love the Brn</l>
					<l>She also came among them &amp; was reciev&apos;d</l>
					<l>into Society in 1745: but afterwards</l>
					<l>absented herself for a while till after she</l>
					<l>had married Br John Hinchcliff in 1749,</l>
					<l>after a while when she came again with her</l>
					<l>Husband to the Meetings of the Brethren</l>
					<l>and since has gone on as a loving Sinner-</l>
					<l>-Heart. She was reciev&apos;d into the Pudsey Congregn</l>
					<l>(at Fullneck) in 1758 and partook the</l>
					<l>1st Time of the Holy Sacrament with the </l>
					<l>Congregn in September 1763. Our Savr</l>
					<l>blessd her Marriage with one Son who is</l>
					<l>yet with his Father and a Member of our</l>
					<l>Society, and one Daughr who is already</l>
					<l>gone home to the Lord. Br &amp; Sisr Greening</l>
					<l>say: that since they have known Sisr</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Hinchcliff they observd in her something</l>
					<l>of the character which the Holy Scriptures</l>
					<l>give us of the Mother of our Lord: that is</l>
					<l>she was poor in her own Eyes, quiet and </l>
					<l>yet hearty. When at the late settling of the</l>
					<l>Helpers Conference in this Congregn our </l>
					<l>Savr directed that she should be a Member</l>
					<l>thereof, it had a very blessed Effect on her</l>
					<l>Heart, she expressd herself about it with Love</l>
					<l>Shames &amp; counted herself very poor &amp; unfit.</l>
					<l>The Sunday before her Departure having</l>
					<l>been at the Meetings with her Husband she</l>
					<l>afterwards was overheard comforting a dejected Sisr very</l>
					<l>heartily &amp; lovingly on the Tuesday Br Green</l>
					<l>-ing providentially calld at her House and </l>
					<l>Br Hinchcliff being out on his Business, she</l>
					<l>sat down and convers&apos;d awhile very heartily </l>
					<l>about her own inward poverty, expressing at the same</l>
					<l>time (tho indirectly) her Love towards our</l>
					<l>dear Savr, &amp; more directly her Love to her Husband, her</l>
					<l>care &amp; concern that her Sons Soul might</l>
					<l>prosper, and that he might be preserved for</l>
					<l>the Lord. She then appeard pretty well in</l>
					<l>Health as she was also the next Day till</l>
					<l>afternoon, when she complain&apos;d of her Head</l>
					<l>&amp; soon after sitting down was gone to her</l>
					<l>Lord in a minute of two in a quiet and </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>easy Manner (with scarce any Struggle</l>
					<l>of the Body) in the 52d Year of her Age. </l>
					<l>Her Corpse had afterwards a lovely aspect</l>
					<l>as teh Countenance of a reconciled com-</l>
					<l>-forted Sinner which had placidly slept</l>
					<l>in the Lord. She was also a most loving</l>
					<l>Daughter in Law to Br Hinchcliffs Father</l>
					<l>&amp; Mother who are both very ancient &amp; could </l>
					<l>not enough express how kind &amp; affectionate</l>
					<l>she had been to them, and who have therefore</l>
					<l>a real Loss in her Departure, as well as</l>
					<l>other necessitous People, whom she made </l>
					<l>it her Pleasure to help. For the Lord had</l>
					<l>given her a loving compassionate Heart.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
