<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Hutchinson_Hannah_Ful_SS_43</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1168.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The S Sr Hannah Hutchinson, who departed</l>
					<l>April 4th 1810 at Fulneck, was born at</l>
					<l>Littemoor near Pudsey Nov. 22. 1784</l>
					<l>From her childhood she attended with her</l>
					<l>Mother and Sister the preachings here in Fulneck</l>
					<l>and by that means got a desire, to live in the </l>
					<l>Brns Congn In July 1800 she obtained leave,</l>
					<l>to become an inhabitant of the Sisters house</l>
					<l>here Tho&apos; she was of a reserved turn yet it</l>
					<l>could be observed, that it was her consern both</l>
					<l>to learn to know herself as a poor sinful being</l>
					<l>and also the healing and sanctifying virtue</l>
					<l>of Jesus&apos; blood. In March 1803 she was recd</l>
					<l>into Congn and May the 4 followg into the S</l>
					<l>Srs Choir which oppertunities proved a blessing</l>
					<l>to her heart, and an encouragement to devote</l>
					<l>herself with soul and body to our Savour as his</l>
					<l>Dear bought property</l>
					<l>In autumn the same year she was seized with</l>
					<l>a bad fever, which brought her so low, that</l>
					<l>she was not expected to recover again, nor did</l>
					<l>she expect it hersalf, but was quite resegned</l>
					<l>to our Saviours will; however the means used</l>
					<l>for her recovery proved effectual thro&apos; the</l>
					<l>Lord&apos;s blessing. March 29th 1804 she</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1169.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>partook the first time of the H Comn and </l>
					<l>rec.d a special blessing on that occasion</l>
					<l>After this she spent 2 years in a happy and</l>
					<l>comfortable way; but in the years 1806 meet</l>
					<l>ing with troubles of various kinds she was</l>
					<l>thereby much affected in soul and Body, and </l>
					<l>grew so poorly, that it was feared, she whold</l>
					<l>fall into a decline; on which account</l>
					<l>she went for some time to her Parents</l>
					<l>house to be nursed. On this occasion like</l>
					<l>wise our Saviour proved her kind Physician</l>
					<l>both in Soul and Body, and she recoverd</l>
					<l>her health and chearfulness. She often</l>
					<l>spoke of that period with many tears,</l>
					<l>and would express herself to this effect:</l>
					<l>Our Saviour alone knows, what I have</l>
					<l>had to feel. Tho&apos; I was sure, that I had</l>
					<l>obtained pardoning grace in our Savior&apos;s</l>
					<l>blood and that my sins and transgressions</l>
					<l>were forgiven, yet it was as if I could fin</l>
					<l>no help, and being of a high Spirit and </l>
					<l>not willing to humble myself. I even re</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>solved in my mind to leave the Congn</l>
					<l>But thanks, eternal thanks to him who</l>
					<l>held his hand over me in all trials and</l>
					<l>temptations, and proved my Counselor</l>
					<l>and faithful friend. In January 1807</l>
					<l>she was appointed a Teacher in our Boardg</l>
					<l>School nch, she served with faithfulness till</l>
					<l>December 1809, and was beloved and re</l>
					<l>pected by the children commited to her </l>
					<l>care. Finding herselfe again in a poor</l>
					<l>state of health, she asked permission</l>
					<l>to leave the School, and went again to her</l>
					<l>Parents Altho&apos; she had a secret intimation</l>
					<l>that this sickness would terminate in </l>
					<l>her happy dissolution, yet now &amp; then</l>
					<l>she conceived a hope, that she would</l>
					<l>recover. Some uneasiness which had oc</l>
					<l>curred sometime before, at first desturbed</l>
					<l>her mind; but she was inabled to forget</l>
					<l>the things behind &amp; obtained that comfort</l>
					<l>able assurance, that our Saviour had par</l>
					<l>doned her for ever thing, &amp; she could</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1170.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>leave this world in peace with every body.</l>
					<l>Her cough &amp; other complaints, which she</l>
					<l>bore with petience, increasing more &amp; more,</l>
					<l>she longed for the time of her desolution.</l>
					<l>March 31 she injoyed the H. Comn for</l>
					<l>the last time, which proved a great</l>
					<l>blessing &amp; comfort to her; In Gratitute</l>
					<l>for the tender care which her Parents</l>
					<l>took of her, she prayed that our Savior</l>
					<l>would richly bless &amp; comfort them.</l>
					<l>Her last declarations concerning herself</l>
					<l>are contained in that hymn: Thy</l>
					<l>thoughts of peace &amp; H B. N. 387.</l>
					<l>which she also wished to be sung</l>
					<l>at Her funeral. Apr 2d Br Benade</l>
					<l>at her request prayed once more with </l>
					<l>her during a blessed feeling of our</l>
					<l>Saviours presence, &amp; on the 4th early</l>
					<l>in the morning it pleased our Sa</l>
					<l>viour to call her into her eternal rest.</l>
					<l>Aged 25 years 4 months &amp; 11 days.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
