<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Lawton_Elizabeth_Ful_3_12</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>went home July 30<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi>. 1770</l>
					<l>The course of Life of the Single Sister Eliz<hi rend='superscript:true;'>t</hi> Lawton</l>
					<l>I was Born in the parish of Mirfield April 12. 1744 &amp; Baptzd in the Church of England</l>
					<l>And in My Childrens years frequented the meetings of the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rnn</hi> along with My parents</l>
					<l>which was in that Time kept in Mirfield &amp; what they spoke &amp; sung of our Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>was very pleasing to me. I had also the satisfaction to be Educated at the school</l>
					<l>kept by the Sisters &amp; to injoy the Childrens Meetings &amp; got a pleasing Idea</l>
					<l>of our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> that He loved the children &amp; coud make them Happy. thus</l>
					<l>I spent My Childrens years having no distress of any kind till about my</l>
					<l>8<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>th</hi> year when it pleased our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> to take my mother very Suddenly</l>
					<l>home, by which occasion my Sister &amp; I went to live with a maried B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp;</l>
					<l>Sister who propos&apos;d profferd to take Care of us at my dear mothers departure.</l>
					<l>Here I continiued for sometime, till I was persuaded to go &amp; live in a family</l>
					<l>to have the Care of a little Child; but my first inquiry was, do they belong</l>
					<l>to the B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rnn</hi>? I was answerd no, but they were good freinds,</l>
					<l>I Spoke with B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Grosse who was the child<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rens</hi> parent, &amp; He seam&apos; d not to</l>
					<l>incurrage me in it, but yet He gave me leave &amp; tenderly reminded</l>
					<l>me to keep Close to our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; He woud help me thro&apos;, I had not been long</l>
					<l>in this place before I perciv&apos;d quite the contrary, to whatever had been</l>
					<l>told me I had many incitements to loose company &amp; conversation&apos; besides</l>
					<l>various hardships to Strugle with, which occasiond a dissorder to fall</l>
					<l>into my feet, so that I was necessiated to return unto my father in hopes</l>
					<l>of being cure&apos;d of my Lameness, when I came to my fathers house, I found</l>
					<l>my youngest B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> in the smallpox, which dissorder I also got in a few</l>
					<l>weeks Time &amp; had no other prospect but of going home, during this</l>
					<l>Sickness I got alively impression of the Single Sisters in a dream, being</l>
					<l>present with them in a Room were they made the finest Musick</l>
					<l>I ever heard in all my Life which affected me very much.</l>
					<l>about My 14<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>th</hi> year my natural deprivity bore Such an asendancy over</l>
					<l>me, that I often wish&apos;d My father had not belonged the B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rnn</hi> for then, I wou&apos;d</l>
					<l>have pursued the world &amp; all the pleasures which my inclination and</l>
					<l>Circumstance cou&apos;d admitt of, &amp; Certainly shou&apos;d have gone on to my</l>
					<l>my utter ruin, had not my good &amp; gracious Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> impressd upon my</l>
					<l>mind a constant apprehension of a future slate &amp; that his Life wou&apos;d</l>
					<l>be of no Long dureation, thus I went on haveing all my immagination</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>im bitterd with a painful conviction that I pored every intended preasure</l>
					<l>till the year 60 March 25<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>th</hi> having the favour to be present at the Gr<hi rend='superscript:true;'>t</hi> Girls</l>
					<l>Festival in Fulneck, what I saw &amp; injoy&apos;d in the Meetings of that day, was</l>
					<l>an abiding Grace unto my Heart Especialy the Last discourse held by</l>
					<l>B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Latrobe, which was a convinceing proof to me that my Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> had distined</l>
					<l>me, a Happy Lot a moment then which bowed me before him in gratitude &amp; shame.</l>
					<l>I kept a Sole Hankering I retain&apos;d a strong desire to attain my call &amp; with Earnestness begd tenderly for</l>
					<l>admition to the choirhouse which was also granted &amp; on Jan<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ry</hi> 13. 1761 I injoyd</l>
					<l>that great Grace of the coming an inhabbitant, in which I had not</l>
					<l>been many weeks before the H Ghost was perceptively bussey in shewing</l>
					<l>me the deep depravity of my nature &amp; tho&apos; I often prayd my dear Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>to show me all my missery; yet by my Close &amp; reserved disposition I felt</l>
					<l>many Times more then was possible for me to bear, Especially about</l>
					<l>may 1762 when in the Greatest anguish of my troubled Soul I brouk out</l>
					<l>in powerful Supplication to my Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> to help me with all Speed for I</l>
					<l>could hold it out no longer. he comforted &amp; let me feel this peace and</l>
					<l>gracious absolution &amp; it felt so to me as if my pardon was now seal&apos;d in</l>
					<l> Heaven, &amp; on the 19<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>th</hi> of the same month I had the Grace to be recieved</l>
					<l>into the congregation. I went on happy &amp; chereful for some time but</l>
					<l>when my Sinfulness appear&apos;d again, I became repeatedly in the same dismay</l>
					<l>&amp; did not like to be known by my Labourers &amp; Sisters, as I was known to my</l>
					<l>dearest Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; when my Choir companions had leave one after another to</l>
					<l>go to the H Communion &amp; I left behind, it gave me Scarcely pain! yet whenever</l>
					<l>I know expected I shou&apos;d be thought on for the communion, I prayd directly to my</l>
					<l>Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> not to give leave, least I shou&apos;d Eat &amp; drink my own damnation</l>
					<l>but to give me an upright &amp; open Heart</l>
					<l>in the year 1766 I was Spoke with by B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Bealer who recommended openness of</l>
					<l>Heart, I took new courrage &amp; spoke my Situation to my Labourers just as I felt</l>
					<l>&amp; it proved an abiding blessing to me &amp; I resolved not to remove from Jesus&apos; feet</l>
					<l>till I felt tho Gracious absolution &amp; a recconciliation to be that poor Sinner w<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>ch</hi></l>
					<l>the Holy Ghost was daily Labourering to bring me too.</l>
					<l>the Speaking by Sr. Loral for the first Festival after Her arrival I felt such</l>
					<l>a Sympathy from Her as incurraged me to a fresh confidence in My Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> that</l>
					<l>He was the only Sinners friend, &amp; the Same year had the Grace to a Candidate</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>for the Holy communion &amp; was comforted from the following words trust not in</l>
					<l>thy own fitness, but in My Sufficiant Merits, &amp; got a real Longing for this</l>
					<l>Highest Good which I participated of Sept<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>m</hi> 12 the same year to my deep abasement</l>
					<l>for it proved a Saceremental Joy to Soul &amp; body &amp; has Strength? &amp; renewd the Gratitude of</l>
					<l>my Hearts Love to him whenever I partook of His precious body &amp; blood therefore her own d?ing</l>
					<l>about a 12 month ago, our happily departed Sister was prceive&apos;d to become sickly</l>
					<l>but had no particular complaint, that any Medicine cou&apos;d be prescribed for</l>
					<l>Her relieve unless Something of a Cold, that terminated into a Cough that plagued Her very</l>
					<l>much at Times &amp; also weakend Her consitution so much that she was obliged</l>
					<l>about 3 months ago to remove into the sick room &amp; as she was one night in</l>
					<l>Her bed, she percived a Shudder, or as she Exprest Herself something came over Her</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>that Creapt along</hi> from Head to foot &amp; Left an impression of a death Shudder as if she</l>
					<l>shou&apos;d immediatly depart, she sent for the choir keeper &amp; with firm appearance </l>
					<l>beleived our Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> intended to take Her soon &amp; tho&apos; she grew a little better yet the</l>
					<l>Sisters perceived that a great altoration had happened to Her &amp; accordingly removed</l>
					<l>Her into the now Sickroon intended for the retirement of those Sisters who are in</l>
					<l>all likelyhood candidates for there Eternal Sabbath, which proved the Happiest</l>
					<l>Period this dear Sister ever injoyd in all Her Time Here Her Sabboth soon</l>
					<l>commenced &amp; she percived the Ease &amp; comfort in submitting to be the poorest &amp;</l>
					<l>worst of Sinners, &amp; thro&apos; the Strictness in herself brought on many conversation</l>
					<l>how she had reflected upon others to the no small pain of Heart &amp; Conscience</l>
					<l>yet our Gracious Lord comforted &amp; heard Her pain of mind, over every un-</l>
					<l>-faithfulness which she thro&apos; Grace was made conscious of &amp; believed Her most</l>
					<l>present Sickness to be prepartory <hi rend='underlined:true;'>Consequence</hi> to Her present &amp; future <unclear>in?</unclear></l>
					<l>in the Happiness which our Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> had died to purchas for Her! for she cou&apos;d now</l>
					<l>injoy the comforts of the Sinnors fellowship with Her sisters (<hi rend='underlined:true;'>which she before</hi></l>
					<l>was so Much Stralend in&apos; least she shou&apos;d be known to be that wretched Creature</l>
					<l>she knew Herself to be, but now thro Grace I can take to all &amp; yet have</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>done with all</hi>) &amp; (as His needy Sinner co&apos;d say He is the only desire of my</l>
					<l>Soul &amp; my Souls propritor, when Her Sister from Ockbrook came to see Her</l>
					<l>she was exceeding Glad &amp; thankful &amp; reccommended Her with the rest of her</l>
					<l>relations to the Gracious Love &amp; Mercy of our dearest Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>, till He took</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>her in His arms. she now begun to long for the injoyment</l>
					<l>of the Holy sacrement once more <hi rend='underlined:true;'>which she for the 2</hi><hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>d</hi><hi rend='underlined:true;'> Time received it in the sickroom</hi></l>
					<l>which was brought to Her by B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Charlsworth which &amp; was a particular blessing to</l>
					<l>Her Heart, B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Charlsworth took a remarkable notice &amp; leave of Her, &amp; when</l>
					<l>she heard that He was sick she said, He will be yet before me with My Lord &amp;</l>
					<l>God, <hi rend='underlined:true;'>when I come there</hi>, but the sisters thought not so; but she answerd yes you</l>
					<l>will find it so, &amp; then it was percived she altered very fast &amp; on the 28<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>th</hi></l>
					<l>took very little notice as the pain in Her Breast was very Voilent which made</l>
					<l>Her restless &amp; desirious to be released by Her dearest Bridegroom</l>
					<l>about half an hour before Her departure S<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi>  Lorel went to see Her &amp;</l>
					<l>she Beccon&apos;d for Her not to speak one word, saying I am going to get a little</l>
					<l>rest &amp; seem&apos;d quite composed, &amp; if the Sick waiter had not watchd Her</l>
					<l>Closely she wou&apos;d have Slipt away in a Sleep according to her own desire but</l>
					<l>the drawing of Her Breath gave the Signal &amp; the blessing of Her choir</l>
					<l>was imparted as Her Happy soul took flight to rest for Ever in the arms of its</l>
					<l>Eternal Husband, in the Evening about 6 a Clock July 30. 1770 -</l>
					<l>In the 27<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>th</hi> year of her Age</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
