<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>McMillan_I_Ful_3_149</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>c</hi>Millan, excuted at Ayr May [Friday] 25. 1810.</l>
					<l>He was tried &amp; condemned Apr. 17 &amp; 18 for having</l>
					<l>administered poison to a young woman, </l>
					<l>which occasioned not only the death of her</l>
					<l>child, but her own death. He was a native</l>
					<l>of Scotland</l>
					<l>[Friday] 20 Mar. I called upon him the first time.</l>
					<l>He expressed his pleasure at seeing me (M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>Paul having the night before told him who</l>
					<l>I was). He told me be had been in Gracehill</l>
					<l>in the way of trade. But otherwise he did</l>
					<l>not say much.</l>
					<l>He was unwell, thro’ the agitation of his mind. His distress was</l>
					<l>augmented, as he had been quite confident he would be acquitted,</l>
					<l>even to the very last. He thought his fate very hard, tho’ he</l>
					<l>??? he had received justice at the trial. He felt much</l>
					<l>23 &amp; 25 / Visited him again. He was greatly dis</l>
					<l>tresed at that part of the sentence, by which</l>
					<l>his body was to be given to the Surgeon.</l>
					<l>Endeavoured to pacify him, and lead his atten</l>
					<l>tion to concerns of his soul. His mind greatly</l>
					<l>relieved by Gaolor mentioning, he understood</l>
					<l>fr. the Provost, his body would scarcely be</l>
					<l>asked for by Surgeons at Edinburgh.</l>
					<l>At these visits he appeared rather selfrigh</l>
					<l>teous, priding himself upon his supposed</l>
					<l>moral conduct in every other respect, ex</l>
					<l>cepting the crime for which he was con</l>
					<l>demned.</l>
					<l>28. / He was greatly alarmed with the future</l>
					<l>judgment. He said, he saw sin now to be</l>
					<l>a very great evil. He seemed distressed</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>that he did not feel sufficient fluency &amp;</l>
					<l>eloquence in praying. I endeavoured to</l>
					<l>put him to rights on that <unclear>head</unclear>. Henry</l>
					<l>Cowen had just been with him, and I ra</l>
					<l>ther suspect, that he &amp; I  <unclear>J. Gac</unclear> perplex</l>
					<l>his mind with subjects of that kind.</l>
					<l>May. 1 / Saw him again, He seems to in</l>
					<l>crease in selfknowledge, and in desire <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>to</hi></l>
					<l>after our Savior. The Meth. Minister</l>
					<l>came in. I thought his manner of speak</l>
					<l>ing, to the Prisoner very suitable. He ur</l>
					<l>ged him to use the utmost simplicity</l>
					<l>in ???? applying to our Savior, and </l>
					<l>to come to him just in he was, without</l>
					<l>thinking to make himself better.</l>
					<l>[Thursday].3. / Was nearly an hour with him. He</l>
					<l>said he had no goodness or merit at all</l>
					<l>to plead bef. God. He had comitted innu</l>
					<l>merable sins, for which God might justly</l>
					<l>condemn him, independent of the crime</l>
					<l>for which he suffered. He was able to</l>
					<l>give up his mother &amp; relatives to God,</l>
					<l>and not distress himself any more on</l>
					<l>their account. He did not intend to</l>
					<l>leave anything behind him in writing</l>
					<l>as he thought it was not becoming a</l>
					<l>criminal to speak with too much as</l>
					<l>surance of himself, and it might tend</l>
					<l>to make others presume on the mercy</l>
					<l>of God, and harden them in sin.</l>
					<l>[Thursday].10./ Prisoner feels more composed this</l>
					<l>he is sensible Religion has made a change</l>
					<l>upon him - afraid to be too confident</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>temptation, till I fell in with this woman</l>
					<l>I was too weak to resist God knows what</l>
					<l>distress I have felt since and still feel, but</l>
					<l>I believe be hath pardoned me.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I die in peace with all mankind</l>
					<l>I have nothing against Prsecutor, Jury</l>
					<l>or Judge.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I shall always have reason to pray for par</l>
					<l>don to the very last moment for there is</l>
					<l>no perfection in this world.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;It is finished!&quot; How delightful. It is</l>
					<l>the most precious sentence in the Bible</l>
					<l>to a Sinner who can do nothing himself,</l>
					<l>and has given to believe in it.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;When I have <unclear>escaped</unclear>, I shall remember</l>
					<l>in heaven, My Crimes; it will add to my</l>
					<l>Joy. ??? say: He loved &amp; washed his</l>
					<l>sin. they have no? recollection of sin. </l>
					<l>&quot;What a mercy I was so well attended,</l>
					<l>the Lord will reward you.&quot; I said: We</l>
					<l>are by nature sinners like you &quot;No.</l>
					<l>He said, &quot;how unmindful are we of the</l>
					<l>slippery path It is very slippery&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;How many happy hours do I now spend in</l>
					<l>intercourse with my Savior&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;The heart is deceitful, especially mine</l>
					<l>I greatly fear it.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I have attempted to do good works, but they have</l>
					<l>been only an Insult to God, they were done to buy</l>
					<l>God&apos;s favor but now I wld wish to do it out</l>
					<l>of love to my Savior.&quot;</l>
					<l>[Friday]. 18/ Was in Prison first- 2 1/2 getting  M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Paul</l>
					<l>to let me in at the end J.  <unclear>Genocty</unclear>  came</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>&quot;I have just read Rom VII. I think it very</l>
					<l>applicable to <hi rend='underlined:true;'>my</hi> case, especially: &quot;O wret</l>
					<l>ched man that I am.&quot;</l>
					<l>I read a passage of Taylor to him. He</l>
					<l>seemed much struck with it. He thought</l>
					<l>much of the hymn; Come ye Sinners</l>
					<l>poor &amp; wretched &amp;c. which I repeated.</l>
					<l> &quot;My time passes very quickly in me</l>
					<l> ditation &amp; prayer.</l>
					<l>&quot;I wish my relations, fellow prisoners</l>
					<l>&amp; all mankind wld. take warning by</l>
					<l>me -- I earnestly pray for them.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;What a blessed thing it is that we have</l>
					<l>the gospel.</l>
					<l>&quot;I wish I may be supported at the last.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;When M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>c</hi>Lean came to me the day of Con</l>
					<l>demnation, his observation had no im</l>
					<l>pression upon me.&quot;</l>
					<l>He was 2 days in Carlisle Jail came to</l>
					<l>Wigton beginning of December.&quot;</l>
					<l>His relatives much <unclear>built</unclear> in their worldly</l>
					<l>concerns by his removal.</l>
					<l>&quot;I was never a hardened Sinner, but I at</l>
					<l>tempted religion in my own strength.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I knew much more of Bible before</l>
					<l>but my memory fails.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I heard the Sentence with gt confusion</l>
					<l>it did not seize till I came into the</l>
					<l>passage.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I think I leave a good hope but I am jealous</l>
					<l>lest my heart shld. be deceived by Satan.&quot;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>[Saturday]. 19. / M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Lawson came in. Prisoner got a</l>
					<l>letter, Barber came. He had dreamed much</l>
					<l>of me, thinking I was not well and he led me</l>
					<l>down the street. He said nothing new.</l>
					<l>He wishes he could make a firm cove</l>
					<l>nant with the Lord.</l>
					<l>[Monday] 21./ Went to the Prison at 2. &quot;tonight I felt</l>
					<l>greatly distressed with a sense of my sins, they</l>
					<l>stood all before me, But I was relieved by a</l>
					<l>most uncommon feeling of happiness, I felt my</l>
					<l>heart glow, full of joy, sense of pardoning love</l>
					<l>I cannot express it. Surely I am not decei</l>
					<l>ving myself. I am a great, very great sinner</l>
					<l>but I think God&apos;s mercy is greater. I love to</l>
					<l>trace the sufferings of X [Christ]. there I see Divine</l>
					<l>love.&quot; Letter he got on [Saturday] was fr. his Mini</l>
					<l>ster, who gave evangelical advice.</l>
					<l>Prisoner now speak with more feeling,</l>
					<l>emotion.</l>
					<l>Tuesday 22./ Mor. M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Lawson &amp; I were in. Prisoner menti-</l>
					<l>oned the sympathy of his frnds &amp; sayd he desired</l>
					<l>comfort for it, but added what is the friendship</l>
					<l>of the world <hi rend='underlined:true;'>now</hi> to me, if I have not friendship of</l>
					<l>God.&quot; He heard of X&apos;s [Christ&apos;s] sympathy with emotion.</l>
					<l>&quot;I have lived in pleasure, but it had a sting.</l>
					<l>In midst of a jovial companions I wondered</l>
					<l>I would not be happy.&quot; Here in jail the</l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>Lord shall wipe tears </hi>time has gone swiftly</l>
					<l>&amp; quickly, never did it pass so quickly. the</l>
					<l>fatal day is near. time flies &amp; has an end</l>
					<l>but God&apos;s mercy endureth forever.&quot;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>&quot;Lord will wipe away tears&quot; Many thousand</l>
					<l>tears have I shed here. and shall continue to</l>
					<l>weep till the last. tho&apos; <hi rend='underlined:true;'>now</hi> my tears are</l>
					<l>mixed with joy. the more I feel of the</l>
					<l>love of God, the more heinous do also my</l>
					<l>sins appear, but his love prevents despair.&quot;</l>
					<l>-&quot;God&apos;s pardoning love fills me with joy</l>
					<l>&apos;it shall be my ??? while here and ???</l>
					<l>eternity I shall sing; to him that <hi rend='underlined:true;'>loved</hi> &amp;c&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;O that it is a precious promise, there shall</l>
					<l>be a fountain &amp;c.</l>
					<l>&quot;At first I could not attend to anything the</l>
					<l>Ministers said to me, I could not remember</l>
					<l>their conversationx, during the very prayers</l>
					<l>my mind was distracted. but now I could</l>
					<l>wish at to have them all day with me, I feel</l>
					<l>happy in their company and happy in the</l>
					<l>recollections.&quot; <hi rend='underlined:true;'>Ques.</hi> &quot;Do you not think your</l>
					<l>indifference arose in part; fr want of convic</l>
					<l>tion of your sins, your supposed innocence?&quot;</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>Ans.</hi> &quot;Yes. But now I have nothing to rely</l>
					<l>I continue as but free grace.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I continue jealous over myself, but I sense</l>
					<l>my strength will be equal to my day.&quot;</l>
					<l>[Wednesday] 23./ M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Lawson &amp; I were in. &quot;My best actions have</l>
					<l>be sinful. It was my deceitful heart wh</l>
					<l>harried me on to comission of this crime.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I had oft good desires, but they were lost.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I prayed in Wigton Jail, but it was for life</l>
					<l>&amp; liberty. my heart clave to the earth. my</l>
					<l>treasure was there. How I hope my treasure</l>
					<l>is in Heaven. I pray with conviction &amp; compas</l>
					<l>of my sins.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Tho&apos; Devil&apos;s sin was forgiven him, yet divine</l>
					<l>judgements were not removed in this world, so</l>
					<l>I think, it is with me.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;My case formerly was like Israelites, who</l>
					<l>prayed for divine direction, yet when it run</l>
					<l>counter to their own inclinations, they wld.</l>
					<l>not follow it; now I hope I wish to give my</l>
					<l>whole heart to Jesus.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;I hope my inprisonment will be a blessing</l>
					<l>to my fate. I wish it may be a warning to all.</l>
					<l>I may have reason to bless God for it on <hi rend='underlined:true;'>their</hi></l>
					<l>account to all eternity.&quot;</l>
					<l>[Thursday]/ 24./ Saw him at 2. Rev<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> <unclear>Anld</unclear> had just come</l>
					<l>out, with whom I had some talk. Expressed his</l>
					<l>astonishment on Prisoner&apos;s composure.</l>
					<l>Asked me, what I thought it arose from.</l>
					<l>I told him, Prisoner had been convinced of</l>
					<l>&amp; confessed his crime, had cried for mercy,</l>
					<l>and <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>confessed he</hi> professed himself now to</l>
					<l>have a good hope of Salvation. M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Anld</l>
					<l>did not think that the evidence was so</l>
					<l>strong to condemn him, as the Indictment</l>
					<l>charged him not with the Child&apos;s death</l>
					<l>but only with that of the woman, and </l>
					<l>the <hi rend='underlined:true;'>intention</hi> of this appeared not proved;</l>
					<l>indeed Prisoner always denies having had</l>
					<l>the least intention of that kind.</l>
					<l>Was not long with Prisoner, as a friend of</l>
					<l>his came in to speak of some family</l>
					<l>concerns, and I could not pray with him</l>
					<l>on that account for want of time.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>He said: Sting of death was now gone</l>
					<l>These texts particularly comfortable:</l>
					<l>God so loved world. Came not call righ</l>
					<l>teous. J.C. came into world to save</l>
					<l>Sinners.</l>
					<l><unclear>Baily Shirkland</unclear> had been in, I &quot;He asked me,</l>
					<l>said Prisoner,&quot; if I had employed my time well?</l>
					<l>I was going to tell him / but he just went</l>
					<l>away / that tho&apos; it was my duty to employ</l>
					<l>my time, I could never have done it to good pur</l>
					<l>pose, if the Lord had not given me his grace;</l>
					<l>and that whatever I might have done, I had</l>
					<l>nothing to rely upon but the finished work</l>
					<l>of Christ.&quot;</l>
					<l>In our meeting this evening I read Luke XV</l>
					<l>and then mentioned that this chapter had</l>
					<l>been particularly comforting to the Prisoner,</l>
					<l>and that I had reason to think, he had him</l>
					<l>self felt something of that love of X. [Christ] to sinners</l>
					<l>which is there so strikingly represented. </l>
					<l>We closed with an prayer kneeling during which</l>
					<l>all seemed greatly affected.</l>
					<l>In the night 3 ??? watchd with Prisoner.</l>
					<l>I. <unclear>Gunby</unclear> told me next morning, that in the</l>
					<l>early part of night Prisoner had been so affected</l>
					<l>with his approaching end as to tremble, but</l>
					<l>he grew gradually composed.</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>[Friday]. 25. / Execution Day</hi>. I went to the Prison soon</l>
					<l>after 9 but hearing, that Stevenson &amp; Lawson</l>
					<l>&amp; several others were in, I did not go to him. And</l>
					<l>understanding Mr. Auld was to come at 10 and</l>
					<l>wanted to be alone with Prisoner, I returnd</l>
					<l>home, but went back again before 11.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='9'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Auld had not yet arrived, but he came soon.</l>
					<l>Meanwhile I waited in the guard room</l>
					<l>Shaw came; and when Auld came out, we</l>
					<l>went in together. Prisoner was just then</l>
					<l>taking leave of his brother / who had come</l>
					<l>last night / the scene was affecting and very</l>
					<l>trying to him; but he recovered himself in</l>
					<l>a few monents. I had addressed &amp; prayed with</l>
					<l>him. I then spoke a few words, and desired him</l>
					<l>to fix on a Psalm to be sung, he <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>gave an</hi> mentioned Psalm 107</l>
					<l>Gauchy presented. I then prayed. Shaw</l>
					<l>now went away, but Maclean came in. He</l>
					<l>spoke to him, another psalm was sung, and then</l>
					<l>he prayd. Maclean then urged Prisoner to</l>
					<l>pray; be did it, but seemed put to. Steven</l>
					<l>son now came in. Maclean &amp; I went out for</l>
					<l>1/2 hour, and then returned. Stevenson was</l>
					<l>still speaking to him &amp; then prayed. Priso</l>
					<l>ner wished the hymn no. in Wise Coll.</l>
					<l>to be sung: &quot;The hour of my depature&apos;s come &amp;c.</l>
					<l>I then prayed with him.</l>
					<l>All present were now ordered to leave him, except us Ministers.</l>
					<l>Stevenson now pro</l>
					<l>posed to him to kneel down &amp; offer a silent prayer</l>
					<l>He did so for about 10 minutes, and uttered the</l>
					<l>2 or 3 last sentences aloud: &quot;Lord Jesus receive</l>
					<l>my spirit, that I may join in the song of</l>
					<l>praise to the Lamb, that was slain <hi rend='underlined:true;'>forever</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>&amp; ever</hi>. He then said: &quot;The Lord&apos;s goodness</l>
					<l>to me hath been very great, O that I could</l>
					<l>love him better. It was intimated, the Exe</l>
					<l>cutioner would previously come &amp; tie his</l>
					<l>arms. Stevenson encouraged him very affectio</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='10'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>nately, reminded him, Our Savior had an expe</l>
					<l>rimental fellow feeling with us in distress.</l>
					<l>Just then Bailey Donaldsorn came &amp; told him</l>
					<l>his time was come, <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>fell</hi> he replied. &quot;I am ready</l>
					<l>Sir,&quot; Executioner tied his arms behand very</l>
					<l>gently. He went out imediately followed by</l>
					<l>us 3 Ministers. In Outer passage went ????</l>
					<l>&amp; an acquaintance of his, <unclear>Mr Ken of Constant</unclear></l>
					<l>send a short paper he had signed, expression</l>
					<l>of his thanks <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>to Prisoner, and at</hi> ??? ?????</l>
					<l>and that he hoped for mercy thro&apos; atoning</l>
					<l>blood of Jesus.&quot;</l>
					<l>He went forward with steady steps. we</l>
					<l>took leave of him, He spent 3 or 4 mi</l>
					<l>nutes is silent prayer, <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>droppe</hi> made the</l>
					<l>sign, but executioner was not imedi</l>
					<l>ately ready. He died almost without</l>
					<l>struggle.</l>
					<l>He was wonderfully composed, &amp; to the last</l>
					<l>asserted his hope was solely built on the</l>
					<l>Atonement. When he had risen fr. his</l>
					<l>last prayer in the cell, he said; &quot;The Lord</l>
					<l>God fear. this was his last observation,</l>
					<l>The <unclear>crowd</unclear> was great, but care been taken</l>
					<l>taken that the Prison was not crowded.</l>
					<l>When he was suspended, Stevenson &amp; I &amp; the</l>
					<l>2 Baillies the Dean of Guild went into the</l>
					<l>Constable. He came out at 3 o&apos;cl.</l>
					<l>His corpse was this evening taken away by</l>
					<l>2 Glasgow Doctors in a g<unclear>ig</unclear>, who had to be</l>
					<l>guarded thro&apos; the town, a yet were pelted</l>
					<l>wiht stones. I got home at 4 o&apos;Cl.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='11'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>lest he shoud say &quot;peace, peace where there</l>
					<l>is no peace&quot; afraid his repentance is</l>
					<l>not sufficiently deep and that he cannot</l>
					<l>sorrow for sins as he ought. enjoys more</l>
					<l>liberty in prayer.</l>
					<l>[Saturday]. 12 / met with M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Watson in the Prison, and had</l>
					<l>not much conversation with the Prisoner.</l>
					<l>[Monday]. 14./ Methodist minister &amp; I had not been long in</l>
					<l>when the Prisoner&apos;s brother, Alexander, came in</l>
					<l>and as they were going to a last farewell of</l>
					<l>each other, we soon left him.</l>
					<l>[Tuesday]. 15./ Was nearly an hour alone with Prisoner,</l>
					<l>and he talked a good deal. Rev<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi>. Arthur Stewart</l>
					<l>of Kirkeowen / 3 miles fr. Wigton / preaches the</l>
					<l>Gospel, is a pious old man, had great regard</l>
					<l>for Prisoner, and was greatly affected with his</l>
					<l>fate. Prisoner has written to him / I heard af</l>
					<l>terwards that the Schoolmaster had written</l>
					<l>to Alexander, the Dyer, saying Prisoner had born</l>
					<l>a very good character in the parish; and wishing</l>
					<l>him to visit the Prisoner./ Prisoner said, he</l>
					<l>was going to write to his principle prosecu</l>
					<l>tor, who, he heard, was greatly troubled now,</l>
					<l>to assure him he died in peace with all men</l>
					<l>and hoped God would be merciful to his soul.</l>
					<l>Afterwards told me, he had been persuaded by a friend not to write.</l>
					<l>Prisoner&apos;s father was a weaver, he was brought</l>
					<l>up to that business, &amp; had little land.</l>
					<l>He can protest with his dying breath, that </l>
					<l>he did not intend to take the woman&apos;s life</l>
					<l>was ignorant of the strength of the poison</l>
					<l>that he got it according to her repeated requests,</l>
					<l>was in a great hurry when he brought it her</l>
					<l>for his father was lying upon his death bed</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='12'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and would not have him to be absent that</l>
					<l>he <unclear>instructed</unclear> the woman to be cautious in</l>
					<l>the use of it, especially to keep fr. getting</l>
					<l>cold, to which she replied, that her Master</l>
					<l>would have little or no more Out-door</l>
					<l>work to do for her. They did not suppose</l>
					<l>the child to be quickend at the time, and</l>
					<l>therefore thought it was no sin to use</l>
					<l>means to produce abortion, they only</l>
					<l>wished to hide their shame. I particu</l>
					<l>larly interrogated him upon this part of</l>
					<l>the crime, and what he now thought re</l>
					<l>specting his conduct. He said, he <hi rend='underlined:true;'>now</hi></l>
					<l>felt convinced, that his first connexion</l>
					<l>with the woman was a damnable  sin,</l>
					<l>that taking life in any state of existence</l>
					<l>&amp; under any circumstances, not absolutely</l>
					<l>unavoidable, was a heinous crime. He</l>
					<l>would be absolutely without hope if it were</l>
					<l>not, that God so loved the world &amp;c.</l>
					<l>Regarding his former life, he said: I was sober</l>
					<l>honest, &amp; generally respected, went diligently to</l>
					<l>church, but I sought more the presise of men,</l>
					<l>than that of God. I had no life in my soul</l>
					<l>he saw little need of grace, &amp; therefore never</l>
					<l>seriously prayed for it. To what an awful</l>
					<l>length of wickedness have I been driven,</l>
					<l>by no resisting temptation and being left</l>
					<l>to myself. but I hope the Lord will yet</l>
					<l>grant me Repentance unto life.</l>
					<l>With regard to my notions of religion they</l>
					<l>are not grearly altered, tho&apos; my views of the </l>
					<l>Gospel are clearer and I feel something</l>
					<l>of their influence. I in a measure knew</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='13'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and sometimes thought of these truths</l>
					<l>before, but they never impreseed my mind</l>
					<l>as they do now.&quot; The fear of death was</l>
					<l>greatly taken fr. him, and he could be con</l>
					<l>tented &amp; happy to die in an ordinary way</l>
					<l>but his death was peculiarly bitter, and he</l>
					<l>felt especially for his friends. He was afraid</l>
					<l>he could no so forget them as he ought to</l>
					<l>do. I told him, it was not required, we shld</l>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>love</hi> our special concern for friends, but <hi rend='underlined:true;'>so</hi></l>
					<l>commit them to our Savior and leave them</l>
					<l>in the hands of a faithful friend, as not to</l>
					<l>fret &amp; never rule? against God. Referred to</l>
					<l>Xs [Christ&apos;s] words: &quot;Son behold thy mother &amp;c. This</l>
					<l>consoled him. He said, &quot;I with my fds. may</l>
					<l>take warning by me, and walk cautiously</l>
					<l>on the slippery paths of life, shld my unhappy</l>
					<l>fate be the means of awakening, and</l>
					<l>converting any of them, I shld have cause</l>
					<l>to rejoice even at my misfortune. Indeed</l>
					<l> I wish sinners at large may take war</l>
					<l>ning by me.&quot; &quot;I fear the depravity of</l>
					<l>my heart, lest I shld deceive myself in my</l>
					<l>present hope; I think I could speak with mor <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>assurd</hi></l>
					<l>assurances, if I was at large in the world,</l>
					<l>and <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>could</hi> had more opportunities to show</l>
					<l>the sincerity of my Repentance.&quot;</l>
					<l>I have been reading Luke XV. It is an en</l>
					<l>couraging chapter. And that is a re[le]vant</l>
					<l>passage: &quot;Turn ye Prisoners of <hi rend='underlined:true;'>hope</hi></l>
					<l>I pointed out to him Isaiah 1-3 with</l>
					<l>its reference in Luke IV. 18.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='14'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>&quot;The forepart of ??. I sleep little. I used to</l>
					<l>dread this life. but now I spend it in sweet</l>
					<l>meditation.</l>
					<l>[Thursday]. 17./ He is 3 mos. 35 years of age was never</l>
					<l>married, is a linen weaver. He went to</l>
					<l>Whitehaven, In to be out of the way for a</l>
					<l>few days not apprehending any danger.</l>
					<l>Here he was taken while walking carelessly</l>
					<l>about in the market. 19 weeks confined</l>
					<l>in Wigton Jail. persuaded by all there was</l>
					<l>not fear urged to escape, wh. cld. easily be</l>
					<l>affected but was confident of acquittal.</l>
					<l>&quot;My escape would have gratified my frds</l>
					<l>but now I think I have reason to be</l>
					<l>thankful I did not do it.&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;At first when I came here, I had not appa</l>
					<l>tite but I forced myself, as people said I</l>
					<l>was going to starve myself, I wished no<hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>t</hi></l>
					<l>clamour to be raised for my gt. sins was</l>
					<l>the praise of man, or I would not come here.&quot;</l>
					<l>???? he wld not have done what he</l>
					<l>did to hide his shame/</l>
					<l>&quot;David watered his couch with his tears</l>
					<l>Mary M. bathed X&apos;s [Christ&apos;s] feet, but my hard heart</l>
					<l>does not feel that compunction, O for</l>
					<l>deeper sorrow!&quot;</l>
					<l>&quot;Peter said, Lord thou knowest I dare not</l>
					<l>say so, but I may say: thou knowest I de</l>
					<l>sire to love thee, O what beauty is there</l>
					<l>in our Savior.&quot;</l>
					<l> &quot;When I was very young; I had a woman</l>
					<l>with child, it greatly distressed me, and I </l>
					<l>long desird it but I then <unclear>setted</unclear> something</l>
					<l>upon the child.&quot; I afterwards avoided</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
