<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Mortimer_Sarah_Ful_SS_2</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Our late sr Sarah Mortimer who departed happily Jan. 2 1810 at Fulneck </l>
					<l>Our happily departed Sr Sarah Mor</l>
					<l>timer, was born June 3 1780 at Scoles</l>
					<l>in the parish of Birstal, and baptized</l>
					<l>in the Church of England. Her Mother</l>
					<l>dy&apos;d before she was a year old, and she</l>
					<l>being a very weakly Child &amp; not likely</l>
					<l>to live, was put out to be nursed to</l>
					<l>a married Br &amp; Sr in Wyke, who had no</l>
					<l>Children, &amp; who took so much care of </l>
					<l>her in every respect, as if she had been</l>
					<l>their own Child. Sthe was sent to the </l>
					<l>Brns School in Wyke as soon as her</l>
					<l>health would perpi admit of it, It</l>
					<l>was then conducted by the sisters Mary </l>
					<l>Watson / now in Gracehill/ and Benigna</l>
					<l>Planta / now in Okbrook./ who both with </l>
					<l>this good advice to the Children, often</l>
					<l>remainded them, how needful is was, not</l>
					<l>only to come to School to work &amp;c.</l>
					<l>But also to get an impression of our</l>
					<l>Saviour&apos;s love, that they might be happy, </l>
					<l>and grow up for him, who had suffered</l>
					<l>so much for us. They used every week</l>
					<l>to learn Verses out of the Hymn Book.</l>
					<l>This was a favourite imployment of hers,</l>
					<l>and with the rehearsal of them, she</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>often edified those people she lived</l>
					<l>with; and it was by these means she felt</l>
					<l>the first imprission of our Saviour&apos;s</l>
					<l>love towards her. Living near the </l>
					<l>Srs House she was often visited by</l>
					<l>them, and had the favour to go in </l>
					<l>and out amongst them, whereby she</l>
					<l>got a desire to belong to the Brns</l>
					<l>Congn. Her Father being agreable</l>
					<l>to it, both she and her Sr obtained</l>
					<l>leave to live in the Srs Oeconomy at Little More</l>
					<l>and moved thither March 14th 1792,</l>
					<l>where she enjoyed manyy blessings,</l>
					<l>especially in attending the meetings at</l>
					<l>Fulnek. When that Oeconomy broke</l>
					<l>up, in 1794, she with some more Srs</l>
					<l>moved to Wyke. She would rather</l>
					<l>have gone to Fulneck; but in a short</l>
					<l>time grew became reconciled about to it, and </l>
					<l>indeed she never found reason to re</l>
					<l>pent. That small family lived at  </l>
					<l>that time very happily together, and in a bles</l>
					<l>sed course; particularly amongst the </l>
					<l>great Girls, each was zealous, to get be</l>
					<l>fore the other in prospserity. From this Period</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>she dated her the foundation of her happiness</l>
					<l>which was laid more deep and sure in the all atoning </l>
					<l>sacrifice of a Crucified Saviour and</l>
					<l>Redeemer. Nov. 30th the same year she</l>
					<l>was rec&apos;d into the Congregation, &amp; Jan. 10th 1796</l>
					<l>had the favour to partake for the first</l>
					<l>time of the H. Comn, and the year</l>
					<l>following 4th of May she was rec&apos;d into </l>
					<l>the Sgle Srs choir. Soon after this it</l>
					<l>happened to be a very trying time, </l>
					<l>as the Srs could get no work for several</l>
					<l>months, on which account many returned</l>
					<l>to their homes; but she not being willing to return home,</l>
					<l>chose to stay, tho&apos; her living should be ever</l>
					<l>so poor. But our merciful heavenly</l>
					<l>Father who knows the wants of all</l>
					<l>his Children; raised up some particular</l>
					<l>friends, who assisted them with every</l>
					<l>thing most nessecary; so that those, whose</l>
					<l>faith was only as a Grain of Mustard seed,</l>
					<l>and stayed nevertheless was quite put to shame.</l>
					<l>She often spoke of that period with </l>
					<l>gratitude, and it inabled her to place</l>
					<l>her whole dependance on our Saviour</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>both with regard to her internal and </l>
					<l>external course. In 1801 she rec&apos;d a</l>
					<l>appointment to have the care of</l>
					<l>the great Girls in Gumersal Tho she</l>
					<l>felt herself unfit for such a situate</l>
					<l>yet she submitted to it out of Obe</l>
					<l>diance; and calling to mind, how</l>
					<l>much the Lord had done for her,</l>
					<l>she thought it was but little what</l>
					<l>she could do in return. We can give</l>
					<l>her that testimony, that she was faith-</l>
					<l>ful in the charge committed to her</l>
					<l>not only in teaching them their work,</l>
					<l>but in making their internal prosperity, was a</l>
					<l>subject of her progress. She had of</l>
					<l>late years several heavy trails, which</l>
					<l>affected her much; but our Saviour</l>
					<l>in whom she put her trust and con-</l>
					<l>fidence, supported her, so that she</l>
					<l>with resignation submitted to his will</l>
					<l>In the beginning of last year /1810/ she </l>
					<l>got a heavy could which settled on her </l>
					<l>Lungs, and made her feel very weak</l>
					<l>and poorly; in Sept. she came here</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>to Fulnek to partake of the H. Comn</l>
					<l>in fellowship with her Choir; being</l>
					<l>over taken in a heavy storm of thun-</l>
					<l>der, and lightening, she was much agi-</l>
					<l>tated and grew worse from that time,</l>
					<l>Now and then she had a faint hope</l>
					<l>of her recovery; but feeling nevertheless miser</l>
					<l>able her health and strength declin-</l>
					<l>ing, she was soon resigned to our</l>
					<l>Saviours will. It was her earnest</l>
					<l>wish and prayer that he would show</l>
					<l>her every guilt, &amp; chance &amp; purify her</l>
					<l>from every stain in his precious Blood, </l>
					<l>that she might appear before him as a </l>
					<l>pardoned reconciled sinner; When an </l>
					<l>anxious thought at times would arise;</l>
					<l>she was inabled with confidence to </l>
					<l>look to him, whose strengtht was</l>
					<l>made perfect in her weakness. </l>
					<l>She would often express herself to </l>
					<l>the following purpose:</l>
					<l>&quot;Ah! when I look back on past years, </l>
					<l>I cannot help weeping for grief,</l>
					<l>But Christ wipes away all my tears,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>And readily grants me relief: </l>
					<l>By faith I behold in his wounds</l>
					<l>A cure for my sins and self-will;</l>
					<l>His goodness towards me abounds,</l>
					<l>And his hand is held over me still.&quot;</l>
					<l>During her confinement she injoyed</l>
					<l>twice the H. Comn which was a great</l>
					<l>refreshment and strengthtning to her. </l>
					<l>She loved &amp; was beloved, &amp; was truly</l>
					<l>thankful for every kindness shown</l>
					<l>towards her. She bore her pains</l>
					<l>with great petions patience, and often said:</l>
					<l>&quot;Dear Saviour! help me,&quot; and also </l>
					<l>asked her friends to pray for her.</l>
					<l>Jany 2d 1811 the happy moment came</l>
					<l>when she was permitted to leave</l>
					<l>this world, and see him face to face</l>
					<l>in whom she here believed.</l>
					<l>Aged 30 years and 6 Months. </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
