<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Oates_James_Ful_3_53</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Departed June 2d 1761.</l>
					<l>The great Boy James Oates was born at Norwood Green in 7th</l>
					<l>Parish of Halifax Sept the 14th 1745, was baptized in ye Church of England,</l>
					<l>but has been amongst ye Brn from a Child, during which State he was always bore</l>
					<l>ye Character of plain downright &amp; honest, was beloved by ye Labourer of the Plan wherein</l>
					<l>he lived &amp; of those</l>
					<l>by the Childns Father</l>
					<l>who visited him from time to time for his genuine Simplicity.</l>
					<l>He was rec&apos;d into the great Boys Choir Jany ye 13th 1760, after which it was</l>
					<l>obvious, that the getting a true acquaintance with the Man of Sorrows lay</l>
					<l>very near his Heart. When he was visited &amp; spoke with from time to time by</l>
					<l>his Choir Labourers they always found him ye same Simple &amp; openhearted</l>
					<l>course, andently desiring to become a Joy to that Heart which broke in Death for</l>
					<l>him; for which reason the Close of his Conversation with them was generally</l>
					<l>about coming into ye Choirhouse, where he might spend his time uninterrupted</l>
					<l>by in a true Devotion of Soul &amp; Body to ye humanity of Christ, the Boys Choir</l>
					<l>heads &amp; Prince. Accordingly this favour was granted him Apr. ye 21st 1760 to his</l>
					<l>inexpressible Joy. The Business which he followed in ye Choirhouse was that</l>
					<l>of a Stuffweaver, which he began with his father while at home principally</l>
					<l>and exercised great Diligence thereat principally with a View to come soon</l>
					<l>into ye Choirhouse &amp; that there he might be as little burthensome as possible.</l>
					<l>He shewd as much Diligence at his Work here as one could well expect of a Boy in</l>
					<l>his Years, but being naturally of an active turn of mind &amp; strong in body he often</l>
					<l>sollicited to be put to another business which required harder Labour &amp; more Ex-</l>
					<l>ercise. But this being not convenient according to our Circumstances, he was</l>
					<l>told to pursue that business which he had learnt. Herein he shewd such an unfeig-</l>
					<l>ned obedience as was exemplary to all of other Boys. (However by his continual</l>
					<l>sitting &amp; faithfulness at his work it is supposed the Disorder he got in his Bowels</l>
					<l>was contracted.) About a Year ago he first begen to complain of a Pain in his Bowels</l>
					<l>which sometimes was so violent th as obliged him to leave of Work &amp; keep to his Room,</l>
					<l>wherein obedience he made use of all Medicines given to him by our Physician, but</l>
					<l>his Desire to be again amongst ye Boys at his Work, was sometimes ye Moti for</l>
					<l>his saying he was well when it was not entirely so. However his Disorder seemingly</l>
					<l>left him, &amp; he began to gather Strength, but secretly his Thoughts were principally</l>
					<l>set upon going home, which he often utter&apos;d to his Labours with longing tears &amp; even</l>
					<l>was so sure of this Point, that he desired his Companions in ye Shop to take notice</l>
					<l>that he would be at home with our Savr &amp; his tabernacle laid in ye burying Ground before</l>
					<l>next Midsummer. This he also told the Boy Wm Ashley when he was waiting for his last</l>
					<l>kiss last last October, that he would be with him before Midsummer.</l>
					<l>In this situation he</l>
					<l>went on, improving in</l>
					<l>the knowledge of himself</l>
					<l>&amp; acquaintance with that</l>
					<l>Heart who confesses himself</l>
					<l>to the poor &amp; needy; Confideng</l>
					<l>tow and clear admist all</l>
					<l>the Sensations of his own</l>
					<l>Poverty &amp; often weeping</l>
					<l>after the Soul of Christ</l>
					<l>whose Comunucation he</l>
					<l>found to be his life.</l>
					<l>He was rec&apos;d into the Congn March yes 23d last, to his great Joy &amp; Abasement,</l>
					<l>for he often said when others were rec&apos;d he was not worthy of such a great Grace; Soon</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>after which he began to sicken with his old Disorder &amp; was obliged to betake</l>
					<l>himself entirely to ye Sickroom. His first Thoughts were: now I shall go home</l>
					<l>notwithstanding which he was obedient to ye Physicians in taking every thing he</l>
					<l>prescribed &amp; soon became such a Compainion to his Sickwaiter as he Scarcely ever</l>
					<l>had before for his Sinerlikeness, gratitude, clearness of heart &amp; constancy in ye</l>
					<l>enjoyment of our Savr. His Patience in his Sickness &amp; Pain was astonishment</l>
					<l>to everybody, which was alleviated by nothing but his heart living in the Torments</l>
					<l>Pain &amp; Anguish of his beloved, whose Nearness &amp; Converse was the Occupation of</l>
					<l>his Soul by Day &amp; Night. If any Br or Boy wanted to refresh himself he know</l>
					<l>not how to do it better than by visitng our dr Jas. Oates, who was always found</l>
					<l>conversing most intimately with our Savr with Clearness &amp; Serenity &amp; oftentimes</l>
					<l>with Tears. In his Sleep this happy converse was not interrupted, but went on in</l>
					<l>the same track as when awake, being often heard speaking with our Savr by those</l>
					<l>who watch&apos;d with him </l>
					<l>saying: my good Savr, my</l>
					<l>dear Savr, my best Savr!</l>
					<l>There was nothing at all of falsehood or obliquity to be</l>
					<l>found in him, but that same downright honest openhearted &amp; genuine Simplicity</l>
					<l>Shun in all his Words &amp; Actions constantly panting for the last kiss.</l>
					<l>May the 9th he was all the Day in an Extali, continually occupied with our</l>
					<l>Savr &amp; his coming so that the Hearts of many Brn who heard him were melted &amp;</l>
					<l>their Eyes overflowd. He often enquird about John Morgan, who lay ready for ye</l>
					<l>departing kiss with him in ye same room &amp; express&apos;d his Concern for him, wishing</l>
					<l>him safe with our Savr. He also mentioned something of the Band he kept with</l>
					<l>Jo. Morgan in the begining of his Sickness &amp; declared of himself how it had been</l>
					<l>with him &amp; how he had spent his time before he came to ye knowledge of our Savr,</l>
					<l>that since that time our Savr slept before his heart he had loved him with all his</l>
					<l>might, but was ashamed his Love was not stronger, Since the friend of his Soul</l>
					<l>had done so much for him &amp; earn&apos;d his Soul &amp; Body a thousand times over.</l>
					<l>Upon being asked whether he would choose to go to our Savr now or wait untill He</l>
					<l>came to visit the Congn, his answer was, I cannot stay, he has charmed my</l>
					<l>Heart, but if it pleased our Savr I would do either; often uttering at Intervalls</l>
					<l>On the first Sight of him persenally! &amp; frequently call&apos;d out Sleepd &amp; waking:</l>
					<l>My Savr come soon!</l>
					<l>While the Congn were enjoying the Lords Course in the Congn Hall about 5</l>
					<l>Mimtes before Jo. Morgan went home (tho&apos; he knew nothing of Morgans Situa-</l>
					<l>tion) he burst out in this prophetic Strain, saying to himself. &quot;Yes, yes, my Savr</l>
					<l>I now see thou will come soon, Yes I know thou wilt, Ay, Ay, thou will, oh yes</l>
					<l>I see it very plain, I see thou art a-coming, Ay, Ay, thou at there a-smiling,</l>
					<l>Thou art coming just now &amp;c.&quot; When he was told our Savr had taken Jo. Morgan</l>
					<l>to himself, he said, I am glad of it &amp; thank him with Joy; now I only wish he</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>would soon come &amp; pay me such another Visit, the sooner the better.</l>
					<l>The 14th The Boys of his Room visited him, he was very lively &amp; told them</l>
					<l>how happy he was &amp; how much he longed to be at home; he wish&apos;d none might</l>
					<l>withold their hearts from our Savr, for his sufferings deserved a thousand times</l>
					<l>more then what they were able to give him, and sayd how happy it would be it</l>
					<l>each of them might obtain the favour which he was a Candidate for. On being</l>
					<l>told that perhaps our Savr had some Views with some of them for which they must</l>
					<l>stay yet longer here below, he replied, &quot;it is very probable, but may they then be</l>
					<l>good Hearts, give him Joy &amp; execute his views, as for me it is my happy Lot to</l>
					<l>go home.&quot; He then made his Observations upon some of ye Boys, &amp; lastly</l>
					<l>they sung several Verses for him, a happy melting feeling attended the whole</l>
					<l>A Brr who had the Watch</l>
					<l>with him observing the Boy</l>
					<l>in a gentle Slumber sat down</l>
					<l>in Stilness &amp; feel into a Doose,</l>
					<l>when imediately he was awake</l>
					<l>again with Dream that our</l>
					<l>Savr came into the Room &amp; </l>
					<l>looking with Surprise</l>
					<l>found the Boy awakd, who</l>
					<l>call&apos;d him &amp; ask&apos;d him, who</l>
					<l>that was that came into the</l>
					<l>Room &amp; awoke him. The Br.</l>
					<l>replied, I saw nobody. Yes, says</l>
					<l>the Boy, there somebody did</l>
					<l>awake me, &amp; I believe it was</l>
					<l>our Savr.</l>
					<l>The 21st when the Meeting was over in which the Congn had been singing&quot;</l>
					<l>O Jerusalem above &amp;c (tho unknown to him) he sent for the Labourer &amp; said</l>
					<l>I only wanted to tell you, I think it cannot be long before our Savr comes &amp;</l>
					<l>takes me with him, I have such a feeling of him as I cannot express, only he</l>
					<l>is very near. This he utter&apos;d with a most tender feeling &amp; Tears on both Sides</l>
					<l>Then a Band was kept. The Conclusion was: I have the best Prospect before</l>
					<l>me, I have not long to continue here, I perceive plainly my Friend draws nearer</l>
					<l>&amp; nearer.</l>
					<l>The 26th He was uncomonly pretty, talk&apos;d charmingly about our Savr</l>
					<l>&amp; his happiness in him. Awaking from Sleep he called out to his Sickwaiter</l>
					<l>&amp; said: Well Charles, now it is all over, now I have no more pain, for I have</l>
					<l>seen our Savr, have been with him, kiss&apos;d his Wounds, &amp; he told me he would</l>
					<l>come again very soon, &amp; take me with him to himself. This he utterd with such</l>
					<l>a Countenance is captivated the Sickwaiter. He then desired his Labourer</l>
					<l>might be call&apos;d, a when he came into the room he lifted up his weak head &amp; said</l>
					<l>with a Smiling pleasant Mien: I have been with our Savr, &amp; there was a most</l>
					<l>Charming Company with him, &amp; bonnily did they sing, ay bonnily, right bonnily,</l>
					<l>&amp; pretty it was, I never heard such bonny singing before. Being ask&apos;d what</l>
					<l>they sung, he answerd with a broken Voice: The Wounds, the Wounds of our</l>
					<l>dear Savr &amp; all abou this Blood &amp; how he suffer&apos;d, &amp;they also sung, that it was</l>
					<l>all done for me, &amp; a great deal more, but I cannot tell it you all; I am sure</l>
					<l>if you had heard it you would say so too, I know he&apos;ll not be long before he comes again</l>
					<l>&amp; that will be a fine coming for me.</l>
					<l>Monday June the 1st in ye morning early Br Abm took his leave of him</l>
					<l>before he set out upon his Journey for Lindsey house. He lay the whole day in a</l>
					<l>happy Sabathu stillness, looking out for his Friend &amp; chearing the Minds &amp; Hearts</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>of everyone who visited him. The 2d In the Forenoon he had another</l>
					<l>happy Band with his Labourer, about that first Moment when he should</l>
					<l>embrace the wounded feet of his Savr &amp; said, I can hold it out no longer,</l>
					<l>to day my Joy will be compleated. In the Afternoon it appeared evident</l>
					<l>that his beloved Bridegroom drew near his heart with Smiles of Grace,</l>
					<l>but his Speech failing him it was difficult to understand what he</l>
					<l>utterd. After the Choir Evening blessing the Labourer went up to the</l>
					<l>Sickroom, found him in a manner absent to all about him, uttering</l>
					<l>something to himself. My dear Savr, my precious Savr, my good Savr</l>
					<l>&amp; as soon as that Verse was sung for him. Now he does get Permission</l>
					<l>to leave this mortal Tent &amp; he lift up his Eyes with such a charming</l>
					<l>Glance as captivated the minds of all about him, seemingly intimation</l>
					<l>he look&apos;d for his last Blessing, whereupon it was imparted to him</l>
					<l>during the Singing of that Verse: O thou holy tormented Corpse,</l>
					<l>do as Elisha did, he is the Child with a penetrating feeling of the</l>
					<l>precious Nearness of the Friend of his Soul, in whose Arms &amp; Bosom</l>
					<l>he fell softly &amp; happily asleep without any other Signs then of a</l>
					<l>Person doasing into the most agreeable Slumber with the</l>
					<l>Blessing of his Choir in the 16th Year of his Age.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
