<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Rainer_Elizabeth_Ful_3_151</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi>. Sr. Elisab. Rainer of Dudleyhill</l>
					<l> departed Dec. 20. 1838, aged 76 years</l>
					<l>Her parents being members of our Church</l>
					<l>she was from early childhood accustomed to at</l>
					<l>tend the public and private meetings in our Chapel.</l>
					<l>What she there heard of the love of our Saviour</l>
					<l>soon made a good impression on her heart, and</l>
					<l>this was strengthened by the instructions she re</l>
					<l>ceived at the Dayschool, and the Scriptural texts</l>
					<l>and the hymns she committed to memory.</l>
					<l>The work of Grace, begun in childhood, progres</l>
					<l>sed as she advanced in years. She was received into</l>
					<l>the cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> and admitted to the H.C. and for a time</l>
					<l>walk worthily of her heavenly calling, prizing</l>
					<l>her connexion with our Church and faithfully</l>
					<l>improving her privileges as a member of the same.</l>
					<l>From her frequent declarations it is evident, that </l>
					<l>she enjoyed much of that spiritual happiness,</l>
					<l>which those only can rightly understand, who by</l>
					<l>watchfulness and prayer keep themselves</l>
					<l>from the world seek for and obtain grace to escape</l>
					<l>the corruption there is in the world thro&apos; sin,</l>
					<l>living the life of faith in the Son of God.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>After her marriage her connexion with the</l>
					<l>cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> was for number of years entirely broken off.</l>
					<l>In proportion as their temporal affairs prosperd</l>
					<l>her desire after spiritual blessings declined, and</l>
					<l>the love of the world gained the accentancy in her</l>
					<l>heart. In mercy to her soul the Lord caused the</l>
					<l>source of her enjoyments to be dried up. Compara</l>
					<l>tive affluence was succeeded by abject poverty</l>
					<l>to which was added much bodily suffering. In this</l>
					<l>These distressing circumstances, like the poverty of</l>
					<l>the Prodidal Son, brought her to herself. She keenly</l>
					<l>felt the loss she had sustained by straying from the</l>
					<l>Good Shepherd and his fold. When speaking of this </l>
					<l>period, she was wont to describe the state of her mind</l>
					<l>in language like the following:</l>
					<l>&quot;When recollecting the many spiritual enjoyments</l>
					<l>of which I had partaken while within the fold of the</l>
					<l>Good shepherd, my heart was ready to break and my</l>
					<l>soul refused to be comforted. Indeed I should have</l>
					<l>sunk into absolute dispondency had it not been that </l>
					<l>the love of the Saviour to sinners, of which I had heard</l>
					<l>so much in early life, and of which He had given me many a</l>
					<l>sweet taste, still had a place in my memory and a hold</l>
					<l>tho&apos; every light one, of on my affection. My bodily suffer</l>
					<l>rings and poverty I disregarded, and could even thank</l>
					<l>the Lord for them as proofs of his love to my soul,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>being convinced that it required severe means to</l>
					<l>subdue the pride and hardness of my heart, and make me</l>
					<l>willing to lie as a poor peaitent at the foot of his cross.</l>
					<l>He did not disappoint my hope; but spoke peace to my</l>
					<l>troubled conscience.&quot;</l>
					<l>At her earnest request she was in 1832 readmitted</l>
					<l>to her former privileges in the cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>. She was then already</l>
					<l>in that state of bodily decrepitude, owing to severe rheu</l>
					<l>matic afflictions in her limbs, that she could hardly move</l>
					<l>from her chair. Her readmision therefore took place</l>
					<l>in her own dwelling. Being assured of the readiness of</l>
					<l>the cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> to receive her, and of their sincere sympathy</l>
					<l>in her distressing circumstances; she broke out gave</l>
					<l>full vent to her feelings of gratitude for the favor con</l>
					<l>ferred on her; and, while tears of penitence and joy</l>
					<l>rolled down her cheeks, made an humble confession</l>
					<l>of her deviations, and of the inward joy she felt at the</l>
					<l>mercy shown to her by our Saviour. Those who were</l>
					<l>present on this occasion will not easily forget the</l>
					<l>solemn scene. The presence and peace of our Saviour,</l>
					<l>while commerating his death in his own ordinance, were</l>
					<l>felt in so sensible a manner, that her hesuible dwelling,</l>
					<l>one of the worst was indeed a Bethal, and the gate</l>
					<l>to heaven, something of the delights of heaven, when there</l>
					<l>injoy in the presence of God over one sinner that repents tho</l>
					<l>gladdened the spirits of the little company. All</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>During the remaining six years of her life her</l>
					<l>bodily sufferings increased more and more, till at last</l>
					<l>she was totally unable to help herself. In the midst of all</l>
					<l>her pains and extreme poverty, she could rejoice in God,</l>
					<l>her Saviour, looking forward in faith, and hope to the</l>
					<l>termination of all earthly misery. You generally</l>
					<l>found her sitting in the corner, with her Bible and </l>
					<l>Hymn book lying open on the table, and not unfre</l>
					<l>quently on approaching her cottage was she heard</l>
					<l>singing there her favorite Hymns, Nothing afforded her greater</l>
					<l>pleasure than holding converse with those who</l>
					<l>loved the Lord, and could enter into her feelings.</l>
					<l>The occasional administration of the Lords</l>
					<l>supper to her were reasons of refreshing from</l>
					<l>the presence of the Lord, and could not fail to impress</l>
					<l>those present with the conviction, that the Good</l>
					<l>Shepherd was carrying his once straying sheep</l>
					<l>in his arms.</l>
					<l>In The evening before her departure observing </l>
					<l>a great change in her, her husband said, he thought</l>
					<l>she was dying, and asked her, if she knew it, and </l>
					<l>whither she was going. She replied, &quot;My Saviour</l>
					<l>is with me, and I am going to Him.&quot;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
