<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Robinson_Sarah_Ful_SS_78</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1380.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The life of the S. Sister Sarah Robinson as wrote by</l>
					<l>herself.</l>
					<l>I was born in Hallifax March 8th 1712</l>
					<l>My parents brought me up very carefully &amp; inxthueted me in</l>
					<l>my principles of the Church of England. I can remember draw</l>
					<l>ings from our Savior from my very Infancy, </l>
					<l>but being of a fret</l>
					<l>I was</l>
					<l>uneasy </l>
					<l>ful &amp; anxious temper oftentimes I shou&apos;d</l>
					<l>offend God. In the night time in my sleep, I often</l>
					<l>dreamt of the dissolution of the World &amp; day of Judgment:</l>
					<l>which made me very uneasy to think how it wou&apos;d be with me</l>
					<l>at that time. My Father died when I was about ten years of</l>
					<l>age, &amp; my Mother being left a widow. she moved with me &amp; two</l>
					<l>younger sisters out of Hallifax to a place called Ovenden my</l>
					<l>Mother being a person deply concern&apos;d for her Salvation,</l>
					<l>she</l>
					<l>many times wept &amp; prayed day &amp; night that both her  &amp; her</l>
					<l>children might please the Lord, which made a great impress</l>
					<l>ion on me. I went frequently with her to Church, and was</l>
					<l>very attentive to what the Minister spoke, &amp; took a pleasure</l>
					<l>in so doing. but this did not satisfy me: it came often into</l>
					<l>it would </l>
					<l>my mind how will it be with me when I die-- &amp; being excee</l>
					<l>dingly frighten&apos;d with Thunder &amp; Lightning I wish&apos;d it might</l>
					<l>always happen on a Sunday when I was at Church, for then</l>
					<l>I thought, if the day of Judgment shou&apos;d come, the Lord wou&apos;d</l>
					<l>have mercy upon me because I wwas in such a holy place</l>
					<l>as I then look&apos;d upon the Church to be. When I was grown</l>
					<l>up I had an inclination to go to service and accordingly</l>
					<l>went to several, but still retain&apos;d my religious turn of mind, </l>
					<l>In my 21st year one of my near relations who was then in York.</l>
					<l>sent for me to go &amp; live with her, as she had always a great</l>
					<l>love for me, I was glad of this, tho my Mother did not like</l>
					<l>to part with me as she was then left alone, this relation kept a</l>
					<l>wines Tavern &amp; I was to be her chamber maid: but being quite a stran</l>
					<l>trouble</l>
					<l>ger to the hurry &amp;  </l>
					<l>of such a city, &amp; seeing &amp; heareing all kind</l>
					<l>of vanitys, of which I was before in great measure ignorant it frigh</l>
					<l>tned me very much seeing myself expos&apos;d to many dangers, I spoke</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1381.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I spoke seriously to my Mistriss with many tears about &amp; beg&apos;d</l>
					<l>her to keep a watchful eye over me, as I was quite unacquted</l>
					<l>with the manner of the place, She spoke tenderly to me pro</l>
					<l>mis&apos;d to care for me, as much as lay in her power; so I </l>
					<l>more chearful in my place, &amp; went on in my usial way, reading</l>
					<l>and praying to the Lord to keep &amp; preserve me and I believe</l>
					<l>he heard my prayers. When my year was out my Mother</l>
					<l>wrote me a tender letter, desiring me to come home to her again,</l>
					<l>I cou&apos;d have had several good places, but cou&apos;d not bear to stay</l>
					<l>against her mind. I went home but still wanted a fine place,</l>
					<l>in order to prefer myself, &amp; it just happen&apos;d that a Gentleman</l>
					<l>come from Wales to Hallifax, who was to take possession of an</l>
					<l>Estate. called Kirkles &amp; they wanting a servant, my Mother</l>
					<l>got me the place: accordingly I went to live with them &amp; my</l>
					<l>Master &amp; Mistress lov&apos;d me very much. about this time I began</l>
					<l>to be thoughtful about going to the Sacrament &amp; toald my mother</l>
					<l>therof she desired me to advise with a friend of hers. who was</l>
					<l>a religious person; accordingly I went &amp; told him my whole</l>
					<l>heart with many tears. He spoke with me about the threatning</l>
					<l>of God to those that do not fear him, &amp; his promises to them</l>
					<l>that love Him. He told me what a good thing it was to have</l>
					<l>a promise to rely upon on ones death bed. but I not finding </l>
					<l>any promise in my heart, &amp; not being  willing to be without,</l>
					<l>I wrote myself some in order to have them by me, when I came</l>
					<l>to my death bed; such as this! Come unto me all ye that are</l>
					<l>weary &amp;c. &amp; many others out of the psalms and other good books,</l>
					<l>for I was seldom without me in my pocket. I remember</l>
					<l>once going to clean my Mistress&apos;s room &amp; there opening my lit</l>
					<l>tle book, I found this passage which said, that God did not re</l>
					<l>quire so much of a poor Servant as of a rich Master, which </l>
					<l>rejoyc&apos;d me very much to think that God was so good to poor</l>
					<l>Servants but then a fear came in my mind because we were</l>
					<l>only two Servants &amp; cou&apos;d therefore only go to Church in the after</l>
					<l>noon I was affraid my Mrs wou&apos;d take it amiss if I shou&apos;d ask</l>
					<l>her to let me go in the Morning I told my Mother of it she</l>
					<l>beg&apos;d me not to be affraid, but speak with my Mrs, which I did </l>
					<l>and she was much pleas&apos;d to find, that I was so well inclin&apos;d &amp;</l>
					<l>fetch&apos;d me her own preparation book to read, which I perus&apos;d</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1382.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I perus&apos;d dilligently the whole week, the prayers being much</l>
					<l>longer then my own. On Sunday Morning she told me at </l>
					<l>my Mother liv&apos;d near the Church, &amp; I intended going to the </l>
					<l>Sacrament, she wou&apos;d give me leave to go &amp; stay there all</l>
					<l>the day. this happen&apos;d on Palm Sunday. The Minister spoke</l>
					<l>much about the Sacrament, &amp; said it was better to go poor &amp; </l>
					<l>unworthy, than not go at all, which comforted me a little. </l>
					<l>but still I found myself asham&apos;d on account of my unfitness;</l>
					<l>Our Savior was near to me. tho I knew him not, for when </l>
					<l>I had receiv&apos;d the Sacrament, it was as if a load was taken of</l>
					<l>my heart, &amp; I con&apos;d beg Him with tears to keep me that</l>
					<l>nothing might happen, which cou&apos;d prove a dishonour to </l>
					<l>His name. Soon after this, I remov&apos;d with the family to Hir</l>
					<l>kles Hall, where my Lady put me with another serious &amp;</l>
					<l>well meaning person into the Nursery &amp; we together had pres</l>
					<l>sure in our religious devotion. We had prayers twice a day</l>
					<l>in the family, which I always attended and also went frequ</l>
					<l>ently to church &amp; to the holy Sacrament. When Mr Ingham</l>
					<l>come about preaching in this Country, as soon as my Mrs</l>
					<l>heard of it, she sent an invitation to him to come &amp; preach </l>
					<l>in Harchet Church, accordingly he came &amp; stay&apos;d in the </l>
					<l>family some days, we had private meetings Night and</l>
					<l>Morning for all that pleas&apos;d to come as long as he stay&apos;d,</l>
					<l>as soon as I heard him, I look&apos;d upon him as an Angel</l>
					<l>of God, &amp; made opportunity when I cou&apos;d to speak with him</l>
					<l>alone tho&apos; always fearing my fellow servants wou&apos;d find it out</l>
					<l>and I shou&apos;d be treated with scorn by them, which also was</l>
					<l>the case, notwithstanding this I persuaded two of those I </l>
					<l>was most intimate with to go with me to hear him once</l>
					<l>More which they did, He exhorted us to love one another</l>
					<l>and not forget to read the holy scriptures &amp; so we parted.</l>
					<l>My Mistress by some circumstances that had happen&apos;d was</l>
					<l>prejudice against Mr. Ingham, &amp; forbidme ever going to </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1383.jpg' n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>hear him again, threatening at the same time, if even I did,</l>
					<l>I shou&apos;d lose my place, this affected me not a ittle. for</l>
					<l>my Eternal Salvation lay very near me at that time. I thought</l>
					<l>by Mr. Inghams doctrine I might perhaps be led into the</l>
					<l>night way to obtain it. I wrote for advice in this case to</l>
					<l>a religious Society with whom my Mother was join&apos;d, in</l>
					<l>answer they advis&apos;d me not to leave my place on this account</l>
					<l>they believ&apos;d he was a good man but a Stranger &amp; no me</l>
					<l>knew how things might turn out., I complied herein</l>
					<l>and stay&apos;d in the family 5 or 6 years longer, but any little</l>
					<l>misfortune that happen&apos;d to the child, I nurs&apos;d put me up</l>
					<l>on thoughts that the Lord was displeas&apos;d with my being</l>
					<l>here, &amp; so concluded to leave my place &amp; go home to my</l>
					<l>Mother, where I con&apos;d serve the Lord (as I thought) more </l>
					<l>dilligently. But when I got home I had not enough of the </l>
					<l>world, but thought I shou&apos;d like to get into place again</l>
					<l>which I did &amp; stay&apos;d there about two years. My Mother</l>
					<l>being old &amp; infirm I resolv&apos;d to go &amp; live with her again. Whi</l>
					<l>I also did. Still retaining the greatest respect for mr</l>
					<l>Ingham as formerly. I soon inquired if he ever came to </l>
					<l>preach in Hallifax. My Mother told me there were </l>
					<l>some people come to preach at a place call&apos;d Worlds End.</l>
					<l>not far from the place I liv&apos;d. that they preach&apos;d good does?</l>
					<l>time, &amp; she shou&apos;d like me to go &amp; hear them, I had not</l>
					<l>much likeing to it. as the meetings were kept in a pri</l>
					<l>vate house: however as my Mother desired it I went the </l>
					<l>week following. When I got there Br Hutchings who kept </l>
					<l>the meeting had begun to sing which I lik&apos;d very well</l>
					<l>the text was, Behold this is the day of Salvation. now</l>
					<l>the Lord was pleas&apos;d to work upon my heart. so that I cou&apos;d</l>
					<l>heartily desire him to let me know my day of Salvation</l>
					<l>to grant me</l>
					<l>but </l>
					<l>Saying. Lord! deny me of what thou wilst only deny me</l>
					<l>not this one thing, that I may know I have an interest</l>
					<l>in a bleeding Savior, the Lord who is ever good was pleas&apos;d</l>
					<l>to show me the vileness of my heart: and also </l>
					<l>gave me comfort </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1384.jpg' n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>comfort in these words. But we beleive through the grace of</l>
					<l>our Lord Jesus Christ, we shall be saved even as they.</l>
					<l>the weeks following I went again to hear Br Hutchings preach</l>
					<l>the treat was. Without shedding of Blood is no remission.</l>
					<l>The lord was pleas&apos;d at this time to reveal himself to me:</l>
					<l>so that it was the sweetest sermon that ever I had heard in </l>
					<l>my life, for I was able to shed tears of joy &amp; love to my bless&apos;d</l>
					<l>Savior, who had Suffer&apos;d &amp; dy&apos;d for me so vile a sinner.</l>
					<l>My Mother being a member of a religious society I went</l>
					<l>with her to the meetings, &amp; they having a great love for</l>
					<l>me, did not like me to give heed to any new preaching</l>
					<l>but wanted me to continue with them, which I cou&apos;d not</l>
					<l>agree to, thinking one shou&apos;d be at liberty to go where one</l>
					<l>was most benifited: Mr Grimshaw being minister of</l>
					<l>that Society. He sent them writings to read together. Which</l>
					<l>I lik&apos;d very much. &amp; went several times to con</l>
					<l>verse with him in their company &amp; also partook of the</l>
					<l>sacrament with them. Which was a great blessing to</l>
					<l>me, but he always advis&apos;d me. not to fail going to hear</l>
					<l>the Brn as I had receiv&apos;d such blessing by their Tes</l>
					<l>timony. I spoke with Br Horne. &amp; after some time had</l>
					<l>the favor to be a member of the Brns society of which I </l>
					<l>was very glad. for I really beleiv&apos;d them to be the people</l>
					<l>that I was called to &amp; it was a particular pleasure to</l>
					<l>me to see any of the Brn &amp; Srs when they came to Hallifax.</l>
					<l>particularly Br Horn for I lov&apos;d him much tho he dealt</l>
					<l>very closely with me about selfrightious &amp; unsinnerlike</l>
					<l>ness of which I was not sensible. </l>
					<l>I dreamt one night</l>
					<l>that I was speaking with Mr Grimshaw &amp; all on a sud</l>
					<l>den. I saw our dear savior coming in the clouds. &amp; the</l>
					<l>brightness of his wounds fill&apos;d the whole element. and I</l>
					<l>ran to fetch my Mother. but awakening out of my sleep.</l>
					<l>was troubled to find it only a dream. for I thought I cou&apos;d</l>
					<l>live no longer, but must go to our Savior. Sometime</l>
					<l>after it pleas&apos;d our Savior to take my dear Mother</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1385.jpg' n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Mother happily home, which was a great trial to me.</l>
					<l>for we had liv&apos;d very agreeably together. </l>
					<l>I wrote to Sr Clagget desiring to think of me. for tho I had</l>
					<l>many offers from friends &amp; relations, yet I cou&apos;d not think</l>
					<l>of settling in the world having no liberty in my heart but</l>
					<l>wanted to live amongst the Sisters. Soon after I had leave</l>
					<l>where</l>
					<l>to come &amp; live at Oxhays were I was tenderly cared for</l>
					<l>by the Sisters.  tho it was somtime before I knew how it</l>
					<l>wou&apos;d go with me finding it very difficult to leave my</l>
					<l>relations and the pleasing things of the world as they</l>
					<l>then appear&apos;d to me; but the Brn &amp; Srs had patience</l>
					<l>with me, &amp; our Savior who is ever faithful, often made it clear</l>
					<l>to me that if I did not abide with his people, I shou&apos;d be</l>
					<l>a miserable creature, this was indeed a school for my heart.</l>
					<l>for not having learn&apos;d to depend on our savior in all circum</l>
					<l>stances, I came into many byways, which affected me so that</l>
					<l>it impair&apos;d my health for some time. I did not tell it my Labou</l>
					<l>ress, fearing lest I shou&apos;d be sent away. &amp; that I cou&apos;d not</l>
					<l>bear, as I lov&apos;d the Choir House as my life.</l>
					<l>In the year 1756 I was seiz&apos;d with a nervous fever &amp; was</l>
					<l>brought so weak thereby, that I expected &amp; look&apos;d for nothing</l>
					<l>else but my dissolution. This sickness prov&apos;d the means</l>
					<l>of our Savior Showing me quite clearly, where I was still</l>
					<l>wanting. &amp; the emtiness of things, that had hither to been</l>
					<l>an anoyance to me in my course. &amp; by the close connections</l>
					<l>I enjoy&apos;d with him at that time. my former heaviness was </l>
					<l>removed. I saw &amp; understood many things betwixt my Savior</l>
					<l>and my own heart, in quite a different light. </l>
					<l>About this time our late Sister writes in a letter to a friend</l>
					<l>the following. I can now say with Jacob I am not worthy</l>
					<l>of the least of thy mercies As the prodigal. I am not worthy</l>
					<l>and</l>
					<l>to be called thy son. as the Publican Lord be merciful to </l>
					<l>and </l>
					<l>me a sinner. as Paul, of Sinners I am chief. and now</l>
					<l>I humbly beg that the Lord will assist me by this spirit;</l>
					<l>that I may also say It is my meat &amp; my drink </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1386.jpg' n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>drink to do thy will O Lord. I hope my dear friend will excus</l>
					<l>me writing more largely on the love of our ever blessed</l>
					<l>Jesus &amp; of the power of his free grace in my poor heart. I</l>
					<l>cou&apos;d like to say much more on the subject, but am a very </l>
					<l>poor writer, I bless God I am what I am. &amp; may He gran</l>
					<l>me ever with Mary to chuse that one thing needful whi</l>
					<l>will help me to say with St Paul I can do all things through</l>
					<l>Christ who strengtheneth me.</l>
					<l>After 4 months Illness I was so far recoverd as to be able</l>
					<l>to be again with my room Sisters, tho I was still so weak in </l>
					<l>Body that for a long time I thought my time in this </l>
					<l>World wou&apos;d be short &amp; heartily rejoice&apos;d at the thoughts</l>
					<l>thereoff. After some time seeing my expectation &amp; desire</l>
					<l>not granted. one Morning feeling myself very weak and </l>
					<l>impatient for the time to come when I might lay down this</l>
					<l>tabernacle, I was speaking to our Savior about it, &amp; it was to me</l>
					<l>as if he stood by me, &amp; ask&apos;d me? Why I was so impatient, direc</l>
					<l>tly that Verse come into my Mind. which gave me comfort,</l>
					<l>altho the time seems long to me: Even here I&apos;m in eternity</l>
					<l>Because I live in jesus: the impression of this I shall ne</l>
					<l>verforget. I grew more satidfy&apos;d. &amp; only wish&apos;d that whether my</l>
					<l>time shou&apos;d be long or short that I might daily live in the </l>
					<l>enjoyment of our Saviors blessings, that thereby I might be</l>
					<l>enabled to bear evry difficulty I might meet with in my</l>
					<l>future course. &amp; to conclude I can say this with shame</l>
					<l>that amidst my many faults &amp; deficiences, our Savior has</l>
					<l>graciously help&apos;d me thro&apos; &amp; many times when I have</l>
					<l>been at a loss which way to turn my heart has been dire</l>
					<l>cted to Him, where I have always found a sufficiency for</l>
					<l>all I wanted. Thus for our late Sisters own account,</l>
					<l>We can give her the testimony that amidst all </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1387.jpg' n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>faults &amp; defects her walk and conversation amongst us</l>
					<l>was such as become a child of God. for these many years</l>
					<l>past she has ardently long&apos;d to depart this life &amp; to be</l>
					<l>at home with her souls redeemer, which came to pass</l>
					<l>when sudden &amp; unexpected on Saturday Jany 23rd </l>
					<l>she remov&apos;d into the sick room and said now I think my </l>
					<l>dear Savior will soon come &amp; take me home to himself.</l>
					<l>on the 24th it was very evident that her dissolution was</l>
					<l>approaching. it was indeed very pleasing to be with her.</l>
					<l>as the prospect she had in view of soon entering into his </l>
					<l>presence where there is fulness of joy caused almost</l>
					<l>evry breath she drew to be an anthem of praise and</l>
					<l>thanksgiving to her crucified savior. Till her latest</l>
					<l>breath she repeated these words my dear Savior come</l>
					<l>soon, come soon. early on Monday the 25th she was</l>
					<l>bless&apos;d to her departure and soon after fell gently and</l>
					<l>th</l>
					<l>happily assleep in the Lord in the 84 year of her age </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
