<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Skelton_John_Ful_3_74</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4286.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The Life of the Widow John Skelton</l>
					<l>who departed at Fulneck June 30th 1773</l>
					<l>He has left us the following in Writing; I was born in</l>
					<l>the Year 1703 in Lightlif in the Parish of Hallifax,</l>
					<l>my Father &amp; Mother belonged to the Church of England. My</l>
					<l>Father died, when I was but a very little Boy, my Mother</l>
					<l>brought me as till I was 8 Years old as carefully as she</l>
					<l>could, afterwards I was put Prentice to a Norwich</l>
					<l>Carrier, where I learned to be very wicked, but yet I had oft</l>
					<l>Convictions, that I lived in quite a wrong Way, yet that</l>
					<l>left me again. In my 25th year I married. When Mr Ingham</l>
					<l>began to preach about in the Country Yorkshire, it came in</l>
					<l>my Mind to go to hear him; but the first Time I got received</l>
					<l>no Blessing from it. The next Night he was to preach at</l>
					<l>Smithhouse, when but I had no thought of going till towards</l>
					<l>Night, when I had a long Struggle whether I should go or not,</l>
					<l>but at last I resolved to go, whatever might come out of it,</l>
					<l>and that Night our Savr got fast Hold of my Heart, so that</l>
					<l>I could after that have gone with Mr Ingham thro&apos; the </l>
					<l>World; but yet I was at a Loss what would become of me</l>
					<l>for I was in such a ruin&apos;d State, &amp; never acquainted Mr</l>
					<l>Ingham that I was so miserable. I went constantly to the </l>
					<l>Preaching, &amp; strove to be as stood as ever I could, in order to find Peace for my Heart, but all in </l>
					<l>vain, till about a Year after, when I got some Comfort;</l>
					<l>yet for all that I thought I was not sure of being happy. I </l>
					<l>went to Speak with Mr Ingham about going to the Sacrament</l>
					<l>in the Church of Engld, then he inquired how it was with me</l>
					<l>&amp; I told him my whole Mind, but he told me, it was not his Way</l>
					<l>to advice People to go to the Sacrament, left it however to me</l>
					<l>to do as I felt it in my Heatr so I went &amp; received a </l>
					<l>Blessing thereby. When the Society was first begun 1741 I was</l>
					<l>received into it. Then the Brn came to Smithhouse &amp; I</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4288.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>went to hear them constantly, &amp; one Night when the Meeting</l>
					<l>was over Br Horne took me into his Room &amp; ask&apos;d me how it</l>
					<l>was with me &amp; I told him my whole Mind, &amp; he spoke very</l>
					<l>friendly with me, &amp; told me, that I might go to all the Meetings</l>
					<l>whence I had an Opportunity, of which I was very glad</l>
					<l>One lvening I went to a meeting at Smith house, &amp; going as</l>
					<l>I was going home quite by myself, I felt something speaking</l>
					<l>to me at my Heart. Thy sins are forgiven thee &amp; ever since</l>
					<l>I have been very happy. March 29 1746 my Wife went home, &amp;</l>
					<l>left me with 7 Childn, 5 Sons &amp; 2 Daughters, &amp; 1 Daughter was</l>
					<l>gone before her. I had a Desire to be rec&apos;d into the Congn</l>
					<l>&amp; Novr 13 1750 I was received, which was a great Blessing to</l>
					<l>my Heart. June 21st 1751 I recd the Sacrament with the Brn the </l>
					<l>first Time, which was such a Blessing to me, as I cannot</l>
					<l>express with Words. So I have lived in the Nearness of our</l>
					<l>Savr ever since.</l>
					<l>Thus far his own Words.</l>
					<l>Nov 27 1758 he moved to Fulneck, where he spent his Time</l>
					<l>in a Simple, childlike Manner, enjoying the Love &amp; Peace of</l>
					<l>God &amp; was beloved by his Brn. He esteemed his Lot highly, to have</l>
					<l>the Favour to live with a People of God taking simply every</l>
					<l>Thing that occurred from the Hand of his dr Lord with to with whom</l>
					<l>he Heart had a true Connexion. It was his great Concern</l>
					<l>&amp; his constant Prayer to our Lord, that his Children might all</l>
					<l>obtain the same Grace &amp; that those, who were connected with </l>
					<l>the Congn might truly make a good use of &amp; prosper before our </l>
					<l>Lord; And this his Desire our Savr granted him in so far that</l>
					<l>he saw the greatest Number of them connected with the Congn</l>
					<l>for which he was very thankful &amp; praised his Lord. Some</l>
					<l>months ago his Strength began to fail, &amp; he thought immediate-</l>
					<l>ly that his stay here would no more be long. Our Savr began</l>
					<l>to take him into his School &amp; to shew him, wherein he was </l>
					<l>particularly still deficient. For some time ago something against</l>
					<l>one of his Brn, with whom he lived, had crept into his Mind</l>
					<l>he said: Tho&apos; he had</l>
					<l>spent many years in the</l>
					<l>Congn &amp; lived in the Enjoy</l>
					<l>ment of the Love of God,</l>
					<l>yet he found it a trying</l>
					<l>Time for him &amp; a School </l>
					<l>for his Heart</l>
					<l>it cost him something to see it in the true Light; but our Savr melted his Heart &amp; gave</l>
					<l>him Grace to embrace the Br with many Tears of Love to the no small joy of those present.</l>
					<l>From that Time the Peace of his Heart &amp;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4289.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>&amp; beloved our Savr &amp; in his Heart pointed at it &amp; wanting</l>
					<l>him to acknowledge it &amp; give it up, yet selfrighteousness</l>
					<l>had so much Power, that he thought he could never forgive it.</l>
					<l>His Labourer had a lovely Bond with him upon that head, which</l>
					<l>made him so uneasy, that he could not sleep the whole Night</l>
					<l>when some of his sons saw him the next day, a strange Work</l>
					<l>was perceived in his Mind &amp; they were truly frighten&apos;d at the </l>
					<l>Expressions he uttered upon that Occasion, &amp; could not help shed</l>
					<l>ding Tears. But it was amazing to see, how our Savr chang&apos;d</l>
					<l>his mind in an instant he called immediately for the Brother</l>
					<l>fell about his Neck kiss&apos;d him with many Tears, with all his &amp; a disagreeableness</l>
					<l>pressed him to his Heart, which caused such in Emotion in</l>
					<l>the Beholders, that they wept for joy, as hardly being able to</l>
					<l>believe what they saw with their Eyes. From that time such an</l>
					<l>Alteration was observed in him, as if he had never not been the </l>
					<l>same Man. He loved the above Br with an unfeign&apos;d Love &amp; could</l>
					<l>not bear, that any spoke a hard Word to him. His Peace of Heart</l>
					<l>&amp; his joy in the Lord was visible in his Countenance. He spoke</l>
					<l>solidly with some of his Children, partly uttering telling them</l>
					<l>where they were in the wrong &amp; partly fearing, how it would go </l>
					<l>with one of them after his Departure. Once at being asked</l>
					<l>by his Labourer how he did, he said: I have nothing to do but to re</l>
					<l>joice in our Savr &amp; to enjoy Him. He is very near to my Heart</l>
					<l>whereby the Tears ran down. One Night our Savr manifested</l>
					<l>his Love to his Heart in such a rich treasure, that he firmly</l>
					<l>believed he should now be called home, &amp; therefore caused his</l>
					<l>Labourer to be called to when be could not express sufficiently</l>
					<l>what our Savr had given him to enjoy But his Hour was not</l>
					<l>so near as he expected. His sickness &amp; was very painful pain increased, which</l>
					<l>he bore with Patience &amp; had still a great Deal to suffer, which made</l>
					<l>him oft call upon the Lord soon to come &amp; take him to himself.</l>
					<l>His Heart remain&apos;d during all that Time cleaving to our Savr</l>
					<l>&amp; he said the Peace of God never forsook him. Those Brn that</l>
					<l>visited him felt exceeding well in his Company. At last on</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4290.jpg' n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>the above one 30th of June at 8 at Night come the wel</l>
					<l>come Hour, when he enter&apos;d into his eternal Rest having</l>
					<l>before obtain&apos;d the Blessing of the Congn &amp; his Choir; having He</l>
					<l>spent in this Vale of Tears 70 Years.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
