<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">Tattersall_Mary_Ful_SS_64</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><facsimile xml:id="facs_1"><surface lrx="1514" lry="1790" ulx="0" uly="0"><graphic height="1790px" url="IMG_1292.jpg" width="1514px"/></surface></facsimile><facsimile xml:id="facs_2"><surface lrx="1549" lry="1922" ulx="0" uly="0"><graphic height="1922px" url="IMG_1293.jpg" width="1549px"/></surface></facsimile><facsimile xml:id="facs_3"><surface lrx="1471" lry="1896" ulx="0" uly="0"><graphic height="1896px" url="IMG_1294.jpg" width="1471px"/></surface></facsimile><facsimile xml:id="facs_4"><surface lrx="1477" lry="1862" ulx="0" uly="0"><graphic height="1862px" url="IMG_1295.jpg" width="1477px"/></surface></facsimile><facsimile xml:id="facs_5"><surface lrx="1433" lry="1783" ulx="0" uly="0"><graphic height="1783px" url="IMG_1296.jpg" width="1433px"/></surface></facsimile><facsimile xml:id="facs_6"><surface lrx="1608" lry="1861" ulx="0" uly="0"><graphic height="1861px" url="IMG_1297.jpg" width="1608px"/></surface></facsimile><text><body><pb facs="#facs_1" n="1"/>
	<p>
            <lb/> The life of the our late S. Sister Mary Tattersall
            <lb/>as wrote by herself.
            <lb/>I was born at Kingcross near Hallifax May
            <lb/>the 29th 1756 and babtized in the Church of England.
            <lb/>In my when very young I remember with
            <lb/>gratitude to my dear Savior to have had a
            <lb/>very tender impression of his dying love in
            <lb/>my heart, &amp; the childrens meetings kept at
            <lb/>that time by the Brethren at Stanery near
            <lb/>Hallifax were of great blessing to me.
            <lb/>In my 7th year it pleas'd our Savior to take
            <lb/>home to himself my dear Mother, whose loss
            <lb/>I had much reason to regret on many accounts,
            <lb/>as she made it her chief study to watch over
            <lb/>me for my welfare, both as to Soul and Body.
            <lb/>In about a year after my Father married again,
            <lb/>by the consent of the Brethren which proved
            <lb/>a great change for me, being much more expos<hi rend="superscript:true;">d</hi>
            <lb/>to many things, that I had hitherto been kept
            <lb/>from. tho' at first, I did not feel that my heart,
            <lb/>| which then I did not know | was drawn aside
            <lb/>from that real simplicity I had enjoy'd in
            <lb/>my connexion with my dear dear savior, yet very soon by means of some particular 
            <lb/>circumstances I gradually began to enter
            <lb/>into things that suited my depraved heart nature</p>
	<pb facs="#facs_2" n="2"/>
	<p>
            <lb/>and I consequently lost for a time my first
            <lb/>impression. I cannot pass over a period of my
            <lb/>life without taking notice of our Saviors faithful
            <lb/>ness towards me his poor child, from my ear-
            <lb/>liest Infancy, &amp; with what unwearied patience
            <lb/>he has sought to keep me his poor wandering sheep
            <lb/>to keep with his fold. In my 12th year having
            <lb/>had repeated admonitions from my Father not
            <lb/>to play with those children that he knew wou'd 
            <lb/>be of not benefit to me | as he was very much
            <lb/>concern'd that I shou'd prosper for the Lord |
            <lb/>but my obstanate heart rejected all his
            <lb/>advice. &amp; I was at that time determined
            <lb/>to pursue my own way till at length our
            <lb/>Savior by means of a dream brought me to a 
            <lb/>recollection, &amp; on reflecting very solidly on
            <lb/>the course I was then pursuing caused
            <lb/>me to turn to him in pray'r promising
            <lb/>him that I wou'd be his intire property.
            <lb/>Some weeks after, when sitting alone in a room
            <lb/>at my work, our Savior particulary manifested
            <lb/>himself to me as on the Cross as bleeding &amp;
            <lb/>dying for my sins which caused me to shed
            <lb/>many tears at his thro' pierced feet. this I
            <lb/>cou'd not at that time comprehend, but how</p>
	<pb facs="#facs_3" n="3"/>
	<p>
            <lb/>how often have I wish'd since that time to
            <lb/>have had that those most happy sensations again which I had then,
            <lb/>I but I have found, that I have had to traverse
            <lb/>this vale of woe &amp; tears by faith, relying on
            <lb/>on my dear Savior, who out of love to my
            <lb/>soul purchas'd it at no less a price than
            <lb/>his own precious blood, &amp; in whom I have that
            <lb/>confidence, that he will lead me safely through
            <lb/>my pilgrimage here below &amp; in his own good
            <lb/>time change my faith into sight, to live in
            <lb/>this presence for ever. In the year 1769
            <lb/>I had the favor to be received among the 
            <lb/>great Girls in the S Srs pray'r Hall in at Ful-
            <lb/>neck, we were 18 in number, and the very
            <lb/>impressive discourse kept by Br Worthington
            <lb/>made a deep impression upon my poor heart,
            <lb/>so that from this that time it became clear to me
            <lb/>that here my lot is was cast to follow my dear Savr
            <lb/>among his people, and on the 6th of May
            <lb/>the same year, I obtained leave to live in
            <lb/>the Srs oeconomy at Littlemore, for which
            <lb/>I was very thankful, and altho I found it
            <lb/>very difficult to come thro in my outwurd
            <lb/>circumstances, &amp; which I certainly cou'd not had
            <lb/>done, had not my Grandmother assisted
            <lb/>me, yet I was determined to weather the storm venture every thing</p>
	<pb facs="#facs_4" n="4"/>
	<p>
            <lb/>having a deep &amp; clear conviction in my heart 
            <lb/>that this was the path my Savr appointed
            <lb/>me to walk in altho at times | owing to my cir-
            <lb/>cumstances &amp; reasoning very dark clouds intercepted to interrupted the clearness of it
            <lb/>for at times for having lost that simplicity I once
            <lb/>had in the Lord, I begun to reason about his 
            <lb/>existance, &amp; if there really was a possibillity that He cou'd
            <lb/>in any Measure, help me thro', thus I went on
            <lb/>for some time, keeping things to myself, which
            <lb/>I shou'd have communicated to those, who
            <lb/>from experience cou'd have directed me
            <lb/>to the service of help, I did not at this
            <lb/>time absent myself in which proved very
            <lb/>detrimental to me. The meetings at this time.
            <lb/>proved a great blessing to my heart, as they
            <lb/>always suited my case in such a Manner 
            <lb/>that I was led to think they were particularly
            <lb/>kept to me. In 1774 I remov'd to the Srs House
            <lb/>in Fulneck, &amp; the year following was recd into the
            <lb/>S. Srs Choir. I now renew'd my covenant with
            <lb/>our Savr, &amp; earnestly pray'd that I might
            <lb/>become More &amp; More devoted to him in
            <lb/> this Choir, than I had been in my Girls
            <lb/>years, but being rather of a legal turn of mind
            <lb/>I had to struggle with myself, not liking</p>
	<pb facs="#facs_5" n="5"/>
	<p>
            <lb/>to acknowlege to our Savr, or to those to whom
            <lb/>I shou'd have placed confidence in, that
            <lb/>I was to blame in Many such things, that which the clear
            <lb/>conviction in my heart, told me was were not
            <lb/>according to the Minds of my dear Lord.
            <lb/>however I pray'd that I might become more 
            <lb/>open hearted, which in the sequel was
            <lb/>granted me &amp; being once at my speaking
            <lb/>my dear Sr Anna Rosel my choir Laboress, she said, "Your
            <lb/>self righteousness will prove your ruin"
            <lb/>these words made a deep impression upon me
            <lb/>and caused me to examine myself more 
            <lb/>minutely, than I had ever done before done and to ask my &amp;
            <lb/>self whether I cou'd surrender both soul, &amp; body to
            <lb/>by our dear Savior in the Congregation, being
            <lb/>I conscious that I had gone on in a very super-
            <lb/>ficial Manner thus far, but from this
            <lb/>time I date my the surrender of my heart to
            <lb/>my best friend; being determined thro' all
            <lb/>difficulties to cleave to, &amp; live alone for Him
            <lb/>March 31st 1777 I had the grace &amp; favor
            <lb/>to be received into the Congn, this was a
            <lb/>day of peculiar blessing to me, hearing 
            <lb/>and I anew devoted myself anew to our Savr
            <lb/>May 2 1780 I partook for the first time</p>
	<pb facs="#facs_6" n="6"/>
	<p>
            <lb/>of the Lords Body &amp; Blood in the H Com<hi rend="superscript:true;">n</hi> with
            <lb/>the Cong<hi rend="superscript:true;">n</hi>, which has proved ever blessed &amp;
            <lb/>memorable to my poor heart.
            <lb/>NB. now the Sisters are to add the remainder also what refers to her last
            <lb/>hours.</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>