<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Taylor_Ann_Ful_SS_71</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Our Dear Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Ann Taylor was Born in Clagheaton May ye 8<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1731</l>
					<l>in Burstol parich, was Baptis&apos;d &amp; educated a pressbeterian her</l>
					<l>Father dieing when she was only Seven years old, &amp; her Mother</l>
					<l>being in low circumstances &amp; uncapable of taking proper care</l>
					<l>of her, her unkle &amp; Aunt took to her, &amp; soon after her Mother</l>
					<l>dieing also she became entirely under of care of her Aunt</l>
					<l>who in ye year 40 was touch&apos;d in heart by our Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> under ye</l>
					<l>preaching of M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Ingham &amp; became a member of that Society,</l>
					<l>to w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> oppertunities she brought ye above child tho: at that </l>
					<l>time, much against her inclination, w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> was more for</l>
					<l>playing with other lightminded Children; this she has often</l>
					<l>since reflected on with concern, &amp; expressed her hearty thanks</l>
					<l>to our dear Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; her aunt for their especial care of her at that</l>
					<l>time. In 45 B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Held haveing of care of ye Yorkshire Children</l>
					<l>&amp; she being admited to there meetings soon begun to love</l>
					<l>them &amp; to have a real tender feeling of her heart. In 46 her</l>
					<l>Aunt comeing to live in an oeconomy, a Sutable place was</l>
					<l>provided for her, where she stay&apos;d a year &amp; then left it of her</l>
					<l>own accord, w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> however gave her much Smart afterward.</l>
					<l>for ye year 50 she had ye favour to live with B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Grass at</l>
					<l>Clagheaton who lov&apos;d her tenderly, but they removeing from thence </l>
					<l>she came to live at Holm with some single women belonging</l>
					<l>to that Society, from, whence she came to live with B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Harlock</l>
					<l>at Lambs Hill, &amp; notwithstanding thus favoured to live with</l>
					<l>Bre<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> &amp; Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> yet she co&apos;d not be satisfyed because she was not</l>
					<l>in ye Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> &amp; therefore beg&apos;d to be taken from that place</l>
					<l>thinking if she was but to live in an oeconomy with Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi></l>
					<l>that then she sho&apos;d soonner come to ye enjoyment of that</l>
					<l>happyness w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> she felt she wanted, to w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> priviledge, upon her</l>
					<l>earnest request Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Mary admited her vis: to Hightown, to live with two sisters</l>
					<l>where according to her expectation, she profited much, became solidly</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>aquainted with our d<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; her own poor heart, so that she gain&apos;d</l>
					<l>ye love of all her Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> &amp; enjoy&apos;d a real fellowship with them.</l>
					<l>May ye 13<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1745 she had ye Grace to become a member of ye Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> to</l>
					<l>her unspeakable consolation. and on ye 20, when ye oeconomy at </l>
					<l>little Gumersel was setled she had ye favour to be one of that happy</l>
					<l>company, of w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> she was very glad &amp; thankfull, remaining in that</l>
					<l>tender feeling for some time, but her impaticent longing for</l>
					<l>still farther Blessings, often caus&apos;d her pain &amp; w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> was renew&apos;d</l>
					<l>constantly when she Saw ye other Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> go to ye Lords Supper. of </l>
					<l>wch she spoak in a particular manner once to a Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>, who</l>
					<l>asking her where she thought ye fault lay, answer&apos;d I don&apos;t</l>
					<l>know, being advised to make application to our dear Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>for a right information, &amp; being asshur&apos;d by ye above Sister</l>
					<l>that she was not forgoten. she accordingly did so, &amp; very simply</l>
					<l>said I feel ye fault is all in my self, childlikly beging to</l>
					<l>be still thought on with regard to that matter, which was</l>
					<l>also done. And on ye 13th of July ye same year she had her</l>
					<l>longing desire satisfyed &amp; was made partaker of her Lords</l>
					<l>Corpse&apos;s &amp; blood in ye holy Sacrament, w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> proved a real &amp;</l>
					<l>lasting Blessing to her heart. But her natural dispossision</l>
					<l>being some what high, she depriv&apos;d her selfe of many happy</l>
					<l>hours w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> otherwise she might have enjoy&apos;d, &amp; this also gave</l>
					<l>occation of concern to those around her <hi rend='underlined:true;'>&amp; some painfull hours</hi></l>
					<l>But our D<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Lamb who know&apos;s all things, found out ways &amp;</l>
					<l>mean&apos;s whereby he cou&apos;d constantly bring her again to ye Sinner</l>
					<l>point, ye this made ye Sisters continue their love to her &amp;</l>
					<l>have paticence with her.</l>
					<l>dec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 56 she was leased with a sore cough atended with a pain</l>
					<l>in her side; by ye continuance of w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> it was judg&apos;d would</l>
					<l>prove a Consumption, tho she her selfe did not believe to</l>
					<l>if she was ask&apos;d at any time if she thought she sho&apos;d go home</l>
					<l>of this sickness, sho&apos;d answer no I can&apos;t believe I shall</l>
					<l>have that favour yet. But ye disorder encreasing, she came</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>upon other thoughts, &amp; said that if she didnot onlter soon it</l>
					<l>would bring her to our Saviour, This made her often wish she </l>
					<l>might once go to live in ye Choir House &amp; there experience in a </l>
					<l>more particular manner her choir grace, w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> favour however</l>
					<l>cou&apos;d not be granted her as an inhabitant but was afterwards</l>
					<l>gratifyd in ye respect on account of chaing of air &amp; better</l>
					<l>convenancy, so on ye 13 of June lest she came here to her great</l>
					<l>joy, hopeing that this wou&apos;d be her last home on earth &amp;</l>
					<l>so growing weaker &amp; weaker she whent into ye Sick Room</l>
					<l>Nov<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> ye 4<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> believing that our dear Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> wo&apos;d soon make her</l>
					<l>ready for himself &amp; take her home where allso she wish&apos;d to</l>
					<l>be. It was always ye greatest pleasure to her when any one</l>
					<l>told her, they thought she w&apos;d soon go to her eternal Bridegroom</l>
					<l>on ye 13 it being ye Elders feastival &amp; she being not able</l>
					<l>to go to ye Hall when ye bell rung for ye absosutation, she </l>
					<l>fell prostrate in her Sick Room &amp; there rec&apos;d that full &amp; free</l>
					<l>absolution from of hands of her dear Head &amp; Elder to her inexp-</l>
					<l>ressable consolation w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> aquainted her dear Sisr. Mary of in</l>
					<l>a very tender manner. On ye 24<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> it being our d<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Mamma&apos;s Birth</l>
					<l>day &amp; tho: she was not capable of being presant at ye oppertunities</l>
					<l>yet she enjoy&apos;d ye sweet nearness of her wounded friend ye whole</l>
					<l>day, at night Sisr Mary came to her, &amp; had some very agreeable</l>
					<l>conversation with her, as she many times had, &amp; ye Choir</l>
					<l>now going to enjoy ye cup of thanksgiving, she was told</l>
					<l>of it, when she tenderly beg&apos;d to be a partaker of ye same</l>
					<l>Grace &amp; Blessing w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> favour was also granted her to her</l>
					<l>great Joy &amp; comfort.</l>
					<l>Sunday 26 she enjoy&apos;d for ye last time ye Corpes &amp; Blood of</l>
					<l>her Beloved in ye Holy Communion.</l>
					<l>Dec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> ye 8 one co&apos;d plainly perceive that her dear Bridegroom</l>
					<l>wo&apos;d soon give her ye last kiss, for w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> she most earnestly,</l>
					<l>long&apos;d. on ye 15<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> she spoak in a very tender &amp; feeling</l>
					<l>manner of ye love &amp; faithfullness of her dearest Friend</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>who had to closly attended &amp; followed her even from</l>
					<l>her childhood, saying ah! He has been my best friend</l>
					<l>indeed, of whom had a strength, I cou&apos;d day much. at </l>
					<l>night she pray&apos;d very proveingly to her dear Lamb, often</l>
					<l>uttering in a faultering tone o! dearest Lamb, take me</l>
					<l>if it be thy time, but if I must yet stay longer</l>
					<l>here, then only keep near my heart &amp; give one paticence</l>
					<l>Then speaking to her Sick waiter said, Thou hast many</l>
					<l>things to forgive me, for I have been a very poor child </l>
					<l>indeed. &amp; so beging pardon in a pretty tender way</l>
					<l>she was assur&apos;d that ye above had not ye least against</l>
					<l>her but realy love&apos;d her. soon after she sent for Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>Mary with whom she kept a hearty band, telling her</l>
					<l>at ye same time, that she firmly believed that her</l>
					<l>dear spouse w&apos;d fetch her home that night w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> ye</l>
					<l>former question&apos;r, she answer&apos;d, but I am ashured of it ye have</l>
					<l>made out all my matters for my Buring &amp; ever thing,</l>
					<l>w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> I hope will be done acordingly, both to your</l>
					<l>Satisfaction &amp; mine &amp; now I have nothing more to do,</l>
					<l>but am quite ready. Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Mary then going to keep ye evening</l>
					<l>Blessing, she sent her hearty Salutaition by her, to her</l>
					<l>her Choir desireing them all to think of her adding, I know our</l>
					<l>dear Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> will kiss me home this night, &amp; then I will </l>
					<l>remember each Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> before him in a particular manner.</l>
					<l>after w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> at Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Marys return she found her still panting</l>
					<l>for ye last kiss, saying o&apos; my dear Lamb: come come soon.</l>
					<l>so she comforted her telling her of that Bloody Sweaty</l>
					<l>agoney w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi> her dear Lord had sufferd for her, in the </l>
					<l>Garden &amp; how on her account he had allso sweated</l>
					<l>death sweat, therefore she sho&apos;d only now have a</l>
					<l>little paticence &amp; that happy mnnite w&apos;d soon come. </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>then the lay a little still, but presantly lifted</l>
					<l>her selfe up &amp; said, come Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Mary &amp; sing me</l>
					<l>ye last verce for I am just now going, then was</l>
					<l>sung, and when in his arm&apos;s lastly thy mouth</l>
					<l>shall pallid grow &amp;c. &amp; then she fell Softly asleep on</l>
					<l>ye warm breast of her dear wounded friend, dureing a Sweet</l>
					<l>litturgy kept by her Choir Labourer&apos;s. between eleven</l>
					<l>&amp; twelve o clock ye same night, in the 28 year of her age</l>
					<l>decb<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 15 1758</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
