<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Thornton_Deborah_Ful_3_22</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l><hi rend='underlined:true;'>Personalia of the Widow Deborah Thornton.</hi> and of the</l>
					<l>Widows house in Fulneck, who Jan 10<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi>. 1771</l>
					<l>The late S<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Deborah Thornton, whose Maiden Name was Walker,</l>
					<l>was born the 13<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>th</hi> of May 1699, &amp; brought up in the Church of</l>
					<l>England. In the Year 1723 she was mar<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi>. to her late Husband</l>
					<l>with whom she lived chearfully &amp; contentedly. She was awakened</l>
					<l>in the Year 1740 by the preaching of the late B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Delamotte &amp; M<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>Ingham. In 1741 she became a Member of the Society at Spen.</l>
					<l>Altho&apos; her Husband did not belong to the B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rn</hi> he laid nothing</l>
					<l>in her Way but rather was helpful to her that she should</l>
					<l>miss no Opportunities among the B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rn</hi>. She became a Widow</l>
					<l>in 1746, at which Time she made a Covenant with our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>to become his entirely in Soul &amp; Body. She soon left her</l>
					<l>House &amp; moved to B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Hunt at Gummersal, &amp; her chief</l>
					<l>Concern was to become better acquainted with our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp;</l>
					<l>his People. In Order to be nearer the Cong<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>n</hi> she moved to</l>
					<l>Widow Robinson in Pudsey. She was found frequently</l>
					<l>alone praying our Savr to have Mercy upon her. In 1750</l>
					<l>she moved to Fulneck which she esteemed as a great Fa=</l>
					<l>vour, &amp; was employed in washing for the Single B<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rn</hi> which</l>
					<l>she performed faithfully. In 1752 she was rec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi>. into the Cong<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>n</hi>,</l>
					<l>which was a Favour she esteemed herself unworthy of, and</l>
					<l>which proved the Means of new Work being begun in</l>
					<l>her by the holy ghost, whereby she learned to know more of</l>
					<l>her deep Depravity &amp; Unbelief; &amp; in this her Distress she</l>
					<l>wept before our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi>, begging Him to wash her in his pre=</l>
					<l>cious Blood. In 1753 she had the Grace to be admitted to</l>
					<l>the holy Communion with the Cong<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>n</hi>. She thought meanly</l>
					<l>of herself, but had that Confidence to our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> that she</l>
					<l>could venture to Him with all her Misery, as a poor Sinner.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>She served 6 Years in the Kitchen of the Children&apos;s Oconomy</l>
					<l>where she did her Work very faithfully &amp; diligently; but</l>
					<l>had also Opportunity of learning to know herself better &amp;</l>
					<l>that she stood daily in Need of fresh Grace. Circumstan=</l>
					<l>ces requiring it, she moved into the Widows House, where</l>
					<l>the holy ghost began a new School with her, by which Means</l>
					<l>many Things were discovered to her which she had not</l>
					<l>attended to before, &amp; which caused her often to weep with</l>
					<l>Concern of Heart on Account of her past Course &amp; to</l>
					<l>pray our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> for a new Look of Grace, &amp; that He would</l>
					<l>heal her wounded Heart with his Blood; He heard her</l>
					<l>Prayer &amp; granted her Request, &amp; she obtained Mercy as a</l>
					<l>Sinner. She was of an anxious Disposition, which,</l>
					<l>with her unfirm State of Body, made her sometimes</l>
					<l>peevish among her S<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rs</hi>;  but she was soon a Sinner about</l>
					<l>it, &amp; thought meanly of herself. Her Sickness, which was</l>
					<l>a heavy One, caused her often to sigh to our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> to take</l>
					<l>her to Himself if it were his Will. She swelled very</l>
					<l>much, but attended the Meetings diligently as long as</l>
					<l>she was able, &amp; was afterwards glad to live under the</l>
					<l>Choir Meeting Hall where she was able to hear the S<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rs</hi></l>
					<l>sing in their Meetings &amp; which was a Blessing to her.</l>
					<l>Her Election of Grace was weighty to &amp; highly prized</l>
					<l>by her. She enjoyed the Communion 3 Times in her Room</l>
					<l>with great Eagerness, &amp; thought each Time would be the</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>last. She slept but little in the Night, but often prayed</l>
					<l>our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> to have Mercy upon her, &amp; in the Day she slept</l>
					<l>in a Chair. She was thankful for all the Kindness shewn to</l>
					<l>her, &amp; often wished with Tears that she was able to express</l>
					<l>her Gratitude rightly for all the Mercy &amp; Patience our Sav<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi></l>
					<l>had shew<hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>?</hi>st to her in her Course in the Cong<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>n</hi>, but in this Point,</l>
					<l>said she, I must remain a great Debtor. She took great</l>
					<l>Delight in the Watch-Word Book, &amp; frequently opened Verses</l>
					<l>in it for herself. What the S<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>rs</hi> related to her concerning</l>
					<l>Christmas &amp; New-Years Night-Watches were very pleasing</l>
					<l>to her. She often said, My Time here will not be very long.</l>
					<l>When S<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Cammerhoff wished her a happy new Year, she</l>
					<l>replied; I shall be compleatly happy when I am with Him,</l>
					<l>&amp; I hope that will be soon. She did not seem to be worse</l>
					<l>than for some Time past, excepting that she was more </l>
					<l>swelled. The 2 last Nights she slept better than she had</l>
					<l>done for a long Time past. Jan. 10<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>th</hi> S<hi rend='underlined:true; superscript:true;'>r</hi> Cammerhoff</l>
					<l>went into her Room as usual, &amp; asked how she did? She</l>
					<l>answered; I am very poorly. She afterwards spoke <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>?</hi></l>
					<l><hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>?</hi> of several Matters, so that her Dissolution</l>
					<l>did not appear to be so near, but she begun to quiver</l>
					<l>being seized with a cold Fit, &amp; immediately her Soul</l>
					<l>took Flight to its Mother-City. We recommended her</l>
					<l>Soul to the Wounds of Jesus, being surprised at her</l>
					<l>sudden Departure.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
