<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Watson_Susanna_Ful_SS_27</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The Life of the Single Sistr Susanh Watson, who went to our</l>
					<l>Savr, July 31st in the Choir House at Fulneck. Concerning</l>
					<l>which the following is Her own account.</l>
					<l>I was born June 25th 1751 at Little Gumersall in</l>
					<l>the Parish of Birstal, Yorkshire, and Baptizd by</l>
					<l>the Brn. In my 6th year my dr Father departed this Life,</l>
					<l>and as I was of a weakly constitution my dr Mother took</l>
					<l>all posible care of me, and altho&apos; her cheif concern was, that I</l>
					<l>might learn to know &amp; Love our dear savr, and to that</l>
					<l>purpose she took me to the Childrns Meetings, where I had</l>
					<l>many drawings of grace in my heart, particularly att</l>
					<l>a meeting held by Br Worthington, wherein he display&apos;d</l>
					<l>the tender regard our dr Savr had for the Childrn that</l>
					<l>he gathord even the smallest tear Shed on his account.</l>
					<l>this was spoke in so feeling a manner, as made a lasting impression on</l>
					<l>my mind, so that I never forgot it. In my 15th year it</l>
					<l>pleasd our Savr to take my dr Mother home to himself</l>
					<l>by means of a very Short sickness. Her last blessing, Just</l>
					<l>before Her happy departure, affected me much, at which</l>
					<l>time She reccommended me in a tender manner to the care</l>
					<l>of my Eldest Sistr, who has ever since faithfully perform&apos;d</l>
					<l>the promise She thon made, and we with my Sistr Mary</l>
					<l>together lived very Comfortably togethor; my sistr taking</l>
					<l>all posible care to preserve us from the world. In my</l>
					<l>girls yoars I already began to feel my natural depravity</l>
					<l>and had a hard Struggle with self my self, which thro&apos;</l>
					<l>our dr Savrs faithfullness towards me torminated in a</l>
					<l>desire to Live with the Sistrs which I made known, and</l>
					<l>obtaind leave to remove to the Houme Oeconimy in my 17 year</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Octbr 16, where I was rec&apos;d in a loving manner, and found</l>
					<l>my self quite at home amongst the Sistrs, till the same</l>
					<l>Oeconimy mov&apos;d to the Little Moore. soon after our</l>
					<l>removal I came into an indiferency in my hoart and</l>
					<l>Suffer&apos;d my went on for some time without much concern</l>
					<l>about my self or the aim of living with Sistrs. till my</l>
					<l>faithfull Savr thro the convictions of his gracious Spirit</l>
					<l>brought me again to Recolection, when I found I had not</l>
					<l>follow&apos;d his intention in calling me, which was that I</l>
					<l>might learn to know and live for him alone in this world;</l>
					<l>this causd me great uneasinoss, which I cou&apos;d by no means</l>
					<l>get rid of, but my dr Savr did not let me remain long in</l>
					<l>before he drew so sensibly near to my heart, that I was</l>
					<l>richly comforted thereby. March 27. 1769 I was rec&apos;d</l>
					<l>into the Congn to my real abasement, and went on for</l>
					<l>Sometime in a humble sence of my own unworthiness,</l>
					<l>but soon lost my self again in my former course of</l>
					<l>indiferency, about which I become quite distressd and</l>
					<l>Miserable, till by discoursing with my Labrss I found</l>
					<l>Comfort, and was able to beleive, that our savr cou&apos;d help</l>
					<l>me in my dispositition as well as all other failings,</l>
					<l>if I only kept close to Him. May ye 4 the same</l>
					<l>year I was rec&apos;d into the Sistrs Choir. which together</l>
					<l>with my becoming a Canditate for the H Cn in 1770.</l>
					<l>gave me the oppertunity of feeling more thon ever my</l>
					<l>natural depravity, as our Savr made it a real schooling</l>
					<l>time to me, I try&apos;d all means to little effect to help</l>
					<l>my self, not knowing our Savr as the Sinners only</l>
					<l>friend, till in the midst of distress he graciously</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>manifested himself to my poor heart in such a lively</l>
					<l>manner, as crucified for me a lost undone sinner,</l>
					<l>as if he had been realy present, assuring me at the same</l>
					<l>time of the forgiveness of all my sins, and I cou&apos;d rely upon</l>
					<l>the allsufficiency of his Merits, as a true poor Sinner, to</l>
					<l>my inexpresible Joy and Comfort, July 17th 1771 I had the</l>
					<l>grace to injoy the H Cn the first time with the Congn</l>
					<l>to my unspeakable blossing, the impression of that great</l>
					<l>grace has been an incouragment to me in the many</l>
					<l>deviations or mistakes I have been senceible of since that</l>
					<l>time, to turn to my dr Savr who has never fail&apos;d to</l>
					<l>Comfort &amp; help his poor me thro&apos; in all Circumstances,</l>
					<l>Thus far her own account</l>
					<l>Our Late Sistr. was of a reserved turn of mind, which</l>
					<l>brought her sometimes into a little anxiety about herself</l>
					<l>Which she espressd in few words, but in that case our dr Savr</l>
					<l>faithfullness towards her, Comforted and Supported her, under the</l>
					<l>feeling sence of her own poverty, as well as of her sickly</l>
					<l>habit of Body, which this last spring took a consumptive</l>
					<l>turn, whereby the comencement of her disolution was -</l>
					<l>apprehonded. She did not at first take it in that light,</l>
					<l>but thought, She might still recover, but as her strength</l>
					<l>daily decreasd it became cloar to hor that our savrs</l>
					<l>intention meaning was to prepare her by this sicknoss for himself,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>She became more resign&apos;d, and spent her time in a still</l>
					<l>converse with her unseen freind, during her abode in the</l>
					<l>Sickroom, where she injoy&apos;d the H-Cn Several times</l>
					<l>to Her comfort and blessing, resigning her self intirely</l>
					<l>to tho will of hor dr Savr awaiting tho happy</l>
					<l>Moment, whon he wou&apos;d graciously release her out</l>
					<l>of all hor pain, which he had made tolerable to hor</l>
					<l>till towards tho later end, whon it was more severe,</l>
					<l>but did not Continue so long, as for tho time of hor</l>
					<l>departure was at hand, and which came to pass on Wensday</l>
					<l>Morning about a Qarter after 4 o Clock, whon she fell</l>
					<l>Softly and happily asleep with tho blessing of hor</l>
					<l>Choir. (in the 25 yoar of hor Age</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
