<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Watson_Anne_Ful_3_115</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>2. Anne Watson, aged 16 years.</l>
					<l>She died early in May 1837 after a lingering illness.</l>
					<l>She was a striking instance of the good effects of Sunday</l>
					<l>school, and also a blessed proof of the faithfulness of the </l>
					<l>lost shepherd in leading the lambs of His flock to His</l>
					<l>fold, and screening them amidst temptation. In meek</l>
					<l>ness and humility this yong girl had sat at the feet of</l>
					<l>Jesus, and learnt lessons of eternal truth from the word</l>
					<l>of His mouth. She was one of the tender plants that</l>
					<l>grew up and flourish unnoticed by the eye of man.</l>
					<l>It was only a few months ago that her parents and</l>
					<l>their family came to reside in this village. Judging</l>
					<l>from the general conduct of the family no one woud</l>
					<l>have expected, <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>that</hi> to find so rich a gem among such rough</l>
					<l>unpolished stones. Hearing of her illness I determi</l>
					<l>ned to visit her, tho&apos; I scarce expected a welcome</l>
					<l>reception from the inmates of the house. But I shall</l>
					<l>never forget my visits to this poor girl; they belong</l>
					<l>to the most agreeable portion of my labour. The first</l>
					<l>time I called I found her lying in a most deplorable</l>
					<l>condition, almost worn out by consumption and too</l>
					<l>weak to sin; the general appearance of the house also and</l>
					<l>of the chamber in which she lay, showed that hers was the</l>
					<l>abode of poverty. But tho&apos; weak in body, she was</l>
					<l>strong in faith, and tho&apos; poor she ??nned all things,</l>
					<l>having the pearl of great price. Instead of needing,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>as I had suffered, instructions in the way of salvation</l>
					<l>she was blessd with the knowledge of an advanced Christian,</l>
					<l>combined with <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>such</hi> genuine humbleness of mind, never imagi</l>
					<l>ning that she knew more than others, or making</l>
					<l>any boast. The spirit of the lowly Jesus of Nazareth</l>
					<l>rested upon her. Asking her the ground of her faith and</l>
					<l>hope, and what enabled her to look forward to death</l>
					<l>with such complacence and even welcoming?, she replied,</l>
					<l>&quot;Jesus died for me on the cross, and He is good to all,</l>
					<l>that put their trust in Him.&quot; I continued, &quot;And do</l>
					<l>you put your trust in Him?&quot; &quot;Yes, I do,&quot; said she</l>
					<l>&quot;I love <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>love</hi> Him, and I believe He loves me; He came</l>
					<l>to seek and save sinners.&quot; I again questioned her, &quot;Where</l>
					<l>my child, did you learn this?&quot; Never shall I forget</l>
					<l>the look she gave me, and the smile that brightened up</l>
					<l>her counteance while she replied, &quot;I learnt it in my</l>
					<l>Bible, sir.&quot; </l>
					<l>She had been a scholar in a Sunday school before</l>
					<l>she came to live here; and amidst all the sin and </l>
					<l>depravity in her father&apos;s house and in the mill, where</l>
					<l>she worked, her soul had imbibed the sincere milk</l>
					<l>of the Word; the lamp of life had enlightened her under</l>
					<l>standing, and she had found her way to the cross of Christ</l>
					<l>where Jesus had spoken peace to her soul. Without</l>
					<l>any human teacher of divine things, or anyone who knew</l>
					<l>what was paning in her mind, the Word of God was her</l>
					<l>guide and light, and, according to her mothers testi</l>
					<l>mony, this blessed book had been her constant com</l>
					<l>panion during her illness the Bible lay under her</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>pillow, and the precious texts, stored in her memory</l>
					<l>were her daily food. On the day of her death, when</l>
					<l>suffering excruciating pain, she expressed the feelings</l>
					<l>of her heart and her joyful confidence in that Divine</l>
					<l>Friend, on whom she depended, by repeated the</l>
					<l>23<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> Psalm: &quot;The Lord is my Shepherd, I shall not</l>
					<l>want.&quot; She was indeed a sheep of <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>Jesus</hi> the </l>
					<l>Good Shepherd, who had led her to the green pa</l>
					<l>stures of His Word and beside the still waters of His</l>
					<l>grave, who healed all her infirmities and was with</l>
					<l>her in the valley of the shadow of death.</l>
					<l>Her submission to the will of the Lord was</l>
					<l>strikingly evident. Being once asked by a friend</l>
					<l>if she wished to get better, she replied, &quot;As it pleases</l>
					<l>God.&quot; The question being put to her, what she would</l>
					<l>ask if the Lord should say to her, as to Solomon, &quot;Ask</l>
					<l>what I shall give them&quot; - she looked very thoughtful</l>
					<l>and said, &quot;I would <hi rend='underlined:true;'>first</hi> ask Him <hi rend='underlined:true;'>what</hi> I should say.&quot; </l>
					<l>As the days of her mortal pilgrimmage drew to</l>
					<l>a close she showed great concern for the souls of</l>
					<l>her companions; and many were the touching ap</l>
					<l>peals, accompanied with fervent prayer, and the ear-</l>
					<l>nest exhortation she addressed to them. &quot;Do not,&quot; she </l>
					<l>would say, &quot;ah! do not trifle with eternal concerns;</l>
					<l>turn to Jesus, He is the Good Shepherd. You must</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>soon die; but Jesus will save you from eternal</l>
					<l>death if you believe in Him, And we shall meet</l>
					<l>again in Heaven.&quot; She further manifested her de</l>
					<l>sire for the spiritual good of others by requesting</l>
					<l>that a Funeral sermon might be preached on</l>
					<l>the Text, &quot;Remember now thy Creator in the days</l>
					<l>of thy youth.&quot; Eccles. XII.1 A vast crowd of young</l>
					<l>people attended, and from the stillness and attention</l>
					<l>which prevailed, I cherish the hope, that the Lord</l>
					<l>made it a blessing to some.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
