<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Wilson_Elizabeth_Ful_SS_62</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1286.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Eliz: Willson. I was born in Yorkshire in</l>
					<l>in the parish of Leeds in Febry 21st 1731. baptized</l>
					<l>in the Church of England. I was educated by my</l>
					<l>parents till I was 13 Years of age, then I was put</l>
					<l>apprentice for 6 Years, wch I serv&apos;d faithfully, tho&apos;</l>
					<l>not without hardships, but I being of a lightsome</l>
					<l>Turn of mind I got thro&apos; better. for at that time I</l>
					<l>knew nothing of our Savr, neither did I think of any</l>
					<l>religion, so I went on without thot, sometimes my</l>
					<l>Father wou&apos;d ask me, come wilt thou go with us to</l>
					<l>hear the preaching to day, at wch  I was griev&apos;d, &amp; said</l>
					<l>no never while I live, will I go to hear them naughty</l>
					<l>people, then my parents thot I shd come into something</l>
					<l>bad, because I seem&apos;d so wild, but for all that, I had</l>
					<l>no liking to that wch  my companions follow&apos;d, but</l>
					<l>always felt an aversion against it in my heart, at that</l>
					<l>time, I did not know how it shd be so, but now I</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1287.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>know that it was my dear Lord that kept me, from</l>
					<l>all hurt &amp; shame. In my 17th Year my Master</l>
					<l>had the misfortune to be kill&apos;d, this struck me very</l>
					<l>much, but that went oft again without thinking any</l>
					<l>further, but that he was at rest; In my 18th Year</l>
					<l>I had a dream wch made such an impression on my</l>
					<l>heart, that I never forgot, my parents were afraid</l>
					<l>that something had happen&apos;d to me, my Mother</l>
					<l>ask&apos;d me if my mistress had been hard with me,</l>
					<l>I answer&apos;d no, it was something that I had dream&apos;d,</l>
					<l>then my Father came to me, &amp; said, come now tell me</l>
					<l>what it is, but my heart was quite full, however</l>
					<l>I told it, &amp; it was, I thot a man came to me, drest</l>
					<l>in a white surples, stood over me, &amp; look&apos;d very solid</l>
					<l>at me, then he spread his hands over me, &amp; then</l>
					<l>folded them upon his breast, &amp; I not knowing that</l>
					<l>will </l>
					<l>I was in Bed, thot I lye quite still &amp; see what</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1288.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>he wd do to me, then he smil&apos;d at me, &amp; began to</l>
					<l>write with his finger upon my forehead, for a good</l>
					<l>while, then he laid his hand upon my head with</l>
					<l>such a powerfull feeling that tears flow&apos;d without</l>
					<l>number, then he look&apos;d again at me and smil&apos;d &amp;</l>
					<l>turn&apos;d away &amp; left me, then I thot I will fetch a</l>
					<l>looking glass to see what was done on my forehead,</l>
					<l>but I thot if he has wrote, I cant read writing, however</l>
					<l>I wd look &amp; when I saw there was written in large</l>
					<l>leders in crimson &amp; I cou&apos;d read it, &amp; it was; I</l>
					<l>will take care of the, thou shalt not be lost, &amp; when</l>
					<l>I awoke my pillow was quite wet with tears, &amp;</l>
					<l>I wept almost the whole Night &amp; cd not help it,</l>
					<l>for the impression remains to this day, &amp; will</l>
					<l>remain till I go to kiss those hands, wch was held</l>
					<l>not </l>
					<l>over me, then I began to think that my time was out</l>
					<l>for then I had almost 2 Years to stay, wch indeed</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1289.jpg' n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>indeed seem&apos;d to me very long, but I began to think I</l>
					<l>will forget this feeling, &amp; be as I was before, but I</l>
					<l>cou&apos;d not, for it always came to me again, once I</l>
					<l>went to my Father &amp; privately took their H. Book,</l>
					<l>&amp; brot it away with me, for I thot I wd see what my</l>
					<l>Sisrs sung out of that book, for they often sung when</l>
					<l>I was there, &amp; when my Mistress &amp; all were in Bed,</l>
					<l>I read in it, &amp; that verse: Yea wounds of Jesus bless</l>
					<l>me now; that verse soon took my mind, for I began to</l>
					<l>think who is that Jesus wch has wounds, I thot I</l>
					<l>know no meaning of this, however I read it over &amp; over</l>
					<l>&amp; the sametime thot, as soon as my time is out, I will</l>
					<l>go to hear those people, that I have despis&apos;d so much,</l>
					<l>perhaps they will tell me more of that Jesus; so I</l>
					<l>did, when my time was out, I went with my parents,</l>
					<l>to hear the Brn to my great joy for the first time, I</l>
					<l>heard them, they told of that Jesus, full of wounds</l>
					<l>wch was made for poor sinners, </l>
					<l>this struck me deeply</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1290.jpg' n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>then I was soon taken into the society, I went on &amp;</l>
					<l>felt our Savr near my heart &amp; was so happy that I</l>
					<l>thot I wanted nothing more, in his way I went on</l>
					<l>for near 7 Years, then I began to think of being recd</l>
					<l>into the Congn, &amp; spoke about it, it happen&apos;d that</l>
					<l>some were recd before me out of my class, &amp; I was</l>
					<l>left, then I was griev&apos;d &amp; thot they chose the worst,</l>
					<l>&amp; leave the best, for I thot myself the fittest, I</l>
					<l>therefore went away perplext indeed, but it did not re</l>
					<l>main long, for my dear Savr soon shew&apos;d me, that</l>
					<l>I was the worst of all, &amp; my happiness was nothing;</l>
					<l>then I felt quite miserable &amp; thot it is no wonder, that</l>
					<l>I am unreceived for I am not fit for the Congn, nor any</l>
					<l>thing else, I thot I had griev&apos;d our Savr so much, that</l>
					<l>I dare not ask him to forgive me, in this situation</l>
					<l>I went on for almost a week, &amp; on Sunday I went to</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1291.jpg' n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>hear Br LaTrobe preach, he began with inviting all those</l>
					<l>that were the most sinfull of all, &amp; said that our Savr</l>
					<l>stood ready to forgive every one that wd come to him, even</l>
					<l>just as you are; O then I thot I will go to him &amp; try</l>
					<l>whether he can forgive me, I therefore threw myself at</l>
					<l>the thro pierced feet of our Savr, &amp; said to him dear</l>
					<l>Savr here is one of the poorest of all thy flock, canst</l>
					<l>thou forgive me. The feeling wch over power&apos;d me, at</l>
					<l>that hour, my poor tongue is not able to express;</l>
					<l>it was as if our Savr said to me, I forgive thee</l>
					<l>all thy sins, yes I forgive thee ev&apos;ry thing &amp; own</l>
					<l>thee as one of my little Flock.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
