<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Eagles_Ann_Ful_SS_47</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Ann Eagles was Born at Cadon in oxfordshire Sept 7th 1734</l>
					<l>Her Parents both died when she was very yong, wich was followd</l>
					<l>with great hardships in Service till She was about 16 years of age</l>
					<l>about which time Br Gusenbower Preachd it Cabworth wher</l>
					<l>she liv&apos;d she hearing him became thoughtfull about her Salva-</l>
					<l>tion, &amp; from that time had a particular drawing also to the</l>
					<l>Bretheren, which made her leave her place that she might</l>
					<l>have opportunity to hear the Gosple &amp; thereupon she came</l>
					<l>live with Br &amp; Sr Ager at Northampton, where from time</l>
					<l>to time she became Acquainted with the Srs of her own Choir</l>
					<l>by whom she was very much Belov&apos;d but cou&apos;d not according to </l>
					<l>her Satisfaction to enjoy her own Choir, to whom she was so</l>
					<l>much attach&apos;d yet her heart was always with them. She long was</l>
					<l>usefull in the Service of Br &amp; Sr Ager &amp; at the same time</l>
					<l>under great obligations to them, since they was the cause of her be-</l>
					<l>ing acquainted with the Congregation, She always show&apos;d great Ten-</l>
					<l>derness and affection in her Childlike behaviour to them. in</l>
					<l>ye year 1756 June 7 She was receivd into the Congregation</l>
					<l>which proved a great blessing to her &amp; She kept in close union</l>
					<l>with her Srs came as often as She cou&apos;d to Bedford it being</l>
					<l>a great way of which gave her great reason to wish &amp; long to</l>
					<l>be in the Choir-house were with she was so delighted. She</l>
					<l>often said if I dont soon come to my dear Srs I believe our</l>
					<l>Saviour will take me to himself, which she often expressd</l>
					<l>to her Choir Labouress, this last year the found it very</l>
					<l>difficult in coming to see us the Small-Pox being in</l>
					<l>Northampton, which She had not had gave her great reason</l>
					<l>to Stay at home, on which account She shed many tears &amp;</l>
					<l>sent Letters to her Srs to let them know from time to time</l>
					<l>how she felt in her heart &amp; so kept up fellowship with them.</l>
					<l>June the 7th She was took with the Small-Pox &amp; as she all</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>along prepar&apos;d her self for going home She went to the Room</l>
					<l>were she was to be with great Chearfullness &amp; Sent word to us</l>
					<l>about her illness on which account Lorel went the 14th of</l>
					<l>June, &amp; arriv&apos;d with her at 11 o clock. at the sight of her</l>
					<l>She was over-come with joy, &amp; embrac&apos;d her to such a degree</l>
					<l>that She was advis&apos;d to keep still, least it might hurt her</l>
					<l>O no said She, I am so glad to see you nothing will hurt me</l>
					<l>how Shall I be thaakfull enough to my dear Saviour for</l>
					<l>such a grace, tho&apos; I have nothing to say in particular but</l>
					<l>to tell you that I am quite ready to go to my dear Savr</l>
					<l>whom I love very much, I am over come with his grace; he is</l>
					<l>so near to me that I can embrace him at any time, after</l>
					<l>She had repeated often how glad &amp; thankfull she was in see-</l>
					<l>ing one of her Choir Sisters She seem&apos;d to grow weak</l>
					<l>Lorel was left alone with her asking her many questions</l>
					<l>&amp; if She thought of going soon to embrace her Bridegroom,</l>
					<l>yes said She, it was made out in my heart before now;</l>
					<l>but since I ses you I cant recollect so well, I am quite resin&apos;d</l>
					<l>&amp; believe it will be soon, then Lorel said to her it will be the </l>
					<l>more joy to you when you get the sight of him sooner then you</l>
					<l>expected upon which She smil&apos;d was quite Chearfull &amp; taken up</l>
					<l>entirely with her Bridegroom, After this uncommon joy she</l>
					<l>seem&apos;d tir&apos;d then Lorel left her but She soon sent for her</l>
					<l>again, she found her in her the same chearfull way, &amp; Sung</l>
					<l>several verses asking then if she understood what was sung</l>
					<l>She said I Sing with you we then percievd a Suden alteration</l>
					<l>the Person which attended her wanted to ease her turn&apos;d her</l>
					<l>on her Bed but not expecting that her time was so near.</l>
					<l>She looking at Lorel who began to sing &amp; her Poor Limbs now</l>
					<l>dying &amp;c under which verse her Soul took its flight about 7 o Clock</l>
					<l>the Same Night, all those about her was agreeable surpris&apos;d at her</l>
					<l>happy departure.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
