<?xml-model href="../../TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Sarah Skelton: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>Moravian Archives: Fulneck, UK</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="Ful_SS_37Skelton">Sarah Skelton</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_37Skelton-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_37Skelton-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_37Skelton-03.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2019-07-03" who="#JAKA1"> </change>
			<change when="2019-06-10" who="#JAKA1">Updated header</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Sarah Skelton</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_37Skelton-01.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The course of life of the S. S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sarah Skelton who departed</l>
					<l>to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> May 3 1778 in the S<hi rend="superscript">isr</hi> House at Fulneck</l>
					<l>she has felt the following acco<add place="above">u</add>nt of hersilf. </l></lg></p>
					<p><lg>
					<l>I was born at Robert Town in the parish of Burstoll,</l>
					<l>Yorkshire and baptiz&apos;d in the Ch: of Eng: in my 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year</l>
					<l>my Mother departed this life, my Father being left with </l>
					<l>5 small Children, sent me to live with one of my</l>
					<l>relations; and remov&apos;d himself with the rest of the Family</l>
					<l>to Pudsey: in about a year after, he took one home again</l>
					<l>that I might have the oppertunity with the rest of the Children</l>
					<l>to go to the meetings at Fulneck, which I did with great</l>
					<l>pleasure for a time when I was about 10 years ould, I begun</l>
					<l>to love the things of this world, and forgot in a great measure</l>
					<l>what I had heard of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> in the meetings. I then left my</l>
					<l>Father, and went to service: which indeed prov&apos;d hurtfull</l>
					<l>to me being led by others into very bad things, and foll</l>
					<l>owing at the same time my own evil inclinations, but</l>
					<l>my faithfull Saviour kept a gracious eye over me, and</l>
					<l>let me feel, that if I went on in this way I shou&apos;d be </l>
					<l>lost forever. My M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> with whome I liv&apos;d, did not like</l>
					<l>me to go to the meetings, but I intreated her one day very</l>
					<l>earnestly, she gave me leave, I then went to my Father</l>
					<l>and laid my case before him, and tould him, I could live</l>
					<l>there no longer, disireing him to take me home again, </l>
					<l>which he did: I then cou&apos;d go to the meetings at Fulne<add place="above">ck</add></l>
					<l>of which I was very glad in my 13th yr I was receivd into </l>
					<l>the G: Girls Choir and from that time our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> begun</l>
					<l>a new work of Grace in my heart, he let me feel what</l>
					<l>a poor lost creature I was by nature, I wept for grace</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_37Skelton-02.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and wanted to be his intirely, I soon got a strong desire to </l>
					<l>go and live with the Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>, but durst not make it known,</l>
					<l>thinking I was too bad; but when I cou&apos;d conceal it no longer</l>
					<l>I ventured to tell my Father, he gave me no incouragement</l>
					<l>at all: but as I cou&apos;d not give it up, I speak to my Labouress</l>
					<l>about it, who promisd not to forget me as it was a </l>
					<l>good while before I got leave to go, and I was weak and </l>
					<l>unsteady in mysilf; the things of this world took again</l>
					<l>hold of me, and provd a temptation to me in many</l>
					<l>respects but my dear Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> never left me, but let me</l>
					<l>feel I was not right, and causd me to be very uneasy</l>
					<l>about my poor Soul, so that I coud do nothing but pray</l>
					<l>him to make out a way for any escape, from the many</l>
					<l>snares and temptation which were in my way.</l></lg></p>
					<p><lg>
					<l>March 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1770 I obtaind leave to go and live with</l>
					<l>the S. S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> at Gumersall, for which I was very thank</l>
					<l>full, and now it was my only desire to prosper in the</l>
					<l>Cong<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> to learn more of mysilf an also to become more</l>
					<l>acquainted with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Feb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 1772 I had the</l>
					<l>favour to be recievd into the Congr which was a great</l>
					<l>comfort to me. May 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1773 I was receivd into the S </l>
					<l>S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Choir; this change prov&apos;d both a blessing and a </l>
					<l>of heart to me, I felt more of my corrupted state</l>
					<l>by nature, but being very close, and not willing to </l>
					<l>be known as I really was: hinderd our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> work </l>
					<l>in my heart, yet I felt him constantly busy to </l>
					<l>bring me to the knowledge of himsilf as the Found</l>
					<l>of poor sinners, but instead of coming to him</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>as a poor Sinner, I stood looking at mysilf so long till</l>
					<l>my misery became greater, it was to me as if all the sins I</l>
					<l>had ever been guilty of, were laid before my eyes, and I </l>
					<l>became quite dark and perplex&apos;d: and thought I had better</l>
					<l>leave the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> then be known just as I was; for I thought, </l>
					<l>certainly no one has ever been like me, when I wou&apos;d have</l>
					<l>turnd to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> it was as if something stood between, so</l>
					<l>that I knew not which way to turn for relief for my poor</l>
					<l>distressed Soul. Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1773 I had the favour to be a </l>
					<l>spectator at the H: Comunion: which I took as a proof</l>
					<l>of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> love to me, that I might know he had not</l>
					<l>forgot me; even when I thought I was forsaken of all, </l>
					<l>and what a feeling I had of his precious nearness</l>
					<l>during that transaction, I can never describe in words;</l>
					<l>this encoraged me so that I coud go on chearfull for some</l>
					<l>time, but the feeling of my misery still oppressd me,</l>
					<l>for it was nor made quite dear to me that I had hinder&apos;d</l>
					<l>our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> work by my own striving, and silf? working, at</l>
					<l>the time when he wanted to bring one to a clearness in</l>
					<l>him and I felt (by the fresh discovery he gave me of my</l>
					<l>great misery and wretchedness) that he was now quite</l>
					<l>intent to do it, and as I cou&apos;d now do no otherwise, I disclosd</l>
					<l>my whole heart to my Labouress; whome I found so tender</l>
					<l>and sympathizing that I was quite asham&apos;d. sometime after</l>
					<l>having not yet feelt our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> forgiveness I came into</l>
					<l>darkness and confusion about it, and was not without</l>
					<l>thoughts of leaving the Congn being continually distress</l>
					<l>on account of my many sins, which I longd to have</l>
					<l>blotted out: and be absolvd from. </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_37Skelton-03.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>in this longing disposition I once retird alone, and prostrated before</l>
					<l>our Savr and he appear&apos;d before me in that bleeding figure as he</l>
					<l>hang upon the Cross, and gave me the asureance that he had</l>
					<l>forgiven one all my sins, this was a comfort which no words</l>
					<l>can describe; thus I became chearfull and was thankfull for </l>
					<l>what I had injoyd. and I feelt an inexpressable desire to be a</l>
					<l>participant of the H: Communion, which grace I was made</l>
					<l>a pertakes off, Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1776 to my great joy, from this time</l>
					<l>I gave mysilf up intirely to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, and wish&apos;d for nothing so</l>
					<l>much as to live in a close connesion with him, till I shall see</l>
					<l>him face to face, - so for her own words --- Since she had the </l>
					<l>favour to be a partaker of the Body and Blood of our Savr in the</l>
					<l>H: Commuion she was very strict with hersilf: the sense she had of her</l>
					<l>own poverty made her always timerous, least any thing shou&apos;d </l>
					<l>creep in between our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and her, and when ever the smallest thing</l>
					<l>did; she cou&apos;d never be easy till it was want&apos;d away by the Blood of</l>
					<l>our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> which had once given her pardon: This watchfullness over</l>
					<l>hersilf prov&apos;d the means of her keeping in a close conexion with her</l>
					<l>unseen friend; she was for some years past at times very sickly, and </l>
					<l>towards the latter end of last year, she got a bad cold and cough;</l>
					<l>which never rightly left her tho&apos; severall means was try&apos;d for that</l>
					<l>purpose, Jan<hi rend="superscript">ry</hi> 18 1778 she mov&apos;d to Fulneck to see if change of air</l>
					<l>wou&apos;d not be of servise to her; but she was soon abliged to move</l>
					<l>into the Sickroom her sickness terminating in a Consumption;</l>
					<l>it was soon clear to her that our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> was hastening to prepare her </l>
					<l>for himsilf: and tho&apos; at times she wish&apos;d to recover, yet she soon resignd</l>
					<l>hersilf to the will of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> that he might do with her as he</l>
					<l>thought best, and so spent her time in the Sickroom in a tender childlike</l>
					<l>hearts conexion with him in her last days here below, she rejoic&apos;d at the</l>
					<l>happy prospect she had in view, often praying that the time might soon</l>
					<l>come, it was very agreeable to be near her the peace of our Savr so surr</l>
					<l>ounded her, it was likewise a pleasure to her to be visited by the Sisters to</l>
					<l>whome she often tould how she long&apos;d to go to her everlasting rest</l>
					<l>which longing desire was happily fulfild May ye 3d in the morning </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
