<?xml-model href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/schema/MoravianMemoirs.xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Crispin Taylor: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>Repository Name</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="#">Name</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-05.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-06.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-07.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2019-06-30" who="#JAKA1">Created Crispin Taylor</change>
			<change when="2019-06-10" who="#JAKA1">Updated header</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Crispin Taylor</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="url"/>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-01.jpg" n="1"/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Crispin Taylor, was born in Wyke in the Parish</l>
					<l>of Birstall April ye 26, 1698, and lived with </l>
					<l>his Father, who learnd him the Trade of a Shoemaker,</l>
					<l>till April 1722, being then 24 years of Age he was</l>
					<l>married to Mary Wilkinson, who is his present Wife,</l>
					<l>and had by her 9 Children, four of which are left</l>
					<l>behind, the other five went home before him. In his</l>
					<l>married State he approved himself a carefull, lo</l>
					<l>ving father and a tender Husband.</l>
					<l>When Mr. Ingham first began to preach here about,</l>
					<l>he soon went to hear him, and his heart was touchd</l>
					<l>by the holy Ghost in the first Sermon he heard.</l>
					<l>From that time, he sought all Opportunities to hear</l>
					<l>the Gospel of our Dr Saviours Death and Attonement</l>
					<l>After the Societies were settled here in Yorkshire,</l>
					<l>and put under the Care of the Brethren, he and</l>
					<l>his Wife upon their Request were also taken in </l>
					<l>amongst them, which was a great Satisfaction to</l>
					<l>both, and proved a Blessing to their hearts, which </l>
					<l>made them some time after very desirous to be ta</l>
					<l>ken into the Congregation and to be in a closer Con</l>
					<l>nexion with the Brn. He therefore spoke with </l>
					<l>Br Toltshig about it, expressing his hearts desire </l>
					<l>to be wholy our Saviours Oct the 1st 1748. he had</l>
					<l>after many earnest and repeated Requests this</l>
					<l>favour granted him tot eh great Joy of his </l>
					<l>heart, for it proved an extraordinary Blessing</l>
					<l>to him, so that his Wife and all about him</l>
					<l>saw a visible Change, he being so chearfull, lively</l>
					<l>and happy, as they never had seen him before.</l>
					<l>This continued with him. He was a simple and up</l>
					<l>right heart, and when he heard any one reason about</l>
					<l><note type="catchword">things</note></l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-02.jpg" n="2"/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>things, he used to say: What is this to us, the Lamb will</l>
					<l>know it best; and again: Let us wait for our Savi</l>
					<l>ours time, his time is allways the best. </l>
					<l>Soon af</l>
					<l>ter this his heart secretly longed to partake of The </l>
					<l>Corpse and Blood of Jesus in the Sacrament, when </l>
					<l>unexpectedly he was sent for, and told by the Brn that </l>
					<l>our dr Saviour; who knew his hunger would soon </l>
					<l>accomplish his desire, and should therefo be confirmd</l>
					<l>and blessed, which made his heart very glad and</l>
					<l>more attached to the Wounds of Jesus. March the 24</l>
					<l>1749. he partook of the holy Communion for the 1st</l>
					<l>time when his Soul and Body was so afected and pe</l>
					<l>netrated thro &amp; thro with the martyrd Corpse &amp;</l>
					<l>blood of Jesus, as he could not express it with Words.</l>
					<l>He was so happy in his heart and felt such Blessings</l>
					<l>that he scarce knew, what he eat of drank, or how</l>
					<l>he walkd or workd for many days, and this sound</l>
					<l>he felt ringing in his ears perpetually: My flesh</l>
					<l>is meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink indeed.</l>
					<l>And indeed it proved itself to him real Life, and </l>
					<l>Meat and Drink to his Heart. When his Wife was</l>
					<l>concernd, that she did not partake with him of the </l>
					<l>same Priviledge, he behaved very tender towards</l>
					<l>her, and comforted her, saying: Have a little Pa</l>
					<l>tience, for the Lambs time is the best.</l>
					<l>Several years ago he had got a Surfeit by heating </l>
					<l>himself with working over hard, which for three years</l>
					<l>past, has at times troubled him much with a</l>
					<l>severe Costiveness and Pain in his Bowels.</l>
					<l>About 10 weeks ago he was taken with it again</l>
					<l>but continued chearfull and quite resigned to our Sa</l>
					<l>viour; Br Oxlee went to see him, and when he </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>looked at him, he found him so solid and groun</l>
					<l>ded, and with such a Sinnerlike Shame, as he never be</l>
					<l>fore had observed in him, So that coming home he said </l>
					<l>to his Wife: Crispin Taylor ripens fast for Eternity</l>
					<l>Oct The 28. He grew worse and could work no more.</l>
					<l>But soon after was obliged to keep his Bed. Br Oxlee</l>
					<l>visited him, and asked him, whether he thought he </l>
					<l>should be soon well again? He answered softly (for</l>
					<l>he feard his Wife would hear him and be grieved at it)</l>
					<l>but yet very chearfully, and said: No, I shall go to my</l>
					<l>Dr Saviour, and further being asked: Whether he should</l>
					<l>like to go home, he answered O yes, with all my heart</l>
					<l>and Soul; I would go this night, if it pleased him, but</l>
					<l>yet I&apos;ll wait till he calls me, for his time is the </l>
					<l>best. Br Hauptmanns soon after came to Scholar to</l>
					<l>speak with the Communion Brn &amp; Srs: and calld on</l>
					<l>to see him, of which he was exceeding glad and</l>
					<l>spoke of it with great Joy. Some days after B</l>
					<l>Oxlee came to see him again, and found him asleep,</l>
					<l>and as he had had no Sleep for many nights,</l>
					<l>because of his extreme pain, he would not</l>
					<l>have him disturbd. But after he got wake his</l>
					<l>wife told him of it. O sayd he: Why didnt you  </l>
					<l>wake me, for I love the Brethren and am very</l>
					<l>glad of their Visits, especially him, who lives</l>
					<l>so near me, and I am allways better after I have</l>
					<l>Seen any of them. Nov: the 12 Br Oxlee visited </l>
					<l>him again; and being asked to pray for him, he </l>
					<l>asked Crispin, what his heart desired most, at</l>
					<l>which he looked up, smiled and sayd: my hearts </l>
					<l>Desire is, to be with my dr Saviour. He spoke</l>
					<l>but low, but one could understand and feel, what</l>
					<l>he said and according to his earnest Request</l>
					<l><note type="catchword">B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></note></l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-04.jpg" n="3"/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Br Oxlee recommended him to the Lambs outstrechd</l>
					<l>arms and bleeding heart with an inexpressible</l>
					<l>feeling. Nov: 19 he grew weaker and weaker and</l>
					<l>being asked: If he would not take any of the Do-</l>
					<l>ctors Medicines &amp; he hereupon answered quite</l>
					<l>loud, saying: It signifies nothing, what I take,</l>
					<l>and you may give me, what ye will, I shall go</l>
					<l>nevertheless go to my dr Savr. Br Hauptmann </l>
					<l>has been to see me, and he has give me some</l>
					<l>thing, which is better, then all the Doctors Stuff</l>
					<l>in the World, meaning the Sacrament of the Corpse</l>
					<l>and Blood of our Savr. </l>
					<l>After that his pains in</l>
					<l>creased more and more, so that he could talk no</l>
					<l>more, but yet was sensible at the time. Nov.</l>
					<l>the 29. notwithstanding his being exceeding weak,</l>
					<l>yet his Disorder, was quite changd from a Severe</l>
					<l>Costiveness to a real Purging, so that there seemd</l>
					<l>to be some hape of his Recovery. They begd much</l>
					<l>that Br Hurlock might come and see him, which </l>
					<l>he soon after did, but found him in such Cir</l>
					<l>cumstances, that he rather despaired of his Re</l>
					<l>covery, But he and the rest of the family were</l>
					<l>much pleased, that he came and saw him. Br</l>
					<l>Oxlee, who came to see him, asked, how he found</l>
					<l>himself, he said: my Brother, perhaps I shall</l>
					<l>not go yet, alltho I should like it, if my dear</l>
					<l>Lamb would call me this night, for I sometimes</l>
					<l>think it long, before he fetches me, but he knows</l>
					<l>best. He was very resignd and notwithstanding</l>
					<l>his violent pain, he sufferd, yet he bore it pa</l>
					<l>tiently and Scarce ever complaind. Dec. 12, Br</l>
					<l>Oxlee visited him again and found him excee</l>
					<l>ding chearfull. He laid hold of his hand, and </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>pulld him down to him to kiss him. He told him</l>
					<l>that he took it very kind that he came so often</l>
					<l>to see him and thankd him many times for it</l>
					<l>He was then a little easier. He was told that </l>
					<l>next Sunday would be the Communion at Grace</l>
					<l>Hall, of which he was very much rejoiced and glad. </l>
					<l>Br Hauptmann came to see him few days after, and </l>
					<l>spoke with him about the insuing feast of the Corpse</l>
					<l>and Blood of our Husband. He found him very </l>
					<l>chearfull &amp; happy and very hungry after the Par</l>
					<l>ticipation of the blessed Communion with the Con</l>
					<l>gregation, The 15. Dec. being Fryday at night</l>
					<l>he alterd very mich for the worse in an instant.</l>
					<l>His Wife perceiving it, asked him, if she Should</l>
					<l>call his Children; he said: Yes. When they came</l>
					<l>in, he was in great pain, notwithstanding that he</l>
					<l>calld them to him, and began to speak tenderly</l>
					<l>to them, as well as his painfull Body and faulte</l>
					<l>ring tongue would admit of. He prayd them and </l>
					<l>even charged them each of them with dying Words</l>
					<l>and weeping Eyes, that they should give themselves </l>
					<l>and cleave to the crucified Saviour, and then rea</l>
					<l>ched out his trembling hand to bless and assure</l>
					<l>them, that if they should cleave to their Saviour</l>
					<l>he would bless them and bring them through, and</l>
					<l>You Betty with all your Children, meaning his</l>
					<l>Daughter, who is married. His poor weeping</l>
					<l>Wife, feeling &amp; seeing that he was going, said:</l>
					<l>Will you go &amp; leave me behind? O says he, cleave to</l>
					<l>the Saviour, cleave to the Savoiur, and I will Soon</l>
					<l>See you again. What, when I come to him? Ay, ay,</l>
					<l>cleave to the Saviour and he will bring You thro.</l>
					<l>He gave her his Hand to confirm it with </l>
					<l><note type="superscript">His</note></l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>					
					<pb xml:id="Ful_3_09_TaylorCrispin-07.jpg" n="4"/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>His Pains growing stronger, he Seemd as if he would</l>
					<l>Ture, to stretch himself. which was into the ever</l>
					<l>lasting Arms and pierced heart of Jesus, where</l>
					<l>he now rests Sweetly and safely, secure and free</l>
					<l>from Sin and earthly Misery.</l>
					<l>F and askd his Wife to assist him, which she willingly</l>
					<l>did: He afterwards seemd as if he would go to Sleep</l>
					<l>His Wife not hearing him breath took, a Candle to</l>
					<l>look at him, and found, that he was really gone</l>
					<l>without the least Sighs or Struggle, looking ex</l>
					<l>ceeding sweet and Smiling, and thus he happily </l>
					<l>departed </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
