<?xml-model href="../../Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Joshua Barker: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>Fulneck, UK</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_58_BarkerJoshua">Joshua Barker</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_58_BarkerJoshua-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_58_BarkerJoshua-01.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2019-06-10" who="#JAKA1">Created file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Joshua Barker</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_58_BarkerJoshua-01.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Departed March 24th 1761</l>
					<l>Our Brother Joshua Barker was born in the Year 1696,</l>
					<l>on the 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> of December at Hopton in the Parish of Mirfield he lived with his</l>
					<l>Father till 19 Years of Age at which time he was put Apprentice to a Broad-Cloth-</l>
					<l>ier in that neighborhood, he was married to his present Widow the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of July</l>
					<l>1719 by whom he has had 8 Childrn two of whom went home in their Infancy</l>
					<l>and one at Mans Estate and of the 5 survising ones, one Son is a member of</l>
					<l>our Society, he liv&apos;d happily with his Wife and being of a religious turn he went</l>
					<l>with his Wife constantly to the Church &amp; Sacrament, and had religious Meet-</l>
					<l>ings kept in his house where they us&apos;d to pray and read Burkets Exposition on</l>
					<l>the new Testament; his self working was for some time in his way, so that to</l>
					<l>be a poor Sinner at the feet of Jesus was a hard matter to him for some time,</l>
					<l>and he was a long time among the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> before he got a feeling of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Dying</l>
					<l>Love in his heart. When Mr Ingham preach&apos;d in the Beginning in these parts</l>
					<l>he went to hear him, his Wife at first was against it; but upon her hearing</l>
					<l>both B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ockertshausen at her own house her Prejudice dropt away and they <add place="above">both</add> went</l>
					<l>both together, he always had a great attachment to the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>, and upon the his</l>
					<l>Land Lords being against the Preaching at his house, he rather left it than com-</l>
					<l>ply with his Desire not to let the Gospel be preach&apos;d there. He soon became</l>
					<l>a Member of our Society, and had the Grace to be receiv&apos;d on the 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of April</l>
					<l>1752 into the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; Nov. 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> in the same year he partook of the highest Good in</l>
					<l>the holy Sacrament for the first time. Within these 2 Years he has occasionally</l>
					<l>said to his Wife I shall not be long here but shall soon be go home, but don&apos;t be trou-</l>
					<l>bled for you will not stay long after me. At the regulating of the Bands and Classes</l>
					<l>anew in January 1760 he became a Bond Servant, in which capacity he was a</l>
					<l>faithfull Helper &amp; belov&apos;d by his B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>, and found a Blessing for his own heart.</l>
					<l>On Monday night the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of November he was taken with a violent and pain-</l>
					<l>full Disorder so that his Disolution was expected before morning, the Vio-</l>
					<l>lence of which was however somewhat abated the next Day when he was visited</l>
					<l>by B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Watson on his return from Huddersfield. He was very chearfull not-</l>
					<l>withstanding his great bodily Pain &amp; in a sinnerlike Connexion with the man</l>
					<l>of Sorrows, whom he said he longed to see face to face, &amp; beg&apos;d him and the </l>
					<l>B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>n to bear him on their hearts, before Him on that account. From his first</l>
					<l>becoming sick he always thought he should yet Permission to leave his mor-</l>
					<l>tal Tent, and from hence be taken the faithfull one to see, at which he</l>
					<l>frequently rejoic&apos;d in his heart, &amp; speaking with a Brother of the great Long-</l>
					<l>ing he felt to be at home with his wounded Friend that only matchless</l>
					<l><note target="catchword">Heart</note></l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
					<div type="page" n="2">
						<head type="page">2</head>
						<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_58_BarkerJoshua-02.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Heart and observing his Wife looked thoughtfull, he said to her when I am</l>
					<l>with him I will speak a good Word for you, that he may soon fetch you also</l>
					<l>and I&apos;m sure he will not deny me my Request and this he comforted her about</l>
					<l>their parting. Soon after the Sacrament, being visited by a B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> he express&apos;d</l>
					<l>his great Longing for that highest Good, in order to strengthen his heart under</l>
					<l>the great bodily pain he felt and declared that the better Death and Passion of</l>
					<l>the Lord Jesus was what his heart rely&apos;d upon and his its only Good for time &amp; </l>
					<l>Eternity. Once being visited he express&apos;d his Desire to be buried with his B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></l>
					<l>at Lambs Hill and seemed grieved that on account of his outward Circumstances</l>
					<l>he must give up that hope but he was soon comforted upon our assuring</l>
					<l>him we wou&apos;d see to it that his desire shou&apos;d be accomplish&apos;d. Jan 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> he had</l>
					<l>his part of the holy Sacrament with some other sick for which End he came on Horse-</l>
					<l>back <del>to the</del> to the Chapel which was the last time of his being there. On the</l>
					<l>Great Sabbath B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Watson carried him the Sacram<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>, and first related <add place="above">to him</add> what</l>
					<l><del>had</del> had pass&apos;d in the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> at G.H. on Maunday Thursday and then <add place="above">in a</add> child-</l>
					<l>like <del>Prayer</del> Prayer beg&apos;d that mouth which spoke his own clean, to speak this</l>
					<l>B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> who could not enjoy the Application of the bloody Gore from his Back in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></l>
					<l>Aeditarium on account of Sickness clean, and to hasten the ripening of this fruit</l>
					<l>of his Deaths Agony &amp; take him home to himself or soon enable him to appear</l>
					<l>again among his B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>. Then he sung: What Lord thee so tormented &amp;c. O led him in</l>
					<l>thy nail holes see his Pardon &amp; Election free &amp;c. Give him absolution, and a gen-</l>
					<l>tle praising Tone, deep Foundation in thy Cross&apos;s Stem, and then during an </l>
					<l>inexpressible tender &amp; melting feeling he receiv&apos;d his share of the holy Sacram<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></l>
					<l>after which he was particularly chearfull and happy and frequently said to his</l>
					<l>Wife, now I have got what I wanted, and seem&apos;d highly blessed. That Night</l>
					<l>was a very painfull night to him and his Disorder very became again very vio-</l>
					<l>lent. On Monday being visited by one of the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> to whom he again signified his</l>
					<l>Longing to be at home which Desire was granted him the next day in the Eve-</l>
					<l>ning about 8o&apos;clock after having lain quiet &amp; still from about 4o&apos;clock with-</l>
					<l>out speaking, he sweetly fell asleep &amp; grew pale on Jesus arm &amp; Bosom, in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></l>
					<l>65<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year of his dying Life, with that Childrens Watch Word; all that</l>
					<l>are in the Graves shall hear his voice. Now there&apos;s no Soul who doth</l>
					<l>not want (ev&apos;n when in her Lords Joy) and doth not quick upon the Grant</l>
					<l>fetch her Corpses revrently.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
