<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memoir</title>
                <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
                <principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
                </principal>
                <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Project Manager</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Developer</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-2020</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
                    <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                    <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Memoirs from the Fulneck Archive</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>			
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_101_Bullock_Brother-01.jpg" n="1"/>
            <p>
            <lb/>Dep<hi rend="superscript:true;">d</hi> Jan. 30, 1764
            <lb/>The Course of Life of the S. B<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>. Bullock
            <lb/>Francis Bullock was born at Heaton Rhodes in the Parish of Bradforth
            <lb/>Sept<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> the 9<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> 1739<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi>, and educated in the Church of England, and
            <lb/>learned the Tanners Business. He was of a very lively Disposition
            <lb/>from his Childhood, and also of a Wild Cast, till he got our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> got
            <lb/>a Hold of his Heart, and this carried him thro' his Childrens and
            <lb/>Boys years without any abiding concern or uneasiness of Mind except
            <lb/>ing at certain times yet there were certain Times when he was
            <lb/>much distressed &amp; exceeding anxious about himself, &amp; was seized
            <lb/>with such a Fear of being Lost that he knew not what to do with
            <lb/>himself, and this Uneasiness has frequently continued 3 or 4
            <lb/>Days &amp; Nights together, but in Time he always shook it off again, by one
            <lb/>Means or other, But altho he was so sprightly &amp; had such an
            <lb/>active Soul, he had also something of a bashful Nature, &amp;
            <lb/>which probably might prove beneficial for to him in many Respects,
            <lb/>for he was preserved pretty much from the Wickedness of the
            <lb/>Times &amp; places he lived in, notwithstanding the Temptations and
            <lb/>Snares he was exposed to. On Easter Sunday 1761 his Curiosity
            <lb/>led him to this place, and during the preaching his Heart was
            <lb/>touched by our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> in a Manner it never had been before, &amp; this
            <lb/>day he looked upon as the Days of his special Call on which our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>
            <lb/>gave him a special Call to become his property; &amp; from this Day
            <lb/>all his old Matters vanished and departed from him &amp; his Connexion
            <lb/>therewith was broken, and his Concern was, to make his Calling sure.
            <lb/>He then wanted to get acquainted with the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi>, but being an entire
            <lb/>Stranger to them knew not how, but made application for permissi
            <lb/>on to go to our Boys School for a few weeks, &amp; this being granted, he
            <lb/>frequented the Childrens Meetings, which proved a Blessing to him &amp;
            <lb/>by this thus he also got an Opportunity to become acquainted with
            <lb/>the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rns</hi> which he esteemed highly. He was rec<hi rend="superscript:true;">d</hi> into the Society at the
            <lb/>next Society Lovefeast, but thinking his Call to be to the Cong<hi rend="superscript:true;">n</hi> he could
            </p>
            <pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_101_Bullock_Brother-02.jpg" n="2"/>
            <p>
            <lb/>not dispose his Mind to settle any longer in the World, and therefore ear
            <lb/>nestly &amp; frequently expressed his Desire to be delivered have the Favour
            <lb/>to live in the Choir House, and which our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> granted him in the same
            <lb/>year viz Nov<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> 9<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> 1761. As we have not his Business is not carried on, in our place he was
            <lb/>necessitated to learn something else &amp; accordingly learned the Wool
            <lb/>Combing business. Here in the Choir House the 
            <lb/> dear holy ghost taught him by Degrees more and more the knowledge
            <lb/>of himself, however he got also a Confidence in our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>, and a certain
            <lb/>assurance that He loved him, and would receive him out of mere Grace
            <lb/>as his property. It was also perceptible to us that our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> had a particular
            <lb/>Hand over him, and had himself numbered him to his people, &amp; on Jan. 1<hi rend="superscript:true;">st</hi>
            <lb/>1763 his Right &amp; Title to the Family of our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> was confirmed to him
            <lb/>by Reception into the Cong<hi rend="superscript:true;">n</hi>. The Spring following he he was sickly
            <lb/>which continued growing upon him till he was obliged to give over
            <lb/>working, and after having rested a little he proposed seeking after
            <lb/>work at his own Business, thinking it might be best for his Health
            <lb/>but upon a Representation of the Danger to which he might expose him
            <lb/>self, and the Loss he would Sustain in not having the continual Opportu
            <lb/>nity to have Fellowship with his B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi>, he declined it, &amp; begged Pardon. Having
            <lb/>been pointed out by our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> to go to Bedford be Cook in the S. B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rns</hi> House
            <lb/>in Bedford, and having, according to Appearance recruited his strength
            <lb/>a little, he went thither July the 6<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> 1763, but soon became sick &amp; unfit
            <lb/>to do that business, &amp; therefore returned to us again Sep<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> ye 8<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> the same
            <lb/>Year, and was very weak, &amp; it seemed as if his Disorder was a Consumption.
            <lb/>His Father desired the B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi> to let him come to his House w<hi rend="superscript:true;">ch</hi> is near Fulneck for a While, thinking
            <lb/>that the Circumstances there might be full as suitable for him, &amp; as he
            <lb/>himself had nothing against it, the Request was considered of &amp; granted
            <lb/>but he was soon clear that being at his Fathers House would not help him
            <lb/>&amp; that this sickness was intended for his being taken to our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> &amp; which he
            <lb/>rejoiced at. He was then very sorry that he was not in his Choir House, &amp;
            <lb/>then in the midst of his B<hi rend="superscript:true;">rn</hi> &amp; several Circumstances in his Fathers House
            <lb/>were heavy to him, however, he cleaved to our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> &amp; had him for his Support
            <lb/>&amp; Companion. He was frequently visited, &amp; many blessed Bands were
            <lb/>kept with him. Our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> manifested himself more fully to his Heart
            <lb/>than ever before, &amp; he spent his Time in a melted Sinnerlike
            <lb/>disposition (nor did any Thing give him Trouble him so much
            </p>
            <pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_101_Bullock_Brother-03.jpg" n="3"/>
            <p>
            <lb/>as that he had not attainted to the Enjoyment of the Lords Body &amp;
            <lb/>Blood in the holy Communion with the Cong<hi rend="superscript:true;">n</hi>, but which he often
            <lb/>spoke about and wished for, but which we could not well think
            <lb/>of on Account of his situation.) During this Sickness which lasted
            <lb/>pretty long, his constant wish was that our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> might soon come
            <lb/>and take him to himself, &amp; which he expressed with a tender Feeling
            <lb/>and many Tears, and not long before his Departure he broke
            <lb/>out in Converse with our Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> in a very pathetic Manner,
            <lb/>saying, "My dear Sav<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi>, I am poor, yea a very poor One, &amp; am
            <lb/>not worthy that thou shouldst take the least Notice of me;
            <lb/>but what shall I say? Thou hast accepted me of me, and
            <lb/>forgiven me all, &amp; last washed &amp; cleansed me in thy preci
            <lb/>ous Blood, &amp; now I wait with longing for the Hour when
            <lb/>thou will take me to thyself: Come Lord Jesus &amp; take me."
            <lb/>which Desire was granted on the 30<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> (Jan) about 8
            <lb/>o'Clock in the Morning, having spent in the 25<hi rend="superscript:true;">th</hi> year
            <lb/>of his mortal Life.
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>