<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Elizabeth Clagget: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget">Elizabeth Clagget</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-12.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-13.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Elizabeth Clagget</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>NAME</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-01.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>This is a memoir of</l>
							<l>S S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Elizt Claggett.</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<l>She has left in her Choir house a good odour behind her,</l>
							<l>so that those who were acquainted with <del>her</del>, and had an</l>
							<l>opportunity to converse with her, will always retain a</l>
							<l>blessed remembrance of the grace which our dear</l>
							<l>Lord had bestowed upon her.</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<l>Tho&apos; she has not, for some time past, frequent<hi rend="superscript">ed</hi> the meetings</l>
							<l>on acct of her disorder, yet it was remarkable that she</l>
							<l>always had a feeling &amp; partook <add place="above">of</add> those blessings which</l>
							<l>were enjoyed by the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> or her Choir, and would speak</l>
							<l>of it to the S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> as if she had been in the meeting.</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<l>Some <del>short</del> time before her dissolution, her peculiar</l>
							<l>disposition, namely a shyness to see or speak w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> any but</l>
							<l>a few particular friends, went to an extreme, but</l>
							<l>this served to her greater humiliation, and she became</l>
							<l>so loving, that she could not sufficiently express her</l>
							<l>gratitude, love &amp; thankfulness to all about her,</l>
							<l>often repeating: I love &amp; think you, I love &amp; thank</l>
							<l>you all. and desired often those who came to her to</l>
							<l>kiss her. It was a great pleasure to be with her in</l>
							<l>her last days, the Serenity &amp; happiness of her heart, not</l>
							<l>withstanding her great pains, made her sick room</l>
							<l>pleasant, tho her disorder would else have been very</l>
							<l>disagreeable to the outw<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> senses of those who came into</l>
							<l>the room. At last, her long &amp; ardent wish to be dissolved</l>
							<l>and with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> came happily to pass on the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></l>
							<l>Inst; with a sensible feeling of her Bridegroom&apos;s</l>
							<l>Nearess, &amp; w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the blessd of her Choir in the 52<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Yr of</l>
							<l>her age.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>I was born in Yorkshire in the year 1715 where I staid with my</l>
							<l>Mothers Relations till the year 20 in which my Mother came &amp; fetch&apos;d me</l>
							<l>to London. I remember to have head some Influences of Grace even in my</l>
							<l>Infant years, but when I was about 14 Years of age, I came under strong</l>
							<l>Convictions. in the rights I was sometimes so terrified, that I thought I</l>
							<l>realy heard the Trumpet give the Signal of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> coming to Judgment.</l>
							<l>I believed I shou&apos;d be in the Number of those who would call on the Rocks</l>
							<l>&amp; mountains to cover them. I made repeated Resolutions of devoting my fu</l>
							<l>ture life if God shou&apos;d spare me a little longer, to his Service. I began to be</l>
							<l>pretty diligent in Prayer, both publick &amp; private, &amp; in the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year of my Age</l>
							<l>having now read in Invitation from one of my Aunts in Yorkshire a religi</l>
							<l>ous woman, to go &amp; stay some Time with her; having first intreated the Lord</l>
							<l>with many Tears, that he wou&apos;d direct this affair, I ask&apos;d &amp; obtaind leave of</l>
							<l>my Father &amp; Mother to go. She encouraged &amp; instructed me as will as she</l>
							<l>could, which I prosicuted in my way, but was never satisfied. when I</l>
							<l>was 17 years old, I went to the Sacrament in the Church of England, for the</l>
							<l>first Time. I was near 19 years old when I returnd back to London, where</l>
							<l>I still continued a kind of religious course, but the Gayeties and Divertions of</l>
							<l>the Town, strongly took hold of my Heart, till in my 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> year, when I got such</l>
							<l>a sense of the total Depravity of my nature, that I believ&apos;d the very marrow of</l>
							<l>my Bones was <add place="above">infected</add> with sin. I had never heard of any ones being awakend</l>
							<l>nor did I know there was such a Thing; so I concluded there was not another</l>
							<l>such vile wretch existing as my self. I got various Books of Devotion</l>
							<l>but cou&apos;d not use any of them; so I concluded they were not calculated for</l>
							<l>such a Creature as I. I then betook myself to David&apos;s Psalms, &amp; from thence</l>
							<l>collected sentences &amp; to Compild Prayers which express&apos;d the Language of my</l>
							<l>Heart. I often fell prostrate on the Floor &amp; with Floods of Tears, lamented</l>
							<l>my wretched state; some-Times I had a Glimmering of hope; these words often</l>
							<l>aleviated my distress &quot;perfect Love casts out Fear, for Fear hath Tor</l>
							<l>ment, to which my heart answerd &quot;Yes Lord, that Fear hath Torment I know</l>
							<l>very well, if there be a Love which casts it out, bestow it upon me.</l>
							<l>another Text also was much in my mind; Except ye eat the Flesh of the</l>
							<l>Son of man &amp; drink his blood ye have no Life in you: to which my Heart</l>
							<l>replied &quot;where shall I get this Blood? Why in the Sacrament, but that I dare</l>
							<l>not partake of lest I eat &amp; drink my own Damnation. (I had intirely left</l>
							<l>off going to the Sacrament, since I came to a sense of my Sinful Nature).</l>
							<l>One Day meditating about that Blood, I resolved on a Saints day to go to</l>
							<l>St Lawrances Church, &amp; by when I come there if I cou&apos;d venture to go to the</l>
							<l>Sacrament, I chose that Place rather than my own Parish Church, for my Friends</l>
							<l>&amp; acquaintance already thought I was out of my Senses, so I concealed every Thing</l>
							<l>which had the appearance of Religion as much as I could. accordingly I went to</l>
							<l>the above mentioned Church: after the first Service I remained dubious whether</l>
							<l>I shou&apos;d stay the Sacrament or not; I then opend my common Prayer Book on</l>
							<l>these Words of the Psalms, &quot;unto the wicked faith God, why dost thou teach</l>
							<l>my Laws or take my Covenant into thy mouth. with this I was quite stund &amp;</l>
							<l>thus I went directly <del>out of the Church</del> home, &amp; then to my chamber, where I</l>
							<l>fell prostrate, &amp; silently pourd forth Streams of Tears. I went on in a</l>
							<l>disconsolate Solitary way conversing but little with any one; at length I con</l>
							<l>tracted some acquaintance with an old women who was a Presbyterian</l>
							<l>She some-Times spoke words of Consolation to me, tho&apos; I afterwards believ&apos;d</l>
							<l>she herself did not understand them. In my 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> year, during the Passion Week</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-03.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>week I enjoid a particular serenity of mind. being wearied of my own strive</l>
							<l>ings, &amp; finding my last Resolutions to be but vain; I steid my self in some mea</l>
							<l>sure upon Grace &amp; Mercy, hopeing it might extend even to me. in this week</l>
							<l>I visited that Woman, I told for of my desire to go to the Sacrament, &amp; also</l>
							<l>related my Scruples, the encouraged me to venture, saying I shou&apos;d thereby</l>
							<l>get strength &amp; nourishment to pursue my future course. I thought tho&apos;</l>
							<l>our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r </hi>would not accept of me before, perhaps he will now; so I con</l>
							<l>cluded that if the same stillness &amp; compoture of mind, I then enjoyd</l>
							<l>continued till Sunday I would venture: it continued, &amp; on Easter Sunday I</l>
							<l>arose in a calm bowedness of Heart, &amp; went to the early Sacrament</l>
							<l>which was kept at my own Parish Church. At receiving of the Bread &amp; </l>
							<l>Wine, an awe seized one, so that my Hand trembled greatly, which caused</l>
							<l>the Minnister to stare <del>at stare</del> at me, but the Love, Peace &amp; Joy which</l>
							<l>in those moments took Possession of my Soul, words cannot express.</l>
							<l>I return&apos;d home so chearful lightsome &amp; happy, that it seem&apos;d to me as</l>
							<l>if I went on Wings. being come Home I met with many Things not very agre</l>
							<l>able, but so passionate as I used to be before, now nothing disturbed me;</l>
							<l>I loved every Body to exceedingly that <add place="above">I thought</add> I could have laid down &amp; let them</l>
							<l>tread upon one. I long&apos;d to be again at Church out of the Sight &amp; hearing of</l>
							<l>Earthly Things, to thither I went again at 10 O&apos;Clock, my Heart was in such a</l>
							<l>desolveing condition that the Tears would now &amp; then Start out of my Eyes, which</l>
							<l>the People observing, told my Relations that now I was indeed gone out of</l>
							<l>my senses for I had Wept at Church; which oblig&apos;d me to get a retired Seat</l>
							<l>among ordinary Old People. In the Nights my Heart would be singing Hosan</l>
							<l>as &amp; Hallelujahs, for I knew not right what to sing or say, nor what had hap</l>
							<l>pen&apos;d to me; other Things as well as my self seemd alterd, &amp; the Scriptures</l>
							<l>as if I had never read them before, but for all this I had Times of Hea</l>
							<l>viness, &amp; if my Feeling was long withdrawn, even of doubting of my Sal</l>
							<l>vation. soon after this a poor Woman <add place="above">coming</add>
								<del>came</del> to my Fathers House to begg</l>
							<l>some relief for her Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> who was ill of a Cancer in her Breast, I had a desire</l>
							<l>to visit the Sick Person, &amp; accordingly went to her Lodging, there I for the first</l>
							<l>time saw Bro<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hutton who was then in his Apprenticeship, &amp; thro&apos; his means I</l>
							<l>become acqainted with Whitefield Wesleys &amp; others of the Methodists, among</l>
							<l>whom I continued till in the year 1740 when the Bre<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> began their Labour</l>
							<l>in England. I knew directly that they were the People for me, since which</l>
							<l>Time I adhered to them entirely. in June 1742 I went with great Reluctance</l>
							<l>but in compliance with my Fathers commands to spend the Summer with</l>
							<l>the rest of our Family at Broadoaks in Essex, I had been there 2 or 3</l>
							<l>Weeks when as Sitting alone in my Room, our Savr presented himself to</l>
							<l>my Heart in his bleeding Wounded Form, &amp; brought me into such a converse</l>
							<l>with his own dear person, as I had never known before, then it was that</l>
							<l>my heart went over to Him, then I was willing to live any where, or be any</l>
							<l>Thing what might be most pleasing to him. His Blood his Death &amp; Almigh</l>
							<l>by Atonement has since that blest Intercouse, remaind my neverfailing</l>
							<l>Source of Comfort &amp; Consolation, in all Trials &amp; Vicissitudes whatsoever.</l>
							<l>his Wounds &amp; bitter Passion, his Death was my confession, &amp; shall be</l>
							<l>till my Eye-Strings break. The Bre<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> rejoied much at my return to</l>
							<l>London at all the Grace our dear Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> had bestowed on me. In June 1742</l>
							<l>my Father having departed this Life, I went by the Direction of the</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Bre<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> to the Childrens Oeconomy in Lambs-Inn, where I</l>
							<l>lived with the bigger Girls. Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I returnd to London, &amp; on the</l>
							<l>30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of the some Instant, that ever memorable day, I was present at the</l>
							<l>settling of the London Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>: what we felt at that time I suppose will by</l>
							<l>no Body be forgot who was there till beyond the Grave, I thought, this is</l>
							<l>none other but the House of God, &amp; here are the Gates of Heaven! There</l>
							<l>I got my incontestable Call, to be visibly united to that Body. on</l>
							<l>the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> day next following, I was rec&apos;d (viz) on Christmass Day </l>
							<l>1743, &amp; had the Favour of being admitted to the <del>Sacrament</del> next follow</l>
							<l>ing Sacrament, which I think to have been Jan. 1743.</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<l>I assisted in the Labour amongst the Single Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> in London according</l>
							<l>to my Small abillity till June 1743 where I was sent by the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> into</l>
							<l>Yorkshire, to have the joint Care of the Single Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Choir there with</l>
							<l>my Sister Susanna &amp; Sister Lloid. In June 1744 I was blest for the</l>
							<l>Office of Vorestehr of the said Choir, &amp; in Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> following, I rec&apos;d the</l>
							<l>blessing for the office I afterwards held amongst the Single Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>, during</l>
							<l>every anointed Prayer of Bror Martin Dobers. In that situation I continued</l>
							<l>till my state of health render&apos;d me incapable of serving my dear Sisters</l>
							<l>as I had hithertoo done; I then sent my Petitions to dear Mammagen</l>
							<l>&amp; Anna Johanna to send a Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> from Germany to supply my Place</l>
							<l>which was at length granted in the year 1748 to the entire satisfac</l>
							<l>tion of my Heart. I laid down my Office at our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Feet with</l>
							<l>more Inclination than I had at first to receive it, <add place="above">being now more unable to fulfill it</add> yet awefully con</l>
							<l>ciding how he might have look&apos;d upon my poor services; and if his</l>
							<l>Heart cou&apos;d upon the whole be satisfied with them? His friendly Counte</l>
							<l>nance cheard me, I begd his absolation for all my Faults Failings,</l>
							<l>&amp; Mistakes, &amp; thus with a throughly comforted &amp; contented Heart I</l>
							<l>enterd into my wish&apos;d for Sabbatick State, I was desirious to go to</l>
							<l>the then now settled Oeconomy at little-moor, hopeing a charge of air</l>
							<l>might be of Service to me where I continued near a year, &amp; realy</l>
							<l>did grow a little better, having rec&apos;d a Letter from my dear Mammagen</l>
							<l>(who was not quite satisfied with my betakeing any self wholy to sick</l>
							<l>ness &amp; Retirement) wherein she mentiond in the most loving &amp; kind</l>
							<l>manner, that she shou&apos;d like to have me go to Duckenfield &amp; do what</l>
							<l>I could amongst the Single Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> there: I laid the matter before our</l>
							<l>Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, &amp; found that notwithstanding the seeming Impossibillity of my</l>
							<l>performing the Journey, my heart was never easey, but when I thought</l>
							<l>of going: thus I came to a Resolution, &amp; having had a blessed Journey</l>
							<l>I arrived there May 1749: from whence I return&apos;d with the whole</l>
							<l>Oeconomy of Sis<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1750. The Bre<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> favour&apos;d
								me</l>
							<l>with one of the Houses on Lambs-Hill, where I lived</l>
							<l>chearful &amp; contented only in an exceeding poor state of Health</l>
							<l>till Feb<hi rend="superscript">ry</hi> 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1753 when I come into the dear Choir-House.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-04.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Here I conclude <add place="above">with</add>
								<del>being persuaded that my season? of life</del></l>
							<l>[Illegible]</l>
							<l>[Illegible] <del>I will only add</del>
							</l>
							<l>my Thanks to all who have <add place="above">had compasion on</add> my very ail</l>
							<l>ing &amp; sickly Tabernacle; and <del>all who</del> have shewn <add place="above">me</add> kindness in Time</l>
							<l>of need, God reward them for it.</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<l>Elizabeth Clagett</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-12.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Our <del>late</del> happily departed D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Laboured under a heavy com</l>
							<l>plication of Disorders for many years, w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> together with ye pecularities of</l>
							<l>her Disposision greatly obstructed <del>that social</del>
								<add place="above">her</add> fellowship &amp; intercourse <add place="above"><del>with</del> with others</add> in</l>
							<l>general; wch was especialy regretted by her choir, so <del>wm</del> many of w<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> she had been</l>
							<l>an annointed Instrument of comfort <del>&amp; consolation as well</del> as edification, &amp;</l>
							<l>a blessed Nurseing Mother in their first awakening. her Maternal</l>
							<l>affectionate concern for ye wellfare &amp; prosperity of the whole Congn &amp;</l>
							<l>particularly that of her Choir, <del>emently</del> she retain&apos;d <add place="above">in the greatest degree</add> thro&apos; various Tryals,</l>
							<l><unclear>doinges</unclear> &amp; vicitudes; so that it was evident <add place="above">that</add> nothing <del>so sensibly</del> affected</l>
							<l>her <add place="above">so sensible</add> as when painful Circumstances occur&apos;d Here &amp; There, either in ye whole, or in</l>
							<l>part or <del>in</del> with individuals; <del>wch has been more conspicuous</del>
								<add place="above">and this has been more evident</add> since her more close</l>
							<l>retirement; in w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> beside her constant happy intercourse with <add place="above">her</add> slaughtered friend;</l>
							<l>she diligently entertained her self with our ever memorable d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Disciple&apos;s Discourses</l>
							<l>w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> she esteem&apos;d ye most consolatory delicaces on this side eternity</l>
							<l>tarying 13 years, 6 months &amp; 11 Days of her abode in her <del>dr loved</del>
								<add place="above">beloved</add> Choir-</l>
							<l>House; she has enjoy&apos;d a Sabattic season, as a poor, frail, disordered</l>
							<l>human Creature, truely sensible of her election of Grace, <del>admireing</del> rejoicing at</l>
							<l>her free salvation, charmd &amp; captivated with ye wounded Person of <add place="above">of her dear Lord</add></l>
							<l> her so faithful Lover. <del>Here</del> she has conducted her</l>
							<l>self as a d<hi rend="superscript">r </hi>Handmaid of Jesus, &amp; as a Pristess of God; but, not</l>
							<l>withstanding this her <add place="above">happy condition</add> as a virgin of yr Lamb, she had many</l>
							<l>weaknesses, Faults &amp; imperfections; w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>
								<del>also</del> she was truely sensible</l>
							<l>of &amp; served for matter of great <del>humbling</del>
								<add place="above">humiliation</add> to her naturally high Spirit.</l>
							<l><del>wch however</del> Grace alone had brought <add place="above">her spirit</add> into Subjection, &amp; set her above</l>
							<l><del>that</del>
								<add place="above">everything</add> false, crooked &amp; designing <del>spirit of dissimulation so prevalent in</del></l>
							<l><del>Ignoble Souls</del>. She <add place="above">had very good &amp; strong natural parts and was</add>
								<del>as she was</del></l>
							<l>which made us regret that she was rendered unfit for publick service thro&apos; her disorder</l>
							<l><del>also</del> a Gifted Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
								<del>what</del> her real Charactor <del>cannot be more justly</del></l>
							<l><del>express&apos;d then in ye following Verses.</del> 2d. p. 171. 3d. 7. &amp; 8 </l>
						</lg></p>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<note>This verse is struck through with a single vertical line</note>
							<l>A Mind to Lowliness inclined;</l>
							<l>A Gall-less Dove&apos;s unspotted mind;</l>
							<l>A mind that strives untir&apos;d</l>
							<l>For a true spiritual Frame</l>
							<l>Shut up herein, that poor I am,</l>
							<l>From hurtful Fancies far retir&apos;d.</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="2">
							<note>This verse is struck through with several vertical lines</note>
							<l>To Souls who know that Mystery,</l>
							<l>Joyful to look upon &amp; see,</l>
							<l>our Love how much He can;</l>
							<l>For comfort of the amaz&apos;d with Guilt</l>
							<l>We Children from the bottom spoilt,</l>
							<l>In Jesus now a finish&apos;d Man;</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<note>These words are written on the right hand side of page, and struck through with several vertical lines.</note>
							<l><del>changes &amp;</del></l>
							<l><del>vicissitudes</del></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb n="6" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_57Clagget-13.jpg" />
					<note>Each text block on this page is struck through with a single vertical line.</note>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>entirely serious, Childlike too;</l>
							<l>In all Essentials fix&apos;d &amp; True;</l>
							<l>An ear that one may trust;</l>
							<l>A hearty genuine Sister&apos;s heart</l>
							<l>To Sympathize with every smart</l>
							<l>w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> chance sometimes &apos;mong Sister&apos;s must.</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<l>In her Choir House the has defused an odorous perfume of that</l>
							<l>sacred unction wherewith her Chast Soul was distingushingly</l>
							<l>parvaded <add place="above">she</add> w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> will forever remain as a fragrant Savour in ye deep</l>
							<l>recesses of those Hearts who had ye <del>happiness</del> pleasure of her more intimate</l>
							<l>union &amp; connection: nor can we by any means leave unremark&apos;d,</l>
							<l>that notwithstanding, <add place="above">this</add> our venebable Sister, did not lately <del>frequent</del></l>
							<l>Personaly frequent ye meetings, on account of indisposision) yet</l>
							<l>her lively spirit happily partook of those divine sensitive Breezes</l>
							<l>in each; w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> to ye admiration of her Intimates, she wou&apos;d distinctly</l>
							<l>communicate. *</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<l>*some short time before this our dear Sister&apos;s approaching</l>
							<l>dissolution was so perceptable to us: (tho, she her self had some</l>
							<l>inkling of it) her pecular natural dispossion prevailed,</l>
							<l>to an extreem; w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>, afterwards served to her <del>great</del> deeper</l>
							<l>humiliation, so that she was altogether incapable of expressing</l>
							<l>her unfaigned gratitude, Love &amp; thankfulness to all about her,</l>
							<l>often repeating: I love &amp; thank you, I love &amp; thank you all!</l>
							<l>w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> she tenderly seal&apos;d with ye warmest kisses.</l>
						</lg></p>
					<p><lg>
							<l>She had many years earnestly long&apos;d &amp; panted for her happy Dismision</l>
							<l>w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>, on ye 12 instant came Blessedly to pass, in ye sweet nearness</l>
							<l>of her D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> eternal spouse, &amp; ye Blessing of her Choir, in ye</l>
							<l>52<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> year of <del>dying</del>
								<add place="above">mortal</add> Life.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
