<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Martha Adkinson: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-2020</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Memoirs from the Fulneck Archive</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Esther Clerk</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<head>Esther Clerk</head>
			<div>
				<pb facs="#facs_1" n="1"/>
			<p>
            <lb/>London th
            <lb/>1718
            <lb/>I think my dear Brn &amp; Srs will Like to
            <lb/>hear Somthing of my Course thro this time which
            <lb/>I gladly do, what may be to the Honour of my Dr Savir
            <lb/>I was Born at Kirton in Lincolnshire
            <lb/>my parants died when I was young so was left
            <lb/>an orphan to providence or to my dr. Creator
            <lb/>and Savir for whom I was Born destined Shurely.
            <lb/>To tell my Dr Brn &amp; Srs of the goodness, the mercy
            <lb/>and kindness, The love and faithfulness of my Dr
            <lb/>Lord and Savir to me a poor Child, my weak words
            <lb/>fall very short to Express the praise that is due
            <lb/>to Him, from he, for his wonders have been without
            <lb/>tale or end, thanks, thousand thanks be, to the
            <lb/>Lamb for ever, and ever.
            <lb/>But I will endeavour to recollect Some particu
            <lb/>lars of the tender leading of my gracious and most
            <lb/>faithful Lord I coud fill a Book which I woud
            <lb/>gladly do to the praise of Him who desires much more
            <lb/>than I can give the furst Impression of grace
            <lb/>I remember was when about 4 years old.
            <lb/>kneeling by a chair with a Book in which was that
            <lb/>words Seek and ye Shall find knock and it shall
            <lb/>be opend unto you I felt Somthing particular at ye time
            <lb/>I had a very quick understanding for my years
            <lb/>and a very Sencible feeling of what was right and
            <lb/>wrong I wanded to be a good child that I might
            <lb/>go to Heaven on that acct I was much praised
            <lb/>which woud have been more hurtful to me But the
            <lb/>Dr. Holy Ghost who had begun his work in my
            <lb/>heart Shewd me Continualy my wicked and sinful
            <lb/>Nature which kept me low and Consious that I
            <lb/>did not deserve that praise, which was a grace to me
            <lb/>at that time</p>
				<pb facs="#facs_2" n="2"/>
				<p>
            <lb/>of it Checked by Satanick pride which I felt very
            <lb/>Sencible, yet from many Circumstances I thought god
            <lb/>must love me, But how it was I coud not tel, I was
            <lb/>a Sinner. In my 11 year was very thoughtful and
            <lb/>Destrest felt guilt with another Impression that I did
            <lb/>not love God, nor coud not praise Him which one
            <lb/>time a little Bird was made use of to Shew me that I
            <lb/>coud not praise my Creator even as a Bird. I had
            <lb/>also Strange Ideas about Him what Form he shud
            <lb/>have and was much perplext about it but by a Dream
            <lb/>I thought God almighty was in a parlour in a
            <lb/>House where I was and that he was a man I
            <lb/>was glad, then I thought one coud be Familliar
            <lb/>with him But not understanding the gracious
            <lb/>leading of my Dear Saviour, I continued Extreamly
            <lb/>Destrest thought I comitted Sin every moment by the
            <lb/>Strange thoughts I had, and thay was of Such a nature
            <lb/>I coud not tel them to any Body nor woud thay under
            <lb/>stood me, but weried indeed with trying to help
            <lb/>my self, a thought came in my mind as I cant
            <lb/>help these thoughts God almighty has nothing
            <lb/>against me, in that moment my Compassionate Saviour
            <lb/>drew near with his love and mercy gave me peace
            <lb/>and as if he had Said to me I have nothing against
            <lb/>thee I was amaized, but didnt how to acct for it, to be
            <lb/>lovd by God <hi rend="strikethrough:true;">and</hi> in Such a manner, from that time
            <lb/>when those thoughts came again I coud believe he had
            <lb/>nothing against me for it, but not understanding the
            <lb/>right poor Sinner path, I came into an Extream
            <lb/>Self rightious Course Striveing with all my might to be
            <lb/>good, by other means then Jesus Blood I got into fast
            <lb/>ing and praying wanting to be as good as the primitive
            <lb/>Christians and I did not like any one Shud he Better then
            <lb/>my self here my Satinck pride shewd it self to a great de
            <lb/>gree <unclear>as</unclear> how unwilling I was to be Saved by Grace. I went
            <lb/>on in this course in a provdential manner I came to London
            <lb/>for my Aunt who Brought up died and I became second
            <lb/>time can orphan She treated me as if she had know my
            <lb/>Destination</p>
				<p>
            <lb/>all wonder of my Dr Saviours love which I did not then under
            <lb/>stand, and it woud be to tedious here to relate, I was in my
            <lb/>14 year when I came to London into Lady Scarbro
            <lb/>Family who Sent for me to wait on her little neice
            <lb/>and my dear Savr gave it into her heart from the furst moment
            <lb/>to be remarkable kind to me as a <unclear>made</unclear> and the whole Family Shewd
            <lb/>great regard and respect for my religous turn of mind
            <lb/>which felt was Sincere (not on Acct of outward gifts
            <lb/>or qualification) but the Dr Holy Ghost in whose School
            <lb/>I then was, gave me a constant sence of my depraved
            <lb/>Nature in all it Shapes, and finding I fell so far short
            <lb/>of that I thought I Shud be, this kept me low and in
            <lb/>some Sense Humble, and kept the Ballance against
            <lb/>that hurtful praise which is often given
            <lb/>I also lived in other Family till I was about 27 such
            <lb/>as Lord Orrory, whose little Daughter I waited on
            <lb/>at Ld Scarbrough, he married and took me with her home
            <lb/>Ld Charlot Edwin and with a Daughter of the Duke
            <lb/>of Buckelugh and how my Dr Savr and great faithful
            <lb/>Shepherd Kept me thro with all my Imperfections
            <lb/>So wonderfuly, So that if I may Humble Say so, I found
            <lb/>favour with God, and man, but I nor no body els thought
            <lb/>what was <unclear>preparing</unclear> for me In my 26 year I returnd to
            <lb/>Ld Scarbro who always recd me of my mother with uncommon
            <lb/>regard, at this time I begun again into self working to and
            <lb/>amaizing degree by prayer and fasting so was <unclear>weried</unclear>
            <lb/>of a Great House may be this way in the year 42 It
            <lb/><unclear>Hapend once when at prayer I felt Somthing very Blessed in</unclear>
            <lb/><unclear>it was quick like the Shooting of a Star but it was my all</unclear>
            <lb/>that was good it was light, peace, joy, all Hapiness in one
            <lb/>moment, I thought it was the Holy Spirit, and woud pray
            <lb/>to feel more of it, soon after I red a letter <hi rend="strikethrough:true;">coming</hi> concerning
            <lb/>the preaching of the Methodists which I had never heard, for 
            <lb/>I was so Biggoted to the Church and it a Shame to go any where its
            <lb/>and was my Eggarans of any other profession but now I thought
            <lb/>I will inquire about them, So it Hapened a Methodist came in my
            <lb/>way and in hearing what was said I was convince of what I want
            <lb/>ed the knowledge of the atonement of our Savr for my Sins
            <lb/>that all his gracious leading was Brought to my mind, so that I
            <lb/>know it was a truth from god, the person lent me a Sermon
            <lb/>Book of Mr Whitfield the more I read the more it was opend</p>
				<pb facs="#facs_3" n="3"/>
				<p>
            <lb/>opend to me my case that I wanted a Saviour my mind took
            <lb/>a turn and I found <unclear>???</unclear> from my Heavy Labour and Savr that
            <lb/>it was this Rightiousnes that I wanted Now I Entered with my
            <lb/>whole mind in the matter, got all the Books I coud of that kind
            <lb/>amongst the Rest I got the Brn little Hymn Book which Suited
            <lb/>me exceedingly Especially one verse viz If I a glimse in my
            <lb/>own Breast feel of  Christians Bliss. then on the truth of
            <lb/>it let me rest that such a life there is. at length my good
            <lb/>Ld found I had got Methodist Books but did not think I was
            <lb/>To deep in the Matter for She had a Better opinion of me then
            <lb/>I woud follow such people but one time being with her at Court
            <lb/>She caught me reading a letter which she took from me where
            <lb/>She found I been once at the Tabernacls. She was much
            <lb/>concernd and took the greatst pains posible to deswade
            <lb/>me from it but I was Devinely convince of the truth
            <lb/>of the Gospel and never waverd one moment, my Lady
            <lb/>forbid me going, I told her I woud not with out leting her
            <lb/>know and I thought I could do with Books here the Family
            <lb/>went into the Country where was a good friend a Minister
            <lb/>who took great pains to prevent me going So Deep in
            <lb/>those things Brought me many Books but to no purpose
            <lb/>my heart was <hi rend="strikethrough:true;">convince</hi> <unclear>assurd</unclear> of the truth, we returnd to London
            <lb/>and I grew very unease and found I coud not do with out
            <lb/>going to here the preaching so Desired leave which coud
            <lb/>not he granted. my good Lady was now very much De
            <lb/>stress about me. She wanted very much to keep me, and
            <lb/>out of love and kindness she did her utmost to prevent it
            <lb/>She wanted me again to be advised by Some Minister I Chose
            <lb/>the Bishop of Oxford  Sackis I was so clear in my
            <lb/>matter and truth of it, I feard nothing I went with my Bro
            <lb/>who accused me of leaveing the Church I said it was
            <lb/>because thay didnt preach of our Saviour Sufferings
            <lb/>and I was fully assured that nothing would Save me, this was
            <lb/>aproved of as to good works I said to the Bishops when
            <lb/>the Tree is good the fruit will be good he was very
            <lb/>tender with me Saw I was Sincere, <hi rend="strikethrough:true;">and</hi> if it was possible I
            <lb/>was more confirmd in my point my Dear Lady was
            <lb/>disapointed and much to be pitied but I could not help it.
            <lb/>here she rested, she had done all she coud, but my Matter
            <lb/>remained to leave hir, or have leave to go to the preaching
            <lb/>at last I coud do no longer So went to here the preaching,
            <lb/>and I was wanted before I got home, my Lady askt me
            <lb/>where I had told her she said I had gone with out leave I
            <lb/>said his Ladyship woud not have given me leave if I had askt</p>
				<p>
            <lb/>upon that she sent me out of the room to see me no more
            <lb/>one thing which made his unwilling to sleep me if I went
            <lb/>to the preaching was fear of the Children and Servants and
            <lb/>when I went with her to Court it was then a shame to be
            <lb/>a Methodist But my Dear Saviour had prepared my way
            <lb/>for me I went to Bed as composed as If nothing had happend
            <lb/>and in the morning I got up like Bird out of a cage and
            <lb/>went to the Tabernacle by 6 a clock from Cavendish Square
            <lb/>of I have said it was a wonder of God, for I had nothing,
            <lb/>no <unclear>respect</unclear>, outwardly how I shud live or get my Bread
            <lb/>I had very little mony many hard things was set before me
            <lb/>and in my self nothing to depend on, no quaintance with him
            <lb/>our Dear Saviour words became Literally true
            <lb/>Seek furst the kingdom of God and it Rightiousness
            <lb/>and all things shall he added unto you
            <lb/>I was a Child turnd out of Doors (was again an orphan)
            <lb/>but my ever faithful Lord whose Hand and Eye was over me
            <lb/>cared for every Step my Lady gave one <unclear>prove</unclear> more of her
            <lb/>kindness to me finding had no aquaintans sent me word
            <lb/>that I Shud Lodge there till I shud get one, the Servants and all
            <lb/>was amaized because I was otherwise no person of courage
            <lb/>but thay didnt know that I had found the pearl of
            <lb/>Great price etc. now I went to me Brother in the Day
            <lb/>till the preaching time at the Taber: my Br was shy and let
            <lb/>me alone, He was very Sorry for my leaveing so good a
            <lb/>place But he lookt into my Books made a good
            <lb/>observation and said all <unclear>protesations</unclear> make the Scriptures
            <lb/>there rule; but if this Inward feeling can be true it most
            <lb/>Come from God it pleaesed my to here him say to much
            <lb/>I inquired of my Br for the Brn Chapel where my little
            <lb/>Hymn Book belonged He directed me but when I came 
            <lb/>there was no preaching I thought I will Enquire at the
            <lb/>Chapel House Sr Wheeler kindly askt me to come in this was in Feb. 1744
            <lb/>Shewd me the Chapel and what she told me at that time of
            <lb/>our Savrs Ruleing amongst his people made such an
            <lb/>Impression on me that I never forgot, it Tallied with my
            <lb/>own Experiance I inquiryed after the Countess of Zenzindor
            <lb/>if she might want a Servant. She was not in England
            <lb/>here I believe it was a great Mercy for me that I had not
            <lb/>much mony for I shud have been exposed to many danger
            <lb/>in takeing a Lodging, for I shud have recd all that had <unclear>Spoke</unclear>
            <lb/>about his Saviour I knowd no differences, in the end after
            <lb/>about a week I went to Speake with Mr Whitfield to
            <lb/>advize with him</p>
				<pb facs="#facs_4" n="4"/>
				<p>
            <lb/>him and I heard of Lady Huntington perhaps she might
            <lb/>help me thro <unclear>him</unclear>, but to the Wound of my most faithful
            <lb/>Lord. I was in no perplexity tho I Saw not the least way
            <lb/>I knowd my cause was good. I found Mr Whitfeld at Br
            <lb/>John Sims, I told my Case quite Symply and the Br Sims
            <lb/>his particular according to her usual kind way in such Cases
            <lb/>took me in, So I left my good Lady and all my friends
            <lb/>with gratful thanks for all her kindness amazeings and I
            <lb/>pray she may not lose her reward. I coud do no other but
            <lb/>follow my Gracious Lord &amp; Savr Br &amp; Sr Sims cared for me
            <lb/>as a Child, their Love tenderness and patienc I shall 
            <lb/>never forget and I am ever in their <unclear>Dept</unclear> Mr Whitefield
            <lb/>and his wife was also very kind but Mr Whit went to
            <lb/>George in a bout Six weeks, which Broke that Connexion
            <lb/>and Br Sims Being atached to the Brn I often went with
            <lb/>them to Fetterlane so by degrees came in Conexion tho
            <lb/>for that time I Recd much Blessing in going to the Taber
            <lb/>but Br Sims moved from Hodgson So Dropt going In
            <lb/><unclear>finely</unclear> and to the tabernacle my good Lord lead me Step by Step as it pleased
            <lb/>him inwardly and outwardly in a most gracious manner
            <lb/>which Brings to mind a few lines, With patience
            <lb/>Immense and love So Intense, he hath led on
            <lb/>I am lost in amazement their when thinking
            <lb/>there on, Now Being come to my proper Home the Dr
            <lb/>Congn when I have Injoyed nothing but Blessing more
            <lb/>then I can express thay have been So many and So great
            <lb/>and my <unclear>heart</unclear> in the Dr Congn So clear and So weighty.
            <lb/>and Say can<unclear> love reset</unclear> to our Savr the Dearst thing to me
            <lb/>I am a Sinner to whom belongs nothing but shame
            <lb/>and Confusion of face, but it has pleased him to open
            <lb/>to me the Treasure of his love and great Salvation
            <lb/>which has been <unclear>treated</unclear> to me by his Spirit by his word
            <lb/>by his Congn (as Tallies) as an <unclear>Elevnat</unclear> truths
            <lb/>for such way my make I must know it as a truth for
            <lb/>my self way truely Convince of unbelieve and can say
            <lb/>of all Sins a curst also my Enmity against our Savr
            <lb/>but when it came to the Highest pitch I felt
            <lb/>if there was another Savior I woud have him Condemnd
            <lb/>for the thought in that moment I was over powerd
            <lb/>with his love and peace and of if he said for all this I
            <lb/>the the feeling and Impression of his nearness bowd
            <lb/>own in the Dust before my gracious Lord and it
            <lb/>ended with</p>
				<p>
            <lb/>with those words. The poor Sinner Happy feeling the Holy Shame
            <lb/>but my self righteous <unclear>man woud</unclear>, <unclear>Stil ????</unclear> me in various shapes but in that
            <lb/>feeling that verse was sealed to me as the greatest truth
            <lb/>o precious precious Blood, the only Holiness that Good
            <lb/>Stil Doop an flow &amp; cover me a c<unclear>ursted</unclear> Sinner without
            <lb/>the preaching, the Hymns, the Scriptures, where opend thee
            <lb/>with such couth and life which I cant Decribe, but
            <lb/>now I am in this strain I cant but go further tho
            <lb/>it leads me in a feild But my Dear Brn &amp; Srs may
            <lb/>take from it what thay please I left Br Sims
            <lb/>with gratful thanks for all their care and want to Mr
            <lb/>Delmots at Black Heath to care for Bettey Holland
            <lb/>whose parants where gone to Germany here I
            <lb/>experienced Somthing particular, in the furst place
            <lb/>to my Shame I was Shown great love an respect from
            <lb/>the Dear Family to Whome I am Bound by tender love and
            <lb/>Gratitude ever to acknowledge but what relates to the
            <lb/>Heart as particular was as I have said the preaching had
            <lb/>been to Blest that tho <unclear>first</unclear> was often Imprest on my
            <lb/>mind the week before So I that I thought I shall speake
            <lb/>out in the Chapel, that is true. Being now all at once
            <lb/>taken from preaching and all meetings what was
            <lb/>amazeing, I injoy such a Sabatic Stillness and the
            <lb/><unclear>Sun Shine</unclear> of peace for that time that I wanted nothing
            <lb/>but was indeed as a child on the Breast I was not yet
            <lb/>In the Congn tho I had <unclear>went </unclear>some time; the Family came
            <lb/>to London and B Holland parants came from Ger. so I 
            <lb/>went with Bettey to live with them but Bettey soon
            <lb/>went to the <unclear>occono</unclear> in Mile end. I know thought much
            <lb/>about reception but it was still some time which was very
            <lb/>wholesom for me, I one time was particular comforted
            <lb/>by those words I <unclear>used </unclear>thy affair will think on as thy <unclear>????</unclear>
            <lb/>loveing head; at length the Hour Struck certainly
            <lb/>in the right moment the Devine Impression upon it
            <lb/>was I am now in my Fathers House this was May
            <lb/>the 18 old Stile 1747 and Sept the 2 following had the
            <lb/>unspeakable grace which word was Impress on my mind on that
            <lb/>day when when I was a partaker of my Dear Savr Body &amp; Blood
            <lb/>in the Holy Sacret in this period <unclear>that</unclear> how good and Blest
            <lb/>was every thing the Liturgies and Solomn meeting beyond
            <lb/>my Expression But in I had the Grace to feel that in my
            <lb/>self I I was poor Creature truely Convince no one worse</p>
				<pb facs="#facs_5" n="5"/>
				<p>
            <lb/>had <unclear>???</unclear> feeling of Sin in all <unclear>????</unclear> which pride Self
            <lb/>produces with the whole train of abomanation on this point
            <lb/>I coud Say much to my Shame of the trouble I have given the
            <lb/>Dear Holy Ghost to Keep me a Sinner Such as me shud be
            <lb/>my Brn &amp; Sr will understand me what that is a solid feeling
            <lb/>what is Sin but not to work Sin God Forbid
            <lb/>In this year I went to Mile end for the children here I had <unclear>some</unclear>
            <lb/>openings of his love and grace Especially relating to my
            <lb/>own Choir grace and I was Devinely Drawn to read
            <lb/>the <unclear>Canticles</unclear>, and those Delicases of our Dr Savr love
            <lb/>to his Chruch was <unclear>opened</unclear> to me with Such truth and 
            <lb/>realtity as I cant express however opend as it was
            <lb/>to See wonderful Beauties it was again closed
            <lb/>to me as clear as if it had been done by our Saviour
            <lb/>own hand By that verse althou the fairest of
            <lb/>Mankind, whose Beauty Strikes Both Heart
            <lb/>Mind But nothing is So fair in the as thy
            <lb/>sweet form upon the ??? and can thro his love
            <lb/>and grace Say nothing has So Strock me as when 
            <lb/>god's Spirit took me to Golgotha o God
            <lb/>be praised. also for leading me more and more in 
            <lb/>to that Matter of Matters which, I hope will continue
            <lb/>till I Behold Him face to face. in this time it is well
            <lb/>know was a period of Some Extravegance (Be it So)
            <lb/>I was at it happend not in them, But for my self
            <lb/>I am truly Convince by my own Experience that
            <lb/>There was a glory from the Lord Indeed to great
            <lb/>for Earthly Minds long to bear but I expect to See
            <lb/>it again in its full glory without a vail between
            <lb/>and with his Sinner brain Surround that Cavity
            <lb/>where I shall Dwell Eternally that verse Suits here
            <lb/>which was So realized in this time by which I will
            <lb/>conclude this unpreakable matter To be enamoured
            <lb/>I know well, to have the heart quite over flowing
            <lb/>for him alone to be So glowing Expression only
            <lb/>me here here fail.</p>
				<p>
            <lb/>I about this time I also had a new School for
            <lb/>my Heart concerning the virgin Station, and found
            <lb/>that only by partakeing of the Nature of the only virgin
            <lb/>Man one Coud Deserve that Charecter these words
            <lb/>was made very Clear - Fair gifts of my creation
            <lb/>quite spilled made the Dispair for this Grace
            <lb/>the Knowlede of my self, (in this particular) I adore
            <lb/>and thank my Lord the Dr Holy Ghost for that Grace, that
            <lb/>was made a means to turn to His precious Blood
            <lb/>which alone can Cleanse our hearts and make all
            <lb/>good. I found it a antidote and help against
            <lb/>all those Sins that stick So close, as self love
            <lb/>self Complaince and a well known brain of
            <lb/>such kind which pride produces - his Grace is
            <lb/>sufficient I thro Mercy Now.
            <lb/>It seems time to come to a conclusion tho many
            <lb/>things comes in mind. In the year 51 I was sent
            <lb/>from Mile end to Ockbrook to care for the Srs there
            <lb/>and Sept 16 57 left Ockbrook to go to Tetherton
            <lb/>and came there on Angels Festival this was so
            <lb/>Blessed a jorney I never can forget thro the near
            <lb/>ness of my gracious Lord and Impresion of the aid
            <lb/>of his Dear Angels, left Titherton July 19 1763
            <lb/>returnd again to Ockbrook, from thence to London
            <lb/>Decbr 11 72 where I hope to finish my poor and
            <lb/>Insignificant Labour In all those places in Sweet
            <lb/>and or wholesome poverty inwardly and ouwardly
            <lb/>His Dear Hand has Brought me thro and I can say with
            <lb/>his deciples I have lacked nothing have been rich in the
            <lb/>midest of poverty, here I woud once more give my due
            <lb/>thanks to my Dr Brn &amp; Srs and particularly those of my own
            <lb/>Choir for their love kindness &amp; patience towards me
            <lb/>but what is due to my Dearst and Best friend and lover
            <lb/>for His Election of grace and for the knowledge of his Dr
            <lb/>wounded person his precious Blood and all what
            <lb/>he is to me I conclude with the 30th verse of the 43
            <lb/>chapter of Ecclesiasticus which will express my mind
            </p>
			</div>
            </body>
            </text>
</TEI>