<?xml-model href="../../Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Eleanor Luty: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty">Eleanor Luty</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-04.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-05.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-06.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-07.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-08.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Eleanor Luty</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="#JAKA1" when-iso="2019-12-02">Converted for semanti markup</change>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-10" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Eleanor Luty</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-01.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>The life of the Single Sister Elenor Luty.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>I was born Sep<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1718 at Killing Hall near</l>
							<l>near Harrowgate, in the Parish of Ripley, and was </l>
							<l>brought up in the Church of England. My Mother</l>
							<l>kept a strict eye upon me <add place="above">wishing</add> to preserve me from the</l>
							<l>temptations of the world. When I was about 6 years</l>
							<l>old, I used to read in the New Testament, and was </l>
							<l>always very inquisitive with my School M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> what</l>
							<l>could be the meaning of many things <add place="above">at that time</add> beyond my capacity. </l>
							<l>In my 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year I was <del>catichised</del>
								<add place="above">examined</add> by the Minister of our</l>
							<l>Church <add place="above">in the doctrines of Christianity</add> as a preparation for the holy Communion, preveius</l>
							<l>to the enjoyment of it, and was confirmed by the Bishop</l>
							<l>durring his visit in these parts. The above mentioned</l>
							<l>Minister told me and several young people that our own </l>
							<l>hearts were our greatest enemies; this I could not compre-</l>
							<l>hend <del>th</del>at that time, tho&apos; under concern for my Salvation.</l>
							<l>My Confirmation had a very blessed effect, encreasing my</l>
							<l>anxiety, and making me more in earnest to seek the Lord.</l>
							<l>I now resolved not to rest satisfied till I had found him,</l>
							<l>and made my Calling and Election sure.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>A few hours before my Fathers departure, he sent for</l>
							<l>all his Children 10 in number, to give each his farewell </l>
						</lg>
						<note type="catchword">Benediction</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Benediction, but I being from home was sent for, and</l>
							<l>told that my Father could not depart till I came to receive</l>
							<l>his last blessing, which be imparted to me with his hand</l>
							<l>upon my head, the fervency of his prayer made a deep</l>
							<l>impression on me. In my 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year I went to live with</l>
							<l>a Milliner as a Servant at Rippon, here I was in great</l>
							<l>danger of being drawn into things contrary to the mind of</l>
							<l>my Saviour, had not his protecting hand been over me.</l>
							<l>The minister who baptized me, wished me not to stay</l>
							<l>any longer in that place, and procured another in a reput-</l>
							<l>able family, here I lived 2 years, and they having no child<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi></l>
							<l>treated me exceeding kind, and beloved in all respects as</l>
							<l>a Father and Mother to me, during their time I had a dan-</l>
							<l>gerous Illness, to that the Physican disposed of my recovery</l>
							<l>and I was in great distress of soul, without any clearness</l>
							<l>of my happiness, not knowing how to obtain it, for my</l>
							<l>Master and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> frequently told me it was time enough</l>
							<l>to be uneasy about my soul, but I found their advice was</l>
							<l>wrong, being much alarmed of my stake of heart, how-</l>
							<l>ever it pleased the lord at that time to restore me to proper</l>
							<l>health. I went for sometime to my Sister of Killing-</l>
							<l>Hall, here I began to think of settling in the world, and</l>
							<l>engaged so far, that I promised marriage to a young</l>
							<l>man with whom I thought I could live happy, but</l>
							<l>whilst preparations were making for our marriage </l>
						</lg>
						<note type="catchword">a</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-03.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>a clergyman, who had heard of me, by one of my former</l>
							<l>Mistresses, wished me to go in service to the marquis</l>
							<l>of Thockingham near Sheffield to which I consorted, here</l>
							<l>I felt very uncomfortable, there being a great number</l>
							<l>of Servants, who were persecutors of our Savior and his </l>
							<l>People, and I was very uneasy among them, being much</l>
							<l>afraid I should suffer harm in my Soul, and never be saved.</l>
							<l>I frequently went to hear David Taylor preach, his Sermons</l>
							<l>were very applicable to my case, more especially when he</l>
							<l>treated of our Saviors sufferings for poor sinners. At this</l>
							<l>time I was very much hurt with all the Servants, partic-</l>
							<l>ularly the Steward, who said that all tho went to hear</l>
							<l>those preach should have a small house that stood near</l>
							<l>the Fishpond to receive grace in, and the Pond to wash</l>
							<l>their sins away, but not long after, this same man was</l>
							<l>drowned in that very pond. I now resolved to leave this</l>
							<l>place, as I could not be happy here, so I left them, and not</l>
							<l>knowing <add place="above">any</add> body but the Farmer where I first heard David</l>
							<l>Taylor preach, I beged him to conduct me to my Mother, </l>
							<l>which he did as far as Leeds, from there I walked home</l>
							<l>to my Parents, being quite tired of Service, among uncon-</l>
							<l>verted People, my relations being at that time also in an </l>
							<l>unconverted state of mind, I was resolved <add place="above">to leave</add> them and seek</l>
							<l>a people of God with whom I could be in fellowship</l>
						</lg>
						<note type="catchword">the</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-04.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>The Methodists preached in our neighborhood, but</l>
							<l>I found no clearness to join their concession, I accidently</l>
							<l>met with a person who informed me that there</l>
							<l>was a sort of people in Pudsey, who would suite me.</l>
							<l>Upon this information I left my Fathers house on foot,</l>
							<l>and did not know one step of the way, but thought</l>
							<l>if I could meet with a carrier that went that road,</l>
							<l>I would go with him, accordingly I soon met with one</l>
							<l>and we walked together to the place I was seeking.</l>
							<l>I arrived Sep<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1742, and stayed 15 weeks in Pudsey</l>
							<l>working for my living till at last Sis<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gussinbaus</l>
							<l>who then lived with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hillas took me to her</l>
							<l>self, on that very day the young man came to the house,</l>
							<l>whom I had promised marriage, and wanted to fetch me,</l>
							<l>but I told him that I would marry no man at present</l>
							<l>for I belonged intirely to our Savior, he told me that</l>
							<l>my mother wanted it to take place, but I persisted in</l>
							<l>my resolution, and was soon after taken by B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></l>
							<l>Heckenwalder to Low house, where there was an ocon-</l>
							<l>omy of S. S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> near Fulneck, I no sooner arrived there</l>
							<l>than I melted into tears of gratitude at the feet of my</l>
							<l>dear Savior, for his unwearied patience, love and</l>
							<l>faithful care in bringing me safely to his people.</l>
							<l>I remained so happy for sometime in this place that</l>
							<l>I thought it a Heaven upon earth, but after more </l>
						</lg>
						<note type="catchword">insight</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-05.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>insight into the nature of a Congregation my feel-</l>
							<l>ings altered, I entered into a close examination of </l>
							<l>myself, how for this change of circumstance would</l>
							<l>suit with my turn of mind. At last thro&apos; the grace</l>
							<l>of our Savior I came to this resolution to take up my</l>
							<l>cross and follow Him, and to submit to his Will in every</l>
							<l>tryal, he thought best for me and which I soon experienced</l>
							<l>as I sow one after the other, received into the Congregation</l>
							<l>to which I thought I had a might preferable to Him,</l>
							<l>Our Savior suffered this tryal to be a means of my</l>
							<l>becoming better acquainted with myself and pointed</l>
							<l>out to me what was my hindrance in not attaining to</l>
							<l>the priviledges of the Congregation / namely/ my</l>
							<l>self righteousness and unbroken spirit</l>
							<l>I became sensible of it, and owned it to eaternal </l>
							<l>thro&apos; his enabling grace resigned to his Will</l>
							<l>He granted me that favor June 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1746 to be rec&apos;d </l>
							<l>into the Congregation, and what was still much gined</l>
							<l>to partake of his Body and Blood in the holy Sacram.</l>
							<l>March 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1747 which excited me anew to surrender</l>
							<l>myself entirely to His Guidance, and I entreated our</l>
							<l>Savior to give me now grace, that I might be obedint</l>
							<l>to his holy Spirit, and do what would be pleasing</l>
							<l>to Him. Soon after this I want to London to assist</l>
						</lg>
						<note type="catchword">in</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb n="6" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-06.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>in washing for the Children <add place="above">School</add> at Milend. In 1753</l>
							<l>returned to Fulneck into the S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> house here. Sometime</l>
							<l>after went again into service in Fulneck, and again re-</l>
							<l>turned into my favorit house among the S. S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></l>
							<l>Since my coming to the Congregation I have exper-</l>
							<l>ienced many tryals informally and externally, and</l>
							<l>am sensible I have nothing to boast of with respect</l>
							<l>to my natural disposition, which <add place="above">has</add> caused others</l>
							<l>and myself much trouble, but my <del>Savior</del> good Savior</l>
							<l>whom I love above all things in Heaven or earth</l>
							<l>bears with me, and has kept my confidence unshak-</l>
							<l>en in Him to this moment; and will no doubt do</l>
							<l>it to the end. I cannot omit a circumstance,</l>
							<l>which is a proof of my Lords parental love and care</l>
							<l>over me. My dispotion was not only unbroken</l>
							<l>and selfrighteous, but besides this, I had</l>
							<l>a too anxious care for the things of this life, which</l>
							<l>carried me so far, that I found myself in a dangerous</l>
							<l>way of loosing the enjoyment of my Saviors sweet</l>
							<l>nearness thereby. I was very fond of work, which</l>
							<l>is undoubtedly right in its place, but even this I</l>
							<l>carried too far, my mind being so much taken up</l>
							<l>with it, but our Savior who knew this to be the case</l>
							<l>permitted me to have a dangerous fall from a chair, </l>
						</lg>
						<note type="catchword">bu</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb n="7" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-07.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>by means of which my right arm was so disabled</l>
							<l>that I never after could work as I had done before,</l>
							<l>this was a painful circumstance, and I could</l>
							<l>not look on it in any other lights, than as a chas-</l>
							<l>tisement from the Lord, for acting contrary to </l>
							<l>conviction, but I am now richly comforted, with</l>
							<l>that promise: All things shall work together</l>
							<l>for good to them that love God. I am his sheep</l>
							<l>and nothing shall pluck me out of his Hand.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Thus far her own Account.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Our late Sister has given to genuine and </l>
							<l>upright account, both of her internal and external</l>
							<l>course that we find no occasion to add any thing</l>
							<l>particular thereto. She has been for sometime thro&apos;</l>
							<l>her advanced age, and bodily infirmities, confined</l>
							<l>to her room, and her mental faculties perceptibly</l>
							<l>decreasing, made it in several respects heavy to </l>
							<l>herself and very troublesome to those who had to do</l>
							<l>with her, and great patience was requisit to</l>
							<l>wait on her; but we must acknowledge as she</l>
							<l>herself expresses it that she was certainly</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="8">
					<head type="page">8</head>
					<pb n="8" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_70Luty-08.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>one of our Saviors Sheep / and even amidst </l>
							<l>her incoherent conversation she was sometime</l>
							<l>before her departure, pleasing to all who visit-</l>
							<l>ed her, for when her mind was composed she</l>
							<l>would repeatedly say: that nobody should be</l>
							<l>uneasy about her, for whenever we should </l>
							<l>hear that she was departed, either by night</l>
							<l>or day, we mnight be sure that she was happy</l>
							<l>by with our dear Savior.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>On the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of March in the afternoon she</l>
							<l>particularly desired to be blessed for her depart-</l>
							<l>ures which was accordingly <add place="above">done</add> because she believed</l>
							<l>she should go to our Savior that night, which</l>
							<l>came to pass in her 81<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> year.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>On March 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> she fell softly &amp;</l>
							<l>happily asleep in the 81<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> of her age. </l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
