<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>John Plaisted: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted">John Plaisted</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted-04.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">John Plaisted</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-11" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>John Plaisted</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted-01.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Departed Nov. 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1761</l>
							<l>Personalia of the Single Br. John Plaisted</l>
							<l>He <add place="above">writes</add> of himself, I was born at West Titherton Wilt-</l>
							<l>shire Febr the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1729. My Parents were religious People</l>
							<l>of the Church of England, <del>untill</del>
								<add place="above">when</add> the Methodists came into </l>
							<l>that Country <del>and then</del> my Father join&apos;d them, at which</l>
							<l>time I was <add place="above">about 12 years old. In my 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year I was</add> in some measure awakend by the Preaching</l>
							<l>of Br Cennik, grew very uneasy about my Salvation</l>
							<l>and followed the Ptreachers about the Country in order to hear</l>
							<l>something which might satisfy my Heart. My elder</l>
							<l>B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> not understanding nor liking this Course, perswa-</l>
							<l>ded me to go to Service with a Farmer, who lived not far</l>
							<l>from the B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> Chapel, they having come about this Time</l>
							<l>to Titherton. This he did out of a Principle of Love to me</l>
							<l>thinking thereby my Mind wou&apos;d be diverted <del>of</del>
								<add place="above">from</add> that uneas-</l>
							<l>iness and melancholy which constantly attended me. </l>
							<l>Here I lived 2 years. My Master not suffering me to hear</l>
							<l>the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> but compelled me to pass by the B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> Chapel on</l>
							<l>Sundays and to go to Church. When the distress of my Mind</l>
							<l>on this Account often made me weep, the other young</l>
							<l>Men my fellow Servants, being of a wild and Worldly</l>
							<l>turn of Mind, laugh&apos;d me out of it, by which means</l>
							<l>I forgot and stifted all conviction, took to the same</l>
							<l>Courses with them, and pursued all sorts of Vice and</l>
							<l>Worldly Pleasure which that Country afforded with</l>
							<l>all my Might till I was about 23 Years of Age; my Fa-</l>
							<l>ther did not fail from time to time to put me in Mind</l>
							<l>of my former Grace, and to admonish me in harmony</l>
							<l>with the dear H. Ghost in my heart, to give myself up</l>
							<l>to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, But shame and Confusion on Account of my</l>
							<l>backsliding and the entanglements of the World so over-</l>
							<l>came me! that I could not resolve to be entire-</l>
							<l>by our Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> till I heard the Word of Reconcilation and</l>
							<l>Atonement in the Blood and Sufferings of Jesus</l>
							<l>Christ by B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cennick again, about the beginning</l>
							<l>of the Year 53. This struck and Captivated my <del>Heart</del></l>
							<l>Heart in such a Manner, that I coud not resist any</l>
							<l>longer; the Man of Sorrows in his Crosses Form</l>
							<l>drew near my Heart and I went and prayed in-</l>
							<l>cessantly for the Assurance of <add place="above">my</add>
								<del>Grace</del> Election <add place="above">of Grace</add> which</l>
							<l>I also happily obtained, but not withstanding this I</l>
							<l>could not be entirely at rest and satisfied untill I</l>
							<l>was quite amongst that People to which I knew I belong&apos;d</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>and got Leave to live with the S B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> at Foxham in the</l>
							<l>Year 55, where B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Schulze was Labourer and received</l>
							<l>me into the House according to the entire Wish and Joy</l>
							<l>of my Heart. Here I prospered in the Hearts Acquain-</l>
							<l>tance with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and had the Grace to be receiv&apos;d into</l>
							<l>the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1756. But the B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> Oeconomy</l>
							<l>in Foxham being broke up before my Reception into the</l>
							<l>Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> I went to live with a married B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> in the same Place,</l>
							<l>where I remaind a Year and 1/4, and from thence came</l>
							<l>to live with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Samuel Utley at Tiherton. Here I</l>
							<l>had the inexpressible Grace in May 1758 to be made</l>
							<l>a participant of the Body and Blood of the Lord in</l>
							<l>the holy Sacrament with the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. Those Years that</l>
							<l>I lived with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Samuel Utley proved an unspeakable Bless</l>
							<l>ing, and of great Reality to my Heart, for here it was</l>
							<l>that I became rightly acquainted both with my</l>
							<l>self and also with the Friend of my Soul, who gran-</l>
							<l>ted me the Grace to ground my self <del>and also</del> as a</l>
							<l>Sinner upon his Sufferings and Merits, and I wan-</l>
							<l>ted nothing to render my Days quite to my Satisfaction</l>
							<l>but the Grace and happiness to live in the S. B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi></l>
							<l>Choir House at Lambshill, my longing desire after</l>
							<l>which was so strong, that I oftentimes cou&apos;d scarce</l>
							<l>sleep for thinking about it and speaking with our</l>
							<l>Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> to make a way for me to go live there, and it</l>
							<l>was a great Joy to me, when I got the promise from</l>
							<l>our dearest Johannes that I should once go theither</l>
							<l>and at last the Hour came that I got Permession</l>
							<l>to go to Lambshill, which almost overcame me with</l>
							<l>Joy, and accordingly I got ready and set out for that</l>
							<l>Place in May; so transported that as I went along</l>
							<l>I scarce knew wether I walk&apos;d, run, or leap&apos;d; and</l>
							<l>indeed I did all of them so that had any Body seen me</l>
							<l>they might have thought I was not right in my Head</l>
							<l>and the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of June I arrived <add place="above">at</add>
								<del>with</del> the dear S. B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi>.</l>
							<l><add place="above">on</add>
								<del>at</del> Lambshill, were I was at home directly and found</l>
							<l>this to be the Place for me according to the Impressi-</l>
							<l>on I had always had of it, and from the first of my</l>
							<l>arrival here till this Day have always thought I</l>
							<l>shall never be transptanted any were else till it is my</l>
							<l>Sav<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Time to take me to the Congn, which is around him.</l>
							<l>So far his own Account.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted-03.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>The Bretheren here soon got a real Love to him and he to</l>
							<l>them, and his genuine Simplicity and Honesty approved</l>
							<l>him to all our Hearts. In the first weeks he was employ&apos;d in</l>
							<l>various Matters and afterwards he became our Cooks w<add place="above">h</add>ere</l>
							<l>he approved himself as an indefatigable and faithful B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></l>
							<l>to our great Contentement, and we were thankful for him</l>
							<l>in this Place. His character was, a truly simple upright</l>
							<l><add place="above">B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></add>
								<del>heart</del> in whom there was nothing crook&apos;d or treachorous</l>
							<l>and withal had a sensible and tender Heart, whose only</l>
							<l>Object was the Man of Sorrows, and <add place="above">in</add> his Choir Course was</l>
							<l>steady and happy, and his Election was w<add place="above">e</add>ighty to him. He</l>
							<l>frequently spoke to his intimate Acquaintance even in</l>
							<l>his healthy Days of his longing Desire to be at home, <add place="above">with</add>
								<del>by</del></l>
							<l>our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, and particularly some Days before his Sickness</l>
							<l>he would often say, it what a happiness will that be, when</l>
							<l>I once shall be like our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> in one Point, viz, to be laid</l>
							<l>out as a Corpse as he was. Thursday Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> he was</l>
							<l>seized with a violent Pain in his Head and Back, and</l>
							<l>the next Day took to his Bed and continued to have great</l>
							<l>Pain. He said directly he was very positive he should go</l>
							<l>home in this Sickness; and when he was lightheaded, which</l>
							<l>was pretty much the case, his Fancies were about nothing</l>
							<l>but going to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>; and would often call out I must</l>
							<l>go, he calls me; or he has sent a Messenger for me to</l>
							<l>conduct me home to him &amp;c. The 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the small pox came</l>
							<l>out and he was exceeding full and of a <del>bad</del>
								<add place="above">heavy</add> kind, but a-</l>
							<l>midst his great Pains he spent his Time very hapnily</l>
							<l>in Converse with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, wishing the Hour would soon</l>
							<l>come that he might have Permission to leave the mor-</l>
							<l>tal Tent; and thus his Days were spent to the Blessing</l>
							<l>and Satisfaction of those B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> about him and those</l>
							<l>who visited him. About the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> he was considerably</l>
							<l>easier than he had been, and many B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> begun to think he</l>
							<l>would recover, but he still remaind steady with respect to</l>
							<l>his Certainty <del>to</del> that he should go, for said he, our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></l>
							<l>himself has been with me, and assured me of it. When</l>
							<l>Verses were sung about his Bed he always join&apos;d <del>in</del></l>
							<l>and sung aloud, with a peculiar happy Feeling, even</l>
							<l>if he was lightheaded, yea and when nobody sung by</l>
							<l>him, he spent a good deal of time <add place="above">in</add>
								<del>with</del> singing for him</l>
							<l>self. Towards the Evening of the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> it was clear</l>
							<l>that his Hour was not far off; he was sensible,</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_59_John_Plaisted-04.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>but could not speak very intelligibly, yet the Word my Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></l>
							<l>come and take me we could often understand. At 10 o&apos;</l>
							<l>clok this Evening his departing Liturgy was sung, and</l>
							<l>during the singing, Go to thy Lord, and blush for Shame</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>His Torments comfort thee</l>
							<l>He loves, and calls thee now by Name</l>
							<l>In his Arms clasp&apos;d to be.</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="2">
							<l>Thy dear Soul redeem&apos;d with Smart </l>
							<l>We do now deliver</l>
							<l>Into Jesus pierced Heart</l>
							<l>There to be for ever.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>The blessing of his Choir was imparted to him and his</l>
							<l>Soul took Flight to his beloved Saviour.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
