<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p/>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-01.jpg" n='1'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Memoir
					<lb/>of B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> C. F. Ramftler&apos;s Minister of
					<lb/>the Brethrens&apos; Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> in Bristol.
					<lb/>who departed this life Oct<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 26<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1822.
					<lb/>Aged 56 1/2 years. Written by himself
					<lb/>If Parentage and descent under
					<lb/>any circumstances be cause for glorying
					<lb/>I think I have where of to glory. Both
					<lb/>my Grandparents on the Parental side
					<lb/>left home and kindred and property &amp;
					<lb/>whatever was dear to them in the world
					<lb/>for conscience sake, my Grandfather
					<lb/>being a Moravian Emigrant and
					<lb/>my Grandmother Marchioness de
					<lb/>Monton being one of the French Refugees.
					<lb/>Of myself I will not glory, cannot
					<lb/>glory, save that by the Cross of Christ
					<lb/>the world has been crucified to me, and 
					<lb/>I unto the world, that amidst my
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-02.jpg" n='2'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>manfold infirmities his power has rest-
					<lb/>ed upon me, and that my numberless Sins
					<lb/>have I believe been blotled out with his
					<lb/>precious Blood.
					<lb/>My Father was
					<lb/>born at Herrnhut July 6<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1740, and at the
					<lb/>time of my birth was accountant for the
					<lb/>Bailiwick of Barby in Saxony, which the
					<lb/>Brethrens unity then held upon a long lease.
					<lb/>There I first saw the light of this World
					<lb/>March 12<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1780, and shall ever be thankful
					<lb/>to my God and Redeemer, that born and
					<lb/>educated in the Bosom of the Brethrens
					<lb/>Church, I obtained a Birthright to this
					<lb/>household of God, and have been pre-
					<lb/>served from selling this Birthright.
					<lb/>My preservation from gross Sin,
					<lb/>and my early impressions of Divine
					<lb/>Grace, are to be solely ascribed under
					<lb/>Divine blessing to a careful education
					<lb/>which preserved me the from temptations
					<lb/>and checked my evil propensities.
					<lb/>My dear Mother often told me that dur-
					<lb/>ing her pregrancy with me she had fer-
					<lb/>vently prayed that I might rather not
					<lb/>live than not become an heir of heaven
					<lb/>and that I might become a Preacher
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-03.jpg" n='3'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>righteousness preferably among the Hea-
					<lb/>then. My affectionate Father treated
					<lb/>me with a degree of severity and I stood
					<lb/>in awe of him, while My Mother found it
					<lb/>the most effectual Method of controlling me
					<lb/>to remind the that by evil doing, I offended
					<lb/>that Saviour whose love to me had prompt-
					<lb/>ed him to lay down his life for me. By
					<lb/>my lively and active disposition I fell into
					<lb/>many errors, and gave frequent uneasei-
					<lb/>ness to my Parents. In my 6<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> Year I
					<lb/>remember to have had the first indelible
					<lb/>impression of a Spiritual Nature, at the
					<lb/>meeting on Good Friday in which the Lord&apos;s
					<lb/>Death is commemorated. When the Words
					<lb/>were read: &quot;And he bowed the head, and gave
					<lb/>up the Ghost,&quot; and the Congregation fell
					<lb/>on their knees in prayer, or power pervad-
					<lb/>ed my Mind which I did not then under-
					<lb/>stand, but which times without number,
					<lb/>has since then been brought to my reco-
					<lb/>lection, as a drawing of grace, and a div
					<lb/>call to give my heart to him who died for
					<lb/>my Sins.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-04.jpg" n='4'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>After having acquired the rudiments,
					<lb/>of learning in the Day School at Barby
					<lb/>I was by my Parents and at my own desire
					<lb/>removed to the Boarding School at Klein-
					<lb/>welke in my 7<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> year. Though separated
					<lb/>this early from home at the distance of
					<lb/>about 150 English miles, I was delighted 
					<lb/>with the idea of the change, the number
					<lb/>of companions, &amp; the opportunity of improve-
					<lb/>ment. The mode of living was poor, nor
					<lb/>was the Method of instruction best calcu-
					<lb/>lated to improve the mind. After a while
					<lb/>I lost my vivorcity, and became homesick.
					<lb/>A dangerous illness seized me, when I
					<lb/>had been little more than a year at Klein- 
					<lb/>welke: an abscess in the lungs reduced
					<lb/>me to a skeleton, deprived me of the power
					<lb/>of speech and brought me to the very
					<lb/>brink of the grave. My Father upon
					<lb/>receiving the information hastened to
					<lb/>see me, and resolved in reliance upon
					<lb/>God, to take me home in that enfeebled state.
					<lb/>Altho&apos; told by my Medical attendants, that
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-05.jpg" n='5'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>probably I should be a Corpse, before I
					<lb/>could reach home and that it ever I should
					<lb/>recover, My speech would never be restored
					<lb/>and consequently the idea of Making a
					<lb/>preacher of me must be entirely given up
					<lb/>The very thought of returning home cheered
					<lb/>me, and a commodiens carrarge with
					<lb/>a bed and a careful nurse being provided
					<lb/>the Journey was accomplished in 5 days
					<lb/>in delighthul weather, my arrival at home
					<lb/>taking place Sep 26<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1787. On the third day
					<lb/>of the Journey we passed a very uneven
					<lb/>and stony road the violent shaking of
					<lb/>which broke the abscess, and led to a co-
					<lb/>pious discharge of Matter, with a dis-
					<lb/>tresssing Congh, which made my Father
					<lb/>momentarily apprehend My death. While
					<lb/>it proved thro&apos; divine Mercy, that this very
					<lb/>circumstance laid the foundation to my
					<lb/>cure which was afterwards gradually pro-
					<lb/>moted by the use of Iceland moss and other 
					<lb/>remedies under the faithful care of D<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>
					<lb/>Luberkuhn. This I regard as the first
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-06.jpg" n='6'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>striking interposition of Providence in the
					<lb/>renewed gift
					<lb/>of life and in the redoubled
					<lb/>obligation thereby imposed upon me to
					<lb/>devotee that life to him, to whose service
					<lb/>I had been devoted at Baptism, and ded-
					<lb/>cated by many parental prayers.
					<lb/>After my recovery I again attended
					<lb/>the Day School, where the opportunities
					<lb/>for making progress in learning were
					<lb/>scanty untill in My 12<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> year I received
					<lb/>private lessons by a Candidate for the
					<lb/>Lurtheran ministry preparatory to my
					<lb/>entrance into the Pedagogium of the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi>
					<lb/>Unity then established at Barby. Next
					<lb/>to the pleasures of Gardening and hus-
					<lb/>bandry, in which during my childhood
					<lb/>I was delighted to share in the fertile soil
					<lb/>of my native place. My mind was intent
					<lb/>upon the acquirement of knowledge, and
					<lb/>in that view readily sacrificed the former
					<lb/>delights. Altho I cannot say that my mind
					<lb/>was then truly Spiritualized, yet my de-
					<lb/>sire to devote my life to the Ministry in
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-07.jpg" n='7'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Unity was then almost as strong
					<lb/>and distinct as at any Subsequent period,
					<lb/>tnor am I aware of any secular Motive,
					<lb/>save the opportunity of study, wherein I
					<lb/>found my element. My religious views were
					<lb/>simple, and centered in the love of Christ &amp;
					<lb/>the obligation of loving him in return. The
					<lb/>experience of the efficacy of this theme fa-
					<lb/>miliarily and affectionately presented to the 
					<lb/>youthful mind, tho&apos; not always productive
					<lb/>at the time of the desired benefit, has in
					<lb/>later Years made it my pleasing duty, to
					<lb/>direct Children in the course of My Minis-
					<lb/>terial labours, to that Saviour, whose his-
					<lb/>tory in it important bearings they can
					<lb/>both understand and feel, while dry ar-
					<lb/>gument and doctrinal statement leave
					<lb/>their hearts cold and dead.
					<lb/>April 1<hi rend='superscript:true;'>st</hi> 1792 I entered the Pedagogium
					<lb/>as a Pupil, and during the 5 1/2 Years of
					<lb/>My residence in it visited My Parents
					<lb/>House but once in the week, for two hours
					<lb/>on Sunday, altho&apos; at the distance of but
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-08.jpg" n='8'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>a few hundred Yards. Under the excel-
					<lb/>lent tuition of my Preceptors I now made
					<lb/>rapid progress, and took much pleasure
					<lb/>in my studies, altho&apos; the very close con-
					<lb/>finement occasionally produced lowness
					<lb/>of spirits. In this period while sin
					<lb/>strengthened with my youth, the Saviour&apos;s love
					<lb/>overcame its dominion, and while my 
					<lb/>conversion to God was gradual and it is
					<lb/>impossible for me to point out the date
					<lb/>of its commencement, I could trace that
					<lb/>by the Grace of God I became what by nature
					<lb/>I neither was nor desired to be. The private
					<lb/>and confidential advice of the Laborer of
					<lb/>the Acadimicians in Barby will ever
					<lb/>be held in grateful remembernce by me.
					<lb/>June 17<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1792 I was received into the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi>
					<lb/>Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n </hi>and on Maundy Thursday in the 
					<lb/>following year partook the first time of
					<lb/>the H Communion; nor did I ever regret
					<lb/>having this early been admitted to this feast
					<lb/>which proved a powerful check to my Sinful
					<lb/>nature, and profitable Season for self
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-09.jpg" n='9'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>examination whenever it returned.
					<lb/>My Classical studies having been
					<lb/>compleated I was in Oct<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 1797 transferred
					<lb/>with 13 companions to the Theolgical Se-
					<lb/>minany at Niesky. The Lectures delivered
					<lb/>in this institution were profitable to me,
					<lb/>I took notes of their contents, and devoted My-
					<lb/>self with a degree of assiduity to the study
					<lb/>of Divinity. But the simplicity of my mind
					<lb/>received a shock, mental poison I swal-
					<lb/>lowed mixed with mental food, vain conceit
					<lb/>and self dependance seized me, Sceptical
					<lb/>sentiments laid hold of me and I even con-
					<lb/>templated the abandonment of the proposed
					<lb/>career of my life, in which I was prevented
					<lb/>by my judicious Uncle, whom I visited
					<lb/>several times in Lower Lusatia. Amidst
					<lb/>the waywardness of my Mind and the awak-
					<lb/>ening passions of my Sinful heart, in which
					<lb/>My Superiors treated me with more harshness
					<lb/>than wisdom, the desire of preaching the
					<lb/>Gospel returned to my mind, and an acquaint-
					<lb/>ance which I formed with a neighbouring
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-10.jpg" n='10'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Lutheran Clergyman in the Village of
					<lb/>Arndorf led to an invitation from him
					<lb/>that I would make a trial of preaching
					<lb/>in his Church, which I did when barely
					<lb/>17 years of age. As this was done without the
					<lb/>previous permission of the Inspector of the
					<lb/>Seminary, I received a sharp rebuke, but
					<lb/>afterwards with the Sanction of the U.E.C.
					<lb/>preached twice again in Chuches before
					<lb/>I quitted the Seminary.
					<lb/>In Feb<hi rend='superscript:true;'>y</hi> 1800, I returned to Barby.
					<lb/>the Journey being performed in very se-
					<lb/>vere weather, and in my passage thro&apos;
					<lb/>Leipsic I spent some time at the house
					<lb/>of a friend awaiting myself of the oppor-
					<lb/>tunity of attending various Lectures at
					<lb/>that University. Now I spent a few
					<lb/>Months very agreeably at the house of
					<lb/>my Parents, and occupied myself in
					<lb/>part with copying Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> Acc<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ts</hi>. In July
					<lb/>of the same year I received a call to be
					<lb/>Schoolmaster at Neusalz in Silesia,
					<lb/>which was my first station of Service
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-11.jpg" n='11'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>and well calenlated to try and humble
					<lb/>me. The Children of the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> committed
					<lb/>to my care, had been much neglected by
					<lb/>my predecessor, inexperience induced
					<lb/>me to adopt severe measures, and I was
					<lb/>employed in teaching the Alphabet and
					<lb/>first rudiments of learning. Yet I en-
					<lb/>joyed thro&apos; mercy the love and confidence
					<lb/>of the Parents, was supported by B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r </hi>
					<lb/>Nitschky the Minister of the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> and
					<lb/>saw that My labour was not in vain
					<lb/>in the Lord. I lodged in the S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>le</hi> B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> House
					<lb/>My maintenance was very Scanty and
					<lb/>I was obliged to copy accounts to supply my
					<lb/>need. Here I had also pretty frequent op-
					<lb/>portunites of assisting the Minister in
					<lb/>the public proclamation of the Gospel
					<lb/>wherein I look much pleasure. A strik-
					<lb/>ing preservation of my life during my
					<lb/>residence at Neusalz strengthened my
					<lb/>conviction that my God had still work
					<lb/>for me to do in this World, and moved me
					<lb/>to consecrate myself anew to my Preserver
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-12.jpg" n='12'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>and Redeemer. May 1<hi rend='superscript:true;'>9th</hi> 1801 I went by
					<lb/>the dedication and in the company of a 
					<lb/>friend to the River Oder at the
					<lb/>distance of about 2 miles from  the town.
					<lb/>In high spirits did my companion pro-
					<lb/>ceed and encourage me to follow him.
					<lb/>But suddenly he sunk in an unexpect-
					<lb/>edly deep place of the river, and rose no
					<lb/>more. I stepped after him with a view to
					<lb/>rescue him, attempting to seize his arm
					<lb/>the water rose above my head, and I lost
					<lb/>all power of voluntary motion, consider-
					<lb/>ing my life as lost. By an inexplica-
					<lb/>ble Providence, however I was raised &amp;
					<lb/>found myself standing again on firm
					<lb/>Ground, thankful for my deliverance
					<lb/>but agonized on account of the loss of my
					<lb/>friend. Hastily and in an almost dis-
					<lb/>tracted state of mind I procured assis-
					<lb/>tance, removed the drowned body, and
					<lb/>adopted all practicable means to re-
					<lb/>susitate it but in vain. Thus one
					<lb/>was taken and the other left.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-13.jpg" n='13'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>At the conclusion of the Synod in 1801
					<lb/>I received a call to be a Teacher in the Aca-
					<lb/>demy for Young Noblemen at Uhyst. Self-
					<lb/>denying as my station at Neusalz had
					<lb/>been I left it with considerable regret, be-
					<lb/>cause I enjoyed the love and friendship of
					<lb/>Many, and had not been left destitute of
					<lb/>the blessing of my God. In Uhyst from the
					<lb/>Superior mode of instruction, as well as
					<lb/>the greater convenience in the mode I
					<lb/>life, My abode was pleasant, in addition
					<lb/>to our domestic circle I enjoyed confiden-
					<lb/>tial intercounse with the Clergyman of
					<lb/>the Parish, at whose house I spent many
					<lb/>evenings after the labour of the day for
					<lb/>profitable relaxation. Both at the Aca-
					<lb/>demy and Church I had frequent oppor-
					<lb/>tunities of testifying of the Grace of God
					<lb/>in Christ Jesus. Dreary as the Country
					<lb/>about Uhyst is, the village standing in
					<lb/>the midst of extensive fir forests, and con-
					<lb/>fined as my Society there was, the removal
					<lb/>of the Academy to Great Hennersdorf near
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-14.jpg" n='14'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Hernhut after I had been only half a year
					<lb/>there proved painful to me. In Hennersdorf
					<lb/>also I resided only half a year being in 
					<lb/>the spring of 1803 called to England, to oc-
					<lb/>cupy the place of first Teacher in the
					<lb/>newly founded Boarding School at Fair-
					<lb/>field near Manchester.
					<lb/>This call which constituted a new
					<lb/>Epoch in my life, and directed My whole
					<lb/>official career, and moreover was very
					<lb/>much contrary to my inclination, and
					<lb/>plans, and prospects, I could not accept,
					<lb/>until it had been sanctioned by lot.
					<lb/>Paying a farewell visit to my Parents, I 
					<lb/>took a painful leave of them, of many dear
					<lb/>friends, and of my Native land. At Hern-
					<lb/>burgh I embarked for Hule, and by contrary
					<lb/>winds was detained three weeks at Cuxhaven
					<lb/>as a lonely Passenger in the ships cabin.
					<lb/>when at length having reached the open Sea
					<lb/>and English Privateer seized us, under
					<lb/>the mistaken Idea that the French had made
					<lb/>themselves Masters of Hamburgh.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-15.jpg" n='15'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>The Privateer belonging to Colchester, <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>we were</hi>
					<lb/>we were carried to the Harbour of Wivenhoe
					<lb/>4 miles from that town. Thus my arrival
					<lb/>in England seemed very inauspicious;
					<lb/>coming to a place to which I had no re-
					<lb/>commendation, Where I could not be intro-
					<lb/>duced to a Single individual. My situation
					<lb/>was peculiarly irksome. The English
					<lb/>language I had indeed learned to read, but
					<lb/>hearing it for the first time in common con-
					<lb/>versation I found it very difficult to un-
					<lb/>derstand it, nor could I readily express
					<lb/>myself in it. How to proceed, I knew not
					<lb/>and therefore took my quarters at the Rose
					<lb/>and Crown Inn Wivenloc, untill I might
					<lb/>be favored with an answer from Br. Woltin
					<lb/>in London to whom I wrote. Sunk into mourn-
					<lb/>ful meditations, I wandered in the fertile
					<lb/>fields, admiring the beauty of the land-
					<lb/>scape, but feeling myself cut off from
					<lb/>all human endearments. Nothing cou&apos;d
					<lb/>have cheered My mind, but the conviction
					<lb/>that here I was in obedience to a divine
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-16.jpg" n='16'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>call, and that he who called me would not 
					<lb/>have nor forsake me. In all my future
					<lb/>situations and difficulties, it has been my
					<lb/>great support and consolation, that not by
					<lb/>my own choice nor even by mere human 
					<lb/>appointment but according to the mode of
					<lb/>appointing to office in our Church, I occupied
					<lb/>the places, which I old occupy, and was en-
					<lb/>gaged in the employments in which I was
					<lb/>engaged from time to time. The solitude
					<lb/>also in which I now felt myself, directed
					<lb/>my mind to the more frequent Communion
					<lb/>with my Divine Friend and Saviour.
					<lb/>By the arrival of B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Wollin I was
					<lb/>relieved and with him proceeded to London
					<lb/>from whence after a few days, I went to
					<lb/>Fairfield the place of my destination.
					<lb/>It was consoling after so long an interval
					<lb/>to be again in a B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>. which on fu-
					<lb/>ture occasions after Journies, I have often
					<lb/>experienced as a peculiar refreshment
					<lb/>admist the various defects of our Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ns</hi>
					<lb/>there is a flowing together of Soul, between
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-17.jpg" n='17'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>their members, and a facility of becoming
					<lb/>acquainted and even intimate with one
					<lb/>another as belonging to one family, which
					<lb/>I have no where met with out of our Com-
					<lb/>mnnity. I reached Fairfield July 15<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1803.
					<lb/>and has cordially received by B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Willet
					<lb/>the Domestic Manager, and B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> J. Hyland &amp;
					<lb/>T. Bird the Assistant Tenchers of the newly
					<lb/>established Boarding School. My difficul-
					<lb/>ties under God were greatly eased by the
					<lb/>friendship of B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>. W. Foster the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>
					<lb/>Helper there, also by B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Clemens the
					<lb/>Minister. The situation was sufficiently
					<lb/>trying us may easily be conceived when
					<lb/>it is considered that with my imperfect
					<lb/>acquaintance with the language and man-
					<lb/>ners of the Country, it desolved principally
					<lb/>on me to regulate the School, and to form
					<lb/>as well as execute the needful plans for
					<lb/>it future success. Moreover it was incum-
					<lb/>bent upon me immediately and from thence
					<lb/>for two years to live alone with 10 Boys or 12
					<lb/>as the School rapidly increased.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-18.jpg" n='18'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Indeed the success with which the Lord
					<lb/>blessed us was for beyond expectation, so
					<lb/>that in a Year&apos;s time it became necessary
					<lb/>to add a story to the house, which then was
					<lb/>immediately filled with between 50 &amp; 60 Board-
					<lb/>ers and continued to contain that number
					<lb/>besides Day-Scholars, while I was em-
					<lb/>ployed in it. It is not in the spirit of vain
					<lb/>glorifying when I say that my whole strength
					<lb/>was assiduously devoted to my Official
					<lb/>Duty, and that my deal in endeavouring
					<lb/>to aid the improvement of my Scholars
					<lb/>was fervent and sincere. My mistakes were
					<lb/>numerous, and my hasty and parssionate
					<lb/>temper in particular, led me into many
					<lb/>errors in Word and action, not in this
					<lb/>situation only but in futune employments
					<lb/>also. It is my shame that nature was
					<lb/>not more decidedly and entirely mortified
					<lb/>by Grace, and that the meek and patient
					<lb/>mind of Christ was not reflected on me, as
					<lb/>it might have been had I with closer Com-
					<lb/>munion with him by faith and in prayer.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-19.jpg" n='19'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>combined more Watchfulness &amp; Circumspection.
					<lb/>The well meant but often ill directed fervor
					<lb/>with which I was apt to act at the impulse
					<lb/>of the moment and the unpremeditated man-
					<lb/>ner with which on those occasions I was ac-
					<lb/>customed to express my Sentiments and feelings
					<lb/>not unfrequently harsh, gave offence and
					<lb/>wounded the feelings of those whom I affec-
					<lb/>tionately loved, and whose welfare it was
					<lb/>my Sincere desine to promote. To deal
					<lb/>plainly and uprightly was my design
					<lb/>but in so doing I sometimes neglected a
					<lb/>kind and courteous deportment. That
					<lb/>life, injury was occasioned thereby than
					<lb/>might have been expected, is to be attri-
					<lb/>buted to the everlasting Mercy of my
					<lb/>Saviour, whereby the frendishiss of must
					<lb/>with whom I was connected was preserv-
					<lb/>ed to me, and their apology for my hasty
					<lb/>manner was readily made, in the con-
					<lb/>viction of my good intention. The chas-
					<lb/>tening of my own mind by the Spirit of
					<lb/>God was often painful and severe after
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-20.jpg" n='20'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>my warm temper had misled me to an 
					<lb/>inconsiderate mode of proceeding.
					<lb/>After three months residence in Eng-
					<lb/>land I begun to address discourses to the Chil-
					<lb/>dren and on the Sunday before Christmas,
					<lb/>preached my first Sermon in the Englishl
					<lb/>language at Duckenfield. On Christmas day
					<lb/>I was favored to deliver my first public tes-
					<lb/>timony at Fairfield. The Lord supported &amp;
					<lb/>granted me acceptance. I accustomed my
					<lb/>self to take great pains in waiting and
					<lb/>committing to memory the discourses w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi>
					<lb/>from that time I was frequently called to
					<lb/>deliver, and altho&apos; that degree of prepara-
					<lb/>tion was not continued when I obtained
					<lb/>more practice and fluency, yet I never re-
					<lb/>gretted having submitted to that labor, nor
					<lb/>ever without necessity addressed a Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>
					<lb/>until having premeditated the subject of
					<lb/>the address being persuaded that diligent
					<lb/>ffort in every, and more especially in Pas
					<lb/>ral and ministerial employment, is a
					<lb/>ered duty, and that the unction of the 
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-21.jpg" n='21'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Holy Spirit is not only given in answer
					<lb/>to prayer at the time when a discourse
					<lb/>is delivered, but also in the Study or Clo-
					<lb/>set where it is prepared.
					<lb/>In June 1805 I received the painful
					<lb/>intelligence of the decease of my dear
					<lb/>Mother, which affected me more than Words
					<lb/>can express. Abont the same time I re-
					<lb/>ceived the appointment to be Assistunt
					<lb/>of the S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>le</hi> B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Labourer, still retaining
					<lb/>My former Situation in the School. Sub-
					<lb/>sequently the office of Co. Labourer with
					<lb/>Br Arm, on account of the infirmities of
					<lb/>the latter, was committed to me and I ob-
					<lb/>tained a private residence in the S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>le</hi> B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi>
					<lb/>house, altho&apos; spending the greater part of
					<lb/>the day in the School. In the beginning
					<lb/>of the Year 1809 My strength seemed ex-
					<lb/>hausted by continual exertion. My health
					<lb/>appeared to decline, and some relaxation
					<lb/>was thought the necessary. A strong desire
					<lb/>which I had once more to visit my aged
					<lb/>Father and my native Country induced
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-22.jpg" n='22'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>me
					<lb/>the resolution to set out for Germany
					<lb/>notwithstanding the war which was then
					<lb/>carried on and the rigid exclusion of Eng-
					<lb/>land from all communication with the
					<lb/>European Continent by the System of Na-
					<lb/>polien. In reliance upon divine protection
					<lb/>I proceeded in May by way of London
					<lb/>and Harwich to the Island of Heligoland
					<lb/>near the mouth of the Elbe, which was then
					<lb/>the Depot of English Merchandize. From
					<lb/>thence I was with some other passengers
					<lb/>conveyed about 60 miles across the Ocean
					<lb/>to a lonely part of the Westphalian coast
					<lb/>in a small boat in which during a
					<lb/>whole night we were exposed to the most
					<lb/>imminent danger. When landing on
					<lb/>the next evening and delivered into the
					<lb/>hands of people who made exorbinant
					<lb/>gains by the necessities of travellers
					<lb/>whom they might deliver to the French
					<lb/>for Military execution, I ways by then
					<lb/>forwarded in an open vehicle on bye-
					<lb/>roads and thro&apos; forests during a beau-
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-23.jpg" n='23'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>tiful moinlight night, in constant dread
					<lb/>of being seized. The Lord however was my
					<lb/>protector and after varions adventures I
					<lb/>arrived safely in the City of Bremen
					<lb/>where Alderman Tideman whose Sons
					<lb/>I had educated at Hennersdorf give me
					<lb/>a kind and hospitable reception. Among
					<lb/>the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Society in this city I spent a
					<lb/>few edifying days, holding some meetings
					<lb/>with them. By way of Brunswichk, Where
					<lb/>I enjoyed much friendship at B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Stobwasser
					<lb/>house, I proceeded to Gnadau where my
					<lb/>dear Father met me with whom I then
					<lb/>walked to Barby.
					<lb/>Scarcely had I spent or week under
					<lb/>the Parental roof during which I became
					<lb/>acquainted with my Stepmother also
					<lb/>when on Sunday after I had preached in
					<lb/>Hall
					<lb/>the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>Chapel</hi> intimation was given
					<lb/>that the Mayor of the Town, by order of
					<lb/>the neighbouring Prefect intended to ar-
					<lb/>me as as an English Spy. Immedi-
					<lb/>ately therefore I was obliged to decamp
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-24.jpg" n='24'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>across the river Elbe; and now proceed-
					<lb/>ed to Hernhut and other places in Lusatia
					<lb/>to visit the members of the U.E.C.
					<lb/>whose Sessions I attended for an hour
					<lb/>and to enjoy intercourse with many friends.
					<lb/>On my return I spent some days with 
					<lb/>me Father in secret seeing also my 
					<lb/>only Brother and Sister and then went again
					<lb/>by way of Bremen and Varel, to embark
					<lb/>for Heligoland which was done during
					<lb/>the night at a lonely part of the coast.
					<lb/>In Heligoland I waited 2 days in a crowd-
					<lb/>ed and uncomfortable lodging for the
					<lb/>sailing of the English Packet which took
					<lb/>me to Harwich after a three days Sail;
					<lb/>during the night my only couch was
					<lb/>the hard floor of the Cabin, with my
					<lb/>Portmanteau for a pillow. The hardships
					<lb/>of this journey did not injure but ma-
					<lb/>terially invigorate my health, so that
					<lb/>after my return to Fairfield in the Month
					<lb/>of Sept, I was again ready to resume my
					<lb/>active and laborious duty. My
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-25.jpg" n='25'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>scholastic employment however were on
					<lb/>the point of terminating, for I soon recd
					<lb/>a call to be Minister and Labourer of
					<lb/>the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> at Bedford. Before entering on
					<lb/>that office my Marriage become neces-
					<lb/>sary, and with respect to the choice of
					<lb/>or partner for life, I now happily enabled
					<lb/>to leave myself implicitly to the direction
					<lb/>of my divine Lord. After much conside-
					<lb/>ration on my part and that of my eccle-
					<lb/>siastical superiors, the S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>le</hi> S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Eliz<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> Greves
					<lb/>of Bristol was fixed upon, and after my
					<lb/>arrival in that city was accepted by me
					<lb/>the proposal being made to her, she ac-
					<lb/>cepted it as coming from the hands of 
					<lb/>the Lord. In Bristol I enjoyed so much
					<lb/>friendship and kindness, that the place
					<lb/>ever since has been peculiarly dear to
					<lb/>me. From thence I also paid a visit to
					<lb/>my venerable friend and Br Clemens
					<lb/>in Both, and in both places preached
					<lb/>several times with freedom.
					<lb/>Dec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 14<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1809 our Marriage took
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-26.jpg" n='26'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>place, being performed at S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>t</hi>. James Church
					<lb/>by the Rev<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi>. T.T. Biddulple. My wife
					<lb/>had the affliction on the very day of
					<lb/>her marriage to be informed of the depar-
					<lb/>ture of her Father, whose funeral I
					<lb/>attended before we left Bristol. In her
					<lb/>I had precisely such a Partner as was
					<lb/>good for me, altho&apos; her difficulty of
					<lb/>hearing impeded conversation, and
					<lb/>was on many accounts afflictive to
					<lb/>her, My manner towards her altho&apos;
					<lb/>I always esteemed her was not as
					<lb/>kind and affectionate as she deserved.
					<lb/>Spirituality and humility of mind,
					<lb/>prudence and circumspection of
					<lb/>conduct, and an affectionate faithful-
					<lb/>ness of disposition together with domes-
					<lb/>tich habits and love of retirement were
					<lb/>the distinguishing features of he
					<lb/>character. She was given me in mer-
					<lb/>cy put up with my failings and at-
					<lb/>tended with watchful assiduity to my 
					<lb/>wants. In office also she was useful
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-27.jpg" n='27'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>and by conversations with the S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> in those
					<lb/>Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ns</hi>, I have served was a blessed help-mate
					<lb/>to me. Another mercy of the Lord was the
					<lb/>gift of a faithful servant whom we obtained
					<lb/>immediately upon our arrival at Bedford
					<lb/>and who, while I write this, has continued
					<lb/>for 21 Years with us, acquitting herself
					<lb/>with exemplary faithfulness, and Making
					<lb/>our interest and pleasure her own. But
					<lb/>while I write she as well as I is with
					<lb/>drawn from activity. Domestic affliction
					<lb/>such as we had not hitherto experienced,
					<lb/>is sent, and doubtless sent in mercy &amp;
					<lb/>compassion lest we be condemned with the
					<lb/>World.
					<lb/>But to return to My Narrative:
					<lb/>soon after our Marriage we proceeded from
					<lb/>Bristol to Fairfield, when at the house of
					<lb/>B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Foster we experienced much kind-
					<lb/>ness. On Christmas Eve an expectation
					<lb/>being entertained that I was to preach a
					<lb/>farewell Sermon the concourse in the
					<lb/>Chapel was such that a Second Service
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-28.jpg" n='28'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>after the first became necessary to acco-
					<lb/>modate the multitude. Jan<hi rend='superscript:true;'>y</hi> 7<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1810 B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>
					<lb/>T. Moore ordained me a Deacon of the
					<lb/>B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Church, my wife being at the same
					<lb/>time accepted an Acoluth. The 11<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> of the
					<lb/>same month we arrived at Bedford &amp;
					<lb/>were on the 14<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> when the Anniversary
					<lb/>of that Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> was celebrated introduced
					<lb/>by my predecessor B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> S. Church as its
					<lb/>future Labourers. Goodness and mercy
					<lb/>appointed me to this post at which I
					<lb/>laboured 3 Years with delight, and which
					<lb/>with the late B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> J. Hartley I may call
					<lb/>my halcyon station. With zeal I entered
					<lb/>upon my Office and with forbearance &amp;
					<lb/>affection was I received, and treated by
					<lb/>the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>. Uniform peace and brother-
					<lb/>by union distinguished the course of this
					<lb/>dear flock and few occurnences of a dis-
					<lb/>tressing nature marred My happiness.
					<lb/>In addition to My Minesterial duties
					<lb/>which were laborious but pleasing to me
					<lb/>I had the inspection of the Girls Boarding
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-29.jpg" n='29'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>school, which added to my comfort, and at
					<lb/>which I was occupied 3 hours daily in the work
					<lb/>of instuction. It was likewisel an addition to
					<lb/>my opportunities of serving My Saviour to
					<lb/>preach regularly in several neighbouring
					<lb/>villages. In how far My activity was prompt-
					<lb/>ed by a single view to the Glory of God, and the
					<lb/>Salvation of Sinners, I do not venture to pro-
					<lb/>nounce; difficult as I find it positively to
					<lb/>ascertain my own motives for acting, I ap-
					<lb/>prehand that a constitutimal and vestless
					<lb/>disposition, finding personal gratification
					<lb/>in being constantly employed, had a share
					<lb/>in it. The Lord however blessed my endeavour
					<lb/>and covered My Sins, which were greater
					<lb/>and more numerous than I can describe
					<lb/>My reproofs of others were often severe, and
					<lb/>not couched at all times in the language
					<lb/>of compassion, and alas! how apt aare we
					<lb/>to forget our own blemishes in attempt-
					<lb/>ing to rectify those of others.
					<lb/>To my great Surprise I received to-
					<lb/>wards the end of the year 1812 a call to be
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-30.jpg" n='30'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> helper and Minister of Fulneck
					<lb/>and the neighbouring Country Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ns</hi>, and
					<lb/>with my wife to be Labourer of the Marr<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi>
					<lb/>Choir there. It was a hard stroke, and while
					<lb/>feeling the pangs of sep<hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>e</hi>aration from a
					<lb/>most beloved flock, I foresaw the difficul-
					<lb/>ties of the extensive sphere of labour w<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ch</hi>
					<lb/>awaited me, and the numerous perplexi-
					<lb/>ties connected with my new appointment.
					<lb/>However having the conviction that the Sum-
					<lb/>mons came from the Lord, obedience was
					<lb/>my only and immediate choice. The
					<lb/>farewell at Bedford was mutually
					<lb/>affecting and painful. Feb<hi rend='superscript:true;'>y</hi> 3<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> 1813
					<lb/>we arrived at Fulneck, and after I had
					<lb/>been by B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>. T. Moore ordained a Presby-
					<lb/>ter of the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Church, I entered upon my
					<lb/>labours with alacraty. The Presidency
					<lb/>of the E.C., and the general oversight of
					<lb/>the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ns</hi>. in Yorkshire added to
					<lb/>my responsibilites, and I required more
					<lb/>&amp; circumspection
					<lb/>humility, than I possessed. A place Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>
					<lb/>has peculiar advantages and excellencies
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-31.jpg" n='31'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>of the inhabitants have truly Spiritual
					<lb/>minds, otherwise it is apt to afford oppor-
					<lb/>tunities for scandal and bickering.
					<lb/>Among the widely scattered B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi>
					<lb/>in the County, I found much scope for
					<lb/>exertion, and perceived that My labours
					<lb/>were not in vain in the Lord. The atten-
					<lb/>dance at the public services at Fulneck
					<lb/>was generally numerous, and instances
					<lb/>of awakened and converted sinners were
					<lb/>not wanting whom I hope to meet in Para-
					<lb/>dise as my joy and crown of rejoicing.
					<lb/>While on the other hand many pleasing
					<lb/>hopes of my born babes in Christ were
					<lb/>disappointed, and many tender plants
					<lb/>seemed to be nipped in the bud by the
					<lb/>blasts of the Wordd, I had cause for both
					<lb/>weeping and rejoicing.
					<lb/>A year after my arrival at Fulneck
					<lb/>I experienced another remarkable pre-
					<lb/>servation of my life. I had occasion to
					<lb/>visit an aged Sister 5 miles from home
					<lb/>to administer the Communion to her, On
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-32.jpg" n='32'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>my return the Horse on which I rode threw
					<lb/>me on hard frozen and stony ground, I es-
					<lb/>caped with my temples bleeding and my
					<lb/>shoulder injured, so as to oblige me to car-
					<lb/>ry my arm some time in a sling, with-
					<lb/>out receiving any permanent hurt, &amp; 
					<lb/>providentially our Medical Man rode
					<lb/>past at the very moment and lent me
					<lb/>has immediate assistance. Another call
					<lb/>was this for gratitude, and a new sur-
					<lb/>render of my all to my Saviour&apos;s Service.
					<lb/>In the Year 1818 I was invited by the
					<lb/>U.E.C. to attend the Synod of the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Unity
					<lb/>and proceeded to Hernhut accompanied
					<lb/>by my wife &amp; infant daughter Elizabeth
					<lb/>Graves, who had been born to us Oct. 2<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> 1815.
					<lb/>This dear and only child was an object
					<lb/>of My tenderest solicitude. I baptized her
					<lb/>the Sunday succceding her birth into the
					<lb/>death of Jesus with indescribable feelings,
					<lb/>the responsibility of training an immortal
					<lb/>soul with parental fidelity for the Kingdom
					<lb/>of heaven lay with all its weight upon my
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-33.jpg" n='33'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>mind, but many are the mistakes, omissions 
					<lb/>and neglects of which I stand convicted before
					<lb/>my God in this sacred duty. Indeed my Offi-
					<lb/>cial duties left me little leasure to devote to
					<lb/>the personal instruction of my own child.
					<lb/>In her unfolding faculties I had, combined
					<lb/>with much gratification also a practi-
					<lb/>cal exemplification of the depravity of hu-
					<lb/>man nature from earliest youth. The
					<lb/>affectionate disposition and facility in ac-
					<lb/>quiring knowledge, which we discerned in
					<lb/>our dear daughter gave as much pleasure
					<lb/>and compensated for the pains which the
					<lb/>correction of her evil temper gave us. That
					<lb/>the grace of Christ our Saviour might migh-
					<lb/>tily lay hold of her, and direct her whole heart
					<lb/>and Soul into the path of peace and holiness
					<lb/>continues to be my hearty prayer.
					<lb/>On the journey to and from Hernhut
					<lb/>I had a last opportunity of visiting my
					<lb/>faithful and aged Father, who soon after fell
					<lb/>asleep in Jesus. At the Synod, besides at-
					<lb/>tending in the capacity of Deputy for all
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-34.jpg" n='34'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>the Yorkshire Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ns</hi> I acted as Secretary
					<lb/>and also superintended the copying of the
					<lb/>Synodal worth. In that occasion I became
					<lb/>more intimately acquainted with, and
					<lb/>more firmly attached to the principles
					<lb/>of the B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rns</hi> Unity, being also more clearly
					<lb/>convinced that she carries on the course of
					<lb/>God, and has a worth far beyond what her
					<lb/>small numbers and unobtrusive habits
					<lb/>lead men generally to conceive. In Sept the
					<lb/>same year I returned to my former Situ-
					<lb/>ation in Fulneck. Here I also availed my-
					<lb/>self of many opportunities of co-operating
					<lb/>with Children of God in other Denominations,
					<lb/>considering it to be a peculiar calling of
					<lb/>our Church, to help in uniting the scat-
					<lb/>tered children of God. In Bedford already
					<lb/>it was a pleasing duty to me, in concert
					<lb/>with the Rev<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> Mess<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> Legh Richmond and
					<lb/>Sam<hi rend='superscript:true;'>l</hi> Hilyard to aid in the establishment
					<lb/>of Bible Associations in every part of the
					<lb/>County, and now I preached and assisted at
					<lb/>Public religious meetings in different
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-35.jpg" n='35'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>parts of Yorkshire as far as appeared to me
					<lb/>consistant with My more immediate charge.
					<lb/>My design was to combine with conscien-
					<lb/>tious Attachment to our division, of the fold
					<lb/>of Jesus, a charitable union with all other
					<lb/>children of God, and without compromise
					<lb/>of principle to aid in proving that one is
					<lb/>our Master even Christ, and that we all
					<lb/>are Brethren.
					<lb/>Various sorrowful occurrances during
					<lb/>the latter port of my residence in Fulneck
					<lb/>materially diminished My comforts and
					<lb/>impacted My usefulness, I neither can
					<lb/>nor will exculpate myself (The maxim
					<lb/>&quot;avoid all appearance of evil&quot; I had not
					<lb/>by any means learned and reduced to
					<lb/>practice,) Nor can the Searcher of hearts
					<lb/>pronounce me guiltless. My own consci-
					<lb/>ence charges me with unfaithfulness in
					<lb/>secret and private duties; and while I was
					<lb/>always active in whatever was commit-
					<lb/>ted to me, My activity was not always
					<lb/>directed by the genuine spirit of humility
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-36.jpg" n='36'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>meekness and love. (In the beginning of
					<lb/>1824 a visitation from the U.E.C being held
					<lb/>at Fulneck, the want of a judicious &amp; 
					<lb/>impartial investigation of affairs made
					<lb/>me long for my release from the arduous
					<lb/>and difficult station, which I held for
					<lb/>nearly 12 Years, more especially as I could
					<lb/>no longer act in concert with my near-e
					<lb/>est fellow Labourer.)
					<lb/>During the Provincial Conference
					<lb/>which in July of the Year just mentioned
					<lb/>was held at Fairfield, a call arrived
					<lb/>from the U.E.C. for me, proposing to
					<lb/>My consideration the office of Minister.
					<lb/>and Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> Labourer at  Bristol. This
					<lb/>for once was an appointment which
					<lb/>coincided with my wishes, and which
					<lb/>I should have felt inclined to have chosen for my-
					<lb/>self. Deeply affecting was my farewell
					<lb/>of Yorkshire, where I had both laboured
					<lb/>and suffered for nearly 12 years during the most active
					<lb/>period of my life, a great number
					<lb/>precious Souls to whom the Lord and
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-37.jpg" n='37'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>His spirit blessed my feeble labours, will
					<lb/>he hold in remembrance by me while I
					<lb/>live, and to their continued prayers on my
					<lb/>behalf I attribute the enjoyment of man--
					<lb/>fold benefits. &quot;During 7 Years,&quot; said the Head
					<lb/>of a family to me, &quot;Your Name has not for
					<lb/>a single day been omitted in our prayers.&quot;
					<lb/>My Valedictory Sermon was preached
					<lb/>at Fulneck on Sept 12<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> 1824 to a very large
					<lb/>concourse of people, and on the same day
					<lb/>I introduced B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> J. Holmes as my Succes-
					<lb/>sor.
					<lb/>Sept<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 16<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> I arrived with My dear
					<lb/>Wife and Daughter at Bristol, B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>
					<lb/>Okely our predecessors, having previously
					<lb/>left that place for Dublin. Wide as the
					<lb/>field for active labour was in this new
					<lb/>station, I felt it as repose after toil, the
					<lb/>mental trials connected with it being
					<lb/>much smaller than those in My former
					<lb/>office. The previous acquaintance
					<lb/>which at several former visits I had
					<lb/>made with many members of the
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-38.jpg" n='38'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> at Bristol, greatly facilitated my
					<lb/>speedy familiarity with my incumben-
					<lb/>cies, and with the souls committed to my
					<lb/>care. I do not know that I have enjoyed
					<lb/>life during any proceeding period more
					<lb/>than during my residence at Bristol,
					<lb/>which while I write has continued for
					<lb/>6 1/2 years. The Lord dealt very mercifully
					<lb/>with me, gave me faver in the hearth of
					<lb/>many not only of our own communion
					<lb/>but of Servants and Children of God in
					<lb/>various Churches, whose friendship
					<lb/>was valuable and profitable to me.
					<lb/>The Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> increased considerably and
					<lb/>many truly devoted souls were added
					<lb/>to it. My Saviour owned and blessed me
					<lb/>beyond My utmost expectations.
					<lb/>In 1825 I attended the second time at
					<lb/>a Synod of our Church, being deputed
					<lb/>by Bristol and several other Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ns</hi>.
					<lb/>My stay at Hernhut was agreeable &amp;
					<lb/>busy, close confinement not only dur<hi rend='superscript:true;'>g</hi>
					<lb/>the Synodal sessions but during the
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-39.jpg" n='39'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>remaining hours of the day, when much
					<lb/>writing and translating devolved upon me
					<lb/>made the long to return to my less sedentary
					<lb/>employment at home, where after a very
					<lb/>rapid journey of only 10 days from Hern-
					<lb/>hut arrived again Aug<hi rend='superscript:true;'>st</hi> 28<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> (B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> William
					<lb/>Mallalieu was my pleasant compamon
					<lb/>in going, and B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Blumer that Jan<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> in
					<lb/>returning.)
					<lb/>In addition to the ordinary labours
					<lb/>of My Ministry, I was in various ways
					<lb/>occupied with endeavours to promote our
					<lb/>missionary cause both in and out of Bristol.
					<lb/>I being perhaps part of the accomplish-
					<lb/>ment of my Mothers prayer, that I took
					<lb/>peculiar pleasure in advocating the
					<lb/>extention of our Saviours Kingdom among
					<lb/>the heathen, and had many doors for so
					<lb/>doing opened to me by Providence. In
					<lb/>1829 I undertook I extensive journies by
					<lb/>commission from the London Association
					<lb/>in aid of the Brns Missions, and was both
					<lb/>delighted and edified by finding open doors
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-40.jpg" n='40'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>and open hearts, and unfeigned cordiallity
					<lb/>and cooperation in all places and among
					<lb/>all communities and their Ministers whom
					<lb/>I visited. The latter part of these 2 journies
					<lb/>was however rendered peculiarly pain-
					<lb/>ful and distressing to me by the intelli-
					<lb/>gence which I received at the close of a
					<lb/>day of arduous duty, that My dear child
					<lb/>had been seized with a dangerous illness
					<lb/>at Fulneck, where for 3 years she had
					<lb/>been seperated from us at School, and
					<lb/>that her Mother during my absence had
					<lb/>gone to see and nurse her, the accounts
					<lb/>being very alarming none probably can
					<lb/>conceive what I felt, except a parent of
					<lb/>on only child, just on the point finishg
					<lb/>her education, and of whom pleasing ex-
					<lb/>pectations of fruit from the seed carefully
					<lb/>sown and entertained, such a child I ap-
					<lb/>prehended might have been called into
					<lb/>eternity at a distance of 400 miles from
					<lb/>me, the anxious suspence in which I
					<lb/>was held for several days was the more
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-41.jpg" n='41'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>painful as my appointed duty required that
					<lb/>in this state of mind I should travel and preach
					<lb/>going strangers day by day.
					<lb/>In my return home the intelligence
					<lb/>received was still more alarming, and
					<lb/>I was constrained with the utmost speed
					<lb/>to proceed to Fulneck where thro&apos; mercy
					<lb/>I found the child somewhat better under
					<lb/>her Mothers care, and the faithful atten-
					<lb/>dance on the part of the School. During
					<lb/>this trial I found it difficult to pray
					<lb/>with that Submission, which I had often
					<lb/>urged upon others, I did pray fervently
					<lb/>for the child, and consider her gradual
					<lb/>recovery as an express answer to prayer.
					<lb/>Next to the consoling effect of communion
					<lb/>with My Lord, and the powerful relief
					<lb/>obtained by speaking to him as a friend,
					<lb/>the sympathy of my B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rn</hi> &amp; S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> was truly
					<lb/>soothing to me. I had received many good
					<lb/>things at the hand of the Lord, it was time
					<lb/>that I should submissively receive evil
					<lb/>or rather what at the time appears to
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-42.jpg" n='42'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>be evil, being painful to flesh and blood. 
					<lb/>Active duties I had long exercised, passive
					<lb/>duties I found it much more difficult to
					<lb/>bear. Trials were needed to teach me
					<lb/>patience and confidence, to preserve me
					<lb/>from presumption and undue earthly
					<lb/>attachments, to fit me for bearing with
					<lb/>the infirmities and sharing in the suf-
					<lb/>ferings of others, in fire, to fit me both
					<lb/>for my Ministry and for entrance in
					<lb/>to the evalasting Kingdom of Christ.
					<lb/>In Oct<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 1829 our child was so far restored
					<lb/>as to come home with her Mother, and
					<lb/>since then has continued with us be-
					<lb/>ing cheify instructed by me.
					<lb/>Thus for our late B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>
					<lb/>wrote in the beginning of the Year 1831.
					<lb/>It is to be regretted that he did <hi rend='underlined:true;'>not</hi> bring
					<lb/>his Memoir down to a later period, but
					<lb/>this he was probably prevented from doing
					<lb/>by the increased deficiency in his sight.
					<lb/>The following information has been princi-
					<lb/>pally furnished by his afflicted Widow:
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-43.jpg" n='43'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>My late dear Husband had enjoyed
					<lb/>an uninterupted state of good health untill the
					<lb/>month of May 1830 when having set out
					<lb/>on horseback to visit a member of the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi>
					<lb/>who resided at a distance of some miles
					<lb/>he was overtaten by heavy rain and
					<lb/>not having an opportunity of procuring
					<lb/>a change of clothes thus laid the foundation
					<lb/>a dangerous disease. This continued
					<lb/>for some months gradually to gain ground
					<lb/>though without causing any intermission
					<lb/>in his labours, until the Autumn of that
					<lb/>year when a very laborious Missionary
					<lb/>Tour in which the engaged added so alarm-
					<lb/>ingly to its progress as to make it needful
					<lb/>for him to yeild to the advice of his medi-
					<lb/>cal attendants, and abstain for the pre-
					<lb/>sent from engaging in his ministerial
					<lb/>functions.
					<lb/>This was to him a severe strike; for
					<lb/>labour was his enjoyment, and his rest
					<lb/>was in activity. The Separation was felt
					<lb/>by his flock not less than by himself,
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-44.jpg" n='44'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Diary.&quot; The D.W. from Prov. 3<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> 11 &amp; 12
					<lb/>My Son despise not this chastening of the
					<lb/>Lord, neither be weary of his correction,
					<lb/>For whom the Lord loveth he correcteth
					<lb/>even as a Father the Son in whom he
					<lb/>delighteth&quot; is strikingly appropriate
					<lb/>for this completion of the 51<hi rend='superscript:true;'>st</hi> Year of my
					<lb/>life. O Lord, my God and Redeemer, thou
					<lb/>hast chastened me, but not in anger.
					<lb/>Thou hast wounded me in the tenderest
					<lb/>part, but it is with a view to heal
					<lb/>My sinsick soul. Forbid that I shou&apos;d
					<lb/>despise thy correction, or be weary
					<lb/>of it! Accomplish thy design with me
					<lb/>in this infliction of thy rod I can
					<lb/>distinctly trace abundant and very
					<lb/>undeserved mercies mingled with thy
					<lb/>judgments. Did I place culpable depen-
					<lb/>dence in bodily health and earthly en-
					<lb/>joyments, shew me my impotence, and
					<lb/>wean me from things visible. Were
					<lb/>my eyes improperly fixed on external
					<lb/>objects and on other mens Characters
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-45.jpg" n='45'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>and did I in attempting to be faithful
					<lb/>in office forgot faithfulness to my own
					<lb/>soul, teach to by the privation of clear
					<lb/>sight to look more carefully within, &amp;
					<lb/>to bask in the light of thy Spirit! Help me
					<lb/>to comfort others with the comfort Where
					<lb/>with then comfort test me? Give me an in-
					<lb/>crease of humility, Sympathy, and an
					<lb/>affectionate demeanour! Let the bright
					<lb/>dawn of this morning be a pledge of a
					<lb/>return of brighter days, and still per-
					<lb/>mit me to serve thee on earth if con-
					<lb/>sistant with thy good and perfect will,
					<lb/>if not prepare me for thyself. Be thy
					<lb/>Passion and death my only hope in life,
					<lb/>and when walking through the valley
					<lb/>of the shadow of death.&quot;
					<lb/>His health continued in apparently
					<lb/>the same state till about two months pre-
					<lb/>vious to his decease, when his appetite
					<lb/>began to fail, and he was unable to the
					<lb/>solid food. His strength was now visibly
					<lb/>declining from day to day, and although
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-46.jpg" n='46'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>still continuing in the discharge of
					<lb/>laborious Ministerial duties, it was
					<lb/>evident that unless a material im-
					<lb/>provement soon took place, we could
					<lb/>not expect to see him much longer
					<lb/>among us.
					<lb/>On the 15<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> Oct<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r.</hi> he went to Brockwear
					<lb/>near Tintern, to lay the foundation
					<lb/>of a Chapel there, a cause in which
					<lb/>he felt warmly interested, as he hoped
					<lb/>it Would be the means under the divine
					<lb/>blessing, of conveying the saving know-
					<lb/>ledge of Christ to a very destitute and
					<lb/>degraded population.
					<lb/>Thongh suffering under great
					<lb/>weakness of body he was enabled to go thro&apos;
					<lb/>the duty, and in the evening addressed a
					<lb/>Sermon to a very crowded auditory.
					<lb/>The exertion however was too great for
					<lb/>his strength, and in his return next
					<lb/>day be appeared to suffer under great
					<lb/>exhaustion, sleeping in the Cabin
					<lb/>during the whole of the voyage.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-47.jpg" n='47'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>On Sunday the 21<hi rend='superscript:true;'>st</hi> in a state of extreme
					<lb/>weakess he entered upon his duties as
					<lb/>usual. At the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> meeting at 10 he spoke
					<lb/>on the D.W. for the day. &quot;The memory of the
					<lb/>just is blessed.&quot; A Subject the more touching
					<lb/>because while he treated of it every mind
					<lb/>was impressed with the beleif that the truth
					<lb/>could be soon applicable to himself. He
					<lb/>afterwards preached with great clearness
					<lb/>and warmth on the Words of our Saviour
					<lb/>to the Paralytic man, Matth. 11 2 &quot;Son
					<lb/>be of good cheer thy sins be forgiven thee.&quot;
					<lb/>This occasion was one of a most affecting
					<lb/>nature, and few of those who were present
					<lb/>will easily forget it. The discourse was
					<lb/>listened to as the Words of a dying man,
					<lb/>the Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> felt as it he was taking his
					<lb/>public leave of them, and participated in
					<lb/>the feelings of the Elders of the Church of
					<lb/>Ephesns, Sorrowing most of all that they
					<lb/>should see his face to more. In the after
					<lb/>noon he made an attempt to keep the Widows
					<lb/>Choir Meeting but was obliged by weakness
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-48.jpg" n='48'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>to dismiss them after a short prayer.
					<lb/>On Monday he went to the house of a kind
					<lb/>friend in Clifton, as it was hoped that 
					<lb/>change of air and scene might be of tem-
					<lb/>porary use to him. But this was not the
					<lb/>case, his strength rapidly declined. and
					<lb/>a drowsiness came on him, so that near-
					<lb/>by the whole of that day and Tuesday he
					<lb/>was in a dying state. On Tuesday a friend
					<lb/>called, and found him on the bed, it was
					<lb/>remarked, I fear you feel very weak. 
					<lb/>&quot;Weak, weak, weak,&quot; was his reply. In a
					<lb/> somewhat lower tone. &quot;How very weak
					<lb/>I am, My Saviour well can see.&quot; When
					<lb/>looking round, &quot;I long to be delivered from
					<lb/>the body.&quot; You never felt so before, did you?
					<lb/>it was asked. Oh no! it it seems strange
					<lb/>but one is so useless lying here.&quot;
					<lb/>An Affectionate message was delivered
					<lb/>from B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>. P. La Trobe, adding that he would
					<lb/>gladly come down to assist him, had not
					<lb/>pressing Missionary business prevented.
					<lb/>These words seemed to revise his latent
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-49.jpg" n='49'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>energy and he said with earnestness. &quot;I
					<lb/>wish he would come and preach a mission-
					<lb/>ary Sermon here.&quot; give my best love to them
					<lb/>all and tell him I have a missionany Ser-
					<lb/>mon to preach on Sunday week, and if he
					<lb/>would come and take it, that would indeed
					<lb/>be a good thing.&quot; While promising to de-
					<lb/>liver the message, it was asked, &quot;but do
					<lb/>you look forward to that?&quot; As of recol-
					<lb/>lecting his state, be calmly said, &quot;I look
					<lb/>forward to nothing.
					<lb/>On Wednesday he expressed his desire
					<lb/>to return home, having prepared his
					<lb/>Sermon for that evening, and being parti-
					<lb/>cular desirous to Preach as he said he
					<lb/>had some delightful meditations on the
					<lb/>subject during the morning. He was con-
					<lb/>ducted down stairs and into the Car with
					<lb/>dificulty; on our arrival at home all
					<lb/>his strength seemed to be gone, and after
					<lb/>being supported into his Study he fainted
					<lb/>away. By the application of suitable means
					<lb/>he revived, and being asked how he felt,
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-50.jpg" n='50'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>replied, &quot;I am in very blessed Meditation.&quot;
					<lb/>In the afternoon he was not quite himself
					<lb/>but spoke rather incoherently, and repeated-
					<lb/>ly asked if it was not time for the evening
					<lb/>Service being affraid lest we should deceive
					<lb/>him. About 5 o cleck he became quite sen-
					<lb/>sible, said he was <hi rend='underlined:true;'>very</hi> weak, and asked
					<lb/>who was going to Preach? and when I said
					<lb/>Br Seifferth he seemed quite contented.
					<lb/>I asked him if he felt our Saviours pre-
					<lb/>sence? he said &quot;I feel very happy and long
					<lb/>to go.&quot; I said I thought it would not be long.
					<lb/>He said, &quot;Do for think so? catching at my
					<lb/>words as if quite delighted with the idea.
					<lb/>With the Assistance of a B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r </hi>we got him
					<lb/>up stairs to bed, and called in D<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>. Pretch-
					<lb/>ard, who prescribed for him, but with
					<lb/>out affording relief. During the whole of
					<lb/>the evening he had a troublesome rattle
					<lb/>in his throat, be enquired if we heard it
					<lb/>and made the remark: &quot;That will carry
					<lb/>me a good way to night.&quot; About nine oClock
					<lb/>he fell into a deep sleep from which he
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-51.jpg" n='51'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>never awoke, but peacefully and hap-
					<lb/>pily breathed his last about 2 o Clock in
					<lb/>the morning of Thursday the 25<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> Oct<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 1832,
					<lb/>after a Pilgrimage of 52 years &amp; 7 Months.
					<lb/>Thus was this faithful Servant called
					<lb/>and by his gracious Master into his eternal
					<lb/>rest - a rest, into which, more especially
					<lb/>during the latter period of his illness, he
					<lb/>expressed his most ardent desire soon to en-
					<lb/>ter. When his health was suffering under
					<lb/>the first attack, and his speedy dissolution
					<lb/>was by some apprehended, and by himself
					<lb/>thought not improbable, he expressed his
					<lb/>perfect resignation to the will of God, whe-
					<lb/>ther for life or for death, but <hi rend='underlined:true;'>now</hi> he longed
					<lb/>for repose, his all absorbing desire
					<lb/>was, &quot;to depart, and to be with Christ.&quot;
					<lb/>He said not much in his latter days rela-
					<lb/>tive to his departure, but what be did say
					<lb/>showed that his Mind was in a state of
					<lb/>heavenly peace, &quot;looking for and hasting
					<lb/>to the coming of the Son of Man.&quot; That Sa-
					<lb/>viour whom it had been his delight to
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-52.jpg" n='52'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>It was constantly apparrent that he had one
					<lb/>great object in view - the Service of his Lord
					<lb/>nor was he ready to allow mere consideration
					<lb/>of difficulty or labour for a moment to
					<lb/>interrupt any plan that seemed likely to
					<lb/>advance it. This Singleness of view could
					<lb/>not but win the respect even of those to whom
					<lb/>his uncompromising and (as he has him-
					<lb/>self with humility acknowledged) occasion-
					<lb/>ally harsh manner might have given offence.
					<lb/>In the discharge of his Pastoral duties
					<lb/>he was unwearied, regularly visiting every
					<lb/>member of his flock and attending at the
					<lb/>bed of the sick.
					<lb/>As a <hi rend='underlined:true;'>Minister</hi>, he was a scribe well
					<lb/>instructed unto the Kingdom of Heaven.
					<lb/>His naturally strong talents were furnishd
					<lb/>with materials by assiduous Study. The
					<lb/>word of God was the mine in which he con-
					<lb/>tinually delved, and having in his ownh
					<lb/>heart felt the vitality of its truths, he was
					<lb/>enabled to place them before his heavens with
					<lb/>the clearness of spiritual discernment, and
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-53.jpg" n='53'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>that freshness which self experience alone
					<lb/>can impart. His discourses were distin-
					<lb/>guished by great perspicuity and power,
					<lb/>his mind readily grasped the bearings of
					<lb/>his subject, and he had the faculty of
					<lb/>placing it in a strong light before his
					<lb/>hearers. But above all there was a warmth
					<lb/>of heart and an earnestness for the sal-
					<lb/>vation of souls, which under the operation
					<lb/>of the Holy Spirit brought home the truth
					<lb/>to the heart, and we have with humility
					<lb/>to thank the Lord that his Ministry here,
					<lb/>as well as in former stations, has been
					<lb/>attended by <hi rend='underlined:true;'>his</hi> distinguished blessing, that
					<lb/>many Souls have through him been
					<lb/>brought to a knowledge of their lost state
					<lb/>by nature, and been led to the cross of
					<lb/>Christ, and found pardon and peace thro&apos;
					<lb/>them, and that the weak believer has been
					<lb/>strengthened, the desponding encouraged
					<lb/>the mourner comtorted, and many, we
					<lb/>trust, established and built up in the 
					<lb/>faith.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-54.jpg" n='54'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>It was his delight to present to his fel-
					<lb/>low Sinners that salvation, which was pro-
					<lb/>cured by the sufferings and death of the
					<lb/>incarnate Son of God, in all its fulness
					<lb/>and freeness and to point him to the Lamb
					<lb/>of God as taking away the Sins of the World.
					<lb/>Yet he withheld no part of the counsel of
					<lb/>God. He insisted upon the vital nature
					<lb/>of true faith in Christ, and the conse-
					<lb/>quent necessity of its purifying the heart
					<lb/>and manifesting itself in works of love.
					<lb/>His Sermons had therefore always a
					<lb/>practical character, evangelical prin-
					<lb/>ciples being traced to their legitimate
					<lb/>operations in the Mind and their effect
					<lb/>upon the life. He was well acquainted
					<lb/>with the deceitful workings of the human
					<lb/>heart, and with unsparing hand would
					<lb/>tear away the disguises under which
					<lb/>they were concealed. No hearer was allowd
					<lb/>to forget himself, and his own case under
					<lb/>the consideration of bare generalities, but
					<lb/>the Preacher by making not indeed <hi rend='underlined:true;'>personal</hi>
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_03_RamftlerCF-55.jpg" n='55'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>but individual application of the truth, 
					<lb/>??? to manifest it so as to &quot;come
					<lb/>mind himself to every mans conscience
					<lb/>in the sight of God.&quot;
					<lb/>May the bright paths of active oper-
					<lb/>ation which he had in the Lord&apos;s service
					<lb/>(and for which we ascribe not the glory
					<lb/>to him, but to the grace of God that was
					<lb/>in him) serve as an example to sti-
					<lb/>mulate us all. This defect let us avoid
					<lb/>they were to him a cause of painful 
					<lb/>humilation: but let us recognize the
					<lb/>truths of a devoted diciple of Christ
					<lb/>conspicuous in this his Servant,
					<lb/>and pray that he may have grace
					<lb/>its follow him in as far as he followed
					<lb/>the Divine Master. May the Lord be
					<lb/>graciously pleased to pour down a double
					<lb/>portion of his Spirit on those who are ???
					<lb/>privileged to labour in has vineyard! and
					<lb/>may he call forth and duly qualify many
					<lb/>others who may be willing to spend themselves
					<lb/>and be spent in His Service!
				
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
