<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Robbins_Hannah_Sophia_Ful_3_125</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_54Robbins-02.jpg" n="1"/>
			<p>
            A few particulars relative to the Course of Life of
            <lb/>Hannah Sophia Robbins who departed at Fulneck
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February 1855.</hi>
            <lb/>The following few remarks must necessarily be
            <lb/>very imperfect, as the <hi rend="underline">departed</hi> left behind her few
            <lb/>written Memoranda referring in any measure to her
            <lb/>walk through life.</p>
			<p>
            What is now given are a few details penned
            <lb/>down from memory.
            <lb/>As any references to the <hi rend="underline">departed</hi> can only be of
            <lb/>use and avail, in to far as they may be turned to
            <lb/>practical account by the <hi rend="underline">living</hi>, it is hoped, the
            <lb/>experiences <hi rend="underline">she</hi> made may in some instances be
            <lb/>as <hi rend="underline">beacons for warning</hi>; in others, as <hi rend="underline">calls</hi> to be
            <lb/>followers of the Lord Jesus; and again also as <hi rend="underline">encour</hi>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">agements</hi> to lay hold on Him, who is the Author
            <lb/>and Finisher of <hi rend="underline">our Salvation</hi>.</p>
			<p>
            She was born on the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of November 1823, at
            <lb/>Saint Johns, in the Island of Antigua, where her
            <lb/>parents were at that time serving as Missionaries
            <lb/>of the Church of the United Brethren. Nothing of any
            <lb/>importance can be remembered of her early life.
            <lb/>She was dedicated to the Lord in her childhood,
            <lb/>and instructed in the things pertaining to Godliness
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_54Robbins-03.jpg" n="2"/>
		<p>
            Her stay in the Island of her birth was of six years
            <lb/>duration; until her Father and Mother were called
            <lb/>in December 1829, to superintend the Mission in the
            <lb/>Island of Saint Kitts. </p>
			<p>
            In the Spring of 1833, she along with several
            <lb/>other children, was brought to England for education,
            <lb/>and placed in the Boarding School in this settlement,
            <lb/>when in her tenth year. She remained there till the
            <lb/>summer of 1838, when she removed to the Single
            <lb/>Sisters House in Fairfield; but she had not resided
            <lb/>there long before an evident alteration took place.
            <lb/>Her health, which had hitherto been good, began to
            <lb/>decline. Many means were resorted to, but none ap
            <lb/>peared to restore it; and as it was stated that the
            <lb/>climate did not agree with her constitution, she was
            <lb/>removed in 1843 to the Single Sisters House in this 
            <lb/>place. Her stay here continued, with few intervals, till
            <lb/>1845. In this year she left Fulneck, and went to
            <lb/>Harrogate for the purpose of assisting Miss Hinch
            <lb/>liffe, in her Boarding School for young ladies.
            <lb/>Her health again proved the barrier to her holding
            <lb/>this situation long, and soon she returned again to
            <lb/>Fulneck. An unbroken course of seven years was now
            <lb/>passed in the Sisters House.</p>
			<p>
            In February 1853 she again obtained a situation
            <lb/>as governess in a family residing at Heaton, near
            <lb/>Bradford; For rather more than a year she lived here,
            <lb/>and gained the confidence of the parents, and the
            <lb/>affection of the children. During this time she was
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_125_Robbins_Hannah_Sophia-04.jpg" n="3"/>         <p>resisting the gradual but fatal decease with which she
            <lb/>was visited. It proved, however, more than she could
            <lb/>bear; and, entirely prostrated by it, she was brought
            <lb/>home very ill.</p>
			<p>
            Under prompt and efficient medical attendance and
            <lb/>care, which were blessed by God, she so far rallied
            <lb/>that she was able to assist a little in giving instruction
            <lb/>in the Girls Day School. As long as her strength word
            <lb/>permit her, she persevered; but about the middle
            <lb/>of December last, she felt herself constrained to desist;
            <lb/>and then it appeared evident to all that her de
            <lb/>parture was nigh at hand. Lingering, and yet
            <lb/>struggling on, she wasted away, her existence
            <lb/>almost a burden. And this she continued
            <lb/>until of pleased the Lord to liberate her from her
            <lb/>suffering, on the morning of the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of February.
            <lb/>With regard to her Christian experience, we would
            <lb/>state the following.</p>
			<p>
            During her early years, and throughout her resi
            <lb/>dence in the Boarding School in this place, she
            <lb/>never (that she could recollect) had any distinct
            <lb/>feelings of drawings of Grace; and falling into
            <lb/>the ways of the young, thought little of Christ and
            <lb/>her soul's salvation. In such a state of mind
            <lb/>as this, she left Fulneck, and entered the Single
            <lb/>Sisters House in Fairfeld. Here, as before
            <lb/>stated, her bodily health began to fail; but
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_54Robbins-05.jpg" n="4"/>
			<p>
            here also it was that her first and abiding reli
            <lb/>gious impressions were made. It pleased the
            <lb/>Lord to work upon her heart with His Spirit.
            <lb/>The influences felt were always remembered; and
            <lb/>it was while receiving instruction preparatory to
            <lb/>her admission to the Lord's Supper, and during the
            <lb/>hour of her confirmation, the feelings of Love to her
            <lb/>Saviour were strongest. When in serious mood,
            <lb/>she always looked back to this time with pleasure,
            <lb/>and frequently asserted that she derived much good
            <lb/>and blessing from the discourses of the late Br. Tho<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>
            <lb/>Mallalieu, who was then Minister of the Congregation.</p>
			<p>
            From this date a long blank appears. Satan
            <lb/>was evidently striving hard to root out the good
            <lb/>seed, and ofttimes to human eyes, had succeeded.</p>
			<p>
            She was often then drawn by Godless companions
            <lb/>into a frivolous and unsettled frame of mind;
            <lb/>looking for pleasure to the things and the people of
            <lb/>the world, more than to the things and the people of
            <lb/>God. There was at the time alluded to a craving
            <lb/>after these things in her own heart, so that
            <lb/>worldly schemes were speedily and cordially em
            <lb/>braced and engaged in. Her naturally re
            <lb/>served disposition prevented her at times
            <lb/>from giving expression so much that she felt
            <lb/>whatsoever she did say in respect to her state of
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_125_Robbins_Hannah_Sophia-06.jpg" n="5"/>
			<p>
            heart we believe was strictly truth. Her thorn in the 
            <lb/>flesh was no doubt <hi rend="underline">Irritability of temper</hi>; but this
            <lb/>might be partly traceable to her bodily condition,
            <lb/>and the influence of the malady with which she
            <lb/>was affected.</p>
			<p>
            In the February of last year she returned home
            <lb/>much reduced in strength, and for a time thought
            <lb/>her end was near. Hope however soon revived.
            <lb/>Still she clung to life, and longed for health. From
            <lb/>this time we think we may date a work begun, and
            <lb/>we trust completed, in her by the hand of God. The
            <lb/>finger of the Lord was gradually writing <hi rend="underline">Saved</hi>
            <lb/>upon her heart. A change in her sentiments, her
            <lb/>feelings, and her temper was soon perceptible.
            <lb/> Less of a worldly tone marked her conversations.
            <lb/>Her thoughts were more firmly fixed upon her soul
            <lb/>and God. The irritability of temper gave way; and
            <lb/>resignation, affection, and gratitude characterized
            <lb/>her. It was evident the work if grace had fully set
            <lb/>in. Still she despaired not of life. The complaint, de
            <lb/>ceptive in its working, often deceived her. At times
            <lb/>the hope of recovery almost amounted to confidence
            <lb/>and then again doubt and gloom took possession of her.</p>
			<p>
            In December last the closing conflict began the
            <lb/>days of her pilgrimage, it was evident to all, were number
            <lb/>ed and few. She now became more resigned to the will
            <lb/>of God concerning her, and was at this time very anx
            <lb/>ious to improve the public means of grace that presented
            <lb/>themselves. Her attendance at the Chapel was often against
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_54Robbins-07.jpg" n="6"/>
			<p>
            advice, but go she would, and no doubt received much
            <lb/>blessing. The last Communion in the old year was one of
            <lb/>very great enjoyment to her soul, and then she was al
            <lb/>mosmt too weak to stand. It was the last time she stood
            <lb/>to worship God in these his earthly courts. The ripening
            <lb/>for Eternity was now rapid. There was a craving for
            <lb/>the food of life; and her language was, yet more,
            <lb/>yet more, she could not be satisfied, the cup could
            <lb/>not be filled to overflowing. All who were willing
            <lb/>to lead or point her to Jesus were welcome. Kind
            <lb/>friends were not wanting. To such she was grateful
            <lb/>to the last; and as Christ has said. "Whosoever shall
            <lb/>give a cup of cold water to one of the least of these my
            <lb/>disciples shall in no wise lose his reward," their labour
            <lb/>love and their words shall be rewarded hereafter.</p>
			<p>
            There were several whom she was always peculiarly
            <lb/>anxious to see, the Sisters Hunting and Haster in
            <lb/>particular. Among them was also our dear Br. Libbey,
            <lb/>whose conversation was relished, and whose advice
            <lb/>was willingly and thankfully taken. She regretted very
            <lb/>much she could not see him once more before she died.</p>
			<p>
            In all these things we believe her confidence was not in
            <lb/>man, but in God. She had many conversations with
            <lb/>her Labouress after the idea of her recovery had passed
            <lb/>away. On one occasion, upon her remarking, "She
            <lb/>had no hope of her health returning, and no wish
            <lb/>that life should be prolonged, but a desire to depart
            <lb/>and be with Christ;" it was asked; Upon what do you
            <lb/>ground Your hope of acceptance? Is it on that desire
            <lb/>to depart? or on any good in yourself? She replied with
            <lb/>firmness "Oh. No." Do you feel that the blood of Jesus
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_125_Robbins_Hannah_Sophia-08.jpg" n="7"/>
			<p>
            alone, His finished work on the Cross, can save you
            <lb/>from eternal death? "O Yes" she replied, "that is
            <lb/>all my hope, I have never been able to express my
            <lb/>feelings in words, but I <hi rend="underline">think</hi> the power will come."
            <lb/>She frequently desired the prayers of her friends, and
            <lb/>said "She desired the company of none but thou who
            <lb/>would converse with her on the concerns of her soul." In
            <lb/>review of her past life, the wish that she had lived
            <lb/>more to the glory of God seemed to possess her mind and
            <lb/>fill her with humility. On a message of affection from
            <lb/>her dear absent Minister (Mr Libbey) being given to her,
            <lb/>that he hoped she was enabled to adopt the language
            <lb/>of the verse of N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 418, "In thy wounds, O Jesus" &amp;c
            <lb/>she said "<hi rend="underline">I can</hi>." She was sometimes tempted to
            <lb/>regard her bodily sufferings as a barrier between
            <lb/>herself and that full tide of love she longed, should
            <lb/>flow towards Him who died to redeem her. At
            <lb/>another time she said "Yesterday I felt our Saviour
            <lb/>be so very <hi rend="underline">precious to me.</hi>" You could cast all your
            <lb/>hopes and fear upon him? it was asked "Yes I could"
            <lb/>She then mentioned the comfort she had derived from
            <lb/>reading &amp; meditating on the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Chapter of Saint
            <lb/>John's Gospel. On Sunday afternoon she was very
            <lb/>weak and languid, and greatly dreaded the last strug
            <lb/>gle between soul and body. She was encouraged to
            <lb/>believe that the Lord would spare her by taking all
            <lb/>pain away at that solemn moment, and shew
            <lb/>Himself near her in the dark valley. She took
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_54Robbins-09.jpg" n="8"/>
			<p>
            comfort and said "Tis only the breaking up of the 
            <lb/>earthly tabernacle" and added that "she had no fears
            <lb/>beyond the grave."</p>
			<p>
            Last Sunday to Br Willey visited her. She felt encour
            <lb/>aged by his words, and desired him to call again,
            <lb/>little thinking that her end was so near.
            <lb/>Throughout the night she was unusually restless, and,
            <lb/>when a little composed, was anxious that her father
            <lb/>should read and pray with her. He did so, and when
            <lb/>prayer was ended, she requested two hymns to be
            <lb/>read, viz; "Rock of ages, cleft for me" &amp;c
            <lb/>and, "Jesus, Lover of my Soul" &amp;c</p>
            <p>She lingered on till morning, and when her dis
            <lb/>solution was known to be at hand, Br Willey
            <lb/>was sent for, who prayed, and blessed her for her
            <lb/>departure. About half past eight she gently fell
            <lb/>asleep, after a pilgrimage of 31 years and 2 months.
            <lb/>Her hope, we believe, was firmly anchored within
            <lb/>the veil, and the language of her experience is
            <lb/>"Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy
            <lb/>youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years
            <lb/>draw nigh, when thou shall say, I have no
            <lb/>pleasure in them. </p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>