<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mary Scott: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_59Rogers">Anna Rogers</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_59Rogers-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_59Rogers-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_59Rogers-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_59Rogers-04.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Mary Scott</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_63Scott-01.jpg" n='1'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Septr the 5th 1764 Mary Scott a Single Women in Hallifax who
					<lb/>was before her last sickness in no Connection with us went Hapily to our Savr
					<lb/>she was born in the above mentiond Townin 1734; Her Parents being Church people
					<lb/>Educated her in the same Way, her Mother was Concerned for her own Salvation;
					<lb/>and when, Mr. Ingham preached several times in Hallifax Church, she
					<lb/>went to hear him, as also afterwards the Brn; &amp; took this her Child alone
					<lb/>with her, but afterwards she became Sick, &amp; went I Happily out of
					<lb/>time in 1746 in relyance upon Jesus Merits. This her Daughter was
					<lb/>then in her 13 Year, she Liv&apos;d all the rest of her time with her Father
					<lb/>&amp; Kept House for him, as a Dutifull Obedient Child, but did not follow
					<lb/>the Brn. any more After her Mothers departure, but went to Church &amp;
					<lb/>led a Still &amp; quiet life, bore a good Character amongst all those that Knew
					<lb/>her. About 2 Year ago she had the first Symtoms of a Consumption and
					<lb/>Dropsy, but was restored again by timely Assistance; However a Troublesome
					<lb/>Cough &amp; Shortness of Breath attended her ever After, she came during that time
					<lb/>now &amp; then to the Stanery to hear the Brn which always left on impression
					<lb/>upon her mind, however she being inclin&apos;d to be good, the Convictions to Seek
					<lb/>forgiveness of Sins in our Savr &amp; his Bloody Visits remained a Mistery to
					<lb/>Her. About Christmass last past her Cough increased to a great degree &amp;
					<lb/>the Dropsial Symtoms Appeared low again, this she went on to the
					<lb/>latter end of February, when she disired one of our Single Srs: to tell the
					<lb/>Br: who comes to the Stanery to come to see her, &amp; Br. Schulze who has the
					<lb/>care of that plan at present went on February the 28th to see her the first
					<lb/>time, when she told him her great concern to be saved with many Tears
					<lb/>and he painted the Friend of Sinners as Crucified to her heart, which had
					<lb/>also its wished for Effect, for she soon Observed that all her former Piety
					<lb/>availed nothing, which gave her great pain. About a fortNight after
					<lb/>it was made clear to her that all selfmade Piety was an Abomination to
					<lb/>our Saviour, &amp; she ventur&apos;d as one who all her Life time had endeavoured to
					<lb/>establish a Rightiousness of her own, as a Sinner to our Saviour, &amp; He
					<lb/>as the Sinners Friend drew near her Heart, which gave her great Comfort
					<lb/>&amp; has never left her during her long &amp; painfull Sickness. Br. Schulze
					<lb/>recomended her to the Single Srs who live at Stanery, &amp; they have
					<lb/>visited her partly every Day to her great Comfort. Sr: Whitehead &amp; some
					<lb/>other Sisters from Wike have also several times gone to Visit her.
					<lb/>Sr May &amp; Ann Birkby who Visited this plan visited her likewise on
					<lb/>June the 18th to their Satisfaction, just then her Dropsy being at Height
					<lb/>&amp; she was Swell&apos;d to a High degree. She has been Oblidg&apos;d to sit up
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_63Scott-02.jpg" n='2'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>&amp; has not been in Bed since Mid-Sumer Day, but has indured every
					<lb/>thing with such Uncomon Patience, that it Struk even Natural People with
					<lb/>Amase, to see her so chearfull &amp; Childlike amidst those incredible pains she
					<lb/>indured, which became at last so Troublesome that she had no rest our Sleep
					<lb/>for near a Week togather, &amp; when ever she must be moved or Lifted at any
					<lb/>time, she could not forbear Crying out like one that is pierced thro.
					<lb/>When ever she was overcome with impatience, she Wept soon After
					<lb/>Ask&apos;d pardon of those about her &amp; Called herself a Coward, because she
					<lb/>did not bear more Childlikely, what our Saviour was pleas&apos;d to let her,
					<lb/>indure.  I continued Visiting her for these 27 Weeks every Tuesday
					<lb/>but one, with real Satisfaction; &amp; found her Heart always Tender,
					<lb/>Towards our Saviour, never did I visit any one more glad &amp; Thank
					<lb/>full then she was every time, amidst her Pitefull &amp; Painfull Sickness,
					<lb/>She being poor, our Saviour raised up Friends who assisted her in all
					<lb/>she stood in deed off; and among the rest a Young Women, who has proved
					<lb/>a Friend indeed: One Grace Holdin who was aquainted with her from
					<lb/>a Child, who has spent most of her time with her &amp; Nurs&apos;d her to the 
					<lb/>best of her Knowledge &amp; when even her Dropsy broke &amp; became
					<lb/>disagreeable she has either Dress&apos;d &amp; Kept her clean herself, or procur&apos;d
					<lb/>some Body to do it for her. however by seing Mary Carried on in such
					<lb/>a manner &amp; hearing me Speak with her has likewise get a concern
					<lb/>for her Souls Salvation, &amp; has come to meetings to the Stanery &amp; disires
					<lb/>to be recieved into the Society. When I saw poor Mary the Tuesday before
					<lb/>last her feet Mortifying &amp; her Body full of exquisite pain, it moved
					<lb/>my heart with such pityy &amp; Compassion, that I could not Speak a word
					<lb/>for some time for altho she was Dress&apos;d twice a Day her Feet which had
					<lb/>great holes, began to be so bad that a Kind of Grups grew in it &amp; fell
					<lb/>out of the holes, but this did not last longer then 2 or 3 Days, I visited
					<lb/>her the last time on Septr. the 4th I Kept her a Liturgy with great
					<lb/>Tenderness, &amp; prayed our Saviour to hasten her dissolution &amp; take her soon
					<lb/>out of this bodily pain, which also came to pass the Day Following about
					<lb/>9 o&apos;Clock in the fornoone, when first the one arm became lifeless &amp;
					<lb/>then that whole side she sinking togather disired to be raised up, &amp; said
					<lb/>soon After now my dear Lamb is acoming for me, which were her last
					<lb/>words, &amp; soon after she fall happily asleep in the 30 year of her age
					<lb/>she is now in Peace.
				
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
