<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Marianne Spence: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_55Spence">Marianne Spence</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_55Spence-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_55Spence-02.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#"
				xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
				xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#"> </rdf:RDF></xenoData>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Marianne Spence</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_55Spence-01.jpg" n="1" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Brief Notices concerning the life and</l>
					<l>happy departure from this world into eternity</l>
					<l>of the S<hi rend="superscript:true;">gle</hi> S<hi rend="superscript:true;">r</hi> Marianne Spence who fell asleep</l>
					<l>in Jesus on Monday Morning. June the 18<hi rend="fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;">th</hi> 1866</l>
					<l>at Fulneck.</l>
				</lg></p>
			<p><lg>
					<l>Our late Sister was born on October the 10<hi rend="fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;">th</hi> 1844 at the Mission</l>
					<l>Station of Bethabara in the Island of Jamaica where her parents</l>
					<l>laboured in the Lords Vineyard as esteemed and useful ser</l>
					<l>vants of the Brethrens Church. From her very birth and more</l>
					<l>especially on the day of her baptism on November the 24<hi rend="fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;">th</hi> she</l>
					<l>was by them dedicated unto the Shepherd and Bishop of our</l>
					<l>souls as His redeemed property with the fervant prayer that</l>
					<l>He himself would tend and keep her as one of his sheep</l>
					<l>This prayer was answered; for the Lord our Saviour was ever</l>
					<l>mindful of her and through the days of her childhood youth</l>
					<l>and to the very end of her sojourn here below manifestly led</l>
					<l>her with his rod and staff. The blessed name of Jesus she</l>
					<l>learnt to know and to love from her earliest years. Brought up</l>
					<l>as a little child in the nurture and admonition of the Lord</l>
					<l>under the parental roof she early learnt to love the house, and</l>
					<l>the word of the Lord, and to pray. She was naturally not of a</l>
					<l>robust constitution a weakness in her chest was perceptible</l>
					<l>even in her youngest years tho' as far as I can hear she never</l>
					<l>materially suffered from this cause at that time. In the</l>
					<l>year 1851 her late father brought her and her older sister here</l>
					<l>to Fulneck for education. She remained for 8 years a pupil</l>
					<l>of the Ladies Boarding school here and throughout the whole</l>
					<l>period approved herself a well conducted obedient, &amp; attentive</l>
					<l>scholar who by her gentleness, and amiable peaceful disposition</l>
					<l>gained the love alike of her superiors and companions. Her</l>
					<l>natural abilities although not of a very striking and superior</l>
					<l>character were such as to render her aided by her diligence</l>
					<l>and perseverance a very efficient scholar. Her health was</l>
					<l>upon the whole pretty good during this period although she</l>
					<l>never was very strong and her rapid growth and tall slender figure</l>
					<l>often made her an object of notice to those who knew her age</l>
					<l>This was particularly the case when she was received into</l>
					<l>the Girls Choir in the year 1854. She was of a very placid</l>
					<l>disposition and did not freely speak about herself and her</l>
					<l>spiritual life, but it was very evident that she grew in grace</l>
					<l>as well as in stature and with the lessons of secular wisdom</l>
					<l>diligently learnt the lessons of heavenly wisdom that made</l>
					<l>her wise unto salvation Those to whom her spiritual culture</l>
					<l>was more especially entrusted often observed with much plea</l>
					<l>sure her serious department and manifest relish for eternal</l>
					<l>truths and heavenly pleasures. She ever meekly &amp; thankfully</l>
					<l>received the spiritual advice of her labouress towards whom</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_55Spence-02.jpg" n="2" />
			<p>
				<l>she always cherished feelings of grateful esteem and sincere</l>
				<l>affection. In the autumn of 1854 she removed to the Ladies School</l>
				<l>at Neuwied where she remained for two years. Here she enjoyed</l>
				<l>the faithful and efficient instructions of B<hi rend="fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; subscript:true;">r</hi> Menzel preparatory,</l>
				<l>to her confirmation at Easter 1861, on which occasion she surrendered</l>
				<l>herself anew to the Lord her Saviour who had been the God of her</l>
				<l>childhood imploring him to be with her throughout her youth</l>
				<l>and even for ever. From the School at Neuwied she proceeded</l>
				<l>to Montmirail in autumn 1861, where after another years instruc</l>
				<l>tions she completed her schooldays and at once was engaged</l>
				<l>upon her return to England to enter into the ladies School at</l>
				<l>Gomersal. She had previously at Montmirail been received into</l>
				<l>the choir of Single Sisters, &amp; now forthwith began to trade with</l>
				<l>the talents her Saviour had entrusted to her keeping. For</l>
				<l>above three years she faithfully discharged the important duties</l>
				<l>of a teacher of the young. How her services were appreciated may</l>
				<l>be best learnt from the following letters received by me from</l>
				<l>B<hi rend="fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;">r</hi> K, and S<hi rend="fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;">r</hi> R (--) At Easter this year she came home for a</l>
				<l>few days to her mother. A severe cold prevented her from re</l>
				<l>turning immediately after the Easter vacation to her sphere of</l>
				<l>duty. She hoped a few days rest and careful nursing at home</l>
				<l>might restore her health. But when this hope was blighted her</l>
				<l>desire was to return upon her duties at any rate at the middle</l>
				<l>of the quarter, and when this also was denied her, she at first</l>
				<l>greatly felt her inability to return to her post where she was</l>
				<l>so happy and so beloved. But as she had been a willing and</l>
				<l>useful teacher, she now once again was willing to be an attentive</l>
				<l>and obedient scholar. The Lord wished her to learn how to give</l>
				<l>up all for Him and die happily.-- It was truly edifying to</l>
				<l>witness, the perfect resignation with which our dear Sister</l>
				<l>acquiesced in the will of the Lord and how calmly and content</l>
				<l>edly she submitted her wishes and her will to his over ruling</l>
				<l>gracious providence. It was not the natural placidity of her</l>
				<l>temper nor apathy which enabled her thus to be resigned and</l>
				<l>quiet. For she herself keenly felt the pang of seperation from</l>
				<l>her beloved mother and other dear relatives and friends, and her</l>
				<l>affectionate disposition made her anticipate the grief her mother</l>
				<l>would have to endure by her early removal. But she knew her</l>
				<l>Saviour, who had given her a heart to know him, that He is the</l>
				<l>Lord and she believed that He did all things well she trusted</l>
				<l>Him and therefore could confidently commit herself and her</l>
				<l>dear friends into this most faithful hands. It soon became mani</l>
				<l>fest that rapid consumption would speedily terminate her course</l>
				<l>through life, and as the complaint gained ground from week to</l>
				<l>week, she ripened more and more for heaven and eternal glory.</l>
				<l>She bore her sufferings with exemplary patience, her deafness</l>
				<l>occasionally caused the sorrow casting a momentary gloom over</l>
			</p>
			<cb />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>her bright hopes of eternal joys. In general her mind was kept</l>
					<l>in perfect peace stayed upon the Lord. Whenever asked respecting</l>
					<l>the ground of her hope, or her prospects for eternity, she expressed sim</l>
					<l>ple childlike confidence in her beloved Saviour. He was near to her</l>
					<l>indeed even Christ in her, the hope of glory. There was no trium</l>
					<l>phant rejoicing in her last illness and death, but there was the work</l>
					<l>of righteousness, peace, and there was the effect of righteousness, even</l>
					<l>quietness and assurance for ever, and there was joy, the joy unspeak</l>
					<l>able and full of glory. Her own set in the serene horizon of God's love</l>
					<l>after a calm bright day of genial summer. We do not here dwell</l>
					<l>at length upon those utterances of her last days and hours, which</l>
					<l>are the sacred property of her sorrowing mother and will no doubt</l>
					<l>cheer her often in the remembrance of the past when the loss of</l>
					<l>her beloved child would otherwise overwhelm her with grief</l>
					<l>But we magnify the grace of God that enabled our late Sister every</l>
					<l>to desire to depart and be with Christ which is far better than the</l>
					<l>possession and enjoyment of all temporal treasures here below.</l>
					<l>Our Saviour was very gracious unto her sparing her the conflict of</l>
					<l>a painful separation of soul and body.-- She literally fell asleep in</l>
					<l>Jesus, and slept herself away into eternity. Her ransomed spirit</l>
					<l>fled from the frail tabernacle, early on Monday morning last; to join</l>
					<l>the spirits of just men made perfect Her end was peace. Her age</l>
					<l>was 21 years 8 months, and 8 days.</l>
				</lg></p>
			<p><lg type="stanza" n="1">
					<l>Christs sufferings have delivered her</l>
					<l>from misery, woe, and death</l>
					<l>His word Tis finished proved to be</l>
					<l>The triumph of her faith.</l>
				</lg>
				<lg type="stanza" n="2">
					<l>Happy soul thy days are ended</l>
					<l>All thy mourning days below</l>
					<l>thou by angel guards attended</l>
					<l>Dids't to Jesus presence go</l>
				</lg>
				<lg type="stanza" n="3">
					<l>Trusting on thy Saviours merits</l>
					<l>Thou hast seen thy Lord above</l>
					<l>Waiting to receive thy spirit</l>
					<l>Reaching out a crown of love</l>
				</lg>
				<lg type="stanza" n="4">
					<l>For the joy He set before thee</l>
					<l>Thou didst bear a moments pain</l>
					<l>Die to live a life of glory;</l>
					<l>Suffer, with, thy Lord to reign</l>
				</lg></p>
			<p><lg>
					<l>Fulneck June 21<hi rend="fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; superscript:true;">st</hi> 1866</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
