<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Charles Henry Conrad Von Larisch: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository ref="mlpla000003">Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles">Charles Henry Conrad Von Larisch</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-05.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-08.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-09.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-12.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-13.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="#">Charles Henry Conrad Von Larisch</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2019-11-11" who="#cpirmann">Corrected for structure</change>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Charles Henry Conrad Von Larisch</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-02.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Lindsey House Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1754.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>After the remains of our dear B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larish were intred, the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></l>
							<l>(among whom where many from London) met in the Family Hall in</l>
							<l>Lindsey House and then was Sung that Hymn: O Head so full of</l>
							<l>Bruises &amp; After which the Disciple spoke in English as follows.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>I have but a few words to say on this Occasion, the Liturgy of to</l>
							<l>Day belongs to the Evening when our Saviour went from us, the pre-</l>
							<l>sent Day has besides that, the particular character of all Saints, &amp; that</l>
							<l>gives me a handle to speak something of the Saints, &amp; of the nature of a Saint.</l>
							<l>&apos;Tis a name quite common in the Bible, and if we hear of a good Man</l>
							<l>who left the World 2, or 300 Years ago, then we have not much against</l>
							<l>his appearing in that Character, and are not shock&apos;d by it,</l>
							<l>but the Ideas we have form&apos;d to ourselves of a Saint are such, that</l>
							<l>in the Romish Church itself no body can be called so, till 1000</l>
							<l>Years after his Departure. The reason is because one fears,</l>
							<l>if any one should remain who had seen that Man or</l>
							<l>Woman he would Controul his Sanctity, he would</l>
							<l>say something that would lesson his Opinion of his Wor-</l>
							<l>thiness. I am sure one is greatly mistaken in this Respect,</l>
							<l>but as we are calld to promote the Sinnership we</l>
							<l>are not so Curious to receive that Name, Saint, we</l>
							<l>care not if that Charactor should be heard of no more</l>
							<l>but for all that I would not have it, that we shou&apos;d</l>
							<l>loose the meaning of the Thing together with the name</l>
							<l>Title &amp; Charactor, &amp; should ee prove careless in that point</l>
							<l>I Fear we should be deprived of a great Charactor in the Gos-</l>
							<l>pel Train. A Saint in my Opinion is a Christian,</l>
							<l>who thinks very little, who perhaps may be oblig&apos;d to</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-03.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>think of many things on Account of his Business &amp; of his</l>
							<l>Office, but when I say he thinks not much, I mean that he</l>
							<l>does not care to think much, according to the Inclination</l>
							<l>of his Heart. You will scarcely find a Saint among the great</l>
							<l>Men, the Rich &amp; learn&apos;d Men, perhaps not among the Gen-</l>
							<l>try, or what one calls an easy Person in this World, the rea-</l>
							<l>son is, because all such charge themselves with too ma-</l>
							<l>ny Superfluities, while the necessary condition of becoming</l>
							<l>a Saint, is not to have a great Store of Idle &amp; unnecessa-</l>
							<l>ry things about him. Simplicity &amp; plainness is the Distin-</l>
							<l>guishing, mark of a Saint. I confess that if a Person</l>
							<l>of that Character, happens to want Education &amp; of</l>
							<l>Course what one calls all manner of required Qualities</l>
							<l>hath absoludely not so much notion of the World, as</l>
							<l>to deal in an ordinary Way, in a regular Way, then the</l>
							<l>Sanctity of such a Man, may not comand that Honour</l>
							<l>that Awe, that Reverence which is due to it as long as he</l>
							<l>lives, &amp; it Seems therefore, that I should be afraid to tell</l>
							<l>you now by way of Discourse, what I have already Sung</l>
							<l>of my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larish, whom I always thought a Saint &amp;</l>
							<l>I beleive there are 100 in the Cattalouge on Dypticks of old,</l>
							<l>who were by far not his paramounts, not like him, nor so</l>
							<l>much of a Saint as He. He was a Person void of all</l>
							<l>manner of Education, he had been neglected in all the</l>
							<l>Necessary things of this Life, &amp; after having found the </l>
							<l>Secret, to make himself to be forgotten in this World, after</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>having placed himself behind the Congregation at Hhuth, in</l>
							<l>order to lead a Simple Civil Life, &amp; absolutely not regard-</l>
							<l>ed by any one, which he contriv&apos;d so out of a true Humility,</l>
							<l>for He was a Lord, &amp; had then many Subjects, &amp; a great</l>
							<l>Territory of his own. When he was in that Situation</l>
							<l>he came hither, and met with one of the most Difficult</l>
							<l>Tasks which can be imagin&apos;d, nevertheless he atcheiv&apos;d &amp; per-</l>
							<l>formd it with such surprising Simplicity &amp; wisdom, that</l>
							<l>I cant help owning once more, that I should have been</l>
							<l>embarrass&apos;d in the highest degree to do the like: And I must add</l>
							<l>that if after my Decease one would compare me to that great</l>
							<l>Man, &amp; my Conduct to his many Personal Circumstances, as</l>
							<l>well as real Intricacies, which would be too long to relate</l>
							<l>here (the Saviour knows them, &amp; part of us are not Igorant</l>
							<l>thereof,) it would be mere Courtesey. B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Larish fullfill&apos;d</l>
							<l>his Task with Honour, &amp; has not left one leaf of his Book</l>
							<l>unfinish&apos;d. His end was like to that of all truly great Men, a</l>
							<l>little while before he had not the least thought of going home</l>
							<l>he was Sick, &amp; a very long time knew his sase almost incurable</l>
							<l>but drew no Consequence from it for in approaching Dissolution.</l>
							<l>When he was acquainted of the Turn his Sickness had taken</l>
							<l>&amp; of the approaching Dissolution, &apos;twas very well, &apos;twas</l>
							<l>all the same to him. Those Days passed away in the same</l>
							<l>Strain as the foregoing. He treated that awful matter as simple</l>
							<l>Natural &amp; unconcerndly fill the last gasp as usual, that</l>
							<l>none of the Heroes of this world, nore of the great Geniuses</l>
							<l>needed to be asham&apos;d of the same Exit, Considering the thing in </l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-05.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>itself &amp; without that difference, which makes his case so</l>
							<l>much happier than theirs, as for that, He will never</l>
							<l>change his Exit for that of any Hero of this World, of</l>
							<l>any great man or Philosopher whatsoever that is quite</l>
							<l>out of Question, all I have to say on that part is,</l>
							<l>that he departed this Life like a Hero.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Every one enabled from above to see the hidden Side</l>
							<l>of things, their real Charactor to extricate the real</l>
							<l>point out of appearances, will never Contradict my opini-</l>
							<l>on, about his abode here, having been like his Departure</l>
							<l>I wish with all my Heart, that so many brave B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></l>
							<l>so many wise ones so many well Educated, so many truly</l>
							<l>learned ones. And which is the best of all so many of our</l>
							<l>Sinnerlike good People may obtain.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>His Natural &amp; Simple Charactor that they who</l>
							<l>had not the good fortune to have known him personally</l>
							<l>may be encouragde thereto by his pretty End.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>What I have said is only Introductory to that little</l>
							<l>Hymn which I have Compos&apos;d on his Account &amp; which</l>
							<l>perhaps will be Translated.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l><hi rend="underline">Next follows some Account of his Life &amp; Departure</hi></l>
							<l>Our dear B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charles Henry Conrad von Parish, was born</l>
							<l>Sept 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1711 in Gradenwiz near Cosel in upper Silesia. He</l>
							<l>was descended from the Ancient Famous Family of the Courts</l>
							<l>&amp; Lords of Larish, also of the Lineage of great Nimsdorff</l>
							<l><add place="above">one</add> of whom, in the Service of our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> is already a grain of</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Wheat in Surinam. He inherited from his parents the Lord-</l>
							<l>ships of Shossloehiz Lomniz Zonade &amp; Rodewiz. In his</l>
							<l>tender Youth he became acquainted with Abbot Steinmez &amp; o-</l>
							<l>ther Servants of God, by means of the well known great Just-</l>
							<l>ness awakening, &amp; he was concern&apos;d about his Salvation very</l>
							<l>much, this continued for some time, &amp; on this account he staid a-</l>
							<l>while in <del>Neustad</del>
								<add place="above">Mandel</add> with Abbot Steinmetz, was at Werningrode</l>
							<l>Halle &amp; other Places, where he thought perhaps he might get a</l>
							<l>Blessing for his Heart. Since 1731 he has been acquainted</l>
							<l>with the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> as well in Jena as in other Places &amp; came</l>
							<l>from time to time to Visit the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> in Hhuth, where the</l>
							<l>Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> came ever nearer to his Heart. He found no true rest</l>
							<l>from all his good Performance, nor was delivered from his An-</l>
							<l>xiety till he resolv&apos;d in the Year 1739 to become the intire</l>
							<l>Reward of the Smart of Jesus, at the same time he got</l>
							<l>a Conviction to let every thing be as it was, &amp; to betake him-</l>
							<l>self to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> to stay there; accordingly he did so, with</l>
							<l>a true Blessing for his Heart, &amp; he had at that time true-</l>
							<l>ly blessed times for his Heart with the Single Br<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> assist-</l>
							<l>ed also quite faithfully in Building their Choir House</l>
							<l>there. He was also soon received into the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; partook</l>
							<l>of the Corps &amp; Blood of Jesus in the Sacrament with</l>
							<l>the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>In May 1742, He came over to Engl. were he staid for some</l>
							<l>time especially in Yorks<add place="above">hire</add> &amp; was edifying to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> in his</l>
							<l>Servants office in the Hall which he perform&apos;d very faith-</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-08.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>fully &amp; with his whole Heart from thence he returned in com-</l>
							<l>pany with the Dr Disciple &amp; Mother to Holland &amp; so on to</l>
							<l>M-born &amp; was there May 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1743. Married to our S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Diana</l>
							<l>Raymond after his marriage her his Wife were 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Deacons</l>
							<l>in Engl &amp; conducted it with true Simplicity &amp; many Bless-</l>
							<l>sings afterwards he made Several Journeys to Hhuth &amp;</l>
							<l>Hhaag, in this Year also he visited his Lordships &amp; found him-</l>
							<l>self not only not in a Capacity to execute what he had in-</l>
							<l>tended, but found also such an Entanglement in his worldly</l>
							<l>Affairs, that he thought it best to sell his Estates, to pay</l>
							<l>he Debts, &amp; to give the rest to the Diaconate of the Enity</l>
							<l>which at that time was much streighten&apos;d, for wch in the</l>
							<l>Year 1740 the New House calld Lichtenburg was made over to </l>
							<l>him &amp; fitted up, but because his comfort did not like to tarry</l>
							<l>at Hhaag, he went with her first to Zyest &amp; in the last</l>
							<l>Year again to Engl; &amp; enjoyed by his abode in each Place of</l>
							<l>those Cong<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi> much Grace &amp; Blessings for his Heart, &amp; all</l>
							<l>the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> lov&apos;d him, he had a longer attachment &amp; faithful</l>
							<l>Heart full of love to our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; his Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> &amp; amidst the va-</l>
							<l>rious Circumstances w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi> his weak constitution mostly occasi-</l>
							<l>ond. He was never put off from his point, but his Heart al-</l>
							<l>ways long&apos;d after him, whom he can now see bodily &amp; kiss his</l>
							<l>Wounds.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>The latter Years of his mortal Life he was very Sickly &amp; had</l>
							<l>many disorders in his Body, but especially since the Winter</l>
							<l>53 yet as long as it was possible he came to the Opportunities</l>
							<l>in the Disciples House very diligently &amp; with great Chearfull-</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>ness. According to the Nature of His Disease and frequent casaul-</l>
							<l>ties of all sorts He thought nothing at first of going home, till just</l>
							<l>after his Birthday this year when the Watchword was untill the</l>
							<l>glance extend throughout &amp; then he came upon it very happily</l>
							<l>himself, and he was heard to say when by <del>by</del> himself, to our</l>
							<l>Saviour: My Dear Saviour be thou my all in all &amp; round a-</l>
							<l>about me, I am indeed weak, but thou knowest well how to make,</l>
							<l>it better, and he said: I am indeed spent or very weak, but I</l>
							<l>shall soon go into the Regions of health. Another time, when</l>
							<l>he was in great pain he comforted himself with the sufferings</l>
							<l>of our Saviour, &amp; rejorced at the sweet hour of his release, &amp;</l>
							<l>only wish&apos;d that our Saviour wo&apos;d take him to himself in</l>
							<l>sleep. As he pressd very much to have all his Temporal affairs</l>
							<l>concerning him and his regulated while he was here, therefore</l>
							<l>the Synodal Conclusion of 1753, was thro&apos; the interposition</l>
							<l>of the Disciples House but a few days before his end in</l>
							<l>the name of our God brought into the form customary</l>
							<l>here, and tho&apos; all the necessary forms are yet wanting from both</l>
							<l>the Married parties, yet the Deed is delivered to the satisfac-</l>
							<l>tion of all sides. Oct 26 He got a new disorder &amp; said: that now</l>
							<l>he was ready to waite for the last kiss, when the Brn at his</l>
							<l>desire sung him some verses he rejoyced and said O that</l>
							<l>has strengthned me, &amp; so continued in continual thought</l>
							<l>of going home till the 28 of Octo<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> when he said: to this Ser-</l>
							<l>vant Bro<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Summerskill, this Ev&apos;ning or Tomorrow</l>
							<l>morning the expected hour will <add place="above">come</add> &amp; often asked, is it not yet</l>
							<l>time he sent also 2 or 3 times in the night for B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Johan</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="5">
					<head type="page">5</head>
					<pb n="5" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-09.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>to come and bless him, and when Joh came to him, and sung: pale</l>
							<l>Lips kiss him upon the Heart, he said; o yes, and to that Verse and</l>
							<l>when thy Mouth expiring &amp;c. He said even to Day.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Oct 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Towards Morning he took leave of his Wife and said:</l>
							<l>My dear I kiss thee on thy Heart, here I have been thy Hus-</l>
							<l>band and thy Heart, we was both one Body but now no</l>
							<l>more, I an going to our dear Saviour and shall expect</l>
							<l>thee with my Bridegroom with Joy: Afterwards he</l>
							<l>said to B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Summerskill and his Wife, my dear Children for-</l>
							<l>give me every thing and I thank you for all the Love and</l>
							<l>faithfulness that you shew&apos;d me here and the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> will think</l>
							<l>on you for it, thereupon he said to his Maid (who is no</l>
							<l>Sister) adue I thank you also for all you have done for me, I</l>
							<l>wish you well in the World, about Six o&apos;Clock in the </l>
							<l>Morning he desired Brother John<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> to be called</l>
							<l>again, because he was very weak but re-</l>
							<l>cover&apos;d himself as soon as he saw him w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi></l>
							<l>he did several times before; The rest of the</l>
							<l>Time he was mostly as if he was a-</l>
							<l>sleep, &amp; had thereby sometimes such an</l>
							<l>extraordinary lovely &amp; smiling look</l>
							<l>that the eyes of the Brethren &amp; Sisters</l>
							<l>round about him overflowed. Hutton</l>
							<l>said once, such a look is worth more</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>than 100 Guineas, at last he awoke, rais&apos;d</l>
							<l>himself and said to Brother Johannes</l>
							<l>now Bless me, &amp; then he took his hand &amp;</l>
							<l>laid it himself upon his forehead, &amp;</l>
							<l>so Johannes Blessed him with that</l>
							<l>Verse: &amp; let his Mouth expiring on</l>
							<l>thy dear Breast recline &amp;c. to</l>
							<l>which our dear happy heart said yes</l>
							<l>powerfully: Ater the Blessing</l>
							<l>he look&apos;d about once more, when</l>
							<l>he saw Bro<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Johannes, Wallerville</l>
							<l>Hutton &amp; others standing round</l>
							<l>him, he threw them a kiss, &amp; said:</l>
							<l><add place="above">Fare you well</add> Adue sweetly the holy Ghost has</l>
							<l>impress&apos;d upon all upon my heart</l>
							<l>thy committed to him many Sa-</l>
							<l>lutations <add place="above">&amp; kisses</add> to the Saviour and</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="6">
					<head type="page">6</head>
					<pb n="6" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-12.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>the Church above made perfect</l>
							<l>&amp; perticularly our dear Blessed</l>
							<l>Christle, and he promissd it </l>
							<l>with a plain Yes. His last</l>
							<l>Words were: We all live unto</l>
							<l>him &amp; then he shut his eyes</l>
							<l>again and slept &amp; so accord-</l>
							<l>ing to his wish his Spirit was</l>
							<l>kiss&apos;d away in Sleep &amp; the Brn</l>
							<l>&amp; Sisters round him <add place="above">sung him</add> quite into</l>
							<l>his rest. His Tabernacle displayed</l>
							<l>a very happy look with which</l>
							<l>the Brethren &amp; Sisters present</l>
							<l>in Sarons hall delighted them-</l>
							<l>selves</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l><hi rend="underline">Made by the dear Disciple on Br L. Departure</hi></l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>1st Thou venerable Child of Grace </l>
							<l>Go in thy white and Blood wash&apos;d Dress</l>
							<l>To live there henceforth without Sin</l>
							<l>where many a Soul &apos;fore thee hath been :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="2">
							<l>2nd on all Saints Day thy Corpse is laid</l>
							<l>In God&apos;s green pretty Sharon&apos;s Bed</l>
							<l>Where it shall sweetly rest, till He</l>
							<l>Thinks fit to Change it Gloriously :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="3">
							<l>3rd from the Disciples House there are</l>
							<l>Already Sevral Grains Sown there, </l>
							<l>Marigens and her little ones</l>
							<l>* Kleists, Millers, &amp; Golds Little Sons</l>
							<l>and Christels Bones</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="4">
							<l>4th That Corpse is now laid in the Grave to </l>
							<l>On whose account no doubt we have,</l>
							<l>But he who did inhabit it</l>
							<l>Will fetch it Back when quite made fit :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="5">
							<l>5th Now thou that Body&apos;s noble Guest</l>
							<l>Who us so edified hast</l>
							<l>Because thy Farewell was like that</l>
							<l>which we of Fredrick Whilhelm Great</l>
							<l>Commemorate</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<p>
						<lg>
							<l>Or *Kleists, Millers, Gold&apos;s Child&apos;s mortal Bones</l>
							<l>and my own Son&apos;s</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="7">
					<head type="page">7</head>
					<pb n="7" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_3_05_LarischCharles-13.jpg" />
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>6th Thou wert presentis Animi</l>
							<l>Ev&apos;n in thy Farewell Agony</l>
							<l>Some Days thou&apos;st ready for Adieu</l>
							<l>So that thy our Friend &amp; Mother too</l>
							<l>their Pleasure view</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="2">
							<l>7th I saw it when that Angel dear</l>
							<l>Who waited on our Larish here</l>
							<l>Went to his B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>. He did say</l>
							<l>Beloved only think I pray :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="3">
							<l>8th I thought I waited on a Sheep</l>
							<l>Which happen&apos;d on his Path to keep</l>
							<l>But in its Exit turn&apos;d at length</l>
							<l>To Heroism that little Strength :/:</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="4">
							<l>9th This last Act finds so much Applause</l>
							<l>That Ev&apos;n a Christle hath no cause</l>
							<l>To blush at it, when Ludwig shall</l>
							<l>So clear and chearful leave his Call</l>
							<l>O very well.</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="5">
							<l>10th Should one ask seriously: How so? </l>
							<l>What is it that makes Larish go</l>
							<l>So nobly, &amp; afford a Sight</l>
							<l>of which God&apos;s House hold w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Delight</l>
							<l>Saith. That is right?</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="6">
							<l>11th I answer Larish may be stil&apos;d</l>
							<l>In all Respects a simple Child</l>
							<l>A Child, as Scripture teaches us</l>
							<l>Is otherwise Synonimous</l>
							<l>with Genius.</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
					<cb />
					<p>
						<lg type="stanza" n="1">
							<l>12th Swift&apos;s Wit did end in Lunacy</l>
							<l>A Clark doth loose his Forced Esprit</l>
							<l>Ev&apos;n Newton turns a Simpleton</l>
							<l>But Larish, when ripe to be gone</l>
							<l>a Solomon.</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="2">
							<l>13th Thou Partner of this Man, attend</l>
							<l>And ponder well his happy End</l>
							<l>Let thyself in Child&apos;s Mould be cast</l>
							<l>To shall you be right nobly grac&apos;d</l>
							<l>and shine at last</l>
						</lg>
						<lg type="stanza" n="3">
							<l>14th All ye who&apos;re Saints because the Lamb</l>
							<l>Did take upon him your Sins Shame</l>
							<l>Salute him ye who&apos;re gone to Christ</l>
							<l>You here; turn Children be advis&apos;d</l>
							<l>and so Baptiz&apos;d</l>
						</lg>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
