<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/moravianlives/ML/master/Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu.s3.amazonaws.com/data/ml_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcmullen">Morgan McMullen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bking">Brian King</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Consultant, Machine Learning</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p/>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_73Walker-01.jpg" n='1'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Martha Walker
					<lb/>Some particulars of the life of the late Sing. Sis<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>
					<lb/>Martha Walker, written by herself.
					<lb/>I was Born Dec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 12<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi>. 1725 at Cheadly Home in ye Parish
					<lb/>of Stockport Chesher and Bap&apos;d in ye Church of England, but brought up a
					<lb/>Presb<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> to which religion persuasion my Mother belong&apos;d as I don&apos;t remember
					<lb/> any thing particular of my Chil<hi rend='superscript:true;'>ns</hi> years, I shall pass over that time
					<lb/>without saying any thing of it of that time till I came into my 16<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> year about which
					<lb/>time I left my Father&apos;s House &amp; went to service when not long soon after my
					<lb/>Father dep&apos;<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> this life leaving my Mother with Five Chil<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> of whom
					<lb/>I was oldest, and being naturally of a thinking Disposition I was brought
					<lb/>into great perplexity of mind, and one day being exceedingly distress&apos;d about
					<lb/>not comprehending what wou&apos;d become of us, that Text of 
					<lb/>Scripture darted so powerfully into my Mind I will be a Father
					<lb/>to ye Fatherless &amp; a friend to ye Widow Ps 68.5 that I was comforted
					<lb/>yea and all my needless concern was was directly dissipated believing at ye same
					<lb/>time most positively that ye Lord changeth not, but what he saieth is yea
					<lb/>and Amen In my 17<hi rend='superscript:true;'>th</hi> year circumstances requir&apos;d <hi rend='strikethrough:true;'>it</hi> that I chang&apos;d
					<lb/>my place which was exceedingly alone when and I enter&apos;d into service in a
					<lb/>farmers house in my own native place, which it was in this year that at the time when M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>
					<lb/>Ingham &amp; Mr Taylor came into these parts to preach ye Gosple, which being
					<lb/>soon nois&apos;d about, I with many many more went out of curiosity to hear
					<lb/>I see wherein these Preachers differ&apos;d from the generallity of other People, not
					<lb/>understanding the meaning thereoff, but I was soon brought thereby to most
					<lb/>serious and concern&apos;d reflections about my miserable and lost conditon by
					<lb/>nature, which I saw &amp; feelt so plain that I was at once convinc&apos;d, that if Jesus.
					<lb/>did not save me I was undone forever and tho&apos; I now believ&apos;d ye Minister&apos;s
					<lb/>Testimony that Jesus came into ye world to bleed and die in order to save
					<lb/>Sinners yet ye World and its vanity at times got the uper hand appearing
					<lb/>to me in most butiful and lively Colours for as such I then thought them to be,
					<lb/>and engag&apos;d my heart and mind so at times that they had certainly prov&apos;d Master
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_73Walker-02.jpg" n='2'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>had not my kind Shepheard himself who had already Chosen me for his property him
					<lb/>self became the Conquerer, for after spending thus far of my life in ignorance
					<lb/>way with regard to ye happiness to be enjoy&apos;d in Christ Jesus, and a as a Sinner in
					<lb/>sinfulness, I was under  M<hi rend='fontSize:0.0; kerning:0; subscript:true;'>r</hi> lngham&apos;s preaching on the words now then we are
					<lb/>ambassadors for Christ, as though God did beseech you by us we pray you in
					<lb/>Christ&apos;s stead, be ye reconciled to god Cor. v. 20 brought more particularly to ye (understand the) reality
					<lb/>of the matter in myself, wanting no other peace and seeking none else and when as he repeated
					<lb/>the words: Christ is reconciled to you, I pray&apos;d most sincerly to ye Lord to let me ex
					<lb/>perience ye reallity of this grand truth in my heart with ye and I received the possitive assurance that I 
					<lb/>was excepted by him, and I went home with a deep sense of my fallen condition
					<lb/>but at the same time rejoic&apos;d at ye preciousness of Salvation in Christ Jesus, which
					<lb/>I believed to be attainted too, tho&apos; as yet I had not experience&apos;d it fully for myself, but
					<lb/>was sincerely desirous after the same, and ye next day following ye Lord my God
					<lb/>and Saviour made himself known to my heart, in that form wherein for all my
					<lb/>need he underjustise rigor once on ye Cross didn&apos;t bleed. I shall not attempt to explain
					<lb/>or describe, what I then felt and enjoy&apos;d, as this might only serve to marr what concerns
					<lb/>the most important time of my life, from which time I date my happiness both in
					<lb/>time and to unendless etternity, and as this is better understood by experience
					<lb/>then explination, by every one who can say with me. Now no more I strive in vain
					<lb/>Jesus Christ has wone my heart, First my thoughts and free from pain In his
					<lb/>death. I have a part &amp;c. I shall say no more about this important period but that it was
					<lb/>in my 18th year when I was in the greatest danger and feelt more of my depraved
					<lb/>nature then at any other time in my Life, This put a stop to my running headlong into many
					<lb/>foolish erro&apos;s which otherwise my natural inclinations wou&apos;d have led me to, but as I in
					<lb/>some measure felt a liking for what I thought concerned not Christ I begun to under
					<lb/>stand ye Lord&apos;s will was not mine will was not mine now and I frequently pray&apos;d to him since he had confered
					<lb/>ye greatest of blessings upon me, in forgiving me my Sins also to make known his mind
					<lb/>to me with regard to perticulars which were was a disturbance to me in my enjoyment of him
					<lb/>and entierly to set me at liberty from all but everything that so I might have him alone, and as I found this requir&apos;d a
					<lb/>true resignation to his will, this became a matter of concern with to me praying the Lord frequent
					<lb/>to hear and help me, and since I knew I was his, I durst not do any thing of myself
					<lb/>tho&apos; I often had the greatest inclination there to, but ye Lords hand was over me in a
					<lb/>most particular manner, which I have been more sensible off since then at that time, and according
					<lb/>to my petition so it was with me, for I soon found myself intierly set at liberty from everything all by
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_73Walker-03.jpg" n='3'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>my dear. Saviour understanding he had thoughts of peace over me, after which time
					<lb/>I went on in an uninterrupted intercourse with him my best friend, who was become
					<lb/>my dearest and nearest object in the midst of the World. I then join&apos;d M<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>
					<lb/>Taylor&apos;s Society, but a disagreable circumstance happen&apos;d to him which was were the
					<lb/>occasion of his leaving us, &amp; ye means of B<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> Ockerhousen&apos;s coming into these
					<lb/>parts in order to settle a regular Society of which I was one &amp; frequented the preach
					<lb/>ing at Duckenfield as often as possible, and in 1748 according to my request
					<lb/>I went to live with ye S. S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> at Duckenfield to which I had a particular call
					<lb/>in my heart from our dear Saviour, &amp; being quite clear in my call I spent
					<lb/>my time chearful and happy. In ye year 1750 I came with 9 more S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi>
					<lb/>to live in Tiresall Oeconomy here in Yorkshire and during my stay there I was
					<lb/>rec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> into ye Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> &amp; became Spectator of ye holy comunion which both was
					<lb/>very weighty to me. In Dec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi> 1752 I movd with some more to Fulneck
					<lb/>in order to begin the Choir-house where I&apos;ve spent ye remainder part of my
					<lb/>life. In april following I became partaker of ye holy Sacrament with this
					<lb/>Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> which grace was rec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> by me with a deep sencibility of my unworthiness
					<lb/>which made me very timerous about myself Concerning the same but I was strengthened
					<lb/>by my dear Saviours owning &amp; Comforting me thereby to my great a
					<lb/>basement, so that thro&apos; his grace I have been enabled to partake thereoff every
					<lb/>since when ever this Cong<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> on our Choir has been privilidg&apos;d have been favored with the enjoyment
					<lb/>thereof, to my real strength and help thro&apos; this vale of Tears: and my heart
					<lb/>rejoices when ever its approach the time for it draweth nigh, and it was I to rehearse only
					<lb/>some parts of the particulars of my course, relative to the internal matter since I came
					<lb/>into this house it wou&apos;d at make the description of it too long, therefore, I shall leave it with only asking
					<lb/>the following concerning what the Lord his done on my Soul. I sought him, &amp;
					<lb/>found him, while he drew me with the cords of his love &amp; has overcome me so
					<lb/>far that I am made one Spirit with him, never more to part to an endless
					<lb/>Eternity what I have experience&apos;d in the enjoyment of him from time to time
					<lb/>and how I have been instructed by his faithful Schooling in ye knowledge of
					<lb/>my deep depravity &amp; nothingness, in stillness, will be matter of thanks &amp; praise with
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_73Walker-04.jpg" n='4'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Martha Walker
					<lb/>Our late dear Sister has in the above given a faith
					<lb/>ful &amp; true account of her course thro&apos; time. She was
					<lb/>an humble simple devoted Soul; &amp; counted it a privilege to 
					<lb/>serve our Savior whenever it was in her power. She
					<lb/>has been 45 Years a very faithful Sickwaiter in
					<lb/>the Single Sisters house here, during which time She
					<lb/>has attended the 145 Sisters, who have departed to our
					<lb/>Savior. In her office She was truly disinterested.
					<lb/>impartial, tender to everyone, patient and loving;
					<lb/>so that all both those who have departed under her care, &amp;
					<lb/>who have recoverd, always spoke of her with the greatest
					<lb/>regard, and her memory venerable among us.
					<lb/>She remained in the Sickroom as long as she was
					<lb/>able, till in this seven Months before her departure. She
					<lb/>being troubled with a complaint in her leg, in which She 
					<lb/>sufferd much pain, she beged leave to retire from her 
					<lb/>office, &amp; she spent her time amidst all her suffering
					<lb/>chearfully &amp; happily, in hopes of soon seeing her Savior.
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_73Walker-05.jpg" n='5'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>Her complaint towards the close of her life became
					<lb/>still more extensive spread exceedingly; a mortifi
					<lb/>cation having taken place. But amidst all, she was
					<lb/>exceedingly patient, &amp; ardently longing to be at home
					<lb/>with the Lord. One night, shortly before her end, She
					<lb/>desired that her Choirhelper might be called; to whom
					<lb/>when she came, she said, that she wished to tell
					<lb/>her, how unspeakably happy she was, &amp; how near
					<lb/>she felt our Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>, so that the could almost forget
					<lb/>her bodily pain. In this happy state she continued
					<lb/>till at pleased our Lord, on the 22<hi rend='superscript:true;'>nd</hi> of Jany to receive
					<lb/>her redeemed Soul, which when * she fell gently &amp; hap
					<lb/>pily asleep in the 75 66th Year of her age.
					<lb/>* having rec<hi rend='superscript:true;'>d</hi> the blessing of her Choir
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_73Walker-06.jpg" n='6'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>and we must give her testimony that she lived in a near
					<lb/>Connexion with our Savior, and knew herself as a Sinner
					<lb/>often said She was the poorest Creature our Savior could
					<lb/>have chosen, but was very thankful for her happy Lot
					<lb/>of Grace, the S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> Sometimes wou&apos;d tell her how well She
					<lb/>might have had it in the world, She always said what
					<lb/>would that have been to me it I had never known my Sav<hi rend='superscript:true;'>r</hi>
					<lb/>he is of more worth to me than all this world can give.
					<lb/>towards the latter end of her life She was very often Speaking
					<lb/>of the goodness of our Savior as she frequlently had very
					<lb/>bad rest in the Night she wou&apos;d say in the Morning how near our
					<lb/>savior had heart to her, and that she cou&apos;d tell him every thing
				
			</p>
			<pb facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_73Walker-07.jpg" n='7'/>
			<p>
				
					<lb/>and that it was impossible to tell how kind he was to her
					<lb/>he had never done her any thing but good on Our Last
					<lb/>festival when She with the other sick S<hi rend='superscript:true;'>rs</hi> had her share
					<lb/>of the Holy Com<hi rend='superscript:true;'>n</hi> brought to her, she was remarkably
					<lb/>Cheerful and spoke afterwards of the grace she had enjoy&apos;d
					<lb/>and how near our Savior had been to her, She had, had several
					<lb/>bad nights but no one thought her end so near, or the 6 in
					<lb/>the Night she was taken very Ill and in the Morning
					<lb/>the Doctor went to see her who told her the wou&apos;d not live
					<lb/>long, She was to delighted at the thought of it that She
					<lb/>cou&apos;d not express her Joy, her Breath was so bad that She
					<lb/>cou&apos;d not keep her bed but was oblig&apos;d to sit up day &amp; night
				
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
