<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Fenton_Richard_Ful_3_29</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='Ful_3_29_FentonRichard-01.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The Course of Life, of the great Boy Rich.d Fenton</l>
					<l>who departed Dec. 29 1772.</l>
					<l>Richd Fenton, Son of our Br Richd Fenton was born</l>
					<l>the 16 th of May 1757 at Pudsey, in the Parish of Cal-</l>
					<l>verly. As a Child he went to the Brns School at Lane</l>
					<l>End where he learn&apos;d till he was 12 Years old. In June</l>
					<l>1769 he was bound Apprentice to Br John Spicer</l>
					<l>to learn the Glover&apos;s Business &amp; came at the same</l>
					<l>time to live in the Choir House, where he went on in a</l>
					<l>still &amp; quiet Course to the Satisfaction of his Brn</l>
					<l>In the following Year he began to be sickly, &amp; as all</l>
					<l>endeavours for his recovery proved ineffectual, he grew</l>
					<l>weaker &amp; weaker from time to time &amp; as his Parents</l>
					<l>lived near, it was propos&apos;d to him to go and live with them</l>
					<l>whereby he might enjoy more of their Parental Care &amp;</l>
					<l>Nursing; but he declin&apos;d it. However as he grew more</l>
					<l>helpless, he, in the beginning of last July, agreed to go</l>
					<l>&amp; be with his Parents, where he has enjoyed a happy</l>
					<l>&amp;  sabbatical time waiting with Patience &amp; Resig.</l>
					<l>nation when it would please our Saviour to take him</l>
					<l>into his eternal Joy &amp; Security. He was now &amp; then</l>
					<l>visited by the Brn to whom he declared that altho&apos;</l>
					<l>he was resigned to our Savr yet he know that it would</l>
					<l>be better for him to be with Christ, than to recover</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='Ful_3_29_FentonRichard-02.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>his Health, &amp; live here still longer. He had an Im-</l>
					<l>pression of our Saviour&apos;s love towards him, which made</l>
					<l>him look &amp; pray to our Saviour with Confidence. When</l>
					<l>he was visited by Brn whom he was accquainted with,</l>
					<l>he desired that they might sign sing some Verses with</l>
					<l>him, &amp; several Times he mentioned in particular that</l>
					<l>the following should be sung: I am a poor Sinner, yes </l>
					<l>&apos;tis true I am &amp;c. He came here to the Meetings as long</l>
					<l>as he was able to walk, or ride, which always seem&apos;d</l>
					<l>to be a refreshment to him, &amp; when he was no more able</l>
					<l>to come to the meetings, he was very Sorry for it, especially</l>
					<l>when he thought that he should not have the pleasure</l>
					<l>to attend the meetings on Christmas Eve, on which</l>
					<l>account he propos&apos;d that a couple of Brn should earry</l>
					<l>him to the Hall in a Sedan; But on the 19th of Decr</l>
					<l>in the Night, he had such a gracious visit of our</l>
					<l>Savr that he became quite satisfied, with his not</l>
					<l>being able to come to the meetings on Christmas Eve,</l>
					<l>for when he got up in the Morning &amp; dressed himself</l>
					<l>he began to speak to his Mother about it &amp; told her there</l>
					<l>had happened an alteration with him last Night</l>
					<l>when she asked what way, he told her that our Savr</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>near</l>
					<l>had been very to him &amp; he had kept a band with him</l>
					<l>about every thing, &amp; our Savr had forgiven him all &amp;</l>
					<l>would take him soon to himself. He also said: &quot;I gave</l>
					<l>myself quite anew to our Saviour, &amp; he accepted me as</l>
					<l>his own Child, Believing his time would be short, he</l>
					<l>desired that his Srs in the Choir House might be</l>
					<l>sent for, to tell them how happy our Saviour had </l>
					<l>made him, &amp; that he would soon take him to himself</l>
					<l>to be happy &amp; to live with him forever. Since this</l>
					<l>time he grew weaker so fast, that one could see the</l>
					<l>time of his Departure came on very quickly. Some</l>
					<l>Days before his going home, his Master came to</l>
					<l>see him, &amp; when he was going to leave him, he reached</l>
					<l>his hand to his Master &amp; thanked him for all the </l>
					<l>love &amp; favours he had shewn to him, telling him</l>
					<l>he very likely might never see him any more in this</l>
					<l>World, &amp; so it came to pass, for on Decr 29th, 1772</l>
					<l>in the Moming his Soul took its Flight, to that</l>
					<l>God, who had created &amp; redeemed him &amp; made him</l>
					<l>so happy by his precious Nearness, in the 16th</l>
					<l>Year of his Age.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
