<?xml-model href="../../Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../Projects/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mary Oates: Memoir</title>
				<funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
				<principal><persName xml:id="kfaull">Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
				</principal>
				<principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
					</address>
					<email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
				</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Project Manager</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mmcguire">Michael McGuire</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Developer</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cmasonheimer">Carly Masonheimer</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mcohen">Marleina Cohen</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jhom">Jess Hom</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="mgruner">Marita Gruner</persName>
					<orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="skanneman">Sarah Kannemann</persName>
					<orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
					<resp>Encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="jschaumberger">Justin Schaumberger</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="cpirmann">Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
					<resp>Transkribus, Text Encoding Specialist</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName xml:id="bacharya">Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
					<orgName>Bucknell Univesrity</orgName>
					<resp>Research Assistant</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
					<address>
						<addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
						<addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
					</address>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>Moravian Archives, Fulneck</repository>
						<msName type="memoir" ana="MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates">Mary Oates</msName>
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates-01.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates-02.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates-03.jpg" />
						<msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates-04.jpg" />
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person role="subject">
					<persName ref="mlper000260">Mary Oates</persName>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<settingDesc>
				<place>
					<placeName ref="mlpla000003">Fulneck</placeName>
				</place>
			</settingDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>Created TEI file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="memoir">
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="memoir">
				<head>Mary Oates</head>
				<div type="page" n="1">
					<head type="page">1</head>
					<pb n="1" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates-01.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l><hi rend="underline">Sr Mary Oates dictated the following Ap 8th 1812</hi></l></lg></p>
					<p><lg>
					<l>Thy blood, thy blood the deed hath wrought ye</l>
					<l>I was born June 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1747 in Great Horton, in the Parish</l>
					<l>of Bradford. My father being one of the first B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> there</l>
					<l>he was called home to our Saviour when I was only 2 y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></l>
					<l>old, and my Mother was left with five children of whom</l>
					<l>I was the youngest, I can remember when very young being</l>
					<l>sent to the Children&apos;s meetings and liked them very much</l>
					<l>and hearing of our Saviours love to children, made an</l>
					<l>imprewssion on my heart and that verse; Dearest child<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></l>
					<l>hark and see, what a Saviour now have we prove&apos;d a bles</l>
					<l>sing to me. But yet I sport the years of my youth</l>
					<l>without knowing or experiencing much, untill I was</l>
					<l>anout 18 years. I had a great desire to live in a Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> but</l>
					<l>as I was the only daughter, I could not leave my mother,</l>
					<l>It was at that time the custom, that those who lived</l>
					<l>in the Country might not have the priveledge to be</l>
					<l>re&apos;d into the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> and to partake of the H Comn. On this</l>
					<l>account I felt very unhappy, as it appeared to me that I </l>
					<l>could neither enjoy the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> nor the World. I now fully,</l>
					<l>experienced the truth of that text. The carnal mind is</l>
					<l>enmity with God. I felt my sinful inclinations, and the</l>
					<l>desire to enjoy the World, so strong that I sometimes</l>
					<l>thought; I did not care what became of me, I said once in</l>
					<l>my grief, I will never be in the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> yet my heart condemnd</l>
					<l>me. One night when I had fully determined to drop all</l>
					<l>connection with the Brns people. </l>
					<l>I recd a hurt on my</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="2">
					<head type="page">2</head>
					<pb n="2" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates-02.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>neck in fetching water from a well; I suffered great pain,</l>
					<l>and was brought into a very weak state of health. As soon</l>
					<l>as I was able I went to Fulnec, and called to see S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Seidel</l>
					<l>who was then the Labouress, she looked earnestly at me</l>
					<l>and asked what I thought, for if the hurt had turned</l>
					<l>inwardly, I might have died in a moment, this was</l>
					<l>like a thunderbolt to my soul. I went to the preaching</l>
					<l>but could hear nothing for misiry feeling that I was not</l>
					<l>let to die. I returned home but had no rest. reflecting</l>
					<l>on my unhappy state, my earnest pray&apos;r and desire</l>
					<l>was now that our Saviour would pardon all my sins.</l></lg></p>
					<p><lg>
					<l>At that time there much said in the meetings,</l>
						<l>that <add place="above">if we had any</add> clearness of our sinfulness, we should see our Saviour</l>
					<l>in his crucified form, this brought me into self working</l>
					<l>and I thought that I never could be saved unless I had</l>
					<l>that particular manifestation in which I heard it describd</l>
					<l>However one morning when I awoke, it was as if our</l>
					<l>Saviour said to me. I know the thoughts which I think</l>
					<l>towards thee, thoughts of peace? that word <hi rend="underline">peace</hi>.</l>
					<l>comforted my heart, and has always been something</l>
					<l>to me thro my future course, This was in my 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></l>
					<l>year. I now felt a great desire to be recd into the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></l>
					<l>that favour was granted me April 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1773. and the </l>
					<l>peace of God which I felt on that occasion, I shall</l>
					<l>never forget. I now spent my time happily and</l>
					<l>enjoyed the meetings, when I awoke in the morn<hi rend="superscript">g</hi></l>
					<l>it was my first pleasing thought. I shall hear of</l>
					<l>our Saviour to day. I wished much to partake of </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="3">
					<head type="page">3</head>
					<pb n="3" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates-03.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>the H. Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> but it was long before that favour was granted</l>
					<l>me. A conversation previous to it with the late B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></l>
					<l>Tranecker, proved a great blessing to me, He asked if</l>
					<l>I had felt a clearness that our Saviour had pardoned all</l>
					<l>my sins, to which I answered as mentioned before, upon</l>
					<l>he spoke very encouraging words to me, and said that</l>
					<l>our Saviours ways were different with every poor sinners.</l></lg></p>
					<p><lg>
					<l>Decr 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1776 I had the favour to partake for the first</l>
					<l>time of the H Com<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. In 1779 I removed with my Mother</l>
					<l>Bankhouse, where I spent 3 years very comfortably, tho</l>
					<l>I had many schol schools for my own heart. but our Savior</l>
					<l>helped me and proved my faithful friend.</l></lg></p>
					<p><lg>
					<l>After the happy departure of my dear Mother whom</l>
					<l>I nursed to my end, I went to live at Heckmondwyke</l>
					<l>to care for my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Children, where I staid until</l>
					<l>June 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1783 when I came to the S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> house here.</l>
					<l>I entered this house with my whole heart, according</l>
					<l>to my wished for desire, and no trials whatsoever have</l>
					<l>made me wish to leave it. My own temper and work</l>
					<l>made it sometimes trying, but little uneasinesses</l>
					<l>were soon settled again, and I can truly say that my</l>
					<l>living in this house has proved a Blessing to me.</l>
					<l>Where I have learned to know more of myself and of</l>
					<l>our Saviours leading</l></lg></p>
					<p>
						<lg type="verse">					
					<l>Had I not thee O Lamb of God once bleeding</l>
					<l>Were not thy blood for me a sinner pleading</l>
					<l>Where should I poorest among all the needy</l>
					<l>Find succour ready</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
				<div type="page" n="4">
					<head type="page">4</head>
					<pb n="4" facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAF/Ful_SS_77Oates-04.jpg" />
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>In 1799 my Niece Rachel Oats, with whom I had</l>
					<l>lived 16 years in the S<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> house, was married to B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></l>
					<l>Jackson and went to Jamacia, and two months after</l>
					<l>my <add place="above">oldest</add> B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> who had been as a father to me, departed happily</l>
					<l>These sircumstances were great trials to me, and made</l>
					<l>me look earnestly to our Saviour, for His help even</l>
					<l>in externals and He has never put me to shame.</l></lg></p>
					<p><lg>
					<l>I now commend all my friends and relations to </l>
					<l>the Lord, may He bless them with spiritual &amp;</l>
					<l>temporal Blessings and may he help &amp; support</l>
					<l>me, thro this Vale of tears till I shall have the</l>
					<l>favour to see Him face to face</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
