<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Morgan_John_Ful_3_54</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='Ful_3_54_MorganJohn-01.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Departed May the 9th 1761</l>
					<l>The Youth John Morgan was born at Kensington near London</l>
					<l>May the 26th 1743. He came to the Childns Oeconomy at Bullermeer</l>
					<l>when he was about 3 Years old, and came from thence with the</l>
					<l>whole Oeconomy to Smith house in 1749. During his childhood he</l>
					<l>had a promising Genius and Capacity for learning, and in his</l>
					<l>disposition had something pretty and taking, but with regard to</l>
					<l>his heart there always appeard a tendency to being close, and re</l>
					<l>serv&apos;d, which often made his Brn sigh, least in futurity the same</l>
					<l>should continue and consequently prove detrimental to his Boys and</l>
					<l>Youths course in the Congn</l>
					<l>About the time of the Oeconomies removing from Smith house</l>
					<l>to Lambshill in 1753 there often appeared something of the dear Mo</l>
					<l>thers Labour upon his Heart, particularly when his curiosity of which </l>
					<l>he had a great share led him upon searching into things which he was</l>
					<l>afterwards shy in speaking about. In this course he went on, and </l>
					<l>his Brn were often very mich distressed on his Account, and full of</l>
					<l>fears lest his want of uprightness and openness would make his course</l>
					<l>heavy to himself and painful to our Saviour &amp; his Brn he had how</l>
					<l>every Intervals betwixt, sometimes dear and promising &amp; then again</l>
					<l>dark and gloomy, particularly if any thing manifestly appeared against</l>
					<l>him on account of which he should become a Sinner. However he</l>
					<l>applied himself with exemplary Diligence to writing Congn Accounts,</l>
					<l>and showed a certain pleasure in doing whatsoever was committed to</l>
					<l>him with great faithfulness and punctuallity.</l>
					<l>He was receiv&apos;d into the great Boys choir Jany 9, 1797 by Br Renatus</l>
					<l>which seemingly had a blessed effect upon him for a long time af</l>
					<l>ter, but his close disposition of Mind caused him many anxious</l>
					<l>moments, when he heard he should be spoke with seprately, and he sel</l>
					<l>dom returned from it but with red and wet Eyes on Account thereof.</l>
					<l>He came to live in the Choir-house and learn the shoema</l>
					<l>kers business August the 21st 1758, His diligence at his Work and</l>
					<l>desire to learn the business thoroughly was pleasing to every </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='Ful_3_54_MorganJohn-02.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>one who had to do with him but he laboured under an impedi</l>
					<l>ment in his Eyesight which often pain&apos;d him and made him dis</l>
					<l>pair sometimes of ever learning to work as he should do</l>
					<l>In Novr 1759 he was one of those Youth when our dear Johannes</l>
					<l>has been very orderly ever since he came into the choirhouse,</l>
					<l>always showing Obedience to his Brn and esteeming that as highly </l>
					<l>necessary both in himself and others. Those 3 or 4 Months past</l>
					<l>he has been much more concern&apos;d for a lively Heart, and spoke</l>
					<l>of it with more feeling than formerly, was also more clear and open</l>
					<l>&amp; had a more real connexion with our Savr. In the begining of his </l>
					<l>Sickness which was towards the latter end of April, he did not think</l>
					<l>much of going home, nor did he desire it much because his heart</l>
					<l>was not in so tender to situation towards our Savr as it could &amp;</l>
					<l>should be. Several serious bands were kept with him, whereby</l>
					<l>he discovered a sensibility not observed in him before. The</l>
					<l>5th Instant he altered, told a Labourer he knew he was much</l>
					<l>concern&apos;d on his Account, and not without Reason, for said he</l>
					<l>my heart has not been so lively as it should, but be not distress&apos;d</l>
					<l>or troubled about me, perhaps you may think it would not be agre</l>
					<l>able to me to go home, but I can ease you on that Account, and</l>
					<l>assure you my concern comes not from that Corner, whenever he calls</l>
					<l>me he will take one to himself, I am his &amp; shall certainly go to</l>
					<l>him, this is a clear and made out matter to me, but my concern </l>
					<l>is that my heart is not more lively and warm &amp; that I have not</l>
					<l>enjoy&apos;d his precious nearness as I could and should have done.</l>
					<l>This Conversation was sattisfactory. He also spoke with our Savr</l>
					<l>from that time in a more Sinnerlike but confident manner</l>
					<l>as long as he was able to speak, &amp; also told his Labourers and other</l>
					<l>Brn he now knew he should go home this time express&apos;d also</l>
					<l>a desire after it. At last it was very difficult for him to speak</l>
					<l>but when visited did all in his power to render himself intelligible</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and particularly to express himself about going home. The 7th</l>
					<l>in the Morning he expressed again his desire to go home so as to </l>
					<l>be understood, &amp; about 11 at Night his Sickness took such a turn</l>
					<l>that it was thought he would go directly.</l>
					<l>From this time he took very little notice of any person or thing</l>
					<l>about him but lay quite still seemingly without pain till the 9th</l>
					<l>(that ever memorable day) in the evening while the Congn was</l>
					<l>enjoying the holy Communion, about 1/2 an hour before his de</l>
					<l>parture he came quite to himself, was very sensible of his pain,</l>
					<l>but not able to speak, &amp; 3/4 past 9 while the Congn prostrated</l>
					<l>he was deliverd into the hands of his Redeemer in a peculiar</l>
					<l>tender manner, to whom he breathed out his spirit with the bles</l>
					<l>sing of his Choir, &amp; during the singing of several Verses in</l>
					<l>his 18th Year</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
