<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Anderson_Anna_Rosina</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4472.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Our dear happily departed Sister</l>
					<l>Anna Rosina Anderson, has left</l>
					<l>the following account of herself:</l>
					<l>I was born the 9th of Aug 1727 at</l>
					<l>Berthelsdorf. My Parents belonging to</l>
					<l>the Congn endeavour&apos;d to bring me up</l>
					<l>in the same connection with the Congn</l>
					<l>&amp; sent me from my earliest years every</l>
					<l>Sunday to Herrnhut to the Childrens</l>
					<l>meeting, which the late Count Zinzendorf</l>
					<l>kept. He asked me many questions, and </l>
					<l>tho&apos; I did not always understand him,</l>
					<l>yet it made an impression on my heart</l>
					<l>and I felt a desire to be happy. When</l>
					<l>I was in my 7th year my Father de</l>
					<l>parted happily to our Savior, after</l>
					<l>which the late Count took care of my</l>
					<l>Mother &amp; her children; she came to</l>
					<l>live in the widows house at Herrnhut </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='Anderon_Anna_Rosina_missingimage.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and her children in the Orphan house,</l>
					<l>but I for my part had no inclination</l>
					<l>for it, but chose to stay with my Grand</l>
					<l>father in Berthelsdorf. After a few years</l>
					<l>my Uncle in Lobenstein desired me to</l>
					<l>come and live with him, which I</l>
					<l>was very glad of. I was there above a</l>
					<l>year, but did not find it so agreeable</l>
					<l>as I thought, and I prayed may times</l>
					<l>with tears to the Lord, to help me away</l>
					<l>again, which he graciously did. For it</l>
					<l>happened at this time that the late</l>
					<l>Count came to Ebersdorf and my Uncle </l>
					<l>had an oppertunity to see him;  and</l>
					<l>told him that I was very unhap-</l>
					<l>py here; on hearing this he took me</l>
					<l>under his care, &amp; sent me to Marienborn </l>
					<l>to the Orphan house; I prayed to the</l>
					<l>Lord to preserve me here &amp; make me</l>
					<l>happy, &amp; that I never might come to</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>any other place except among the Brethren,</l>
					<l>because I was sometimes enticed by my</l>
					<l>Uncle to go back with him to his home.</l>
					<l>At that time during a severe sickness</l>
					<l>which I got, I learned to pray earnestly</l>
					<l>for my happiness. I found many friends</l>
					<l>here who wish&apos;d me well and to see me pros-</l>
					<l>per for our Savior; particularly one Sister</l>
					<l>will always be remember&apos;d by me, who,</l>
					<l>when I had recovered, took me with</l>
					<l>her into the garden, and kneeling down</l>
					<l>with me, put up a fervent prayer in</l>
					<l>my behalf to our Savior, which I shall</l>
					<l>never forget. But it was not sufficient to</l>
					<l>make me happy; because I must feel</l>
					<l>my Saviors comfort &amp; forgiveness for my</l>
					<l>own heart, &amp; this happened in a very</l>
					<l>particular manner. Being once quite</l>
					<l>alone in a place I fell down at his feet</l>
					<l>&amp; implored his mercy &amp; forgiveness for all</l>
					<l>my sins thro&apos; his precious blood. At</l>
					<l> that time I felt something, which I </l>
					<l>cannot express, his comfort to my troub-</l>
					<l>led soul and his mercy shown to me,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4473.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>melted my heart in thousand tears. In 1740</l>
					<l>received</l>
					<l>I was after the then usual manner into the</l>
					<l>Childrens Congn which proved a great bles</l>
					<l>sing to me, I devoted my heart to our Savior</l>
					<l>to live to him &amp; serve him; however after</l>
					<l>wards, I must own, I had many things to</l>
					<l>experience by which I learnt better to know</l>
					<l>myself but our Savior was faithful and</l>
					<l>helped me thro&apos;, I always felt freedom to </l>
					<l>speak my mind openhartedly to my Labouress</l>
					<l>which was a great help to me. In the year</l>
					<l>1741 I was received into the great girls Choir</l>
					<l>and in the same year I enjoyed the holy</l>
					<l>Comn for the first time, which was</l>
					<l>an unspeakable blessing to my heart. At </l>
					<l>that time there was a company of great</l>
					<l>girls which the late Count took par</l>
					<l>ticular care of, he kept us Choirmeetings</l>
					<l>and instructed us how to become useful</l>
					<l>in our Saviors service. </l>
					<l>I was appoin</l>
					<l>ted to keep the Childrens &amp; great girls</l>
					<l>bands, and enjoyed </l>
					<l>many blessings from</l>
					<l>our Savior, </l>
					<l>when we spoke together of</l>
					<l>his great love &amp; mercy. </l>
					<l>Soon after</l>
					<l>I had the office of an assistant among</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4474.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>the Children conferred upon me and</l>
					<l>moved in the same year with this Oeco</l>
					<l>nomy to Herrnhag.  All these appoint</l>
					<l>ments taught me to come into closer</l>
					<l>connection with our Savior and showed </l>
					<l>me that I could do nothing of myself.</l>
					<l>His mercy and love shown to me bowed</l>
					<l>me in the dust before him. I had the</l>
					<l>confidence to cleave to him as a poor</l>
					<l>sinner, &amp; believed he would help me</l>
					<l>thro&apos;.  1743 I was accepted an Acoluth</l>
					<l>with a large company, which encou</l>
					<l>rag&apos;d me anew to live to him and</l>
					<l>serve him as a poor Child that has</l>
					<l>nothing to plead but his mercy from</l>
					<l>day to day. 1744 I was receiv&apos;d</l>
					<l>into the S. Srs Choir and 1747 </l>
					<l>blessed for a Deaconess.  1748 I received</l>
					<l>a Call to be S. Srs Labores at Beth</l>
					<l>lehem in America.  In London Febr.</l>
					<l>the 10th I was bless for my office &amp;</l>
					<l>set out in June.  Sept the 20th I</l>
					<l>arrived in Bethlehem after a trouble</l>
					<l>some voyage.  I cannot but take no</l>
					<l>tice, that this year the 13th of Nov.</l>
					<l>was celebrated the first time in</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4475.jpg' n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>America, which brought the first impres</l>
					<l>sion of that in Herrnhag 1741 very</l>
					<l>fresh to my mind, but I was sorry,</l>
					<l>I could not enjoy it in such a moment</l>
					<l>manner as I wish&apos;d to do. I had to</l>
					<l>struggle, particularly in the beginning</l>
					<l>with many difficulties, being young</l>
					<l>and unexperienced, and had no body</l>
					<l>to whom I could open my heart and</l>
					<l>consult with, so as I wish&apos;d; which</l>
					<l>made it sometimes very heavy to me.</l>
					<l>But my dear Savior helped me thro&apos;</l>
					<l>whenever I turn&apos;d to him in my dis</l>
					<l>tress. I visited frequently in the most</l>
					<l>of the country Congns which lay very</l>
					<l>distant from each other. In the year</l>
					<l>1755 a war broke out between the </l>
					<l>French &amp; English, and as the Indi</l>
					<l>ans generally took share and joined</l>
					<l>one of the other party, we had very</l>
					<l>difficult times at Bethlehem and</l>
					<l>Nazareth. First the Settlement of</l>
					<l>the Brethren at the Mahony about</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4476.jpg' n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>27 miles from Bethlehem was destroyed</l>
					<l>by the Indians, where 11 Brn &amp; Srs lost</l>
					<l>their lives, after which many mur</l>
					<l>ders were committed much nearer, till</l>
					<l>at last within 6 miles of Bethle</l>
					<l>hem. We knew that we were closely</l>
					<l>watched by the Indians, who would</l>
					<l>gladly have destroyed the Place, which</l>
					<l>at that time was the only one capable</l>
					<l>of making any resistance to their</l>
					<l>Incursion.  The reports of their cru</l>
					<l>elties at other places kept us in con</l>
					<l>tinual allarm and apprehension,</l>
					<l>particularly as Indians were some</l>
					<l>times observed to lurk about and</l>
					<l>in the place at nights.</l>
					<l>However the strict watch kept by</l>
					<l>the Brn in many parts &amp; particu</l>
					<l>larly about our house, but above all</l>
					<l>the protection of our good Lord, al</l>
					<l>ways frustrated their designs. During </l>
					<l>all these heavy times, our dear Lord</l>
					<l>was our only comfort and his peace </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4477.jpg' n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>was very sensibly felt amongst us. In the</l>
					<l>year 1762 Br Nathanael Seidel arrived</l>
					<l>here from Europe, who had lately been</l>
					<l>married to Sr Anne Joh. Piesch an old</l>
					<l>acquaintance of mine; from whose conver</l>
					<l>sation and support I received much com</l>
					<l>fort. In the year 1764 I received a call</l>
					<l>to return to Europe, Sr Susanna de</l>
					<l>Gersdorf arrived early in that year to</l>
					<l>supply my place, and I left Bethle</l>
					<l>hem in company with Br &amp; Sr Bochler </l>
					<l>and some other Brn &amp; Srs in the begin</l>
					<l>ning of May. We had a very quick</l>
					<l>passage, arrived in London the 24th</l>
					<l>of June, &amp; at Marienborn where the</l>
					<l>Synod was assembled on the 4th of</l>
					<l>July. After the Synod was closed I</l>
					<l>went to Herrnhut and in the year 1765</l>
					<l>received a Call to serve the S. Srs Choirs</l>
					<l>in England. I first went to Fulneck,</l>
					<l>where I staid about a year, &amp; then got </l>
					<l>a Call to Bedford, where I served the </l>
					<l>single Srs untill the year 1772 when</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4478.jpg' n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I return&apos;d again to Fulneck. To go</l>
					<l>any farther in relating my course I </l>
					<l>don&apos;t think needful. Our Saviors pas</l>
					<l>sion and death and that he has rede</l>
					<l>med me poor Sinner with his own pre</l>
					<l>cious blood, is to me above everything</l>
					<l>in time and in eternity. He has helped</l>
					<l>me thro&apos; this vale of tears and given</l>
					<l>me grace to place my confidence in</l>
					<l>him in which I never have been put</l>
					<l>to shame. When I have the favour</l>
					<l>to see him face to face I shall kiss</l>
					<l>his feet with Sinner-tears for all</l>
					<l>his mercy bestowed upon me.</l>
					<l>Thus far has this faithful hand</l>
					<l>maid of Jesus left us an account of</l>
					<l>herself and of that what the Lord</l>
					<l>has done for her Soul. There would</l>
					<l>be much to say of all the proofs of</l>
					<l>grace; wherewith he has crowned her</l>
					<l>endeavours and blessed her services to so</l>
					<l>many souls, in advising, comforting</l>
					<l>and shewing them the way to true hap </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4479.jpg' n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>piness; but we shall content ourselves with</l>
					<l>rendering unto him, who is the giver of all</l>
					<l>good gifts, our humble thanks and prai</l>
					<l>ses for all the mercys bestowed upon her,</l>
					<l>during her pilgrimage here below. Her</l>
					<l>character and the blessing which attented</l>
					<l>her Labour is known and acknowledged</l>
					<l>with thankfulness and we heartily wish</l>
					<l>and pray that we may follow her foot</l>
					<l>steps. In the year 1772 when she the </l>
					<l>second time arrived in Fulneck, the</l>
					<l>S. Srs Choir and Oeconomies in Yorkshire</l>
					<l>were in a very hopeful state and she </l>
					<l>was recieved by them with much love</l>
					<l>and affection. In this vineyard of the</l>
					<l>Lord she laboured with the utmost</l>
					<l>alacrity both of body &amp; mind, deeming</l>
					<l>it her highest priviledge to win Souls for</l>
					<l>Christ. The weakest of the flock were</l>
					<l>always objects of her peculiar care and</l>
					<l>concern, and she spared no pains what</l>
					<l>ever in tending and bearing them in love;</l>
					<l>and in such instances when all means</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4480.jpg' n='9'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>proved ineffectual, it was evident to all around</l>
					<l>her, how she always bemoaned their loss.</l>
					<l>On the other hand our Savior gave her the</l>
					<l>satisfaction to see many faithful hand</l>
					<l>maids, whom she had trained up for the</l>
					<l>Lord, enter into the different services of his</l>
					<l>house, which she always looked upon as </l>
					<l>the greatest favour conferred on herself. As</l>
					<l>the Choir here in Fulneck considerably in </l>
					<l>creased, it was in the year 1780 taken into</l>
					<l>consideration to build a S. Srs house in Wyke,</l>
					<l>and the proposal having been approved of,</l>
					<l>our late Sister had the pleasure to assist</l>
					<l>in laying the foundation stone, which</l>
					<l>was a blessed solemnity. When it was fi</l>
					<l>nished and inhabited by Sisters from</l>
					<l>Fulneck she used to visit them frequent</l>
					<l>ly with great faithfulnes, and took</l>
					<l>particular share in their weal &amp; woe;</l>
					<l>as also in the wellfare of the Sisters</l>
					<l>Oeconomies at Gummersall, Mirfield</l>
					<l>and Littlemore; when several years</l>
					<l>ago the latter was given up, it was a</l>
					<l>great concern to her mind. </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4481.jpg' n='10'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Of late years she grew weak and could</l>
					<l>not be so active in her office as she</l>
					<l>wished, nevertheless her mind was continu</l>
					<l>ally employed for the wellfare of her</l>
					<l>Choir. Great as her delight had been in the</l>
					<l>beginning, to see her Choir in such an in</l>
					<l>creasing and florishing way, so great</l>
					<l>was her concern of late years to see it</l>
					<l>gradually declining in number and but</l>
					<l>few new ones coming in. So much the</l>
					<l>more she wished and prayed that the</l>
					<l>few remaining might truly value their</l>
					<l>lot of grace and enjoy the blessings &amp;</l>
					<l>privileges, which were so precious to </l>
					<l>herself. For as to her own person she</l>
					<l>regretted exceedingly, that in her latter</l>
					<l>days old age &amp; weakness prevented</l>
					<l>her attending every opportunity for </l>
					<l>edification &amp; encouragement as much</l>
					<l>as she wished to do. May the 1st </l>
					<l>1802 she was seized with a paralytic</l>
					<l>stroke, but recovered so far again that she</l>
					<l>on the 4th of May could attend the meetings</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4482.jpg' n='11'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>house. During this winter, her</l>
					<l>weakness </l>
					<l>increased, &amp; </l>
					<l>she was much confined</l>
					<l>room. Febr. 15th 1803, she had </l>
					<l>ther stroke, which quite took away</l>
					<l>use of her right side, &amp; the next day</l>
					<l>had strong convulsions so that we</l>
					<l>expected her dissolution. She had </l>
					<l>often expressed a wish for B. Benade to</l>
					<l>pray with her at her departure which</l>
					<l>was now done, and after the prayer</l>
					<l>the blessing of the Lord was pronoun</l>
					<l>ced over her. The feeling of the peace</l>
					<l>of God on this occasion will leave a </l>
					<l>deep impression on the minds of all</l>
					<l> them who were present. After the</l>
					<l>first paroxysm she fell asleep and</l>
					<l>slumbered for the the most part; but when</l>
					<l>she between times awoke she seemed</l>
					<l>to be sensible, tho&apos; her speech was so</l>
					<l>far gone, that she could only say yes</l>
					<l>or no to the questions asked. The 18th</l>
					<l>some Sisters assembled in her room to </l>
					<l>sing some verses expressing our fore</l>
					<l>taste of that happy lot to be at home </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_4483.jpg' n='12'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>with the Lord; she seemed quite de</l>
					<l>lighted with it and kept awake the</l>
					<l>whole time. The 19th in the afternoon</l>
					<l>she appeared more recollected than before</l>
					<l>and could speak several words, and when</l>
					<l>the girls came to see her, she gave them all</l>
					<l>the hand &amp; said: The Lord bless you!</l>
					<l>Afterwards she slumber&apos;d again till</l>
					<l>about evening, had a very restless night,</l>
					<l>and the 20th in the morning about 7</l>
					<l>a&apos; clock her redeemed and thro&apos; the blood</l>
					<l>of Jesus sanctified soul went gently</l>
					<l>and happy over into the arms of her </l>
					<l>beloved bridegroom, during the singing </l>
					<l>of that verse: When in the arms of </l>
					<l>Jesus, thy lips shall pallid grow.</l>
					<l>Her age was 75 years 6 months. </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
