<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Bell_Christian_Ful_3_31</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='Ful_3_31_BellChristian-01.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>February 1772</l>
					<l>Christian Bell was born in London Decr 7th</l>
					<l>1742 and came as a little Boy into the Children&apos;s</l>
					<l>Oeconomy, he was a very lovely Child, beloved by all</l>
					<l>about him. When he arrived to his Boys Age, he</l>
					<l>was put apprentice to our dear late Br Charlesworth</l>
					<l>in the Merchant Business, during which time be</l>
					<l>behaved himself as an orderly &amp; faithful Apprentices,</l>
					<l>and gave full Satisfaction to Br Charlesworth &amp; others</l>
					<l>about him. I was evident that there was a Work</l>
					<l>of Grace in his Heart, be those who were acquainted</l>
					<l>with him were in Hopes that he would not only prosper</l>
					<l>&amp; become a happy Brother, but that he would also be</l>
					<l>useful in our Savrs kingdom, In these Years he was</l>
					<l>very openhearted &amp; seemed to have no other Concern than</l>
					<l>to be formed by our Savr quite according to his Mind &amp;</l>
					<l>to live for His alone in the World.</l>
					<l>The was received into the Congn April 16th 1754 &amp; on</l>
					<l>August 29 th 1762 he was rec&apos;d into the Single Brns Choir</l>
					<l>March 27 th 1766 he was admitted to the holy Com-</l>
					<l>munion, but which had not the wished for Effect. Soon</l>
					<l>after he went to London where the Snares laid for him</l>
					<l>caught a surprizing Hold of him &amp; a love to the World</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='Ful_3_31_BellChristian-02.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>took place in him, so that his Soul rec&apos;d a Hurt at this</l>
					<l>Time which was never rightly cured again till a little</l>
					<l>while before his Departure.</l>
					<l>After he set up Business for himself, it obliged him</l>
					<l>&amp; to make some Journeys to London, where Temptations</l>
					<l>were renewed, to draw him altogether into the World, and</l>
					<l>altho&apos; the Staff of Corruption &amp; strong tendencies thereto</l>
					<l>lay in him, yet he felt such Strong Convictions, that he</l>
					<l>never could come to a Resolution to go into the World,</l>
					<l>yet this divided Heart &amp; continual Struggle betwixt our</l>
					<l>Savr &amp; the World caused him a heavy &amp; truly unhappy Life</l>
					<l>that one could not see and speak with him without being</l>
					<l>moved with compassion. A Times he was much concerned</l>
					<l>about his unhappy State of Heart &amp; wished our Savr</l>
					<l>might attain his Aim with him; he also was some times</l>
					<l>very sensibly Struck with the strong proofs he had of our </l>
					<l>Savr Faithfulness to him &amp; by seeing how He kept his Hand</l>
					<l>over Him.  This had the effect upon him that he once in</l>
					<l>a particular Manner pray&apos;d our Savr if He saw no other</l>
					<l>way of obtaining his Aim with him to do it by giving him</l>
					<l>or taking him to himself</l>
					<l>a sickly Habit of Body, rather than suffer him to go into</l>
					<l>the World, &amp; he has often considered our Sars Dealings with</l>
					<l>him as an Answer to this Prayer. </l>
					<l>About a half a Year ago, as he was going to Leeds &amp; had still thoughts of pursuing a Worldly Scheme, tho&apos; with much uneasiness of Mind &amp; Having pray&apos;d as above, he stop&apos;d &amp; looked back for his Company when he got a Vomiting of blood, which was the beginning of his last Sickness.</l>
					<l>About 2 months ago it was observed that his tender</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and weakly Constitution turned into a Consumption &amp;</l>
					<l>he declined very fast.  He was frequently visited by</l>
					<l>many Brn, for he was generally beloved, &amp; when it drew</l>
					<l>nearer his End that he himself begun to think, he</l>
					<l>would soon go home, he spoke with great concern, to </l>
					<l>Some of the Labourers whom he had most Confidence</l>
					<l>in &amp; had been best acquainted with, and Lamented</l>
					<l>that he had spend much of his Time so poorly with Rea</l>
					<l>soning, Reading unprofitable Books, neglecting the</l>
					<l>Meetings &amp; other privileges of the Congregation, he</l>
					<l>also said that he never had experienced the true Grace</l>
					<l>as a poor </l>
					<l>in the Blood &amp; Merits of Christ our Saviour Sinner.</l>
					<l>This brought him into such Distress that he thought</l>
					<l>he would be lost. Two Nights before his Departure,</l>
					<l>and being</l>
					<l>when he  was yet pretty strong, he wept &amp; prayed all</l>
					<l>and got</l>
					<l>the Night thro&apos; and got when he also got Comfort from our</l>
					<l>Savr. From that Time his Fear was gone &amp; he longed</l>
					<l>to go to our Savr which was on the 6th of Febr, the same</l>
					<l>Evening he sat up a long while &amp; conversed with 2 Brn</l>
					<l>in a bandlike way in the heartiest &amp; very agreeable</l>
					<l>Manner. He also kept a very openhearted Band with</l>
					<l>a Labourer 2 days before. He himself thought</l>
					<l>he should continue about 3 weeks longer, but the </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='Ful_3_31_BellChristian-03.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Night betwixt the 6th &amp; 7th of Fcbruary, he all at</l>
					<l>once began to hasten, &amp; when his Choir Labourer</l>
					<l>came to him at 5 in the Morning he asked him, if</l>
					<l>he had got full forgiveness from our Savr, &amp; if he</l>
					<l>now was longing to go to Him, both he answered in</l>
					<l>the Affirmive. A few Minutes after it was</l>
					<l>observed that the happy moment approached. He</l>
					<l>was blessed &amp; turned pale during the Verse: When in</l>
					<l>the Armes of Jesus etc. accompanied with a sweet</l>
					<l>feeling of Grace in the 30 Year of his Age.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
