<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Foster_Mary_Ann_Ful_SS_49</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: cmp016@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1196.jpg' n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>A Sketch of the life &amp; happy</l>
					<l>departure of Mary Ann Foster who</l>
					<l>died at Bristol, April 9th 1789.</l>
					<l>From her cradle to her death it may</l>
					<l>be said that she was an affectionate</l>
					<l>&amp; pleasing child, discovering an</l>
					<l>uncommon sensibility in all things</l>
					<l>for one of her age. As early as three</l>
					<l>years old she frequented the Childrens</l>
					<l>Meetings at the Brethen&apos;s Chapel;</l>
					<l>it was evident that he tender mind</l>
					<l>was impressed not with dread but</l>
					<l>with a pleasant serenity whenever</l>
					<l>she heard of death &amp; going to dwell with</l>
					<l>our Saviour, On attening the </l>
					<l>funeral of a Child about her own</l>
					<l>age, she afterwards asked one of</l>
					<l>her companions, if she should like to</l>
					<l>die &amp; be buried like Maria Grinfield</l>
					<l>(who died at the age of three years &amp; a quarter)</l>
					<l>her companion replied &quot;no&quot; to which</l>
					<l>she she said, I am sure I should</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1197.jpg' n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>for thou I should for to my dear</l>
					<l>Saviour -- on being asked if she</l>
					<l>did not fear the Gloomy grave &quot;Oh no</l>
					<l>she replied our Saviour was laid in</l>
					<l>the Grave &amp; I am not afraid, my soul</l>
					<l>will go to him when I die, &amp; I shall </l>
					<l>be drest in white &amp; praise him with</l>
					<l>all the little Angels for ever &amp; ever!&quot;</l>
					<l>The discourse delivered at that</l>
					<l>funeral made a deep impression on</l>
					<l>her tender heart she went home to her</l>
					<l>Momma &amp; relative all she could</l>
					<l>remember of it &amp; said she should</l>
					<l>ask her forgiveness as Maria did of</l>
					<l>her Momma &amp; Papa before she died</l>
					<l>adding, my dear Momma, you will I</l>
					<l>know frogive me for our Saviours sake</l>
					<l>because I am his, he has only lent me</l>
					<l>to you for a little while, her Papa said,</l>
					<l>&quot;Maryann what is it you say,&quot; she replies</l>
					<l>Papa you would not understand it if I told</l>
					<l>you, but Momma does. In her morning</l>
					<l>and evening prayers she entreted her dear</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Savivor to forgive her all her Sins &amp;</l>
					<l>prepare her for his heavnly Kingdom that</l>
					<l>she would thank him for all his love</l>
					<l>while here &amp; sing his praises for ever</l>
					<l>she often concluded with this verse</l>
					<l>out of her little hymn book</l>
					<l>But Saviour dear thou for my good</l>
					<l>Wast pleased a child to be</l>
					<l>And thou didst shed thy precious blood</l>
					<l>Upon the cross for me. </l>
					<l>Come then &amp; take this heart of mine</l>
					<l>O take me as Iam</l>
					<l>I know that I by right am thine</l>
					<l>Thou loving gracious Lamb.</l>
					<l>She could often remark on the Lords</l>
					<l>goodness to her and say that she wanted</l>
					<l>for no good thing, while many poor</l>
					<l>Children were in wants of every thing tho&apos;</l>
					<l>she was no better then they were; On</l>
					<l>Easter day she asked why it was so called</l>
					<l>she was told because our Saviour rose</l>
					<l>in the east and then said, what shall</l>
					<l>in heaven? her friend replied, we shall</l>
					<l>sing the song of Moses and the Lamb&quot; Oh</l>
					<l>that will be delightful she said, how I long to</l>
					<l>die that I may go to my dear Saviour, then </l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1198.jpg' n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>I shall love him more for I shall see him</l>
					<l>and be with him for ever. In the night</l>
					<l>season, she would often wake and say</l>
					<l>here is dorkness, in heaven there is always</l>
					<l>light our dear Saviour is the light &amp; the glory</l>
					<l>there we shall sing the with the Angels</l>
					<l>Hallelujah praise the Lord. One morning</l>
					<l>hearing the servant singing a vain song,</l>
					<l>she went to her &amp; repeated the following verse</l>
					<l>&quot;Stop poor sinner stop and think</l>
					<l>Before you further go</l>
					<l>Will you sport upon the brink</l>
					<l>Of evrlasting one?</l>
					<l>O Molly, said she you are not singing</l>
					<l>our Saviours praise, if you do not begin</l>
					<l>here, you never will in heaven, remember</l>
					<l>I told you so &amp; if ever you tell his, you will</l>
					<l>go the bottomless pit, where Satan is, Oh</l>
					<l>Molly repent and call on our Saviour for</l>
					<l>Mercy, that you may be saved. On the</l>
					<l>Saturday before her last illness she went to</l>
					<l>dine with a friend, and appeared</l>
					<l>uncommonly thoughtful, &amp; was asked if any</l>
					<l>thing had greivd her -- no; but I have a</l>
					<l>secret to tell you, but Momma must not</l>
					<l>know it because it will wet her but she will</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>know it by and bye, dear Maryann what</l>
					<l>can that be, that your Momma must not</l>
					<l>know, she replied with a frightened</l>
					<l>countenance, I an going to leave you</l>
					<l>not to London where Momma thinks to send</l>
					<l>me to school, &amp; has so many new dresses for</l>
					<l>me, but I shall want none of them</l>
					<l>for I shall have a dress where I am going</l>
					<l>which shall be always white &amp; looking</l>
					<l>up to heaven with her little hands</l>
					<l>folded together she said, I am going</l>
					<l>far above those clouds I am going</l>
					<l>to My dear Saviour, who is in heaven, he</l>
					<l>will give a crown of gold &amp; a white robe</l>
					<l>&amp; I shall lay my crown at his feet &amp; I will</l>
					<l>fall down at his feet &amp; worship him</l>
					<l>with all the little Angels in white, her</l>
					<l>friend said, how will you know our</l>
					<l>Saviour for we read in the Revelations</l>
					<l>that St John was mistaken &amp; was</l>
					<l>going to worship an Angel instead</l>
					<l>of the Lord Jesus, she said, I </l>
					<l>shall not mistake for our dear Saviour</l>
					<l>was crusified, you know they nailed</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1199.jpg' n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>him to the Cross by his hands &amp; by</l>
					<l>his feet, &amp; they peirced his side, I </l>
					<l>shall know him by his wounds, &amp; I will</l>
					<l>Sing in heaven hallelujah praise</l>
					<l>the Lord &amp; All hail the power of Jesus home</l>
					<l>Let Angels prostrate fall</l>
					<l>Bring forth the royal children</l>
					<l>And crown him Lord of all</l>
					<l>The week following on the 4th of April</l>
					<l>she was seized with a putrid sore throat</l>
					<l>And fever, she suffered with such</l>
					<l>uncommon patience as astonished</l>
					<l>all around her, to a friend that</l>
					<l>visited her she said with a smile</l>
					<l>I am doing to sing the song Moses</l>
					<l>&amp; the Lamb before you dear Momma</l>
					<l>do not grieve for me, I am soon going</l>
					<l>to our dear Saviour, he has only lent</l>
					<l>me to you for a little while if you lose</l>
					<l>me you will give me up to him, do</l>
					<l>no cry because Maryann is going to</l>
					<l>heaven, you will come by &amp; bye, we shall</l>
					<l>meet again Momma let one he burried</l>
					<l>like the Sisters &amp; let all the Sisters have</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>gloves and ribbons and meet around my</l>
					<l>coffin with the Minister to sing verses, and</l>
					<l>afterwards follow me in white to the grave</l>
					<l>her Momma answered her that ii should</l>
					<l>be as she wished desired, she  also begged</l>
					<l>that her coffin might be like Maria</l>
					<l>Grinfield&apos;s which was granted, she</l>
					<l>said, I should like so be buried in</l>
					<l>the Chapel burying ground, but I</l>
					<l>cannot expec that, as I am not in the</l>
					<l>Society you know but never mind,</l>
					<l>my soul will be with our dear Saviour,</l>
					<l>my body shall rise from the pithole</l>
					<l>Sr Jones&apos;s so that is no matter but</l>
					<l>when the weather is fine, will you</l>
					<l>visit my grave sometimes to remember</l>
					<l>Maryann? on the night before her</l>
					<l>departure, she attempted to sing</l>
					<l>Hallelujah praise the Lord which</l>
					<l>she had often done, but now her throat</l>
					<l>was so bad that she could only repeat</l>
					<l>the words - The next day about noon</l>
					<l>not being able to speak her dear little</l>
					<l>hands folded together with her lips</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb xml:id='IMG_1200.jpg' n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>moving in the attitude of prayer</l>
					<l>then her spirit calmly departed</l>
					<l>into the hands of him who gave it</l>
					<l>being aged only 4 years and a half.</l>
					<l>Chifton</l>
					<l>Octr 19th 1829.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
